<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/2008/25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/2008/25"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Haryana Police Act, 2007"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/2008/25/eng@2017-01-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/2008/25/eng@2017-01-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/2008/25/eng@2017-01-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/2008/25/eng@2017-01-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Haryana Police Act, 2007</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 25 of 2008]</p>
        <p>[June 2, 2008]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide a new State police law for establishment, regulations and management of the police, redefine its role, duties and its responsibilities and to enable it to function as an efficient, professional, effective, accountable, people friendly and responsive agency by taking into account the emerging challenges of policing, enforcement of rule of law, the concern for security of the State and the people, good governance and human rights.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Haryana in the Fifty-eighth Year of the Republic of India.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Definitions and Interpretations</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Haryana Police Act, 2007.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Haryana.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>“Cattle” include cows, buffaloes, elephants, camels, horses, asses, mules, sheep, goats and swine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>“Commissioner” means Commissioner of Police appointed as such under Section 8 of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>“Competent authority” means the authority as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>“Group C posts” means the posts so categorized under the relevant State Service Rules;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>“Insurgency” includes waging of armed struggle by a group or a section of population against the State with a political objective including the separation of a part from the territory of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>“internal security” means preservation of sovereignty and integrity of the State from disruptive and anti-national forces from within the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>“militant activities” include any violence of a group using explosives, inflammable substances, firearms or other lethal weapons or hazardous substance in order to achieve its political objectives;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>“municipal area” means the area as defined in the Haryana Municipal Act, 1973 (24 of 1973) and the rules made there under;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>“organized crime” includes any crime committed by a group or a network of persons in pursuance of its common intention of unlawful gain by using violent means or threat of violence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>“police district” means the area as is notified under section 10 of Chapter II of this Act as distinct from a revenue district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>“place of public amusement and public entertainment” include such place as may be notified by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>“police officer” means any member of the police service of the State constituted under this Act and includes Indian Police Service (IPS) officers of State cadre;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>“public place” means any place to which the public have access and includes,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a public building, market, malls, trains, buses, monuments and precincts thereof; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>any place accessible to the public for drawing water, washing or bathing or for purposes of recreation;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>“regulations” means regulations made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>“rules” mean rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>“service” means the police service constituted under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>“State Government” means the Government of the State of Haryana in the Administrative Department;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>“subordinate rank” means all ranks below the Assistant or Deputy Superintendent of Police</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.t">
                  <num>(t)</num>
                  <p>“terrorist activity” includes any activity of a person or a group using explosive or inflammable substances or firearms or other lethal weapons or noxious gases or other chemicals or any other substance of a hazardous nature with the aim to strike terror in the society or any section thereof, and with an intent to overawe Government established by law.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Words and expressions used in this Act but not defined specifically shall have the meanings assigned to them in the General Clauses Act, 1897 (Act 10 of 1897), the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974) and the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (Act 45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Constitution and organization of police service</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of police service.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>There shall be one Police service for the State, constituted by the State Government under this Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law or any of the provisions of this Act, members of the police service shall be liable for posting anywhere in the State and outside the State as ordered by the competent authority and to any branch of the service in the State, including any of its specialised wings.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Organization and composition of Police service.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act,-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the police service shall consist of such numbers in various ranks and have such organization or cadres as the State Government may, by general or special order, determine and shall include the members of the Indian Police Service allocated to the State;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the direct recruitment to various gazetted and non-gazetted ranks in the police service shall be made through a State Level Police Recruitment Board or District Level Police Recruitment Boards by a transparent process, adopting well codified systems which shall be framed under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the pay, allowances, service conditions, mode of recruitment of the police personnel shall be such as may be prescribed from time to time;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>police personnel shall at all times remain accountable to the law and responsive to the lawful needs of the people and shall observe codes of ethical conduct and integrity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Director General, Additional Director General, Inspector General, Deputy or Assistant Inspector General.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the overall direction and supervision of the police service, the State Government shall appoint a Director General of Police who shall exercise such powers perform such functions and duties, and have such responsibilities and such authority, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint one or more Directors General of Police, Additional Directors General, and as many Inspectors General, Deputy or Assistant Inspectors General of Police as may be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by a general or special order direct in what manner and to what extent Additional Director General or an Inspector General or a Deputy or Assistant Inspector General of Police shall assist and aid the Director General of Police in the performance, exercise and discharge of his functions, powers, duties and responsibilities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Selection and term of office of Director General of Police.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall appoint the Director General of Police from amongst the officers holding the rank of Director General of Police.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director General of Police so appointed shall have a minimum tenure of one year subject to his normal date of superannuation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Legal and Finance officers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint adequate Legal officers and Finance officers to aid and advise the Director General of Police on legal and financial matters, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may also appoint in every District Police Unit and City Police Commissionerate, as the case may be, one or more Legal officers to advise the police on legal issues and matters including the adequacy or otherwise of the available evidence as deemed necessary in various cases investigated by them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Appointment of officers under sub-sections (1) and (2) shall be made in the manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Administration of police in municipal areas, major urban areas and other notified areas.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may, be notification in the Official Gazette, establish for each of the major urban areas as may be notified for the purpose from time to time, a police system which is capable of handling the typical complex problems of crime, public order and internal security in urban or suburban areas, which call for quick and comprehensive response springing from purposeful direction, unitary chain of command, professional competence, functional specialization, and legal authority coupled with accountability as follows:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the State Government may appoint a police officer not below the rank of Inspector General of Police to be the Commissioner for any area specified in a notification issued by the State Government in this behalf and published in the Official Gazette;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Commissioner shall exercise such powers, perform such functions and duties and shall have such responsibilities and authority as are provided by or under this Act or as may otherwise be directed by the State Government by a general or special order:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may direct that any of the powers, functions and duties, responsibilities or authority exercisable or to be performed or discharged by the Commissioner shall be exercised, or discharged subject to the control of the Director General of Police:</p>
              <p>Provided further that in any area for which a Commissioner is appointed and is empowered to exercise any power or perform any function or duty under this Act or any other Act, the District Magistrate shall not exercise the same power or perform the same function or duty notwithstanding the fact that such area forms part of a district within the territorial jurisdiction of the District Magistrate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Creation of police range.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, divide the entire geographical area of the State into one or more police ranges. Each range, comprising two or more police districts, shall be headed by an officer of the rank of Inspector General of Police who shall supervise the police administration of the range and report to the Director General of Police.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Police districts.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government, in consultation with the Director General of Police, may by notification in the Official Gazette, declare any area within the State to be a police district. The administration of the police throughout such district shall vest in the Superintendent of Police of a district who may be assisted by as many Additional, Assistant or Deputy Superintendents of Police, as deemed necessary and are notified.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>District Level Special Cells and Sub-Divisions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of dealing with a particular category of crime or providing better service to the community at large including victims of crime, the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, create one or more Special Cells in each police district, to be headed by an officer of not below the rank of Inspector.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette divide each police district into as many Sub-Divisions as deemed necessary, to be headed by an officer of the rank of Assistant or Deputy Superintendent of Police.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Police stations.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, on recommendation of the Director General of Police and by notification in the Official Gazette, create as many police stations with as many outposts as may be necessary, in a police district as deemed necessary, duly keeping in view the population, the area, the crime situation, the workload in terms of law and order and the distances to be traversed by the inhabitants to reach the police station.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each police station shall be headed by a Station House Officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector of Police.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be a crime investigation unit of appropriate strength in each police station.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district may constitute a Community Liaison Group as may be prescribed for each Police station comprising respectable local residents of the area including the representatives of the weaker sections and women with unimpeachable character and antecedents and aptitude for community service to aid and advise the police in its functioning.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Terms of office of key police functionaries.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An officer posted as Inspector General of Police of a range or Superintendent of Police of a district shall have a minimum term of one year:</p>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that any such officer may be removed by the appointing authority from his post before the expiry of the minimum tenure prescribed consequent upon:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>promotion to a higher post; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>conviction, or charges having been framed, by a court of law in a criminal offence; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>punishment of dismissal, removal, discharge or compulsory retirement from service or of reduction to a lower rank awarded under the relevant Discipline and Appeal Rules; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>suspension from the service in accordance with the provisions of the said rules; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>incapacitation by physical or mental illness or otherwise becoming unable to discharge his functions and duties; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the need to fill up a vacancy caused by promotion, transfer, or retirement.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In exceptional cases, an officer may be transferred from his post by the competent authority before the expiry of his tenure for gross inefficiency and negligence or where a prima facie case of a serious nature is established after a preliminary enquiry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Coordination with district administration.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of efficiency in the general administration of the district, the Superintendent of Police of a district shall maintain proper coordination with the District Magistrate or Deputy Commissioner of the district. It shall be lawful for the District Magistrate, in addition to the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974) and other relevant Acts, to coordinate and direct the functioning of the police with other agencies of district administration in respect of matters relating to the following:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>promotion of land reforms and the settlement of land disputes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>extensive disturbance of the public peace and tranquility in the district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>conducting elections to any public body;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>handling of natural calamities and rehabilitation of the persons affected thereby;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>situation arising out of any external aggression or internal disturbances;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any similar matter, not within the purview of any one department and affecting the general welfare of the public;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>removal of any persistent public grievance; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>communal or caste clashes.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of coordination, the District Magistrate may call for information of a general or special nature, as and when required, from the Superintendent of Police of a district and heads of other departments of the district. Where the situation so demands, the District Magistrate shall pass appropriate orders and issue directions in writing, to achieve the objective of coordination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of coordination, the District Magistrate shall ensure that all departments of the district, whose assistance is required for the efficient functioning of the police, render full assistance to the Superintendent of Police of a district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Railway Police.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, create one or more special railway police districts with required number of Railway Police Sub-Divisions and railway police stations consisting of such railway lines and other railway areas in the State as it may notify, and appoint a Superintendent of Police, one or more Assistant and Deputy Superintendents of Police and such other police officers for policing such district in the manner as may be prescribed or may notify one or more police stations in each police district to police the railway lines and other railway establishments within their area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The police stations as may be notified shall be responsible for prevention, detection and investigation of crime, enforcement of law and maintenance of order in trains passing through their area, in railway lines area and other railway area falling in their jurisdiction in the manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>State Intelligence and Criminal Investigation Wings.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Police shall have a State Intelligence Wing for collection, collation, analysis and dissemination of intelligence and a separate State Crime Investigation Wing for collection, collation and analysis of criminal intelligence and for investigating heinous crime with inter-state, inter-district ramifications, major economic offences, cyber crime and other cases of serious nature as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Technical and Support Service</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall create and maintain such specialised and technical agencies and services, under the Director General of Police as considered necessary or expedient for promoting efficiency of police service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The services so created shall include a full fledged Forensic Science Laboratory at the State Level, and a Finger Print Bureau, the State Crime Record Bureau, Telecommunication Wing and such other establishments as may be required from time to time. The Director General of Police may hire or engage services of any person or body of persons qualified for this purpose on contractual basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Police shall have a Research Wing to undertake specific studies relating to policing and crime in the State. The Director General of Police may hire or engage services of any person or body qualified for this purpose on contractual basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Police Training.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall establish a Police Training Academy at the State Level and as many Police Training Colleges and Police Training Schools as deemed necessary for ensuring efficient post-induction training of all directly recruited police personnel in various ranks, pre-promotion training for all those promoted to higher levels and such other general and specialized in-service training courses for police personnel of different ranks and categories as may be required from time to time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall also provide for appointment, by rules, of appropriate number of officers from the police service, or paramilitary forces or armed forces or other professional organizations, in such Police Training Academy, College and School, after careful selection having due regard to aptitude, academic qualifications, professional competence, experience and integrity. The State Government shall evolve a scheme of monetary and other incentives to attract and retain the best of the available talent in the service to the faculties of such training institutions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No police officer shall be deployed on duty without undergoing and passing any basic training as may be prescribed. No Police Officer shall be promoted to any higher rank without undergoing and passing pre-promotion training as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Oath or affirmation by police personnel.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every member of the police service enrolled under this Act shall, on appointment and completion of training, make and subscribe before the Superintendent of Police of a district or Commissioner, as the case may be, or another officer appointed in that behalf by him, as the case may be, an oath or affirmation, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Certificate of appointment.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every police officer of or below the rank of Inspector shall on appointment receive and insignia and a certificate in the form as may be prescribed. The certificate shall be issued under the hand and seal of such officer as the State Government may by general or special order direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The certificate of appointment shall become null and void, and the insignia shall be deemed to be withdrawn whenever the person named therein ceases to belong to the service or shall remain inoperative during the period such person is suspended from the service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Special police officers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district or any officer, specially empowered in this behalf by the State Government, may, at any time by a written order issued under the hand and seal of such officer, appoint, for a period as specified in the appointment order, any able-bodied, educated and willing person between the age of 18 and 50 years, whom he considers fit to be a Special Police Officer to assist the service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every special police officer so appointed -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall on appointment, undergo prescribed training and thereafter receive a certificate in a form approved by the State Government in this behalf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>shall have the same powers, privileges and immunities and be liable to the same duties and responsibilities and be subject to the same authorities as an ordinary police officer;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>shall be honorary. However the State Government, may by special order, prescribe the honorarium to be paid to such special police officers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>who refuses to act as a special police officer or neglects his duties, shall be liable on conviction by a court to a fine of minimum of one thousand rupees.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Rank structure in civil and armed police.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The service shall have such ranks and posts as may be prescribed or as may be notified by the State Government. The recruitment, training, posting, deputation, promotion, code of conduct, discipline, punishment and appeal and other service conditions of various ranks of service shall be as per rules.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>District Armed Reserves and State Armed Police Battalions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>To assist the civil police in enforcement of law and maintenance of order or in situations of likely breach of peace and in disaster management functions, in escort of prisoners, as well as to discharge such other duties which may require special weapons and tactical teams or presence of armed police, the State Government shall create Armed Police Units or Special Armed Police Units with appropriate manpower strengths in the form of an Armed Police Reserve for each police district, and appropriate number of Armed Police Battalions for the State. The constitution, recruitment, training, deployment and administration of such reserves and Battalions shall be as per rules made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Superintendence and Administration of Police</heading>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Superintendence of State Police to vest in State Government.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendence of State Police shall vest in and be exercised by the State Government in accordance with the provisions of this Act, and any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>State Police Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, within three months of the coming into force of this Act, establish a State Police Board to exercise the functions assigned to it under the provisions of this Chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Composition of Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Police Board shall consist of following members:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Minister as its Chairperson;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Home Minister as Vice-Chairperson;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Leader of the Opposition in the State Assembly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>a retired High Court Judge or Advocate General, Haryana;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Secretary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary in charge of the Home Department;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the Director General of Police as its Member- Secretary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>three non-political persons (hereinafter referred as ‘Independent Members’) of high integrity, expertise and competence in administration, law enforcement and security related matters shall be nominated by the State Government. Out of these, one shall be the retired officer of Indian Administrative Service and one retired Indian Police Service officer. The third member shall be nominated by the State Government from the field of public service, legal profession or social organizations with at least fifteen years experience in that field.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Note:- The Independent Members shall be honorary members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No serving Government employee shall be appointed as an Independent Member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any vacancy in the State Police Board shall be filled up as soon as practicable after the seat has fallen vacant:</p>
              <p>Provided that if there is no Home Minister then the Chief Minister may nominate any other Minister as the Vice-Chairperson.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Eligibility of Independent Members.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The person to be appointed as Independent Member of the State Police Board shall –</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be a citizen of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>be at least a graduate of a recognized university;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>have not been convicted by a court of law or against whom charges have been framed in a court of law;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>not have been dismissed or removed from service or compulsory retired on the ground of corruption or misconduct; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>not be of unsound mind.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Term of office of Independent Members.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A person shall be appointed as an Independent Member for a period of three years. The same person shall not be appointed for more than two consecutive terms.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Removal of Independent Members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>An Independent Member may be removed from the State Police Board by the State Government on any of the following grounds-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>proven incompetence; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>proven misbehavior; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>incapacitation by reasons of physical or mental infirmity or otherwise becoming unable to discharge his functions as a member.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the grounds mentioned in sub-section (1), an Independent Member shall be removed from the State Police Board if he incurs any of the grounds of ineligibility specified under section 27.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Functions of State Police Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Police Board shall perform the following functions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>aid and advise the State Government in discharge of its functions and responsibilities under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>frame broad policy guidelines for promoting efficient, effective, responsive and accountable policing in accordance with the law; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>review and evaluate organizational performance of the service in the State.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Expenses of State Police Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The expenses on account of allowances and travel of the Independent Member shall be borne by the State Government in the manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Administration of State Police.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The administration of the State Police throughout the State shall be vested in the Director General of Police and in such Additional Directors General, Inspector General, Deputy Inspectors General of Police and other police officers as may be appointed under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The administration of police in a district shall vest in the Superintendent of Police of a district:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may intervene in the exercise of the powers of administration by the Director General of Police; or any other authorized officer only in accordance with the prescribed rules, regulations or in exceptional circumstances involving urgent public interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Powers and responsibilities of Director General of Police.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>As the head of the service, it shall be the responsibility of the Director General of Police to -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>make operational the policies and any action plans approved by the State Government; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>administer, control and supervise the service to ensure its efficiency, effectiveness, responsiveness and accountability.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Police establishment committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may constitute a police establishment committee (hereinafter referred to as the “establishment committee”) with the Director General of Police as its Chairperson and two other senior officers not below the rank of Inspector General of Police posted within the police organization of the State as members for administrative matters.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The establishment committee may prepare an action plan for improving the infrastructure facilities, professionalism, general discipline in the service, moderanisation, training, welfare of the police personnel and any other work assigned by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Policing in the context of public order and internal security challenges</heading>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Internal Security Scheme.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Director General of Police shall, with the approval of the State Government, draw up an Internal Security Scheme for the entire State as well as for each of the districts and urban areas notified, to deal with problems of public order and security of State as specific to the area.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Updating standard operating procedure.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Internal Security Scheme shall incorporate regularly updated and comprehensive standard operating procedures for the action to be taken by the police, independently or in coordination with other concerned agencies in the period preceding, during, and in the aftermath of problems of each kind.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Creation of Special Security Zone.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If and when the security of the State in an area is threatened by insurgency, any terrorist or militant activity, or activities of any organised crime group, the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare such area as a Special Security Zone:</p>
              <p>Provided that such notification shall be placed before the State Legislature, within a period of six months from the date of issue, or the first sitting of the Legislature, whichever is earlier.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Police structure.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall create an appropriate police structure and a suitable command, control and response system, for each Special Security Zone.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Functioning of different wings.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government, in order to ensure coordinated functioning of different wings of the administration, shall set up, in each Special Security Zone, a suitable administrative structure which shall integrate administrative and developmental measures in the area with the police response to deal with the problems of public order and security.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Standard operating procedures.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Director General of Police shall, with the concurrence of the State Government, issue orders, laying down standard operating procedures to be followed by the police in a Special Security Zone.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Banning and regulation of certain devices and substances.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, on the recommendation of the Director General of Police, and for reasons to be recorded in writing, ban or regulate the production, Sale, storage, possession or entry of any devices, or equipment, or any explosive, poisonous, chemical, biological or radioactive articles or substances, or any inflow of funds, in a Special Security Zone, if the use of such devices, or equipment, or any explosive, or poisonous, chemical, biological or radioactive articles or substances, or any inflow of funds, in a Special Security Zone, is reasonably considered a threat to internal security or public order in the area, in any manner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Framing of rules.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government, for any Special Security Zone falling within the State, may frame rules to prevent and control the activities of persons or organizations, which may have an impact on internal security or public order.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Effective Crime Investigation</heading>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Investigations by District Police.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, create in every district, a specialized crime investigation unit, headed by an officer not below the rank of Inspector with an appropriate strength of officers and staff, for investigating economic and heinous crimes. The personnel posted to this unit shall not be diverted to any other duty, except under very special circumstances with the written permission of the Director General of Police.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Selection of officers.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officers posted in special crime investigation units shall be selected on the basis of their aptitude, professional competence and integrity. Their professional skills shall be upgraded, from time to time, through specialised training in investigative techniques, particularly in the application of scientific aids to investigation and forensic science techniques.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Investigation of crimes.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officers posted to the special crime investigation units may investigate crimes such as murder, kidnapping, rape, dacoity, robbery, dowry-related offences, serious cases of cheating, misappropriation and other economic offences, as notified by the Director General of Police, besides any other cases specially entrusted to the unit by the Superintendent of Police of a district.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Legal and forensic advice.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Necessary legal and forensic aid may be made available to investigating officer during investigations.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Role, Functions, Duties and Responsibilities of the Police</heading>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Role, functions and duties.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The role and functions of the police shall broadly be,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to prevent and detect crime;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to protect life and property and maintain law and order;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to preserve public order;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to provide possible help to people in distress or in situations arising out of natural or man-made disasters;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>to facilitate orderly movement of people and vehicles;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>to collect intelligence relating to matters affecting public peace, crime, social harmony and security of state and take appropriate action;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>to take charge of all unclaimed property and take action as per rules;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>to prevent and control public nuisance;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to enforce any other duty assigned by law.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Senior police officer performing duties of subordinate officer.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A senior police officer may perform any duty assigned by law or by a lawful order to any officer subordinate to him, and may aid, supplement, supersede or prevent any action of the subordinate by his own action or that of any person lawfully acting under his command or authority, whenever the same shall appear necessary or expedient for giving more complete or convenient effect to the law or for avoiding any infringement thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Police officers to keep diary.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of every officer in-charge of a police-station to keep a general diary in such form, as shall, from time to time be prescribed by the State Government and to record therein, all complaints and charges preferred, the names of all persons arrested, the names of the complainants, the offences charged against them, the weapons or property that have been taken from their possession or otherwise, and the names of the witnesses who have been examined.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every police station shall keep such records registers, forms and returns as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director General of Police may specify such returns, reports and statements connected with prevention and detection of crime, maintenance of order, performance of duties, administration and management of the police service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Regulation, Control and Discipline</heading>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Regulations.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Director General of Police shall be competent to make regulations or issue orders, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or the rule framed thereunder regarding,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>prevention and investigation of crime;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>maintenance of law and order;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>regulation and inspection of the police organization and of the work performed by the police officers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>regulating the issue and use of arms and ammunition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>wearing of uniform;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>prescribing the places of residence of the members of the police service;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>institution, management and regulation of any Non-Government fund for the purpose connected with the police administration or welfare of police personnel;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>regulation, deployment, movements and location of the police;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>assigning duties to officers of all ranks and grades, and prescribing the manner and the conditions subject to which, they shall exercise and perform their respective powers and duties;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>regulating the collection and communication of intelligence and information by the police;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>prescribing the records registers and forms to be maintained and the returns to be submitted by different police units and officers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>community policing;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>functioning of police stations and other units;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>training of the police force and management of training institutions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>generally, for the purpose of administering this Act and for rendering the police more efficient, and preventing abuse of power or neglect of duties by them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list1.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>covering any aspect of police administration which is not covered under the provisions of this Act or rules framed thereunder.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Police officers to be always on duty.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every police officer shall be considered to be always on duty and may at any time be deployed in any part of the State or outside the State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Abdication of duties.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No police officer shall abdicate his duties or withdraw himself from his place of posting or deployment, without proper authorization.</p>
              <p>Explanation:- An officer who, being absent after expiry of authorized leave without reasonable cause shall be deemed within the meaning of this section to have withdrawn himself from the duties of his office.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Employment in office of profit.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No police officer shall engage in any other employment or office of profit whatsoever, other than his duties under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for causing disaffection.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, intentionally causes or attempts to cause, or does any act which is likely to cause disaffection towards the Government established by law, amongst the members of a police force, or induces or attempts to induce or does any act which is likely to induce, any member of police force to withhold his services or to commit a breach of discipline, shall be punished with imprisonment which may extent to one year, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
              <p>Explanation:- Expression of disapprobation of measures of the Government with a view to obtain their alteration by lawful means, or of disapprobation of the administrative or other action of the Government, do not constitute an offence under this section unless they cause or are made for the purpose of causing or are likely to cause disaffection.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Restrictions respecting right to form association, freedom of speech.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-55.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-55.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No member of a police force shall, without the express sanction of the State Government -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-55.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political association, or with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political associations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-55.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any other society, institution, association, or organization that is not recognized as part of the force of which he is a member or is not a purely social, recreational or religious nature: or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-55.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>communicate with the press or publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other documents except where such communication or publication is in the bona fide discharge of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic, scientific character or is of a prescribed nature.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation. If any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or organization is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under clause (b) of this sub-section, the decision of the State Government, thereon, shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-55.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No member of a police force shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any demonstration organized by any body of persons for any political purpose or for such other purposes as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Penalty.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-56.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-56.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No member of a police force shall, without the express sanction of the State Government -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-56.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political association, or with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political associations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-56.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any other society, institution, association, or organization that is not recognized as part of the force of which he is a member or is not a purely social, recreational or religious nature: or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-56.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>communicate with the press or publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other documents except where such communication or publication is in the bona fide discharge of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic, scientific character or is of a prescribed nature.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation:- If any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or organization is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under clause (b) of this sub-section, the decision of the State Government, thereon, shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-56.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No member of a police force shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any demonstration organized by any body of persons for any political purpose or for such other purposes as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Employment of police officer beyond the State to which they belong.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, a member of the police force of Haryana State may discharge the functions of a police-officer in any part of any other State and shall, while so discharging such functions, be deemed to be a member of the police force of that State and be vested with the powers, functions and privileges and be subject to the liabilities of a police officer belonging to that State’s police force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Extension of disciplinary laws of State to member of service when serving outside State.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where any detachment of the police force of Haryana State is serving in any part of any other State, whether independently or by being attached to the police force of that other State, then, every member of the said detachment, while discharging the functions of a police officer in that other State, shall continue to be subject to the same laws in respect of discipline as would have been applicable to him, if he had been discharging those functions within Haryana State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Police Accountability</heading>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>State Police Complaint Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, within three months of the commencement of this Act, establish at the State Level, a Police Complaint Authority, which shall be either a retired Judge or a retired civil servant, not below the rank of Secretary to the State or a lawyer well versed with criminal law and with an experience of at least twenty years in the relevant field, for inquiries and investigations into the complaints against the police officers and officials of the State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Ineligibility.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be ineligible to be appointed as Authority, if he-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is not a citizen of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is above seventy years of age;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is employed as a public servant;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>holds any elected office, including that of member of Parliament or State Legislature or any local body;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>is a member of or is associated in any manner with, an organization declared as unlawful under any existing law;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>is an office bearer or a member of any political party;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>has been convicted for any criminal offence involving moral turpitude or for an offence punishable with imprisonment of one year or more;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>is facing prosecution for any offence mentioned in clause (g) above and against whom charges have been framed by a court of law; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and has been so declared by a competent court.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and conditions of Authority.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-61.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-61.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The term of office of the Authority shall be of three years unless. -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-61.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he resigns at any time before the expiry of his term; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-61.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>he is removed from the office on any of the grounds mentioned in section 62:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that he may be appointed for a second term also if deemed appropriate by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-61.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The remuneration, allowances and other terms and conditions of service of the Authority shall be as such as may be notified by the State Government from time to time and shall not be varied to his disadvantage after appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Removal of Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-62.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority may be removed by the State Government on the grounds of -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-62.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>proven misconduct or misbehavior;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>persistence neglect to perform duties;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>occurrence of any situation that would make him ineligible for appointment under section 60; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>engaging himself during his term of office in any paid employment outside the duties of his office.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Supporting staff of Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall be assisted by adequate number of officers well versed with the law, finances, in investigative techniques etc. and the requisite supporting staff with terms and conditions and allowances as may be prescribed for the efficient discharge of its functions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Conduct of business.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall devise his own rules for the conduct of his business.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Authority.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-65.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-65.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority shall inquire into allegations of “serious misconduct” against police personnel as detailed below, either suo motu or on a complaint received from any of the following:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-65.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a victim or any person on his behalf on a sworn affidavit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-65.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the National or State Human Rights Commission.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-65.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation. “Serious misconduct” for the purpose of this Chapter shall mean any act or omission of a police officer that leads to or amounts to -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-65.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>death in police custody;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-65.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>rape or attempt to commit rape;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-65.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>grievous hurt in police custody:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the Authority shall inquire into a complaint of such arrest or detention, only if he is satisfied prima facie about the veracity of the complaint;</p>
              <p>Provided further that no anonymous, synonymous, and pseudonymous complaints shall be entertained.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-65.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may also inquire into any other case referred to it by the Director General of Police or the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In the cases directly enquired by him, the Authority shall have all the powers of a civil court trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Act 5 of 1908) and in particular in respect of the following matters:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses and examining them on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>discover and production of any document;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from any court or office;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>issuing authorities for the examination of witnesses or documents; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any other matter as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Decisions and directions of Authority.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-67.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the cases directly inquired by the Authority, he may, upon completion of the inquiry, communicate his findings to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-67.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall consider the findings and recommendations of the Authority and take appropriate action.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>District Police Complaint Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-68.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may notify and constitute a District Police Complaint Authority for each district as and when required.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <heading>General Offences, Penalties and Responsibilities</heading>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Regulation of public assemblies and processions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-69.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district or an officer not below the rank of Assistant or Deputy Superintendent of Police may, where necessary, direct the conduct of all assemblies and processions on any public road, street or thoroughfare, and specify the routes by which and the time at which such a procession may pass.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of any person intending to organize a procession on any road, street or thoroughfare, or to convene an assembly at any public place, to give intimation in writing to the officer incharge of the concerned police station.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district or any officer not below the rank of Assistant/ Deputy Superintendent of Police, on receipt of such intimation or otherwise, and upon being satisfied that such an assembly or procession, if allowed without due control and regulation, is likely to cause a breach of peace, may take necessary steps including making provisions for satisfactory regulatory arrangements, on which alone such assembly or procession may take place. Under special circumstances to be recorded in writing, the concerned officer may also prohibit the assembly or procession in public interest. All orders and directions shall be given within forty-eight hours of receipt of intimation, as far as possible.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-70">
          <num>70.</num>
          <heading>Regulation of use of music and other sound systems in public places.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district or any officer not below the rank of Assistant or Deputy Superintendent of Police may regulate the time and the volume at which music and other sound systems are used in connection with any performances and other activities in or near streets or any public place that cause annoyance to the residents of the neighborhood.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-71">
          <num>71.</num>
          <heading>Directions to keep order on public roads.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-71.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district or any police officer authorized by him in this behalf, through a general or special order, may give reasonable directions to the public to keep order on public roads and streets, thoroughfares, or any public place, in order to prevent obstruction, injury, or annoyance to passers-by.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-71.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district may issue general directions under sub-section (1), in respect of the whole district or any part thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-72">
          <num>72.</num>
          <heading>Penalty and composition of offences.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-72.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever contravene the provisions of sections 69, 70, 71 and 79 of this Act shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-72.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>However, either before or after the institution of prosecution, these offences may be compounded by such officers or authorities, and for such amount, as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-72.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence has been compounded under sub-section (2), the offender, if in custody, shall be discharged and no further proceedings shall be taken against him in respect of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-73">
          <num>73.</num>
          <heading>Power to reserve public places and erect barriers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-73.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district may, by public notice, temporarily reserve for any public purpose, any street or other public place, and prohibit the public from entering the area so reserved, except on such conditions as may be specified.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-73.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of Police of a district may authorize any police officer to erect barriers and other necessary structures on public roads and streets, to check vehicles or occupants thereof for violation of any legal provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-73.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making such order, the Superintendent of Police of a district shall specify the necessary steps ensuring the safety of passers-by.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-73.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The temporary structures shall be removed once the purpose for which they were installed is over.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-74">
          <num>74.</num>
          <heading>Obstruction in police work.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person, who obstructs the discharge of duties and functions of a police officer, shall, on conviction, be liable to simple imprisonment not exceeding three months or with fine or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-75">
          <num>75.</num>
          <heading>Unauthorized use of police uniform.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-75.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, not being a member of the service wears, without obtaining permission from an officer authorized in this behalf by the State Government by a general or special order, a police uniform or any dress having the appearance or bearing any of the distinctive marks of that uniform, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment not exceeding six months or with fine or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-76">
          <num>76.</num>
          <heading>Refusal to deliver up certificate etc. on ceasing to be police officers.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-76.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, having ceased to be a police officer, does not forthwith deliver up his certificate of appointment, clothing accouterment and other wherewithal supplied to him for the execution of his duty, shall on conviction by a court of law, be liable to a minimum fine of one thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-77">
          <num>77.</num>
          <heading>False or misleading statements made to a police officer.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-77.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever makes a false statement or a statement which is misleading in material particulars to a police officer for the purpose of obtaining any benefit shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with a fine not exceeding five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-78">
          <num>78.</num>
          <heading>Dereliction of duty by a police officer.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-78.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-78.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whoever, being a police officer-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-78.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>intentionally abdicates duties or withdraws from duties; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-78.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>uses criminal force against another police officer, or indulges in gross insubordination; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-78.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>engages himself or participates in any demonstration, procession or strike, or resorts to, or in any way abets any form of strike, or coerces or uses physical force to compel any authority to concede anything, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with a fine not exceeding ten thousand rupees or with both.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-79">
          <num>79.</num>
          <heading>Offences by public.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-79.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-79.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person who commits any of the following offences on any public road, or street or thoroughfare, or in any municipal council or corporation or notified area for the purpose of this section, to the inconvenience, annoyance or danger of the residents or passers-by, shall on conviction by a court, be liable to imprisonment not exceeding one month or with fine of not less than one thousand rupees or with both-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>allowing intentionally any cattle to stray, or keeping any cattle or conveyance of any kind standing longer than is required for loading or unloading or for taking up or getting down passengers, or leaving any conveyance in such a manner as to cause inconvenience or danger to the public or uses the public road or thoroughfare or footpath for sale or storage of goods;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>indulges in a drunken brawl or affray or assaults any person or indulges in any indecent exposure of the body;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>neglecting to fence in or duly protect any well, tank, hole or other dangerous place or structure under his charge or possession; or otherwise creating a hazardous situation in a public place;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>defacing, or affixing notices, or writing graffiti on walls, buildings, road signs or other structures without the prior permission of the custodian of the property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>willfully damaging or sabotaging any public alarm system;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>knowingly and willfully causing damage to an essential service, in order to cause general panic among the public;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>acting in contravention of a notice publicly displayed by the competent authority in any Government building:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-79.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the police shall take cognizance of this offence only upon a complaint made by an authorized functionary of the concerned office;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-79.1.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>causing annoyance to a woman by making indecent overtures or calls or by stalking:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-79.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the police shall take cognizance of this offence only upon a complaint made by the victim, or any person authorized by her;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-79.1.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>releases any obnoxious gas or fluid which causes annoyance or inconvenience or likely injury to anyone.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-79.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever commits any offence under sub-section (1), on subsequent conviction shall be liable to enhanced punishment, including imprisonment not exceeding three months.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-80">
          <num>80.</num>
          <heading>Prosecution of police officer.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-80.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act when the accused person is a police officer except on a report in writing of the facts constituting such offence by, or with the previous sanction of an officer authorized by the State Government in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-81">
          <num>81.</num>
          <heading>Prosecution for offences under other laws.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-81.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions as contained in section 300 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974), nothing in this Act shall be construed as preventing any person from being prosecuted and punished under any other law for anything done or made punishable by this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-82">
          <num>82.</num>
          <heading>Limitation of actions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-82.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Chapter after the expiry of the period of limitation as provided for in section 468 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974). For computing the limitation period, provisions of Chapter XXXVI of the code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974), shall apply.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-X">
        <num>X</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-83">
          <num>83.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Superintendent of Police to be exercised by Commissioner.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-83.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All powers, functions and duties of the Superintendent of Police of a district described in this Act shall be exercised, in respect of areas notified under section 9 of this Act, by the Commissioner or any other officer authorized in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-84">
          <num>84.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of fees and rewards.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-84.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All fees paid for licenses or written permission issued under this Act, and all sums paid for the service of processes by police officers and all rewards, forfeitures and penalties or shares thereof which are by law payable to police officers as informers shall, save in so far as any such fees or sums belongs under the provisions of any enactment in force to any local authority, be credited to the State Government;</p>
              <p>Provided that with the sanction of the State Government or under any rule made by the State Government in this behalf, the whole or any portion of any such reward, forfeiture or penalty may for special services, be paid to a police officer, or be divided amongst two or more police officers.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-85">
          <num>85.</num>
          <heading>Method of proving orders and notifications.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-85.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any order or notification published or issued by the State Government or any officer under any provision of this Act, and the due publication or issue thereof may be proved by the production of a copy thereof in the Official Gazette, or of a copy thereof signed by such officer, and certified by him to be true of an original published or issued according to the provisions of the section of the Act applicable thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-86">
          <num>86.</num>
          <heading>Validity of rules and orders.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-86.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No rule, regulation, order, direction, or notification made or published and no adjudication, inquiry or act done under any provision of this Act, or under any rules made thereunder, which is in substantial conformity with the same, shall be deemed illegal, void or invalid merely by reason of any defect or form.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-87">
          <num>87.</num>
          <heading>Officers holding charge of or succeeding to vacancies competent to exercise powers.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-87.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever in consequence of the office of a Commissioner or police officer becoming vacant, any officer holding charge of the post of such Commissioner or police officer or succeeds, either temporarily or permanently, to his office, such officer shall be competent to exercise all the powers and perform all the duties respectively conferred and imposed by this Act on such Commissioner or police officer, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-88">
          <num>88.</num>
          <heading>Licenses and permissions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-88.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any license or written permission granted under the provisions of this Act shall specify the period and locality for which and the conditions and restrictions subject to which, the same is granted, and shall be given under the signature of the competent authority and such fee shall be charged therefor, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-88.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any license or written permission granted under this Act may at any time be suspended or revoked by the competent authority, if any of the conditions or restrictions is infringed or evaded by the person to whom it has been granted, or if such person is convicted of any offence in any matter to which such license or permission relates.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-88.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any such license or written permission is suspended or revoked, or when the period for which the same was granted has expired, the person to whom the same was granted shall for all purposes of this Act, be deemed to be without a license or written permission until the order for suspending or revoking the same is cancelled, or until the same is renewed, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-88.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person to whom any such license or written permission has been granted, shall, while the same remains in force, at all reasonable times, produce the same, if so required by a police officer.</p>
              <p>Explanation. For the purpose of this section any such infringement or evasion by, or conviction of, a servant or other agent acting on behalf of the person to whom the license or written permission has been granted, shall be deemed to be infringement or evasion by, or as the case may be, conviction of the person to whom such license or written permission has been granted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-89">
          <num>89.</num>
          <heading>Public notices.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-89.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any public notice required to be given under any of the provisions of this Act shall be in writing under the signature of a competent authority and shall be published in the locality to be affected thereby, by affixing copies thereof in conspicuous public places, or by proclaiming the same with beat of drums, or by advertising the same in such local newspapers of English or regional language or Hindi as the said authority may deem fit, or by any two or more of these means or by any other means as it may think suitable:</p>
              <p>Provided that the competent authority may, on being satisfied that it is in public interest to bring any regulation into force with immediate effect, make such direction or regulation without previous publication.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-90">
          <num>90.</num>
          <heading>Consent of competent authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-90.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever under this Act, the doing or the omission to do anything or the validity of anything depends upon the consent, approval, declaration, opinion or satisfaction of a competent authority, a written document signed by a competent authority purporting to convey or set forth, such consent, approval, declaration, opinion or satisfaction, shall be sufficient evidence thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-91">
          <num>91.</num>
          <heading>Signature on notices.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-91.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every license, written permission, notice, or other document, not being a summons or warrant or search warrant, required by this Act, or by any rule made thereunder, to bear the signature of the competent authority, shall be deemed to be properly signed if it bears a facsimile of his signature stamped thereon.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-92">
          <num>92.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-92.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-92.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made, before the House of the State Legislature, while it is in session. If the House agrees in making any modification in the rule or the House agrees that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-93">
          <num>93.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-93.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, as it deems necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-93.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notification issued under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-94">
          <num>94.</num>
          <heading>Power to try cases summarily.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-94.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974), all offences under this Act shall be bailable and non cognizable and be tried in a summary way by Judicial Magistrate of the first class specially empowered in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-95">
          <num>95.</num>
          <heading>Provisions of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 to apply to this Act.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-95.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974), shall apply, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-96">
          <num>96.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-96.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Police Act, 1861 (Act 5 of 1861), in its application to the State of Haryana, is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-96.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken or any proceeding instituted under the Act so repealed and the rules made thereunder, shall be deemed to have been done or taken or instituted under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-96.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All references in any enactments to any of the provisions of the Act so repealed shall be construed a reference to the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-96.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Punjab Police Rules framed under the Police Act, 1861 (Act 5 of 1861), as applicable to the State of Haryana, shall be deemed to have been framed under this Act till new rules are framed under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
