<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1952/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Punjab Habitual Offenders (Control And Reform) Act, 1952"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Punjab Habitual Offenders (Control And Reform) Act, 1952</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 12 of 1952]</p>
        <p>[August 19, 1952]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for registration of habitual offenders in the State of Punjab and for imposing certain restrictions on them.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to make provision for the registration of habitual offenders and for imposing certain restrictions on them; it is hereby enacted as follows:­</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Punjab Habitual Offenders (Control and Reform) Act, 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall extend to whole of the State of Punjab.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the 31st day of August, 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Code” means the Code of Criminal Procedure (Act V of 1898).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Government” means the Government of Punjab.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“Habitual Offender” means a person –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>who, during any continuous period of five years, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment more than twice on account of any one or more of the offences mentioned in the Schedule to this Act committed on different occasions and not constituting parts of the same transaction; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>who has, as a result of such convictions suffered imprisonments at least for a total period of twelve months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation (1) A conviction which has been set aside in appeal or revision and any imprisonment suffered in connection therewith shall not be taken into account for the above purpose.</p>
            <p>Explanation (2) In computing the period of five years, and periods spent in jail either under a sentence of imprisonment or under detention shall not be taken into account.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Registered person” means a person registered under this Act, as a habitual offender.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Words and expressions used but not defined in this Act shall have the meanings assigned to them in the Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Registration of habitual offenders.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may direct the District Magistrate to make or cause to be made a register of habitual offenders within his district.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions on registration.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person shall be registered under this Act, if more than six months have elapsed since the expiration of the sentence of imprisonment relating to his last conviction.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Procedure in making register.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Upon receiving a direction under Section 3, the District Magistrate shall –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>publish a notice in the prescribed manner calling upon habitual offender ­</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to appear at a time and place specified therein before the person appointed by him in this behalf,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to give to that person such information as may be necessary to enable him to complete the register, and cause a register of habitual offenders to be prepared:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that before entering the name of any person in such register the District Magistrate or an Executive Magistrate not below the rank of second class appointed by him in this behalf shall give him a reasonable opportunity to show­cause why such entry should not be made.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Change of register.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The register when made, shall be placed in the keeping of the Superintendent of Police of the district, who may from time to time report to the District Magistrate such alterations as ought in his opinion to be made therein by way of addition or erasure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Alteration in register.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the register has been placed in the keeping of the Superintendent of Police, and subject to the provisions of Section 8 no person’s name shall be added to the register, and no registration shall be cancelled except by, or under in writing of, the District Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Before the name of any person is added to the register under this section, the District Magistrate shall give notice in the prescribed manner to the person concerned –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to appear before him or any authority appointed by him in this behalf at a time and place therein specified;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to give to him or such authority such information as may be necessary to enable the entry to be made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>***</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that before adding the name of any person to such register, the District Magistrate or a person not below the rank of an Executive Magistrate of the second class appointed by him in his behalf shall give him a reasonable opportunity to show cause why such addition should not be made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Complaints of entry in register.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an entry made, or proposed to be made, in such register either when the register is first made or subsequently, may represent to the Commissioner of the Division against such entry, who shall retain such person’s name on the register or enter it therein or erase it there from, as he may think fit:</p>
            <p>Provided the Government shall be competent, either on its own motion or on an application made in this behalf by the aggrieved person to confirm, alter or rescind any order passed by the Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to take finger impressions, photograph and footprints at any time.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate or any officer appointed by him in this behalf may at any time order the finger impressions, photographs and footprints of any registered person to be taken.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Registered persons to report themselves or notify their place of residence.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The District Magistrate may in respect of any registered person give either one or both of the following directions, namely, that every such person shall in the prescribed manner -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>report himself at fixed intervals, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>notify his place of residence and any change or intended change of residence, and any absence or intended absence from his residence</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be for a term exceeding three years; nor shall it be made unless the necessity for making it has been established to the satisfaction of the District Magistrate, after an inquiry held by such authority and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a registered person in respect of whom the District Magistrate has issued a direction under sub-section (1) changes his place of residence to a district other than that in which he has been registered the provisions of this Act shall apply to him as if he had been registered in that district in pursuance of a direction made under Section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such registered person changes his place of residence to a district other than that in which he has been registered, the relevant entry in the register shall be transferred to the Superintendent of Police of that district.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to restrict movement of, or settle registered persons.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the Government considers that it is expedient that any registered person should be -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>restricted to any specified area, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>settled in any place of residence, tar Government may by notification in the official Gazette, declare that such person shall be restricted to the area specified in the notification or shall be settled in the place of of residence so specified, as the case may be:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no such declaration shall have effect for a period in excess of three years</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Before making any such declaration, the Government shall consider the following matters in an inquiry held by such authority and in such manner as may be prescribed ­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the nature and the circumstances of the offences in which the registered person is believed to have been concerned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>whether the registered person follows any lawful occupation, and whether such occupation is a real occupation or merely a pretence for the (i) purpose of facilitating the commission of crimes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the suitability of the restriction­area, or of the place of residence as the case may be, which it is proposed to specify in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the manner in which it is proposed that the person to be restricted or settled shall earn his livelihood within the restriction area or in the place of residence and the adequacy, of the arrangements which are proposed there for.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to vary specified area or place of settlement.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may by a like notification vary the terms of notification issued by it under Section 11 for the purposes of specifying another restriction area or another place of residence, as the case may be, any officer empowered in this behalf by Government, may, by order in writing, vary any notification made under Section 11 or under this section for the purposes of specifying another restriction area, or, as the case may be, another place of residence in the same district.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Verification of presence of registered persons within prescribed area or place of settlement.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every registered person whose movements have been restricted or who has been settled in a place of residence under the provision of this Act shall attend at such place and at such time and before such person as may be directed in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to place registered persons in settlements.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may establish industrial, agricultural, or reformatory settlements and schools and may order to be placed in such settlement or school any registered person:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made unless the necessity for making it has been established to the satisfaction of the Government after an inquiry held by such authority and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order under sub-section (1) shall be for a term exceeding five years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to discharge or transfer person from settlements or schools.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government or any officer authorised by it in this behalf may, at any time, by general or special order, direct any person who may be in any industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlement or school in the State -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to be discharged; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to be transferred to some other settlement or school in the State.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules to carry out the purposes and objects of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for or regulate:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form and contents of the register referred to in Section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the notice referred to in Section 5 shall be published and the means by which the persons whom it concerns, and the village headman, village watchman and landowners and occupiers of the village in which such persons reside, and the agents of such landowners or occupiers, shall be informed of its publication;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the addition of names to the register and the erasure of names therein and the mode in which the notice referred to in sub-section (2) of Section 7 shall be given;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which persons mentioned in Section 10 shall report themselves, or notify their residence or any change or intended change of residence or any absence or intended absence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the nature of the restrictions to be observed by persons whose movements have been restricted by notifications under Section 11 or Section 12;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the circumstances in which registered persons shall be required to possess and produce for inspection, certificates of identity and the manner in which such certificates shall be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conditions as to passes under which persons may be permitted to leave the place in which they are settled or restricted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <blockList id="section-16.2.list1.h.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the conditions to be inserted in any such pass in regard to:­</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-16.2.list1.h.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the places where the holder of the pass may go or reside;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-16.2.list1.h.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the persons before whom, from time to time, he shall be bound to report himself; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-16.2.list1.h.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>the time during which he may absent himself;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the place and time at which, and the persons before whom, registered persons shall report in accordance with the provisions of Section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the authority by whom and the manner in which the inquiry referred to in Section 14 shall be held;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the inspection of the residences and villages of any registered persons;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the terms upon which registered persons may be discharged from the operation of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the management, control and supervision of industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlements and schools;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the works, on which, and the hours during which, persons placed in an industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlement shall be employed, the rate at which they shall be paid, and the disposal, for the benefit of such persons, of the surplus proceeds of their labour; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the discipline to which persons endeavoring to escape from any industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlement or school, or otherwise offending against the rules for the time being in force shall be subject, the periodical visiting of such settlement or school and the removal from it of such persons as are considered expedient to be removed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Penalties for failure to comply with terms of notice under Section 5 or Section 7.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever, without lawful excuse, the burden of proving which shall lie upon him -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>fails to appear in compliance with a notice issued under Section 5, Section 7, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>intentionally omits to furnish any information required under either of those sections, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>when required to furnish information under either of those sections, furnishes as true any information which he knows or has reason to believe to be false, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>refuses to allow his finger­impressions, photographs and footprints to be taken by any person acting under an order passed under Section 9;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may be arrested without warrant, and shall on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Penalties for breach of rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any registered person who contravenes any rule, notice, direction or order made under this Act the breach of which is not otherwise provided for shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on a first conviction with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, or with both; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on any subsequent conviction, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who commits an offence made punishable by this section which is not a cognizable offence as defined in the Code may be arrested without a warrant by any officer in charge of a police station or by any police officer not below the rank of a sub­inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Arrest of registered person beyond prescribed limits.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a registered person is found outside the area or place of residence to which his movements have been restricted or in which he has been settled, in contravention of the conditions, under which he is permitted to leave such area, or who escapes from an industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlement or school in which he has been placed may be arrested without warrant by any police officer, village headman or village watchman, and shall be taken before Executive Magistrate, within 24 hours of such arrest, and the Executive Magistrate, on proof of the facts, shall order him to be removed to such area or place or to such settlement or school, as the case may be, there to be dealt with in accordance with this Act or any rules made there under.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rules for the time being in force for the removal of prisoners shall apply to all persons removed under this section or under any other provision of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that an order from the Government or from the Inspector General of Prisons shall not be necessary for the removal of such persons.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Duties to report arrival and departure.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person, authorised or appointed in this behalf, shall forthwith report to the officer in charge of the nearest police station the arrival or departure of -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a person who has failed to give information in answer to a notice under Section 5 of the Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a registered person under the Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for breach of such duties.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who fails to comply with the requirements of Section 20 shall be deemed to have committed an offence punishable under the first part of Section 176 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Saving from effect of repeal of the Criminal Tribes Act, 1924.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Criminal Tribes Act, 1924 (Act VI of 1924), every person who stood registered under that Act at the commencement of this Act and who is a habitual offender, as defined in sub-section (3) of Section 2 of this Act shall be deemed to be a registered person under this Act, provided that more than six months have not elapsed since the expiration of the sentence of imprisonment relating to his last conviction at the time of the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With respect to such persons as are referred to in the next preceding sub-section, all orders passed under Sections 10, 11 and 16 of the Criminal Tribes Act (VI of 1924) shall be deemed to have been passed under Sections 10, 11 and 14 of this Act, respectively.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All settlements established under the Criminal Tribes Act (VI of 1924) and existing at the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been established under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of courts in questions relating to certain notifications.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court shall question the competence of any authority making or issuing any notification, order or direction, under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Saving of certain orders.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall empower any authority to pass an order under Section 10 or Section 11 of this Act in respect of a person against whom an order under Section 565 of the Code or under the Restriction of Habitual Offenders (Punjab) Act, 1918 (Punjab Act V of 1918), is in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall be competent to pass an order under Restriction of Habitual Offenders (Punjab) Act, 1918 (Act V of 1918), or under section 565 of the Code, in regard to a person against whom any order under this Act is in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Saving of existing rules.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The rules framed under the Criminal Tribes Act (Act VI of 1924) shall continue in force in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, and shall so remain in force until they are replaced by rules framed under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1952/12"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1952/12/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <subsection id="schedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All offences mentioned in Chapter XII of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All offences punishable under the following sections of the Indian Penal Code.:­</p>
                <p>[302, 303, 304, 307, 311, 326, 327, 328, 329, 363, 364, 365, 366A, 366B, 368, 369, 376, 377, 379, 380, 381, 382, 384, 385, 386, 387, 392, 393, 394, 395, 396, 397, 398, 399, 400, 402, 409, 411, 412, 413, 414, 420, 449, 450, 454, 455, 456, 457, 458, 459 and 460]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any offence under section 3 of the Public Grabbing Act, 1867.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any offence under Essential Supplies (Temporary Powers) Act (Act No. XXIV of 1945), Rules and orders framed and issued thereunder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
