<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/55/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/55"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, 1969"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1969-12-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, 1969</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 55 OF 1969</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 29th December, 1969.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twentieth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the formation within the State of Assam of an  autonomous State to be known as Meghalaya and for matters  connected therewith.</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Assam Reorganisation (Meghalaya) Act, 1969.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:</p>
              <p>Provided that different dates  may be appointed for different  provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means such date  as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, appoint for the formation of the autonomous</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>State;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" article" means an article of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" autonomous State" means the autonomous State of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Meghalaya formed under section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" constituency" means a territorial constituency provided  by order made under section 12 for the purpose of  election to the Legislative Assembly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  appointed by the President under article 324;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Governor" means the Governor of Assam exercising his  functions as Governor in relation to Meghalaya by  virtue of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other  instrument, having immediately before the appointed  day, the force of law in the whole or in any part of  the autonomous State;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Legislative Assembly" means the Legislative Assembly of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Meghalaya;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" Meghalaya" means the autonomous State referred to in  section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Legislative Assembly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" Official Gazette" means the Official Gazette of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
                <listIntroduction>Meghalaya or the Gazette of India; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>FORMATION OF THE AUTONOMOUS STATE OF MEGHALAYA</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FORMATION OF THE AUTONOMOUS STATE OF MEGHALAYA</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Formation of Meghalaya.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the appointed day,</p>
              <p>there shall be formed within the State of Assam an autonomous State to  be known as Meghalaya which shall, subject to the provisions of sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>section (2), comprise the following tribal areas, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the United Khasi- Jaintia Hills District as described in  sub- paragraph (2) of paragraph 20 of the Sixth Schedule  to the Constitution (exclusive of the proviso thereto)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>but excluding the areas transferred to the Mikir Hills  autonomous district by the notification of the</p>
              <p>Government of Assam No. TAD R 31 50 149 dated the 13th</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list7">
                <listIntroduction>April, 1951, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list7.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Garo Hills District specified in Part A of the  table appended to paragraph 20 aforesaid.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, before such date as the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, fix for the purpose not being a  date later than the appointed day, the District Council for the  autonomous district of the North Cachar Hills or the Mikir Hills or  both, as the case may be, has or have by resolution passed by a  majority of not less than two- thirds of the members thereof, expressed  a desire that the said autonomous district or districts shall form  part of Meghalaya, the President may, by order, make a declaration to  that effect and accordingly, on and from the appointed day, the North</p>
              <p>Cachar Hills District or the Mikir Hills District or both, as the case  may be, shall also form part of Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Executive power of Meghalaya.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The executive power of</p>
              <p>Meghalaya shall be vested in the Governor and shall be exercised by  him either directly or through officers subordinate to him in  accordance with this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this section shall--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be deemed to transfer to the Governor any functions  conferred by any existing law on any other authority;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>prevent Parliament or the Legislature of the State of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Assam or Meghalaya from conferring by law functions on  any authority subordinate to the Governor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Extent of executive power of Meghalaya.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act, the executive power of Meghalaya shall extend  to the matters with respect to which the Legislature of Meghalaya has  power to make laws:</p>
              <p>Provided that in any matter with respect to which the Legislature  of Meghalaya, the Legislature of the State of Assam and Parliament  have power to make laws, the executive power of Meghalaya shall be  subject to, and limited by, the executive power expressly conferred by  this Act or by any law made by Parliament upon the Union or the State  of Assam or the authorities thereof or, as the case may be, by the</p>
              <p>Legislature of the State of Assam upon the State of Assam or  authorities thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the appointed day, the executive power of the</p>
              <p>State of Assam shall not extend, in relation to Meghalaya, to the  matters with respect to which the Legislature of Meghalaya has  exclusive power to make laws under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that, save  as otherwise provided in this Act, the executive power of the State of</p>
              <p>Assam shall, in relation to Meghalaya, continue to extend to the  matters with respect to which the Legislature of Meghalaya has no  power to make laws.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Council of Ministers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be a Council of</p>
              <p>Ministers with the Chief Minister at the head to aid and advise the</p>
              <p>Governor in the exercise of his functions in relation to Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The question whether any, and if so, what, advice was  tendered by Ministers to the Governor shall not be inquired into in  any court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Other provisions as to Ministers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Minister shall  be appointed by the Governor and the other Ministers shall be  appointed by the Governor on the advice of the Chief Minister, and the</p>
              <p>Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the Governor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council of Ministers shall be collectively responsible to  the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before a Minister enters upon his office, the Governor shall  administer to him the oaths of office and of secrecy according to the  form set out for this purpose in the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Minister who for any period of six consecutive months is  not a member of the Legislative Assembly shall at the expiration of  that period cease to be a Minister.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances of Ministers shall be such as the</p>
              <p>Legislature of Meghalaya may from time to time by law determine and,</p>
              <p>until the Legislature so determines, shall be determined by the</p>
              <p>Governor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Advocate- General for Meghalaya.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor may, if he  thinks fit to do so, appoint a person who is qualified to be appointed  a Judge of a High Court to be Advocate- General for Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the Advocate- General to give advice  to the Government of Meghalaya upon such legal matters, and to perform  such other duties of a legal character as may, from time to time, be  referred or assigned to him by the Governor, and to discharge the  functions conferred on him by or under this Act or any other law for  the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Advocate- General shall hold office during the pleasure of  the Governor, and shall receive such remuneration as the Governor may  determine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Conduct of business.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All executive action of the</p>
              <p>Government of Meghalaya shall be expressed to be taken in the name of  the Governor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Orders and other instruments made and executed in the name of  the Governor shall be authenticated in such manner as may be specified  in rules to be made by the Governor, and the validity of an order or  instrument which is so authenticated shall not be called in question  on the ground that it is not an order or instrument made or executed  by the Governor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor shall make rules for the more convenient  transaction of the business of the Government of Meghalaya and for the  allocation among Ministers of the said business.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Chief Minister as respects the furnishing of  information to Governor, etc. It shall be the duty of the Chief</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Minister of Meghalaya--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to communicate to the Governor all decisions of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Council of Ministers relating to the administration of  the affairs of Meghalaya and proposals for legislation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to furnish such information relating to the  administration of the affairs of Meghalaya and  proposals for legislation as the Governor may call for;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if the Governor so requires, to submit for the  consideration of the Council of Ministers any matter on  which a decision has been taken by a Minister but which  has not been considered by the Council.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>THE LEGISLATURE</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE LEGISLATURE</p>
            <p>General</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Legislature of Meghalaya.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall  be a Legislature for Meghalaya which shall consist of the Governor and  the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly to be  filled by persons chosen by direct election from constituencies in</p>
              <p>Meghalaya shall be fixed by the Central Government by notification in  the Official Gazette after consultation with the Election Commission,</p>
              <p>but shall not be less than thirty- five or more than fifty- five.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor may, if he is of opinion that any minority  communities in Meghalaya need representation in the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly and are not adequately represented therein, nominate not more  than three members of such communities, not being persons in the  service of the Government, to the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Delimitation of constituencies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Election Commission  shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute the total number of  seats in the Legislative Assembly as fixed under sub- section (2) of  section 11 to single member constituencies and delimit them on the  basis of the latest census figures having regard to the following  provisions, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, consist  of geographically compact areas, and in delimiting  them, regard shall be had to the physical features,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>existing boundaries of administrative units, facilities  of communication and public convenience;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>every constituency shall be so delimited as to fall only  within an Assembly constituency of the Legislative</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly of the State of Assam;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the population of each constituency shall, as far as  practicable, be the same throughout Meghalaya.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of assisting the Election Commission in the  performance of its functions under this section, the Commission shall  associate with itself such number of associate members not exceeding  five as the Governor may nominate to represent Meghalaya:</p>
              <p>Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to  vote or to sign any decision of the Election Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate  member falls vacant, it shall be filled as soon as may be practicable  by the Governor in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>publish its proposals for the delimitation of  constituencies, together with the dissenting proposals,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-12.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>if any, of any associate member who desires publication  thereof, in the Official Gazette and in such other  manner as the Commission may consider fit, together  with a notice inviting objections and suggestions in  relation to the proposals and specifying a date on or  after which the proposals will be further considered by  it;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.4.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have  been received by it before the date so specified, and  for the purpose of such consideration hold one or more  public sittings at such place or places as it may think  fit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.4.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>after considering all objections and suggestions which  may have been received by it before the date so  specified, determine by one or more orders the  delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or  orders to be published in the Official Gazette; and  upon such publication, the order or orders shall have  the full force of law and shall not be called in  question in any court.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As soon as may be after such publication, every such order  shall be laid before the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon the completion of each census, the total number of seats  in the Legislative Assembly and the division of Meghalaya into  territorial constituencies shall be readjusted by such authority and  in such manner as Parliament may by law determine:</p>
              <p>Provided that such readjustment shall not affect representation  in the Legislative Assembly until the dissolution of the then existing</p>
              <p>Assembly.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- In this section," latest census figures" means the  census figures with respect to Meghalaya ascertainable from the latest  census of which the finally published figures are available.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Power of Election Commission to maintain delimitation orders  up- to- date.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>correct any printing mistake in any order made under  section 12 or any error arising therein from  inadvertent slip or omission;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division  mentioned in any such order are or is altered, make  such amendments as appear to it to be necessary or  expedient for bringing such order up- to- date.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notification under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is issued, before the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Electors and electoral rolls.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The persons entitled to  vote at an election of members shall be the persons entitled by virtue  of the provisions of the Constitution and the Representation of the</p>
              <p>People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950), to be registered as voters at elections  to the House of the People.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The electoral roll for every constituency shall consist of so  much of the electoral roll for an Assembly constituency of the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of the State of Assam as relates to the areas  comprised within each such constituency and it shall not be necessary  to prepare or revise separately the electoral roll for any such  constituency.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Right to vote. Every person, whose name is for the time being  entered in the electoral roll for a constituency, shall be entitled to  vote at the election of a member from that constituency.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Qualification for membership. A person shall not be qualified  to be chosen to fill a seat in the Legislative Assembly unless he--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is a citizen of India and makes and subscribes before  some person authorised in that behalf by the Election</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Commission an oath or affirmation according to the form  set out for the purpose in the First Schedule;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is not less than twenty- five years of age; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is an elector in any constituency in Meghalaya.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Election to the Legislative Assembly. The provisions of Part</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>I, Chapters III and IV of Part II and Parts III to XI of the</p>
              <p>Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951), and of any rules  and orders made thereunder for the time being in force, shall apply to  and in relation to the elections to the Legislative Assembly of</p>
              <p>Meghalaya as they apply to and in relation to an election to the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of a State, subject to such modifications as the</p>
              <p>President may, after consultation with the Election Commission, by  order, direct.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Duration of Legislative Assembly. The Legislative Assembly,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>unless sooner dissolved, shall continue for five years from the date  appointed for its first meeting and no longer, and the expiration of  the said period of five years shall operate as a dissolution of the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly:</p>
              <p>Provided that the said period may, while a Proclamation of</p>
              <p>Emergency issued under clause (1) of article 352 is in operation, be  extended by Parliament by law for a period not exceeding one year at a  time and not extending in any case beyond a period of six months after  the Proclamation has ceased to operate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Sessions of Legislative Assembly, prorogation and  dissolution.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor shall, from time to time, summon the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit,</p>
              <p>but six months shall not intervene between its last sitting in one  session and the date appointed for its first sitting in the next  session.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Governor may, from time to time,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>prorogue the Legislative Assembly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>dissolve the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Right of Governor to address and send messages to Legislative</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor may address the Legislative Assembly and  may for that purpose require the attendance of members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor may send messages to the Legislative Assembly,</p>
              <p>whether with respect to a Bill then pending in the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly or otherwise and when a message is so sent, the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly shall with all convenient despatch consider any matter  required by the message to be taken into consideration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Special address by the Governor.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At the commencement of  the first session after each general election to the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly and at the commencement of the first session of each year,</p>
              <p>the Governor shall address the Legislative Assembly and inform the</p>
              <p>Assembly of the causes of its summons.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provision shall be made by the rules regulating the procedure  of the Legislative Assembly for the allotment of time for discussion  of the matters referred to in such address.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Rights of Ministers as respects Legislative Assembly. Every</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Minister and the Advocate- General for Meghalaya shall have the right  to speak in, and otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly, and to speak in, and otherwise to take part in  the proceedings of, any committee of the Legislative Assembly of which  he may be named a member, but shall not, by virtue of this section, be  entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Speaker and Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution  for his removal from office is under consideration.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any sitting  of the Legislative Assembly, while any resolution for the removal of  the Speaker from his office is under consideration, the Speaker, or,</p>
              <p>while any resolution for the removal of the Deputy Speaker from his  office is under consideration, the Deputy Speaker, shall not, though  he is present, preside, and the provisions of sub- section (4) of  section 23 shall apply in relation to every such sitting as they apply  in relation to a sitting from which the Speaker or, as the case may  be, the Deputy Speaker is absent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Speaker shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise  to take part in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly while any  resolution for his removal from office is under consideration in the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly and shall, notwithstanding anything in section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, be entitled to vote only in the first instance on such resolution  or on any other matter during such proceedings but not in the case of  an equality of votes.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Secretariat of Legislative Assembly.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly shall have a separate secretarial staff.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislature of Meghalaya may by law regulate the  recruitment, and the conditions of service of persons appointed, to  the secretarial staff of the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until provision is made by the Legislature of Meghalaya under  sub- section (2), the Governor may, after consultation with the Speaker  of the Legislative Assembly, make rules regulating the recruitment,</p>
              <p>and the conditions of service of persons appointed, to the secretarial  staff of the Legislative Assembly, and any rules so made shall have  effect subject to the provisions of any law made under the said sub-</p>
              <p>section.</p>
              <p>Conduct of business</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Voting in Assembly, power of Assembly to act notwithstanding  vacancies and quorum.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all  questions at any sitting of the Legislative Assembly shall be  determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting  other than the Speaker or person acting as such.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Speaker or person acting as such shall not vote in the  first instance, but shall have and exercise a casting vote in the case  of an equality of votes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly shall have power to act  notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership thereof, and any  proceedings in the Legislative Assembly shall be valid notwithstanding  that it is discovered subsequently that some person who was not  entitled so to do sat or voted or otherwise took part in the  proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until the Legislature of Meghalaya by law otherwise provides,</p>
              <p>the quorum to constitute a meeting of the Legislative Assembly shall  be ten members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at any time during a meeting of the Legislative Assembly  there is no quorum, it shall be the duty of the Speaker or person  acting as such either to adjourn the Assembly or suspend the meeting  until there is a quorum.</p>
              <p>Disqualifications of members</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications for membership.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall be  disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he holds any office of profit under the Government of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>India or the Government of any State or the Government  of Meghalaya other than an office declared by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Legislature of Meghalaya by law not to disqualify its  holder;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a  competent court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>if he is not a citizen of India, or has voluntarily  acquired the citizenship of a foreign State or is under  any acknowledgment of allegiance or adherence to a  foreign State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>if he is disqualified by or under any of the provisions  of Chapter III of Part II of the Representation of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951), as applied to and in  relation to the Legislative Assembly by section 17.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of this section, a person shall not be deemed  to hold an office of profit under the Government of India or the</p>
              <p>Government of any State or the Government of Meghalaya by reason only,</p>
              <p>that he is a Minister either for the Union or for such State or for</p>
              <p>Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises as to whether a member has become  disqualified for being such a member under the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1), the question shall be referred for the decision of the</p>
              <p>Governor and his decision shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before giving any decision on any such question, the Governor  shall obtain the opinion of the Election Commission and shall act  according to such opinion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for sitting and voting before making an oath or  affirmation or when not qualified or when disqualified. If a person  sits or votes as a member of the Legislative Assembly before he has  complied with the requirements of section 26, or when he knows that he  is not qualified or that he is disqualified for membership thereof, or  that he is prohibited from so doing by the provisions of any law made  by Parliament or the Legislature of Meghalaya, he shall be liable in  respect of each day on which he so sits or votes, to a penalty of five  hundred rupees to be recovered as a debt due to Meghalaya.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Powers, privileges, etc., of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act and to the rules and standing orders regulating  the procedure of the Legislature of Meghalaya, there shall be freedom  of speech in the Legislative Assembly of Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No member of the Legislative Assembly of Meghalaya shall be  liable to any proceedings in any court in respect of anything said or  any vote given by him in the Assembly or any committee thereof, and no  person shall be so liable in respect of the publication by or under  the authority of the Assembly of any report, paper, votes or  proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In other respects, the powers, privileges and immunities of  the Legislative Assembly and of the members and the committees thereof  shall be such as may from time to time be defined by the Legislature  of meghalaya by law, and until so defined, shall be those for the time  being enjoyed by the House of the People and its members and  committees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall apply  in relation to persons who by virtue of this Act have the right to  speak in, or otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly or any committee thereof as they apply in  relation to members of that Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Salaries and allowances of members. Members of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assembly shall be entitled to receive such salaries and  allowances as may from time to time be determined by the Legislature  of Meghalaya by law and, until provision in that respect is so made,</p>
              <p>such salaries and allowances as the Governor may, by order, determine.</p>
              <p>Legislative powers and procedure</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from taxation of properties of the Union and the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State of Assam and of certain vehicles registered in Assam or</p>
              <p>Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The property of the Union shall, save in so far as</p>
              <p>Parliament may, by law, otherwise provide, be exempt from all taxes  imposed by Meghalaya or by any authority within Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall, until Parliament by law  otherwise provides, prevent any authority within Meghalaya from  levying any tax on any property of the Union to which such property  was immediately before the commencement of this Act liable or treated  as liable so long as that tax continues to be levied in Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The property of the State of Assam shall, so long as the  property of Meghalaya in the rest of Assam is exempt from taxes  imposed by the Government of Assam or by any authority within the</p>
              <p>State of Assam, be exempt from all taxes imposed by Meghalaya or by  any authority within Meghalaya.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No vehicle registered at any place in the State of Assam, not  being a place in Meghalaya, and transiting through Meghalaya shall be  liable to any tax under any law enacted by the Legislature of</p>
              <p>Meghalaya so long as any vehicle registered at any place in Meghalaya  and transiting through the territory of Assam (not comprised in</p>
              <p>Meghalaya) is exempt from payment of any tax under any law enacted by  the Legislature of the State of Assam.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Inconsistency between laws made by Parliament and laws made  by the Legislature of Meghalaya.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any provision of a law made by  the Legislature of Meghalaya is repugnant to any provision of a law  made by Parliament which Parliament is competent to enact, or to any  provision of any existing law with respect to one of the matters  enumerated in the Concurrent List in the Seventh Schedule to the</p>
              <p>Constitution, then, subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the  law made by Parliament, whether passed before or after the law made by  the Legislature of Meghalaya, or, as the case may be, the existing  law, shall prevail and the law made by the Legislature of Meghalaya  shall, to the extent of the repugnancy, be void.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a law made by the Legislature of Meghalaya with respect  to one of the matters enumerated in the Concurrent List in the Seventh</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/55/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/55"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Constitution, which the Legislature of Meghalaya is  competent to enact under this Act contains any provision repugnant to  the provisions of an earlier law made by Parliament or an existing law  with respect to that matter, then, the law so made by the Legislature  of Meghalaya shall, if it has been reserved for the consideration of  the President and has received his assent, prevail in Meghalaya:"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/55/eng@1969-12-29"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <paragraph id="scheduleto.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall prevent</p>
                <p>Parliament from enacting at any time any law with respect to the same  matter, including a law adding to, amending, varying or repealing the  law so made by the Legislature of Meghalaya.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>Inconsistency between laws made by the Legislature of the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>State of Assam and laws made by the Legislature of Meghalaya. Where a  law made by the Legislature of Meghalaya with respect to one of the  matters enumerated in Part C of the Second Schedule contains any  provision repugnant to the provision of an earlier law made by the</p>
                  <p>Legislature of the State of Assam which that Legislature is competent  to enact, or to any provision of any existing law with respect to that  matter, then, the law so made by the Legislature of Meghalaya shall,</p>
                  <p>to the extent of the repugnancy, be void unless the law has received  assent under section 39 after the Governor has obtained the advice of  the Chief Minister of Assam:</p>
                  <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall prevent the</p>
                  <p>Legislature of the State of Assam from enacting at any time any law  with respect to the same matter including a law adding to, amending,</p>
                  <p>varying or repealing the law so made by the Legislature of Meghalaya.</p>
                  <p>Explanation 1.-- In this section and in sections 35 and 59,</p>
                  <p>" existing law" means any law, ordinance, order, bye- law, rule or  regulation passed or made before the appointed day by any Legislature,</p>
                  <p>authority or person having power to make such a law, ordinance, order,</p>
                  <p>bye- law, rule or regulation.</p>
                  <p>Explanation 2.-- In this section and in sections 39 and 50, the  reference to the advice of the Chief Minister of Assam shall, while a</p>
                  <p>Proclamation issued in relation to the State of Assam under clause (1)</p>
                  <p>of article 356 of the Constitution is in operation, be construed as a  reference to the instructions from the President.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>Special provisions as to financial Bills.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-37.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill or  amendment shall not be introduced into, or moved in, the Legislative</p>
                  <p>Assembly except on the recommendation of the Governor if such Bill or  amendment makes provisions dealing with any of the following matters,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-37.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-37.1.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the imposition, abolition, remission, alteration or  regulation of any tax;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-37.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the regulation of the borrowing of money or the giving  of any guarantee by Meghalaya, or the amendment of the  law with respect to any financial obligations  undertaken or to be undertaken by Meghalaya;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-37.1.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the custody of the Consolidated Fund or the Contingency</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-37.1.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>Fund of Meghalaya, the payment of moneys into, or  withdrawal of moneys from, any such Fund.</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-37.1.list5.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund  of Meghalaya;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-37.1.list5.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the declaring of any expenditure to be expenditure  charged on the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya, or the  increasing of the amount of any such expenditure;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-37.1.list5.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund  of Meghalaya or the public account of Meghalaya or the  custody or issue of such money:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that no recommendation shall be required under this sub-</p>
                  <p>section for the moving of an amendment making provision for the  reduction or abolition of any tax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-37.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill or amendment shall not be deemed to make provision for  any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) by reason only that it  provides for the imposition of fines or other pecuniary penalties, or  for the demand or payment of fees for licences or fees for services  rendered, or by reason that it provides for the imposition, abolition,</p>
                  <p>remission, alteration or regulation of any tax by any local authority  or body for local purposes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-37.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill, which, if enacted and brought into operation, would  involve expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya, shall not  be passed by the Legislative Assembly unless the Governor has  recommended to the Assembly the consideration of the Bill.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>Procedure as to lapsing of Bills. A Bill pending in the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Legislative Assembly shall not lapse by reason of the prorogation of  the Assembly, but shall lapse on a dissolution thereof.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Assent to Bills. When a Bill has been passed by the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Legislative Assembly, it shall be presented to the Governor and the</p>
                  <p>Governor shall declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he  withholds assent therefrom or that he reserves the Bill for the  consideration of the President:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Governor may, as soon as possible after the  presentation to him of the Bill for assent, return the Bill if it is  not a Money Bill together with a message requesting that the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-39.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly will reconsider the Bill or any specified  provisions thereof and, in particular, will consider the desirability  of introducing any such amendments as he may recommend in his message  and, when a Bill is so returned, the Legislative Assembly shall  reconsider the Bill accordingly, and if the Bill is passed again by  the Assembly with or without amendment and presented to the Governor  for assent, the Governor shall not--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>give assent in the case of a Bill containing provisions  of the nature referred to in section 36 except after  obtaining the advice of the Chief Minister of Assam;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>withhold assent in the case of any other Bill.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 40, a</p>
                  <p>Bill shall be deemed to be a Money Bill if it contains only provisions  dealing with all or any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) of  section 37 or any matter incidental to any of those matters and there  is endorsed thereon the certificate of the Speaker of the Legislative</p>
                  <p>Assembly signed by him that it is a Money Bill:</p>
                  <p>Provided that a Bill shall not be deemed to be a Money Bill by  reason only that it provides for the imposition of fines or other  pecuniary penalties, or for the demand or payment of fees for licences  or fees for services rendered or by reason that it provides for the  imposition, abolition, remission, alteration or regulation of any tax  by any local authority or body for local purposes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Bills reserved for consideration. When a Bill is reserved by  the Governor for the consideration of the President, the President  shall declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he withholds  assent therefrom:</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Provided that where the Bill is not a Money Bill, the President  may direct the Governor to return the Bill to the Legislative Assembly  together with such a message as is referred to in section 39, and when  a Bill is so returned, the Legislative Assembly shall reconsider it  accordingly within a period of six months from the date of receipt of  such message, and if it is again passed by the Legislative Assembly  with or without amendment, it shall be presented again to the</p>
                  <p>President for his consideration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-41">
              <num>41.</num>
              <heading>Requirements as to sanction and recommendation to be regarded  as matters of procedure only. No Act of the Legislature of Meghalaya  and no provision in any such Act shall be invalid by reason only that  some recommendation or previous sanction required by the Constitution  or this Act was not given, if assent to that Act was given--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>where the recommendation required was that of the Governor,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>either by the Governor or by the President;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where the recommendation or previous sanction required was  that of the President, by the President.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Procedure in financial matters</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>Procedure in Legislative Assembly with respect to estimates.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-43.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>So much of the estimates as relates to expenditure charged upon  the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya shall not be submitted to the vote  of the Legislative Assembly, but nothing in this sub- section shall be  construed as preventing the discussion in the Legislative Assembly of  any of those estimates.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>So much of the said estimates as relates to other expenditure  shall be submitted in the form of demands for grants to the</p>
                  <p>Legislative Assembly, and the Legislative Assembly shall have power to  assent, or to refuse to assent, to any demand, or to assent to any  demand subject to a reduction of the amount specified therein.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No demand for a grant shall be made except on the  recommendation of the Governor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44">
              <num>44.</num>
              <heading>Appropriation Bills.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-44.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>As soon as may be after the grants  under section 43 have been made by the Legislative Assembly, there  shall be introduced a Bill to provide for the appropriation out of the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-44.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya of all moneys required to meet--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-44.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the grants so made by the Legislative Assembly; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-44.1.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Meghalaya, but not exceeding in any case the amount  shown in the statement previously laid before the</p>
                  <p>Assembly.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-44.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No amendment shall be proposed to any such Bill in the</p>
                  <p>Legislative Assembly which will have the effect of varying the amount  or altering the destination of any grant so made or of varying the  amount of any expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of</p>
                  <p>Meghalaya, and the decision of the person presiding as to whether an  amendment is inadmissible under this sub- section shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-44.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the provisions of sections 45 and 46, no money  shall be withdrawn from the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya except  under appropriation made by law passed in accordance with the  provisions of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-45">
              <num>45.</num>
              <heading>Supplementary, additional or excess grants.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-45.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-45.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Governor  shall,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-45.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>if the amount authorised by any law made in accordance  with the provisions of section 44 to be expended for a  particular service for the current financial year is  found to be insufficient for the purposes of that year  or when a need has arisen during the current financial  year for supplementary or additional expenditure upon  some new service not contemplated in the annual  financial statement for that year, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-45.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>if any money has been spent on any service during a  financial year in excess of the amount granted for that  service and for that year,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>cause to be laid before the Legislative Assembly another statement  showing the estimated amount of that expenditure or cause to be  presented to the Legislative Assembly a demand for such excess, as the  case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-45.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of sections 42, 43 and 44 shall have effect in  relation to any such statement and expenditure or demand and also to  any law to be made authorising the appropriation of moneys out of the</p>
                  <p>Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya to meet such expenditure or the grant  in respect of such demand as they have effect in relation to the  annual financial statement and the expenditure mentioned therein or to  a demand for a grant and the law to be made for the authorisation of  appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya to  meet such expenditure or grant.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-46">
              <num>46.</num>
              <heading>Votes on Account and exceptional grant.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-46.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding  anything in the foregoing provisions of this Part, the Legislative</p>
                  <blockList id="section-46.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Assembly shall have power--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-46.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>to make any grant in advance in respect of the estimated  expenditure for a part of any financial year pending  the completion of the procedure prescribed in section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>for the voting of such grant and the passing of the  law in accordance with the provisions of section 44 in  relation to that expenditure;</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-43.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to make a grant for meeting an unexpected demand upon  the resources of the autonomous State when on account  of the magnitude or the indefinite character of the  service the demand cannot be stated with the details  ordinarily given in an annual financial statement;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>to make an exceptional grant which forms no part of the  current service of any financial year;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>and the Legislature of Meghalaya shall have power to authorise by law  the withdrawal of moneys from the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya for  the purpose for which the said grants are made.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-43.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of sections 43 and 44 shall have effect in  relation to the making of any grant under sub- section (1) and to any  law to be made under that sub- section, as they have effect in relation  to the making of a grant with regard to any expenditure mentioned in  the annual financial statement and the law to be made for the  authorisation of appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund  of Meghalaya to meet such expenditure.</p>
                  <p>Procedure generally</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-48">
              <num>48.</num>
              <heading>Restrictions on discussion in the Legislative Assembly. No  discussion shall take place in the Legislative Assembly with respect  to the conduct of any Judge of the Supreme Court, or of a High Court,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>in the discharge of his duties.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-49">
              <num>49.</num>
              <heading>Courts not to enquire into the proceedings of Legislative</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Assembly.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-49.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The validity of any proceedings in the Legislative</p>
                  <p>Assembly shall not be called in question on the ground of any alleged  irregularity of procedure.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-49.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No officer or member of the Legislative Assembly in whom  powers are vested by or under this Act for regulating procedure or the  conduct of business or for maintaining order, in the Legislative</p>
                  <p>Assembly shall be subject to the jurisdiction of any court in respect  of the exercise by him of those powers.</p>
                  <p>Legislative power of the Governor</p>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>FINANCIAL PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <part id="part-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>FINANCIAL PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Consolidated Fund.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-51.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the provisions of section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, all revenue received by the Government of Meghalaya, all loans  raised by that Government by the issue of treasury bills, loans or  ways and means advances and all moneys received by that Government in  repayment of loans shall form one consolidated fund to be entitled</p>
                    <p>" the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya".</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-52.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All other public moneys received by or on behalf of the</p>
                    <p>Government of Meghalaya shall be credited to the public account of</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-52.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya shall be  appropriated except in accordance with law and for the purposes and in  the manner provided in this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading>Contingency Fund. The Legislature of Meghalaya may, by law,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>establish a Contingency Fund in the nature of an imprest to be  entitled" the Contingency Fund of Meghalaya" into which shall be paid  from time to time such sums as may be determined by such law, and the  said Fund shall be placed at the disposal of the Governor to enable  advances to be made by him out of such Fund for the purposes of  meeting unforeseen expenditure pending authorisation of such  expenditure by the Legislature of Meghalaya by law under section 45 or  section 46.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-53">
                <num>53.</num>
                <heading>Custody of suitors' deposits and other moneys received by  public servants and courts. All moneys received by or deposited with--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-53.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-53.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any officer employed in connection with the affairs of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-53.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Meghalaya in his capacity as such, other than revenues  or public moneys raised or received by the Government  of Meghalaya, or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-53.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any court within Meghalaya to the credit of any cause,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>matter, account or persons,</p>
                    <p>shall be paid into the public account of Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-54">
                <num>54.</num>
                <heading>Custody, etc., of Consolidated Fund, Contingency Fund and  moneys credited to the public accounts. The custody of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund and the Contingency Fund of Meghalaya, the payment  of moneys into such Funds, the withdrawal of moneys therefrom, the  custody of public moneys other than those credited to such Funds  received by or on behalf of the Government of Meghalaya, their payment  into the public account of Meghalaya and the withdrawal of moneys from  such account and all other matters connected with or ancillary to  matters aforesaid shall be regulated by law made by the Legislature of</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, and, until provision in that behalf is so made, shall be  regulated by rules made by the Governor.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-55">
                <num>55.</num>
                <heading>Certain taxes levied by Assam to be appropriated by</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-55.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, any tax  on the consumption or sale of electricity relatable to entry 53 in the</p>
                    <p>State List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, and any tax on  the sale or purchase of goods relatable to entry 54 in the said List  levied by the Government of Assam shall be collected within Meghalaya  but not including any area comprised within the municipality of</p>
                    <p>Shillong by the Government of Meghalaya, and the proceeds in any  financial year of any such tax leviable within Meghalaya shall not  form part of the Consolidated Fund of Assam, but shall form part of  the Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-55.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where a tax relatable to entry 54 in the State List aforesaid  levied by the Government of Assam is collected by that Government at  the first point of sale or purchase of goods, such portion of the tax  so collected as may be agreed upon by the Governments of Assam and</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya or in default of such agreement, as the Central Government  may determine, shall be payable to Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-55.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The laws with respect to the taxes referred to in sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-55.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>shall have effect subject to such exceptions and modifications as  the Central Government may, by order, specify for the purpose of  giving effect to the provisions of that sub- section.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-56">
                <num>56.</num>
                <heading>Distribution of revenues.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-56.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The grants- in- aid under clause</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-56.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>of article 275 and the share of the taxes on income, the  distributable Union duties of excise, the additional duties of excise  on goods of special importance and estate duty payable to the State of</p>
                    <p>Assam under the constitution (Distribution of Revenues) Order, 1969,</p>
                    <p>the Union Duties of Excise (Distribution) Act, 1962 (3 of 1962), the</p>
                    <p>Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special Importance) Act, 1957</p>
                    <p>(58 of 1957), and the Estate Duty (Distribution) Act, 1962 (9 of</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1962">
                <num>1962.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1962.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>), shall be construed, as from the appointed day, as payable to  the State of Assam and the autonomous State of Meghalaya in such  proportion as the President may, by order, determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1962.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made by the President under sub- section (1) shall  be laid before Parliament as soon as may be after it is made.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-57">
                <num>57.</num>
                <heading>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly. The Governor may, at any time before the  appointed day, authorise such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund  of Meghalaya as he deems necessary for a period of not more than six  months beginning with the appointed day pending the sanction of that  expenditure by the Legislative Assembly:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Governor may, after the appointed day,</p>
                    <p>authorise such further expenditure as he deems necessary from the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of Meghalaya for any period not extending beyond the  said period of six months.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-58">
                <num>58.</num>
                <heading>Apportionment of assets and liabilities. The assets and  liabilities of the State of Assam immediately before the appointed day  shall be apportioned between that State and Meghalaya in accordance  with the provisions contained in the Third Schedule.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>ADMINISTRATIVE RELATIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ADMINISTRATIVE RELATIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-59">
                <num>59.</num>
                <heading>Obligation of Meghalaya, the State of Assam and the Union.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>The executive power of Meghalaya shall be so exercised as to ensure  compliance with the laws made by Parliament, the Legislature of the</p>
                    <p>State of Assam and any existing laws which apply in Meghalaya, and the  executive power of the Union and of the State of Assam shall extend to  the giving of such directions to Meghalaya as may appear to the</p>
                    <p>Government of India or the Government of Assam, as the case may be, to  be necessary for that purpose.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-60">
                <num>60.</num>
                <heading>Control over the autonomous State in certain cases. The  executive power of Meghalaya shall be so exercised as not to impede or  prejudice the exercise of the executive power of the Union or the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government of Assam, as the case may be, and the executive power of  the Union and the State of Assam shall extend to the giving of such  directions to Meghalaya as may appear to the Government of India or  the Government of Assam, as the case may be, to be necessary for that  purpose.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-61">
                <num>61.</num>
                <heading>Entrustment of functions. Notwithstanding anything in this</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-61.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Act,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-61.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the Government of Assam may, with the consent of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-61.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Government of Meghalaya, entrust either conditionally  or unconditionally to that Government or to its  officers functions in relation to any matter to which  the executive power of the State of Assam extends;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-61.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the Government of Meghalaya may, with the consent of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Government of Assam, entrust either conditionally or  unconditionally to that Government or to its officers  functions in relation to any matter to which the  executive power of Meghalaya extends.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-62">
                <num>62.</num>
                <heading>Provisions as to Provisional Legislative Assembly.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-62.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Until  the Legislative Assembly of Meghalaya has been duly constituted and  summoned to meet for the first session under the provisions of Part</p>
                    <p>III, there shall be a Provisional Legislative Assembly which shall  consist of not less than thirty- five and not more than fifty- five  persons as the Central Government may, after consultation with the</p>
                    <p>Election Commission, by order, determine, and such persons shall be  elected in the manner specified in sub- section (2).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-62.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the members of  the Provisional Legislative Assembly shall be elected in the following  manner, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-62.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>there shall be an electoral college for each autonomous  district within Meghalaya which shall consist of the  elected members of the District Council thereof, and  each electoral college shall elect such number of  persons to the Provisional Legislative Assembly as the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>President may, after consultation with the Election</p>
                    <blockList id="section-62.2.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Commission, by order, determine;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-62.2.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the election of members to the Provisional Legislative</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Assembly shall be in accordance with the system of  proportional representation by means of the single  transferable vote and shall be subject to such rules as  the Central Government may, after consultation with the</p>
                    <p>Election Commission, make in this behalf.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may nominate to the Provisional</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly not more than three persons, not being persons in  the service of the Government, to represent any minority communities  in Meghalaya which, in its opinion, need representation in the</p>
                    <p>Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No person shall be qualified to be chosen as a member of the</p>
                    <p>Provisional Legislative Assembly unless he is a person whose name is  for the time being entered in the electoral roll for so much of any  constituency of the Legislative Assembly of Assam as is comprised  within Meghalaya and is not less than twenty- five years of age.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If owing to death, resignation or otherwise, the office of a  member of the Provisional Legislative Assembly falls vacant, it may be  filled up as soon as practicable under and in accordance with the  foregoing provisions of this section.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The term of office of the members of the Provisional</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly shall expire immediately before the first meeting  of the Legislative Assembly duly constituted under this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.7">
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The election by the electoral college under this section  shall not be called in question on the ground merely of the existence  of a vacancy in the membership of any District Council forming part of  the electoral college.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.8">
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Provisional Legislative Assembly constituted under this  section shall, for so long it is in existence, be deemed to be the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly duly constituted under this act, and accordingly  the provisions of Part III shall, so far as may be, apply in relation  to the Provisional Legislative Assembly as they apply in relation to  the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VIII">
              <num>VIII</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VIII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-63">
                <num>63.</num>
                <heading>Special committee for development of Shillong. The Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government may, in consultation with the Governments of Assam and</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, by order, constitute a committee consisting of such number  of persons as it may think fit for advising the two Governments on  matters of common interest with respect to Shillong in the field of  education and water supply in particular, and with respect to its  development and administration in general.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this section, Shillong shall mean the areas  comprised within the cantonment and municipality of Shillong and  include such other areas adjoining the said cantonment or municipality  as may be agreed upon by the Governments of Assam and Meghalaya in  this behalf.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-64">
                <num>64.</num>
                <heading>Provisions as to continuance of courts. All courts and  tribunals and all authorities discharging lawful functions throughout</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Meghalaya or any part thereof immediately before the appointed day  shall, unless their continuance is inconsistent with the provisions of  this Act or until other provision is made by a competent authority,</p>
                    <p>continue to exercise their respective functions.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-65">
                <num>65.</num>
                <heading>Provisions relating to services.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-65.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every person who being a  member of an All- India Service is for the time being borne on the</p>
                    <p>Assam State Cadre of that Service or is otherwise serving in  connection with the affairs of the State of Assam as a member of class</p>
                    <p>I service of that State may be required by the Government of that</p>
                    <p>State to serve in connection with the affairs of Meghalaya for such  period or periods as the Government of Assam may, by order, direct:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-65.1.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that no such order shall be made--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list5.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>before the appointed day, except with the approval of  the Central Government; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list5.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>on or after the appointed day, except in accordance with  such rules as may be made by the Central Government  after consultation with the Governments of Assam and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to any general or special order which the Central</p>
                    <p>Government may make in this behalf, the control over any such person  as is referred to in sub- section (1) shall, for so long as he is  required to serve in connection with the affairs of Meghalaya, be  vested in the Government of Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Such persons serving in connection with the affairs of the</p>
                    <p>State of Assam immediately before the appointed day, not being a  person referred to in sub- section (1), as may be determined by  agreement between the Government of Assam and the Government of</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya or in default of agreement, by the Central Government, may,</p>
                    <p>notwithstanding anything in the terms of their appointments or their  conditions of service, be required to serve in connection with the  affairs of the autonomous State.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All previous service rendered by a person referred to in sub-</p>
                    <p>section (3) in connection with the affairs of the State of Assam shall  be deemed to have been rendered in connection with the affairs of the  autonomous State for the purposes of the rules regulating his  conditions of service.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Nothing in sub- sections (3) and (4) shall be deemed to affect  the power of the Legislature of Meghalaya or the Governor to determine  the conditions of service of persons serving in connection with the  affairs of Meghalaya:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately  before the appointed day to any person referred to in sub- section (3)</p>
                    <p>shall not be varied to his disadvantage except with the previous  approval of the Government of Assam.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-66">
                <num>66.</num>
                <heading>Continuance of existing laws and their adaptations.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-66.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All  laws in force immediately before the appointed day in the autonomous</p>
                    <p>State shall continue to be in force therein until altered, repealed or  amended by a competent legislature or other competent authority.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-66.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the purpose of facilitating the application in relation  to the autonomous State of any law made before the appointed day, the  appropriate Government may, within two years from that day, by order,</p>
                    <p>make such adaptations or modifications of the law, whether by way of  repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient and thereupon  every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations and  modifications so made until altered, repealed or amended by a  competent legislature or other competent authority.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate</p>
                    <p>Government" means as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated  in the Union List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, the</p>
                    <p>Central Government, as respects any law relating to a matter in the</p>
                    <p>Second Schedule, the Govern-</p>
                    <p>ment of Meghalaya, and, as respects any other law, the Government of</p>
                    <p>Assam.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-67">
                <num>67.</num>
                <heading>Autonomous State to be a State for certain purposes of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Constitution. Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act,</p>
                    <p>reference to a State (by whatever form of words) in any of the  following articles of the Constitution shall be construed as including  a reference to the autonomous State, namely:--</p>
                    <p>Articles 12 to 15 (inclusive),  except clause (3)</p>
                    <p>thereof], 18, 19, 23, 25, 28 to 31 (inclusive), 31A, 34  to 51 (inclusive), 58, 59, 66, 73, 102, 110 (1) (f),</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-131">
                <num>131.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-131.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, 138, 149, 150, 151, 161, 209, 210, 233, 234, 235,</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-237">
                <num>237.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-237.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, 251, 252, 256 to 258A (inclusive), 261, 262, 263,</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-268">
                <num>268.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-268.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, 269, 270, 272, 274, to 280 (inclusive), 282, 288,</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-289">
                <num>289.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-289.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-289.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>, 293, 296, 298 to 305 (inclusive), 308 to 311</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-289.paragraph-0.list1.inclusive">
                        <num>(inclusive)</num>
                        <p>, 320, 323 (2), 324 to 329 (inclusive), 339  to 342 (inclusive), 345 to 348 (inclusive), 350, 350A,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-350B">
                <num>350B.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-350B.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-350B.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>, 353, 355 to 358 (inclusive), 360, 361, 364 to 367</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-350B.paragraph-0.list1.inclusive">
                        <num>(inclusive)</num>
                        <p>.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Explanation.-- Reference in any of the articles above specified to  the High Court or to the State Public Service Commission shall be  construed as reference to the High Court of Assam or the Public</p>
                    <p>Service Commission of the State of Assam, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-68">
                <num>68.</num>
                <heading>Power of Governments of Assam and Meghalaya to carry on  trade, etc., in Meghalaya.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-68.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The executive power which the</p>
                    <p>Government of Assam may exercise under article 298 in Meghalaya for  the carrying on of any trade or business and for the acquisition,</p>
                    <p>holding and disposal of property and the making of contracts for any  purpose shall, in so far as such trade or business or such purpose is  not one with respect to which the Legislature of the State of Assam  may make laws, be subject to legislation by the Legislature of</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-68.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The executive power which the Government of Meghalaya may  exercise under article 298 in Meghalaya for the carrying on of any  trade or business and for the acquisition, holding and disposal of  property and the making of contracts for any purpose shall, in so far  as such trade or business or such purpose is not one with respect to  which the Legislature of Meghalaya may make laws, be subject also to  legislation by the Legislature of the State of Assam.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-69">
                <num>69.</num>
                <heading>Power to suspend provisions of this Act in case of failure of  constitutional machinery. Where a Proclamation is issued under article</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-356">
                <num>356.</num>
                <heading>in respect of Meghalaya, the President may, by the same</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-356.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Proclamation or a subsequent Proclamation varying it, suspend also, in  whole or in part, the operation of any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-70">
                <num>70.</num>
                <heading>Construction of references to" State" and" State Government"</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>in other laws in relation to Meghalaya. Without prejudice to the  provisions of sections 66 and 71 the Central Government may, after  consulting the Government of Assam, by notification in the Official</p>
                    <p>Gazette, declare that any reference to a" State" in a Central Act  specified in the notification shall, in its application to Meghalaya,</p>
                    <p>be construed as a reference to the whole or any part of Meghalaya and  any reference to" State Government" in a Central Act specified in the  notification shall in its application to Meghalaya be construed as a  reference to the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-71">
                <num>71.</num>
                <heading>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or  insufficient provision has been made under section 66 for the  adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal  or authority required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the  purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the autonomous</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-71.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>State, construe the law in such manner not affecting the substance as  may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court,</p>
                    <p>tribunal or authority, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-72">
                <num>72.</num>
                <heading>Effect of provisions of Act inconsistent with other laws. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-73">
                <num>73.</num>
                <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-73.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by  order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears  to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the  difficulty.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-73.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid before both</p>
                    <p>Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after it is made.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-74">
                <num>74.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of the Sixth Schedule. The Sixth Schedule in the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Constitution shall stand amended as specified in the Fourth Schedule.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-75">
                <num>75.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of Act 2 of 1934. In section 21A of the Reserve</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-75.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934), in sub- section 1, after the  words" any State", the brackets and words" (including the autonomous</p>
                    <p>State of Meghalaya)", shall be inserted.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-76">
                <num>76.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of Act 37 of 1956. In section 16 of the States</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-76.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Reorganisation Act, 1956 (37 of 1956), in sub- section 1, for clause</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>, the following clause shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-76.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>" (d) in the case of the Eastern Zone,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the Chief Minister and another Minister  of the autonomous State of Meghalaya to be  nominated by the Governor</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-76.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>of Assam and if there is no Council of Ministers  therein, not more than two members from the  autonomous State of Meghalaya to be nominated by  the President; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the person for the time being holding  the office of the Adviser to the Governor of Assam  for Tribal areas.".</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-77">
                <num>77.</num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-77.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-77.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
