<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tobacco Board Act, 1975"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/4/eng@1975-03-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/4/eng@1975-03-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1975-03-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/4/eng@1975-03-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/4/eng@1975-03-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tobacco Board Act, 1975</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 4 OF 1975</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th March, 1975.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the development under the control of the Union  of the tobacco industry.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Tobacco Board Act, 1975.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:</p>
              <p>Provided that different dates  may be appointed for different  provisions of this Act and for different States or different parts  thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is  hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Union should take under its control the tobacco industry.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Board" means the Tobacco Board established under  section 4:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Chairman" means Chairman of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" curing" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 1944), and all  its grammatical variations and cognate expressions  shall be construed accordingly;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" dealer" means a dealer in tobacco;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Executive Director" means the Executive Director  appointed under section 6;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" export" and" import" mean, respectively, taking out of,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>or bringing into, India, by land, sea or air;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" registered" means, except in the expression" registered  grower". registered under Chapter III of this Act and  the rules made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" registered grower" means a person who has obtained a  certificate of registration under section 10 for  growing virginia tobacco.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>THE TOBACCO BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE TOBACCO BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and constitution of the Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect  from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established  for the purposes of this Act, a Board to be called the Tobacco Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid,</p>
              <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire,</p>
              <p>hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to  contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The head office of the Board shall be at Guntur in the</p>
              <p>State of Andhra Pradesh and the Board may, with the previous approval  of the Central Government, establish offices or agencies at other  places in or outside India.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>three members of Parliament, of whom two shall be  elected by the House of the People and one by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Council of States;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>eight] members to be appointed by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government to represent respectively:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Ministry of the Central Government  dealing with Agriculture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list5.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Ministry of the Central Government  dealing with Commerce;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list5.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Ministry of the Central Government  dealing with Finance;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list5.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the Ministry of the Central Government  dealing with Industrial Development;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list5.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the Indian Council of Agricultural</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Research;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list7.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the Government of Andhra Pradesh;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list7.via">
                  <num>(via)</num>
                  <p>the Government of Gujarat; and]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list7.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.4.list7.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>two members to be appointed by the Central Government,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>by rotation in the alphabetical order, to represent the</p>
              <p>Governments of tobacco- growing States  other than the</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list11">
                <listIntroduction>State of Andhra Pradesh, Gujarat and Kanataka];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list11.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>not more than ten members  to be appointed by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government from amongst growers of tobacco,</p>
              <p>dealers and exporters (including packers) of tobacco  and tobacco products, manufacturers of tobacco products  and from amongst persons who, in the opinion of the</p>
              <p>Central Government, are experts in tobacco marketing or  agricultural economics:</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list16">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the number of members appointed under this  clause from amongst the growers of tobacco shall not exceed six.]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list16.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the Agricultural Marketing Adviser to the Government of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.4.list18">
                <listIntroduction>India, Department of Rural Development, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.4.list18.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the Executive Director, ex- officio.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4A">
            <num>(4A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It is hereby declared that the office of member of the</p>
              <p>Board shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for  being, a member of either House of Parliament.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall elect, from amongst its members, a Vice-</p>
              <p>Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the  functions of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated  to him by the Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the members and the manner of filling  vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed in the discharge of  their functions by, the members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any officer  of the Central Government (not being a member   of the Board) as is deputed by the Central Government in this behalf,</p>
              <p>shall have the right to attend the meetings of the Board and take part  in the proceedings thereof, but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may associate with itself in such manner and for  such purposes as may be prescribed, any persons whose assistance or  advice it may desire in complying with any of the provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act and a person so associated shall have the right to take part in  the discussions of the Board relevant to the purposes for which he has  been associated, but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.9.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Board or any committee appointed  by it under section 7 shall be invalidated merely by reason of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.9.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.9.list3">
                <listIntroduction>the Board or such committee; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.9.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a  member of the Board or such committee; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.9.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board or such  committee not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Salary and allowances and other conditions of service of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Chairman. The Chairman shall be entitled to such salary and allowances  and such conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, provident  fund and other matters as may, from time to time, be fixed by the</p>
              <p>Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Officers of the Board and other staff.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government shall appoint an Executive Director to exercise such powers  and perform such duties under the Chairman as may be prescribed or as  may be delegated to him by the Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall appoint a Secretary to the Board  to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the Chairman as  may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Executive Director and the Secretary shall be entitled to  such salaries and allowances and such conditions of service in respect  of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters as may from time  to time be fixed by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such control, restrictions and conditions</p>
              <p>(including conditions as to appointment of the officers and other  employees of the Tobacco Export Promotion Council, in the event of the   said Council being wound up) as may be prescribed, the Board may  appoint such other officers and employees as may be necessary for the  efficient performance of its functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman, of the Executive Director, the Secretary and  other officers and employees of the Board shall not undertake any work  unconnected with their duties under this Act except with the  permission of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Committees of the Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may appoint such  committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of its  duties and performance of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall have the power to co- opt as members of any  committee appointed under sub- section (1) such number of person who  are not members of the Board as it may think fit and the persons so  co- opted shall have the right to attend the meetings of the committee  and take part in the proceedings of the committee but shall not have  the right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the Board  to promote, by such measures as it thinks fit, the development under  the control of the Central Government of the tobacco industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>section (1), the measures referred to therein may provide for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.2.list2.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>regulating the production and curing of virginia tobacco  having regard to the following factors, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.2.list2.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the demand for virginia tobacco in India and abroad;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.2.list2.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the suitability of land for growing virginia tobacco;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.2.list2.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>the differences in soil characteristics and agro-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>climatic factors in different regions of the country where  virginia tobacco is grown and the effect thereof on the quality  and quantity of virginia tobacco produced in those regions;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list4.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the marketability of different types of virginia  tobacco;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list4.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the need for rotation of crops; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list4.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the nature of the holdings of the growers of virginia  tobacco whether owned or leased;"]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>keeping a constant watch on the virginia tobacco market,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>both in India and abroad, and ensuring that the growers  get a fair and remunerative price for the same and that  there are no wide fluctuations in the prices of the  commodity;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.2.list6.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>maintenance and improvement of existing markets, and  development of new markets outside India for Indian  virginia tobacco and its products and devising of  marketing strategy in consonance with demand for the  commodity outside India, including group marketing  under limited brand names;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.2.list6.c.list0.cc">
                      <num>(cc)</num>
                      <p>establishment by the Board of auction platforms,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>with the previous approval of the Central Government,</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list9">
                <listIntroduction>for the sale of virginia tobacco by registered growers  or curers, and functioning of the Board as an  auctioneer at auction platforms established by or  registered with it subject to such conditions as may be  specified by the Central Government;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list9.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>recommending to Central Government the minimum prices  which may be fixed for purposes of export of virginia  tobacco with a view to avoiding unhealthy competition  amongst the exporters;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list9.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>regulating in other respects virginia tobacco marketing  in India and export of virginia tobacco having due  regard to the interests of growers, manufacturers and  dealers and the nation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list9.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>propagating information useful to the growers, dealers  and exporters (including packers) of virginia tobacco  and manufacturers of virginia tobacco products and  others concerned with virginia tobacco and products  thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list9.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>purchasing virginia tobacco from growers when the same  is considered necessary or expedient for protecting the  interests of the growers and disposal of the same in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list11">
                <listIntroduction>India or abroad as and when considered appropriate;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list11.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>promoting the grading of tobacco at the level of  growers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list11.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>sponsoring, assisting, co- ordinating or encouraging  scientific, technological and economic research for the  promotion of tobacco industry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list11.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) and subject to priority being given to matters specified  in sub- section (2), the measures referred to in sub- section (1) may  also provide in relation to tobacco, other than virginia tobacco, for  all or any of the matters specified in clauses (c) to (g) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (2) and for this purpose any reference in those clauses to  virginia tobacco shall be construed as including a reference to  tobacco other than virginia tobacco.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall perform its functions under this section in  accordance with and subject to such rules as may be made by the</p>
              <p>Central Government and such rules may in particular make provisions  for ensuring that the Board functions in close liaison with Union  agencies, institutions and authorities concerned with the tobacco  industry (including growing of tobacco) and avoids duplication of  effort.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Dissolution of the Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette and for reasons to be specified  therein, direct that the Board shall be dissolved from such date and  for such period as may be specified in the notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that before issuing any such notification, the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Board to make  representations against the proposed dissolution and shall consider  the representations, if any, of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Board is dissolved under the provisions of sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>section (1),--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all members, notwithstanding that their term of office  has not expired, shall, from the date of dissolution,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-9.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>vacate their offices as such members;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all powers and duties of the Board shall, during the  period of dissolution, be exercised and performed by  such person or persons as the Central Government may  appoint in this behalf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all funds and other properties vested in the Board  shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-9.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>as soon as the period of dissolution expires, the Board  shall be reconstituted in accordance with the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>REGULATION OF PRODUCTION AND DISPOSAL OF VIRGINIA TOBACCO</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>REGULATION OF PRODUCTION AND DISPOSAL OF VIRGINIA TOBACCO</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Registration of growers of virginia tobacco.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person  shall grow virginia tobacco except under, and in accordance with, the  conditions of a certificate of registration obtained from the Board in  accordance with the rules made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In granting or refusing a certificate of registration, the</p>
              <p>Board shall have regard to the demand for virginia tobacco in India  and abroad, and the suitability of the land in relation to which the  certificate is applied for and such other factors as may, having  regard to the needs of the virginia tobacco industry, be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A certificate of registration granted in pursuance of this  section shall be valid for such period as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application for such certificate of registration shall  be accompanied by such fees (not exceeding one rupee for 0. 4 hectare   of the land in relation to which such application has been made) as  may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10A">
          <num>10A.</num>
          <heading>Registration of growers of virginia tobacco seedlings  for commercial purposes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall grow virginia tobacco  seedlings for commercial purposes unless he registers himself as a  nursery grower with the Board in accordance with the rules made under  this Act.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to the growing by a  registered grower of any virginia tobacco seedlings for his own use.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No registered nursery grower shall sell or cause to be sold  any virginia tobacco seedlings grown by him to any person other than a  registered grower."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Registration of curers of virginia tobacco. No person other  than a registered curer shall cure or undertake the curing of virginia  tobacco unless he registers himself as a curer with the Board in  accordance with the rules made under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11A">
          <num>11A.</num>
          <heading>Registration of processors and manufacturers of virginia  tobacco, etc. No person shall process virginia tobacco or manufacture  products therefrom unless he registers himself as such processor or  manufacturer, as the case may be with the Board in accordanec with the  rules made under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11B">
          <num>11B.</num>
          <heading>Licences to be obtained for grading work and construction  of barns, etc. No person shall--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11B.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11B.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-11B.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>take up grading work relating to virginia tobacco for  commercial purposes; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11B.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>take up the construction and operation of a barn,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>unless he obtains a licence from the Board in accordance with the  rules made under this Act.</p>
              <blockList id="section-11B.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11B.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" barn" means a building or structure with a roof of zinc  sheets or tiles having flue pipes, furnace and tiers used for  flue curing of tobacco leaves;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11B.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>" grading work" means separating tobacco leaves into  specific grades on the basis of plant position, maturity, colour,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>body and blemish and in accordance with such specifications  as may be prescribed.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Registration of exporters, packers, auctioneers and dealers.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No person shall export tobacco or any tobacco products or function as  a packer, auctioneer of, or dealer in, tobacco unless he registers  himself with the Board in accordance with the rules made under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Virginia tobacco to be sold at registered auction platforms.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No registered grower or curer shall sell or cause to be sold virginia  tobacco elsewhere than at an auction platform registered with the</p>
              <p>Board in accordance with the rules made under this Act  or  established by the Board under this Act].</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13A">
          <num>13A.</num>
          <heading>Duty of registered dealers and exporters to purchase at  auction platforms, etc. No registered dealer or registered exporter  shall purchase or cause to be purchased virginia tobacco elsewhere--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13A.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>than at an auction platform registered with the Board in  accordance with the rules made under this Act or established by  the Board under this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13A.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>than from any other registered dealer or a registered  grower or curer:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that in relation to any State in which the provisions of  section 13 are not in force, the condition specified under clause (a)</p>
              <p>shall not apply.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13B">
          <num>13B.</num>
          <heading>Duty or buyers of virginia Tobacco at ploaces other than  auction platforms to refrain from certain unfair practices. Every  dealer who purchases virginia tobacco in any State in which the  provisions of section 13 are not in force,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13B.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall pay the full price for the whole quantity of  virginia tobacco so purchased by him at the rate at which he  agreed to purchase such tobacco and shall refrain from claiming  any discount in the weight or other deductions in weight thereof  or any deductions from the price as calculated in accordance  with such rate;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>shall pay the full price for virginia tobacco so  purchased by him as calculated in accordance with the provisions  of clause (a) as expeditiously as possible and in any case  within such reasonable time as may be specified in this behalf  by the Board; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>shall refrain from having recourse to any practices  which the Board may, having regard to the need for protection of  persons selling virginia tobacco in such State and all other  relevant considerations, specify to be unfair practices.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Application, cancellation, fees and other matters relating to  registration. The form of application and the form of certificate of  registration under section 10, the form of application  for  registration of nursery growers for the purposes of section 10A, for  registration of curers for the purposes of section 11, for  registration of processors and manufacturers for the purposes of  section 11A, for obtaining licences for taking up grading work or  construction and operation of barns under section 11B"], for  registration of exporters, packers or auctioneers of, or dealers in,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>tobacco, for the purposes of section 12, and for registration of  auction platforms for the purposes of section 13, the time within  which and the manner in which such applications shall be made, the  fees payable on such applications, the particulars to be specified  therein, the principles and the procedure to be followed in granting  and cancelling</p>
              <p>certificates of registration or the registration of auction platforms  or, as the case may be,  the registration as nursery growers,</p>
              <p>curers, processors, exporters, packers or auctioneers of, or dealers  in, virginia tobacco or as manufacturer of the products of virginia  tobacco or in granting licences under section 11B, the returns to be  submitted and the registers to be maintained by registered growers,</p>
              <p>nursery growers, curers, processors, exporters, packers or auctioneers  of, or dealers in, virginia tobacco or the registered manufacturers of  the products of virginia tobacco or the persons licensed under section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11B">
          <num>11B.</num>
          <heading>and the registers to be kept by the Board shall be such as may be  prescribed]</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14A">
          <num>14A.</num>
          <heading>Power to levy fees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where virginia tobacco is sold at  any auction platform established by the Board under this Act, it shall  be competent for the Board or for any officer of the Board authorised  by it in this behalf to levy fees, for the services rendered by the</p>
              <p>Board in relation to such sale, at such rate not exceeding two per  cent. of the value of such tobacco as the Central Government may, from  time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The fees levied under sub- section (1) shall be collected by  the Board or such officer, equally from the seller of the virginia  tobacco and the purchaser of such tobacco, in such manner as may be  prescribed.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power of inspection. The Board may authorise any of its  members, officers or other employees to inspect in such manner as may  be prescribed any land or premises to verify the accuracy of any  particulars mentioned in any application or any return referred to in  section 14.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Grants and loans by the Central Government. The Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in  this behalf, pay to the Board by way of grants or loans such sums of  money as the Central Government may think fit for being utilised for  the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Tobacco Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be formed a</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Fund to be called the Tobacco Fund and there shall be credited  thereto--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the fees levied and collected under this Act or the  rules made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any sums of money paid or any loans granted by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government for the purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any grants or loans that may be made by any person for  the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the sums, if any, realised by the Board in carrying out  the measures referred to in section 8.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be applied--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the cost of the measures referred to in  section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the salaries, allowances and other  remuneration of the officers and other employees of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the other administrative expenses of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for repayment of any loans.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing powers of the Board. Subject to such rules as may  be made in this behalf, the Board shall have the power to borrow on  the security of the Tobacco Fund or any other asset for carrying out  the purposes of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18A">
          <num>18A.</num>
          <heading>Writing off of losses. Subject to such conditions as may  be specified by the Central Government, where the Board is of opinion  that any amount due to, or any loss, whether of money or of property,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>incurred by, the Board is irrecoverable, the Board may, with the  previous approval of the Central Government, sanction the writing off  finally of the said amount or loss:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such approval of the Central Government shall be  necessary where such irrecoverable amount or loss does not exceed in  any individual case and in the aggregate in any year such amounts as  may be prescribed.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts, including the  income and expenditure account] and the  balance- sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the Central</p>
              <p>Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
              <p>India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be specified by  him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall  be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor- General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Board shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General has  in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
              <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect any of the offices of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and</p>
              <p>Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this  behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded  annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Power to prohibit or control import and export of tobacco and  tobacco products.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by order published  in the Official Gazette, make provision for prohibiting, restricting  or otherwise controlling the import or export of tobacco and tobacco  products, either generally or in specified classes of cases.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All tobacco and tobacco products to which any order under  sub- section (1) applies, shall be deemed to be goods of which the  import or export has been prohibited under section 11 of the Customs</p>
              <p>Act, 1962 (52 of 1962), and all the provisions of that Act shall have  effect accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person contravenes any order made under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, he shall, without prejudice to any confiscation or penalty to  which he may, be liable under the provisions of the Customs Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1962">
          <num>1962.</num>
          <heading>(52 of 1962), as applied by sub- section (2), be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or  with both.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20A">
          <num>20A.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to authorise purchase of  virginia tobacco. Without prejudice to the provisions of clause (g) of  sub- section (2) of section 8 and notwithstanding anything contained in  any other provision of this Act, if the Central Government is  satisfied that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by order  in writing and subject to such conditions and limitations as may be  specified in the order, authorise any body or other agency to purchase  virginia tobacco from the growers and dispose of the same in India or  abroad.]</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Directions by Central Government. The Board shall carry out  such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall furnish to the</p>
              <p>Central Government at such time and in such form and manner as may be  prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, such returns and  statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing  programme for the promotion and development of the tobacco industry,</p>
              <p>as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
              <p>Board shall, as soon as possible after the end of each financial year,</p>
              <p>submit to the Central Government a report in such form and before such  date, as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account of its  activities, policy and programmes during the previous financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be  laid, as soon as may be after it is received, before each House of</p>
              <p>Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Any person who, being required under this Act to  furnish any return fails to furnish such return or furnishes a return  containing any particular which is false and which he knows to be  false or does not believe to be true, shall be punishable with fine  which may extend to five hundred rupees.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Penalties for obstructing a member, officer or other employee  of the Board in the discharge of his duties and for failure to produce  books and records. Any person who--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>obstructs any member or any officer or other employee of  the Board or any other person in the exercise of any  power conferred, or in the discharge of any duty  imposed, on him by or under this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>having control over or custody of any account book or  other record, fails to produce such book or record when  required to do so by or under this Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Other penalties. Whoever contravenes or attempts to  contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of this Act</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or of any rules or regulations made there under  other than the  provisions, punishment for the contravention whereof has been provided  for in section 20 or section 23 or section 24, shall be punishable  with imprisonment for a term which may  extend to two years, or  with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both] and  in the case of a continuing contravention with an additional fine  which may extend to fifty rupees for every day during which such  contravention continues after conviction for the first such  contravention.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the  offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the  company shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all  due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to  be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against  and punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of court. No court inferior to that of a</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try  any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Previous sanction of Central Government. No prosecution for  any offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted except with  the previous sanction of the Central Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government, or the Board or any committee appointed by it, or any  member of the Board or such committee, or any officer or other  employee of the Central Government or of the Board or any agent of or  any other person authorised by the Board, for anything which is in  good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules  made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Suspension of operation of Act.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Central Government  is satisfied that circumstances have arisen rendering it necessary  that certain of the restrictions imposed by this Act should cease to  be imposed or if it considers it necessary or expedient so to do in  the public interest, the Central Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, suspend or relax to a specified extent, for such  period as may be specified in the notification, the operation of all  or any of the provisions of this Act, in all or any of the territories  to which this Act extends.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the operation of any provision of this Act has, under  sub- section (1), been suspended or relaxed, such suspension or  relaxation may, at any time while this Act remains in force, be  removed by the Central Government by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notification issued under this section shall be laid,</p>
              <p>as soon as may be after it is issued, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the  notification should not be issued, the notification shall thereafter  have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case  may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the previous operation of the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Application of other laws not barred. The provisions of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions  of any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the powers and functions of the Vice- Chairman of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the term of office and other conditions of service of  members, the manner of filling vacancies among, and the  procedure to be followed in the discharge of their  functions by, members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the powers which may be exercised and the duties which  shall be performed by the Executive Director and the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Secretary;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the circumstances in which and the authority by which a  member may be removed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the holding of a minimum number of meetings of the Board  every year;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed at the meetings of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Board for the conduct of business and the number of  members which shall form a quorum at a meeting;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list7.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-32.2.list7.g.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the maintenance by the Board of records of business  transacted by the Board and the submission of copies  thereof to the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-32.2.list7.g.list0.ga">
                      <num>(ga)</num>
                      <p>the specifications with regard to grading work  referred to in section 11B;"]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-32.2.list7.h.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>the matters referred to in section 14;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-32.2.list7.h.list1.hh">
                      <num>(hh)</num>
                      <p>the manner of collection of fees under sub- section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 14A;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the powers of the Board, its Chairman, the Executive</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Director and committees of the Board with respect to  the incurring of expenditure;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-32.2.list3.j.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the conditions subject to which the Board may incur  expenditure outside India;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-32.2.list3.j.list0.ja">
                      <num>(ja)</num>
                      <p>the amounts for the purposes of the proviso to  section 18A;]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the preparation of budget estimates of receipts and  expenditure of the Board and the authority by which the  estimates are to be sanctioned;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which the accounts should be  maintained by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>the deposit of the funds of the Board in banks and the  investment of such funds;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>the conditions to be observed by the Board in borrowing  money;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which, and the manner in  which, contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of  the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>the additional matters in respect of which the Board may  undertake measures in the discharge of its functions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>the remuneration and other allowances payable to the  person or persons referred to in clause (b) of sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 9;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list5.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner of, and the particulars to be  contained in, any returns or reports to be made to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Board under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list7.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>the collection of any information or statistics in  respect of tobacco or tobacco products;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list7.t">
                  <num>(t)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed  by, or provided for by rules under, this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should  not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
              <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may make regulations  not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder for  enabling it to discharge its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,</p>
              <p>such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the  committees appointed by the Board and the number of  members which shall form a quorum at a meeting;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the delegation to the Chairman, members, Executive</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Director, Secretary or other officers of the Board, of  any of the powers and duties of the Board under this</p>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the travelling and other allowances payable to persons  associated under sub- section (8) of section 4 or co-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>opted under sub- section (2) of section 7;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list8.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the pay and allowances and leave and other conditions of  service of officers (other than those appointed by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government) and other employees of the Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list10.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of the accounts of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list10.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of the registers and other records of  the Board and its various committees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list10.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the appointment by the Board of agents to discharge, on  its behalf, any of its functions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list13">
                <listIntroduction>Board.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list13.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the time within which full price for virginia tobacco  shall be paid under clause (b), and the unfair practices for the  purposes of clause (c), of section 13B.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No regulation made by the Board shall have effect until it  has been approved by the Central Government and published in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, and the Central Government, in approving a  regulation, may make any change therein which appears to it to be  necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, cancel any regulation which it has approved and, thereupon,</p>
              <p>the regulation shall cease to have effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every regulation made under this section shall be laid,</p>
              <p>as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
