<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1853/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1853/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Shore Nuisances (Bombay And Kolaba) Act, 1853"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1853/11/eng@1853-07-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1853/11/eng@1853-07-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1853-07-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1853/11/eng@1853-07-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1853/11/eng@1853-07-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Shore Nuisances (Bombay And Kolaba) Act, 1853</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 11 OF 1853</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 15th July, 1853.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to facilitate the removal of nuisances and encroachments below  high- water mark in the Islands of Bombay and Kolaba.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- WHEREAS there is a large sea- shore in the islands of</p>
        <p>Bombay and Kolaba, and it is expedient, with a view to the safe  navigation of the harbour of Bombay, and to the public interests  generally, to facilitate the removal of nuisances, obstructions and  encroachments below high- water mark in the said harbour, or upon or  about the shores of the said islands; It is enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Power to give notice to remove nuisance. Mode of giving  notice. Contents. Form.-- It shall be lawful for the Collector of Land-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>revenue at Bombay to give notice requiring the removal of any  nuisance, obstruction or encroachment anywhere below high- water mark  in the said harbour of Bombay, or upon or about the shores of the said  islands; such notice shall be given by affixing the same in some  conspicuous place on or near to the encroachment, obstruction or  nuisance complained of, and by publication thereof in the 2</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, and shall state that, unless the nuisance,</p>
            <p>obstruction or encroachment be removed or abated within one month, the  same will be removed or abated by the said Collector; such notice may  be in the Form No. 1, in the Schedule to this Act annexed, or to the  like effect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Petition by person denying right to remove nuisance. Procedure  thereupon.-- If any person shall deny the right of the said Collector  to effect such abatement or removal, he shall, within one month after  such notice shall have been given as aforesaid, apply to the Supreme</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Court of Judicature at Bombay by petition, setting forth the grounds  of his alleged right and praying that the said Collector may be  restrained from causing such abatement or removal; and the said Court  may thereupon (on the petitioner' s giving sufficient security for   costs), fix a time for hearing and adjudicating upon such petition,</p>
            <p>and give such direction, and make such orders as the said Court may  think just, and the said Court may also make an order for restraining  the alleged nuisance, obstruction or encroachment from being extended,</p>
            <p>or from being abated or removed by the said Collector, until after  adjudication upon the said petition, or the dismissal thereof for want  of prosecution.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Onus of proving right.-- Upon the hearing of every such  petition, the onus of proving the alleged right shall be on the  petitioner.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of time for petition.-- No person shall be allowed,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>after the expiration of such period of one month, to present any such  petition as aforesaid, unless on satisfactorily accounting to the said</p>
            <p>Court for the delay.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>When Collector may cause removal of nuisance. Form of warrant.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Indemnity.-- If no such petition shall be presented within the said  period of one month, or if the same be presented and determined  against the right of the petitioner, or be dismissed for want of  prosecution, it shall be lawful for the Collector to cause such  abatement or removal as aforesaid by any person or persons to be  authorized by warrant under his hand, and such warrant may be in the</p>
            <p>From No. 2 in the Schedule to this Act annexed, or to the like effect;</p>
            <p>and the said Collector, and any person acting under his warrant, shall  not be answerable for any damage unavoidably occasioned in the removal  of any such nuisance, obstruction or encroachment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to sell materials of encroachment.-- The said Collector  may sell the materials of any encroachment or obstruction removed  under this Act, and may apply the proceeds of sale in or towards  payment of the expenses of the removal, and, if any surplus shall  remain, the same shall be forfeited, and be paid and applied in such  manner as the  Central Government] shall direct.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Saving of rights of Government.-- Nothing in this Act shall  prejudice or affect the rights of  the Government in any part of  the said harbour, or of the sea- shore of the said lands, or preclude  or interfere with any such proceedings, civil or criminal, for abating  such nuisances and encroachments as aforesaid, as might have been had  if this Act had not been passed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>" High- water mark" defined.-- The words" high- water mark" in  this Act shall mean the ordinary line of high- water at monsoon tides.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
