<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/9/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/9"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/9/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/9/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to [the whole of India except [the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B, States,]] and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the first day of July, 1887.</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.3.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—Same as that of Maharashtra.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act however ceased to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.3.list4.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 1,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.3.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to sub-section (2), add the following proviso, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.3.list6">
              <listIntroduction>“Provided that on the commencement of the Provincial Small Cause Courts (Bombay Unification and Amendment) Act, 1958, it shall also extend to the Saurashtra and Hyderabad areas of the State of Bombay”.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.3.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to sub-section (3), add the following proviso, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Provided that, in the Saurashtra and Hyderabad areas of the State of Bombay, it shall come into force on the commencement of the Provincial Small Cause Courts (Bombay Unification and Amendment) Act, 1958”.</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 87 of 1958, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. partly by the Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), sec. 2 and Sch. I and partly by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Saving.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to affect—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any proceeding before or after decree in any suit instituted before the commencement of this Act; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the jurisdiction of a Magistrate under any law for the time being in force with respect to debts or other claims of a civil nature, or of Village-Munsifs or Village-Panchayats under the provisions of the Madras Code, or of Village-Munsifs under the Dekkhan Agriculturists’ Relief Act, 1879 (17 of 1879); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any local law or any special law other than the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State Amendments</p>
            <p>Andhra Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 3, in clause (b), after the words “Madras Code” insert the words and figures “or of the laws in force in the State of Andhra Pradesh as it existed immediately before the 1st November, 1956.”</p>
            <p>Vide Andhra Pradesh A.L.Os., 1953 and 1957.</p>
            <p>Tamil Nadu.—</p>
            <p>In section 3, in clause (b), for the words and figures “State of Andhra as it existed immediately before the 1st November, 1956”, substitute the words and figures “territories specified in the Second Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1959.”</p>
            <p>Vide Tamil Nadu (Ad. Ter.) A.L.O., 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Definition.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless there is something repugnant in the subject or context, “Court of Small Causes” means a Court of Small Causes constituted under this Act, and includes any person exercising jurisdiction under this Act in any such Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government*** may, by order in writing, establish a Court of Small Causes at any place within the territories under its administration beyond the local limits for the time being of the ordinary original civil jurisdiction of a High Court of Judicature established in Presidency-town.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court of Small Causes shall be such as the State Government may define, and the Court may be held at such place or places within those limits as the State Government may appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Judge.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a Court of Small Causes has been established there shall be appointed, by order in writing, a Judge of the Court:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the State Government, so direct, the same person shall be the Judge of more than one such Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of times of sitting in certain circumstances.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Judge who is the Judge of two or more such Courts may, with the sanction of the District Court, fix the times at which he will sit in each of the Courts of which he is Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of the times shall be published in such manner as the High Court from time to time directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Additional Judges.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the State Governments so direct, there may be appointed, by order in writing, Additional Judges of a Court of Small Causes or of two or more such courts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An Additional Judge shall discharge such of the functions of the Judge of the Court or Courts as the Judge may assign to him, and in the discharge of those functions shall exercise the same powers as the Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Judge may withdraw from</p>
            <p>An Additional Judge business pending before him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the Judge is absent, the</p>
            <p>Senior Additional Judge may discharge all or any of the functions of the Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Suspension and removal of Judges.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Government of India (Adaptation of Laws) Order, 1937.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to require two Judges to sit as a bench.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government, after consultation with the High Court, may, by order in writing, direct that two Judges of Courts of Small Causes, or a Judge and an Additional Judge of a Court of Small Causes, shall sit together for the trial of such class or classes of suits or applications cognizable by a Court of Small Causes as may be described in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Decision in case heard by a bench.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If two Judges, or a Judge and an Additional Judge, sitting together under the last foregoing section differ as to a question of law or usage having the force of law, or in construing a document the construction of which may affect the merits, they shall draw up and refer, for the decision of the High Court, a statement of the facts of the case and of the point on which they differ in opinion, and the provisions of Chapter XLVI of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882) shall apply to the reference.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If they differ on any matter other than a matter specified in sub-section (1), the opinion of the Judge who is senior in respect of date of appointment as Judge of a Court of Small Causes, or, if one of them is a Additional Judge, then the opinion of the Judge sitting with him, shall prevail.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of sub-section (2), a Judge permanently appointed shall be deemed to be senior to an officiating Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Registrar.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There may be appointed to a Court of Small Causes an officer to be called the Registrar of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a Registrar is appointed, he shall be the chief ministerial officer of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by order in writing, confer upon a Registrar, within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court, the jurisdiction of a Judge of a Court of Small Causes for the trial of suits of which the value does not exceed twenty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall try such suits cognizable by him as the Judge may, by general or special order direct.</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.4.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.4.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—Same as that of Maharashtra.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.4.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act however ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad w.e.f. 4-11-1961—See Gujarat 19 of 1961.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.4.list4.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 12, in sub-section (3), for the word “twenty” substitute the words “one hundred”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 87 of 1958, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958), Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3.</p>
            <p>Tamil Nadu.—</p>
            <p>In section 12, in sub-section (3), for the words “twenty rupees,” the words “two hundred rupees” shall be substituted.</p>
            <p>Vide Tamil Nadu Act 26 of 1995, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-12-1995) sec. 3.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Other ministerial officers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Government of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws), 1937.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Duties of ministerial officers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The ministerial officers of a Court of Small Causes shall, in addition to any duties mentioned in this Act, or in any other enactment for the time being in force, as duties which are or may be imposed on any of them, discharge such duties of a ministerial nature as the Judge directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The High Court may make rules consistent with this Act, and with any other enactment for the time being in force, conferring and imposing on the ministerial officers of a Court of Small Causes such powers and duties as it thinks fit, and regulating the mode in which powers and duties so conferred and imposed are to be exercised and performed.</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—Same as that of Maharashtra.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act however ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad w.e.f. 4-11-1961—See Gujarat 19 of 1961, sec. 19.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list4.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 14, in sub-section (1), for the words “The ministerial officers” substitute the words “The clerks, bailiffs, appraisers and other ministerial officers”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 87 of 1958, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958), Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of suits by Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Court of Small Causes shall not take cognizance of the suits specified in the Second Schedule as suits expected from the cognizance of a Court of Small Causes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the exceptions specified in that Schedule and to the provisions of any enactment for the time being in force, all suits of a civil nature of which the value does not exceed five hundred rupees shall be cognizable by a Court of Small Causes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject as aforesaid, the State Government may, by order in writing, direct that all suits of a civil nature of which the value does not exceed one thousand rupees shall be cognizable by a Court of Small Causes mentioned in the order.</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list2.Bihar">
                <num>(Bihar)</num>
                <p>—In section 15, in sub-section (2), for the words “five hundred rupees” substitute the words “one thousand rupees” and in sub-section (3) for the words “one thousand rupees” substitute the words “one thousand and five hundred rupees”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Bihar Act 3 of 1984, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 21-3-1984).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list4.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—In section 15, in sub-section (3) for the words “one thousand rupees” substitute the words “two thousand rupees”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 67 of 1950, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-1-1951) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958), Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3 and sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceased to apply to the City of Ahmedabad (w.e.f. 4-11-1961)—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19.</p>
            <p>Himachal Pradesh.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list8">
              <listIntroduction>In section 15,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list8.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in sub-section (2), for the words ‘five hundred rupees’ substitute the words “two thousand rupees”; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list8.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>omit sub-section (3).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Himachal Pradesh Act 4 of 1970, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-4-1970).</p>
            <p>Madhya Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 15, in sub-section (3), for the words “State Government” substitute the words “High Court”.</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 19 of 1958, sec. 28 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-1-1959).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list13.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 15, (1) in sub-section (2), for the words “five hundred rupees” substitute the words “two thousand rupees” and (2) in sub-section (3) for the words “two thousand rupees” substitute the words “five thousand” rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list15">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Maharashtra Act 46 of 1977, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-1-1978).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list15.Orissa">
                <num>(Orissa)</num>
                <p>—In section 15, for sub-sections (2) and (3), substitute the following sub-section, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“(2) subject to the exceptions specified in that Schedule and to the provisions of any enactment for the time being in force, all suits of a civil nature of which the value does not exceed two thousand and five hundred rupees shall be cognizable by a Court of Small Causes.”</p>
            <p>Vide Orissa Act 4 of 1998, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 9-3-1998).</p>
            <p>Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—</p>
            <p>Same as that in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
            <p>Vide Punjab Act 3 of 1966, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-3-1966); Act 31 of 1966, sec. 88.</p>
            <p>Tamil Nadu.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list23">
              <listIntroduction>In section 15,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list23.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in sub-section (2), for the words “five hundred rupees”, substitute the words “five thousand rupees”;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list23.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in sub-section (3), for the words “one thousand rupees”, substitute the words “five thousand rupees”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Tamil Nadu Act 26 of 1995, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-12-1995).</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 15, for sub-sections (2) and (3), substitute the following:—</p>
            <p>“(2) Subject to the exceptions specified in that Schedule and to the provisions of any enactment for the time being in force, all suits of a civil nature of which the value does not exceed five thousand rupees shall be cognizable by a Court of Small Causes:</p>
            <p>Provided that in relation to suits by the lessor for the eviction of a lessee from a building after the determination of his lease or for recovery from him of rent in respect of the period of occupation thereof during the continuance of the lease, or of compensation for use and occupation thereof after the determination of the lease, the reference in this sub-section to five thousand rupees shall be construed as a reference to twenty-five thousand rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this sub-section, the expression ‘building’ has the same meaning as in Art.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in the Second Schedule.”</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 17 of 1991, sec. 6 (w.r.e.f. 15-1-1991).</p>
            <p>West Bengal.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.4.list4">
              <listIntroduction>In section 15, (i) in sub-section (2) for the words “two thousand and five hundred rupees” substitute the words “five thousand rupees”.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.4.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in sub-section (3) for the words “five thousand rupees” substitute the words “seven thousand and five hundred rupees”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide West Bengal Act 52 of 1978, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-6-1979).</p>
            <p>Comments</p>
            <p>Once there is want of jurisdiction the availability of material for the finding as to relationship is of little purpose. The decision rendered is vitiated due to want of jurisdiction and has to be set aside. A right judgment by a wrong Court is no judgment in the eye of law; Sudamabai v. Pratap Singh, AIR 1989 MP 117.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Exclusive jurisdiction of Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as expressly provided by this Act or by any other enactment for the time being in force, a suit cognizable by a Court of Small Causes shall not be tried by any other Court having jurisdiction within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court of Small Causes by which the suit is triable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Code of Civil Procedure.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure prescribed in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), shall save in so far as is otherwise provided by that Code or by this Act, be the procedure followed in a Court of Small Causes, in all suits cognizable by it and in all proceedings arising out of such suits:</p>
            <p>Provided that an applicant for an order to set aside a decree passed ex parte or for a review of judgment shall, at the time of presenting his application, either deposit in the Court the amount due from him under the decree or in pursuance of the judgment, or give such security for the performance of the decree or compliance with the judgment as the Court may, on a previous application made by him in this behalf, have directed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person has become liable as surety under the proviso to sub-section (1), the security may be realised in manner provided by section 145 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).</p>
            <p>State Amendment tc "State Amendment"</p>
            <p>Tamil Nadu.—</p>
            <p>In section 15, in sub-section (1), substitute the following proviso, namely:—</p>
            <p>“Provided that an applicant for a review of judgment shall, at the time of presenting his application, either deposit in the Court, the amount due from him in pursuance of the judgment or give such security for the compliance with the judgment as the Court may on a previous application made by him in this behalf, have directed.”</p>
            <p>Vide Tamil Nadu Act 49 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 30-8-1994).</p>
            <p>Comments</p>
            <p>It is settled principle of law that no party shall be made to suffer because of a wrong order passed by any Court. It is because of an order passed by the Court accepting the security that a party did not deposit any further amount. Interest of justice, consequently, requries that in such a case where a contrary view is taken at a subsequent stage by the same Court. Court is obliged to give an opportunity to the party to comply with the provisions of section 17 of the Act before rejecting the application for setting aside the ex-parte decree for non-compliance of the provisions of section 17; Mohan Lal v. Additional District Judge, Nainital, AIR 1989 All 176.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Trial of suits by Registrar.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Suits cognizable by the Registrar under section 12, sub-sections (3) and (4), shall be tried by him, and decrees passed there in shall be executed by him, in like manner in all respects as the Judge might try the suits, and execute the decrees, respectively.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Judge may transfer to his own file, or to that of the Additional Judge if an Additional Judge has been appointed, any suit or other proceeding on the file of the Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Admission, return and rejection of plaints by Registrar.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the Judge of a Court of Small Causes is absent, and an Additional Judge has not been appointed or, having been appointed, is also absent, the Registrar may admit a plaint or return, or reject a plaint for any reason for which the Judge might return or reject it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Judge may, of his own motion or on the application of a party return or reject a plaint which has been admitted by the Registrar, or admit a plaint which has been returned or rejected by him:</p>
            <p>Provided that, where a party applies for the return or rejection or the admission of a plaint under this sub-section, and his application is not made at the first sitting of the Judge after the day on which the Registrar admitted, or returned or rejected, the plaint, the Judge shall dismiss the application unless the applicant satisfies him that there was sufficient cause for not making the application at that sitting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Passing of decrees by Registrar on confession.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, before the date appointed for the hearing of a suit the defendant or his agent duly authorised in that behalf appears before the Registrar and admits the plaintiff’s claim, the Registrar may, if the Judge is absent, and an Additional Judge has not been appointed or, having been appointed, is also absent, pass against the defendant, upon the admission, a decree which shall have the same effect as a decree passed by the Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a decree has been passed by the Registrar under sub-section (1), the Judge may grant an application for review of judgment, and re-hear the suit, on the same conditions, on the same grounds and in the same manner as if the decree had been passed by himself.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Execution of decrees by Registrar.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Judge is absent, and an Additional Judge has not been appointed or, having been appointed, is also absent, the Registrar may, subject to any instructions which he may have received from the Judge or, with respect to decrees or orders made by an Additional Judge, from the Additional Judge, make any orders in respect of applications for the execution of decrees and orders made by the Court of which he is Registrar, or sent to that Court for execution, which the Judge might make under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Judge, in the case of any decree or order with respect to the execution of which the Registrar has made an order under sub-section (1), or the Additional Judge, in the case of any such decree or order which has been made by himself and with respect to which proceedings have not been taken by the Judge under this sub-section, may, of his own motion, or on application made by a party within fifteen days from the date of the order of the Registrar of the execution of any process issued in pursuance of that order, reverse or modify the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period of fifteen days mentioned in sub-section (2) shall be computed in accordance with the provisions of the Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (15 of 1877), as though the application of the party were an application for review of judgment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Adjournment of cases by chief ministerial officer.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When the Judge of a Court of Small Causes is absent and an Additional Judge has not been appointed, or, having been appointed, is also absent, the Registrar or other chief ministerial officer of the Court may exercise from time to time the power which the Court possesses of adjourning the hearing of any suit or other proceeding, and fix a day for the further hearing thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Return of plaints in suits involving questions of title.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing portion of this Act, when the right of a plaintiff and the relief claimed by him in a Court of Small Causes depend upon the proof or disproof of a title to immovable property or other title which such a Court cannot finally determine, the Court may at any stage of the proceedings return the plaint to be presented to a Court having jurisdiction to determine the title.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Court returns a plaint under sub-section (1), it shall comply with the provisions of the second paragraph of section 57 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882), and make such order with respect to costs as it deems just and the Court shall, for the purposes of the Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (15 of 1877) be deemed to have been unable to entertain the suit by reason of a cause of a nature like to that of defect of jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Appeals from certain orders of Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where an order specified in clause (ff) or clause (h) of sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 104 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), is made by a Court of Small Causes, an appeal therefor shall lie to the District Court [on any ground on which an appeal from such order would lie under that section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Revision of decrees and orders of Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The High Court, for the purpose of satisfying itself that a decree or order made in any case decided by a Court of Small Causes was according to law, may call for the case and pass such order with respect thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.Haryana">
                <num>(Haryana)</num>
                <p>—For section 25, substitute the following sections, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“25. Revision of decrees and orders of Courts of Small Causes.—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The District Judge, for the purpose of satisfying himself that a decree or order made in any case decided by a Court of Small Causes was according to law, may, of his own motion or on the application of an aggrieved party made within thirty days from the date of such decree or order, call for the case and pass such orders with respect thereto as he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any revision pending in the High Court against the decree or order made by a Court of Small Causes shall stand transferred to the District Judge exercising ordinary territorial jurisdiction in such cases.”</p>
            <blockList id="section-25.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Haryana Act 27 of 1977, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 9-12-1977).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.2.list2.Punjab">
                <num>(Punjab)</num>
                <p>—Same as in Haryana, except that there is no sub-section (2).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Punjab Act 20 of 1975, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f 21-7-1975).</p>
            <p>Tamil Nadu.—</p>
            <p>For section 27, substitute the following section, namely:—</p>
            <p>“25. Revision of decrees and orders of Courts of Small Causes.—</p>
            <p>The District Judge, for the purpose of satisfying himself that a decree or order made in any case decided by a Court of Small Causes was according to law, may of his own motion, or on the application of an aggrieved party made within thirty days from the date of such decree or order, call for the case and pass such order with respect thereto as he thinks fit:</p>
            <p>Provided that in relation to any case decided by a District Judge or Additional District Judge exercising the jurisdiction of a Judge of a Court of Small Causes, the power of revision under this section shall vest in the High Court.”</p>
            <p>Vide Tamil Nadu Act 32 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-1-1983).</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>For section 25, substitute the following section, namely:—</p>
            <p>“25. Revision of decrees and orders of Courts of Small Causes.—</p>
            <p>The District Judge, for the purpose of satisfying himself that a decree or order made in any case decided by a Court of Small Causes was according to law, may of his own motion, or on the application of an aggrieved party made within thirty days from the date of such decree or order, call for the case and pass such order with respect thereto as he thinks fit.”</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 17 of 1966, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 29-6-1966).</p>
            <p>In section 25, insert the following proviso,—</p>
            <p>“Provided that in relation to any case decided by a District Judge or Additional District Judge exercising the jurisdiction of a Judge of Small Causes, the power of revision under this section shall vest in the High Court.”</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 37 of 1972, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1972).</p>
            <blockList id="section-25.2.list19">
              <listIntroduction>Section 25A</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.2.list19.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—Section 27 shall be re-numbered as section 25A and after section 25A as so re-numbered insert as under:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>CHAPTER</p>
            <p>IVA</p>
            <p>RECOVERY OF POSSESSION OF CERTAIN IMMOVABLE PROPERTY AND CERTAIN LICENCE FEES AND RENT</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Suits or proceedings between licensors and licensees or landlords and tenants for recovery of possession of immovable property and licence fees or rent, except those to which other Acts apply, to lie in Court of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act, but subject to the provision of sub-section (2), the Court of Small Causes shall have jurisdiction to entertain and try all suits and proceedings between in licensor and licensee, or a landlord and tenants, relating to the recovery of possession of any immovable property situated in the area within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court of Small Causes, or relating to the recovery of the licence fee or charges or rent therefor, irrespective of the value of the subject matter of such suits or proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in sub-section (1) shall apply to suits or proceedings for the recovery of possession of any immovable property or of licence fee or charges or rent thereof, to which the provisions of the Bombay Rents, Hotel and Lodging House Rates Control Act, 1947, the Bombay Government Premises (Eviction) Act, 1955, the Bombay Provincial Municipal Corporations Act, 1919 or the Maharashtra Housing and Area Development Act, 1976, or any law for the time being in force, apply.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26A">
        <num>26A.</num>
        <heading>Appeal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie, from a decree or order made by the Court of Small Causes exercising jurisdiction under section 26, to the District Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under sub-section (1) shall be made within thirty days from the date of the decree or order, as the case may be:</p>
            <p>Provided that, in computing the period of limitation prescribed by this sub-section, the provisions contained in sections 4, 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act, 1963, shall, so far as may be apply.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No further appeal shall lie against any decision in appeal under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The District Court may, for the purpose of satisfying itself that a decree or order made in any case decided by the Court of Small Causes was according to law, call for the case in which such decree or order was made and pass such order with respect thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26B">
        <num>26B.</num>
        <heading>Saving of suits involving title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Chapter shall be deemed to bar a party to a suit, appeal or proceeding mentioned therein in which a question of title to any immovable property arises and is determined, from suing in a competent Court to establish his title to such property.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26C">
        <num>26C.</num>
        <heading>Saving of pending proceedings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 16, all suits and other proceedings cognizable by the Court of Small Causes under this Chapter and pending in the District Court or the Court of any Civil Judge on the date of coming into force of the Provincial Small Cause Courts and Presidency Small Cause Courts (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 1984, shall be continued and disposed of by the District Court or the Court of the Civil Judge, as the case may be, as if this Chapter had not been enacted.”</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, secs. 2 and 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of the Second Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Presidency Small Cause Courts Law Amendment Act, 1888 (10 of 1888), sec. 4.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Finality of decrees and orders.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as provided by this Act a decree or order made under the foregoing provisions of this Act by a Court of Small Causes shall be final.</p>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Sections 27A to 27RSections 27A to 27R"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—Same as that of Maharashtra.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 88 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad (w.e.f. 4-11-1961)—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list5.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—After Chapter IV, insert the following new Chapter, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27A">
        <num>27A.</num>
        <heading>Extent of Chapter IVA and its application.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Chapter extend to the areas within the local limits of the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this Chapter shall apply—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-27A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to a Judge or Court, other than a Small Cause Court, invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to any rent due to Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to any rent which has been due for more than twelve months before the date of the application made under the section 27B;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to any rent which is in arrears for a period less than three months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27B">
        <num>27B.</num>
        <heading>Application for distress warrant.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person claiming to be entitled to arrears of rent of any house or premises to which this Chapter extends situate in the local limits of the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes or his duly constituted attorney, may apply to such Court for issuing a warrant under section 27C:</p>
            <p>Provided that before making an application such person shall give 15 days’ notice to the tenant making a demand of the said arrears.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The application made under sub-section (1) shall be supported by an affidavit or affirmation in Form A in the Third Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27C">
        <num>27C.</num>
        <heading>Issue of distress warrant.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Court of Small Causes may thereupon direct the issue of a warrant in Form B in the Third Schedule returnable within six days, addressed to any one of the bailiffs appointed for the purpose:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Court may, on personal examination of the person applying for such warrant, decline to issue the same.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27D">
        <num>27D.</num>
        <heading>Time for distress.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every distress under this Chapter shall be made after sunrise and before sunset, and not at any other time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27E">
        <num>27E.</num>
        <heading>What places bailiff may force open.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The bailiff directed to make the distress may force open any stable, outhouse or other building and may also enter any dwelling-house the outer door of which may be open and may break open the door of any room in such dwelling house for the purpose of seizing property liable to be seized under this Chapter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a room in a dwelling house is in the actual occupancy of a woman, who according to custom, does not appear in public, the bailiff shall give notice to such woman that she is at liberty to withdraw; and, after allowing reasonable time for her to withdraw and giving her reasonable facility for withdrawing, he may enter such room for the purpose of seizing the property, using at the same time every precaution consistent with these provisions, to prevent its clandestine removal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27F">
        <num>27F.</num>
        <heading>Property which may be seized.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In pursuance of a warrant issued under section 27C, the bailiff shall seize the movable property found in or upon the house or premises mentioned in the warrant and belonging to the person from whom the rent is claimed (hereinafter called the debtor) or such part thereof as may, in the bailiff’s judgment, be sufficient to cover the amount of the said rent, together with the costs of the said distress:</p>
            <blockList id="section-27F.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the bailiff shall not seize—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27F.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>things in actual use; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27F.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the necessary wearing apparel, cooking vessels, beds and bedding of the debtor, his wife and children, and such personal ornaments as, in accordance with religious usage, cannot be parted with by any woman; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27F.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>tools of artisans, and, where the debtor is an agriculturist, his implements of husbandry and such cattle and seed grain as may, in the opinion of the Court, be necessary to enable him to earn his livelihood as such, and such portion of agricultural produce or of any class of agricultural produce as may have been declared to be free from liability under the provisions of the next following section; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27F.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>books of account; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27F.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>goods in the custody of the law.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27G">
        <num>27G.</num>
        <heading>Partial exemption of agricultural produce.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27G.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette declare that such portion of agricultural produce or of any class of agricultural produce, as may appear to the State Government to be necessary for the purpose of providing until the next harvest for the due cultivation of the land and for the support of the debtor and his family, shall, in the case of all agriculturists or any class of agriculturists, be exempted from liability to seizure in pursuance of a warrant issued under section 27C.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27H">
        <num>27H.</num>
        <heading>Impounding distress.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27H.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The bailiff impound or otherwise secure the property so seized in or on the house or premises chargeable with the rent.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-I.  Inventory, Notice of intended appraisement and sale.—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On seizing any property under section 27F, the bailiff shall make an inventory of such property and shall give a notice in writing in Form C in the Third Schedule to the debtor, or to any other person upon his behalf in or upon the said house or premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The bailiff shall, as soon as may be, file in the Court of Small Causes copies of the said inventory made, and notice given, under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27J">
        <num>27J.</num>
        <heading>Application to discharge or suspend warrant.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27J.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The debtor or any other person alleging himself to be the owner of any property seized under this Chapter, or the duly constituted attorney of such debtor or other person, may, at any time within fifteen days from such seizure, apply to the Court of Small Causes to discharge or suspend the warrant or to release a distrained article, and the Court may discharge or suspend such warrant or release such article accordingly upon such terms as it thinks just and may give reasonable time to the debtor to pay the rent due from him:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the Court is satisfied that there is sufficient cause for extending the period within an application may be made under this sub-section, it may extend the period to such extent as it may consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27J.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon an application made under sub-section (1), the costs attending it or attending the issue and execution of the warrant shall be in the discretion of the Court, and shall be paid as it directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27K">
        <num>27K.</num>
        <heading>Claim to goods distrained made by a stranger.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27K.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any claim is made to, or in respect of, any property seized under this Chapter, or in respect of the proceeds or value thereof, by any person not being the debtor, the Court of Small Causes upon the application of the bailiff, who seized the property, may issue a summons calling before the Court the claimant and the person who obtained the warrant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27K.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On issuing a summons under sub-section (1), any suit which may have been brought in any other Civil Court in respect of such claim shall be stayed, and such other Court on proof of the issue of such summons and the property was so distrained, may order the plaintiff to pay the costs of all proceedings in such suit after the issue of such summons.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27K.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court of Small Causes shall adjudicate upon such claim as is referred to in sub-section (2) and make such order between the parties in respect thereof and of the costs of the proceedings as it thinks fit; and such order shall be enforced as if it were an order made in a suit brought in such Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27K.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure in a Court of Small Causes in cases under this section shall conform, as far as may be, to the procedure in an ordinary suit in such Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27L">
        <num>27L.</num>
        <heading>Power to award compensation to debtor or claimant.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27L.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case under section 27J or section 27K, the Court of Small Causes may award such compensation by way of damages to the applicant or claimant, as the case may be, as the Court thinks fit and may for that purpose make any inquiry it thinks necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27L.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The order of the Court awarding or refusing compensation under sub-section (1) shall bar any suit for the recovery of compensation for any damage caused by the distress.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27M">
        <num>27M.</num>
        <heading>Power to transfer to District Court cases where subject-matter in dispute exceeds the pecuniary jurisdiction of Court of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27M.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case under section 27J or section 27K, if the value of the subject-matter in dispute exceeds the limits of the pecuniary jurisdiction of the Court of Small Causes, the applicant or claimant may apply to the District Court to transfer the case to itself, and the District Court, on being satisfied that it is expedient that the case should be disposed of by itself, may direct the case to be transferred accordingly, and may thereupon alter or set aside any order passed in the case by the Court of Small Causes and may make such order therein as the District Court thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27M.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every application under sub-section (1) shall be made within seven days from the date of the seizure of the subject-matter in dispute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27M.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In granting applications under sub-section (1), the District Court may impose such terms as to payment of, or giving security for, costs or otherwise as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27M.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure in cases transferred under this section shall conform, as far as may be, to the procedure in suits before the District Court in the exercise of its original civil jurisdiction and orders made under this section may be executed as if they were made in the exercise of such jurisdiction. Every such order awarding or refusing compensation shall bar any suit for the recovery of compensation for any damage caused by the distress which gave rise to the case wherein such order was made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27N">
        <num>27N.</num>
        <heading>Appraisement and notice of sale.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27N.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In default of any order to the contrary by the Court of Small Causes or by the District Court, the Nazir of the Court appointed for the purpose may, at the expiration of fifteen days from a seizure of property under this Chapter, or, as the case may be, of the extended period under the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 27J, appraise the property so seized, and give the debtor notice in writing in Form D of the Third Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27N.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Nazir shall file in the Court of Small Causes a copy of every notice given under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-O.  Sale Application of proceeds.—</p>
            <p>In default of any such order to the contrary, the distrained property shall be sold by an officer of the Court on the day mentioned in the notice given under section 27N and the officer aforesaid shall, on realising the proceeds, pay over the amount thereof to the Court; and such amount shall be applied first in payment of the costs of the said distress and then in satisfaction of the debt; and surplus, if any, shall be returned to the debtor:</p>
            <p>Provided that when the property seized is subject to speedy and natural decay, it may, under special order of the Court, be sold at any time after it is seized:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the debtor may direct that the sale shall take place in other manner, first giving security for any extra costs thereby occasioned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27P">
        <num>27P.</num>
        <heading>Costs of distresses.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27P.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No costs of any distress under this Chapter shall be taken or demanded except those mentioned in Form E of the Third Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27Q">
        <num>27Q.</num>
        <heading>—Account of costs and proceeds.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27Q.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Court of Small Causes shall cause to be kept a book in which all sums received as costs upon distresses made under this Chapter, and all sums paid as remuneration to the bailiffs, and all contingent charges incurred in respect of such distress, shall be duly entered. It shall also cause to be entered in the book all sums realised by sale of the property distrained and paid over to landlords under the provisions of this Chapter.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27R">
        <num>27R.</num>
        <heading>Bar of distresses except under this Chapter and penalty for making illegal distresses.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27R.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No distress shall be levied for arrears of rent except under the provisions of this Chapter; and any person, except a bailiff, a Nazir or an officer of the Court, levying or attempting to levy any such distress shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, in addition to any other liability he may have incurred by his proceedings.”</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 87 of 1958, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 5.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Subordination of Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A Court of Small Causes shall be subject to the administrative control of the District Court and to the superintendence of the High Court, and shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>keep such registers, books and accounts as the High Court from time to time prescribes, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>comply with such requisitions as may be made by the District Court, the High Court or the State Government for records, returns and statements in such form and manner as the authority making the requisition directs.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The relation of the District Court to a Court of Small Causes, with respect to administrative control, shall be the same as that of the District Court to a Civil Court of the lowest grade competent to try an original suit of the value of five thousand rupees in that portion of the territories administered by the State Government in which the Court of Small Causes is established.</p>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—In section 28, in sub-section (2), for the words “five thousand rupees”, substitute the words “ten thousand rupees”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Bombay Act 57 of 1950, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 8-1-1951) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. This Act however ceases to apply to the city of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1960, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list4.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 28, in sub-section (2), for the words “five thousand rupees” substitute the words “twenty thousand rupees”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 46 of 1977, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-1-1978).</p>
            <p>Tamil Nadu.—</p>
            <p>In section 28, in sub-section (2), for the words “five thousand rupees” substitute the words “thirty thousand rupees”.</p>
            <p>Vide Tamil Nadu Act 26 of 1995, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-12-1995).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Seal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Court of Small Causes shall use a seal of such form and dimensions as are prescribed by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Abolition of Courts of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by order in writing, abolish a Court of Small Causes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Saving of power to appoint Judge of Court of Small Causes to other office.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to prevent</p>
            <p>the appointment of a person who is a Judge or Additional Judge of a Court of Small Causes to be also a Judge of any other</p>
            <p>Civil Court or to be a Magistrate of any class or to hold any other public office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Judge or Additional Judge is so appointed, the ministerial officers of his Court shall, subject to any rules which the State Government may make in this behalf, be deemed to be ministerial officers appointed to aid him in the discharge of the duties of the other office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to Courts invested with jurisdiction of Court of Small Causes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>So much of Chapters III and IV as relates to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the nature of the suits cognizable by Courts of Small Causes,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the exclusion of the jurisdiction of other Courts in those suits,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the practice and procedure of Courts of Small Causes,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>appeal from certain orders of those Courts and revision of cases decided by them, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the finality of their decrees and order subject to such appeal and revision as are provided by this Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>applies to Courts invested by or under any enactment for the time being in force with the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes so far as regards the exercise of that jurisdiction by those Courts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) with respect of Courts invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes applies to suits instituted or proceedings commenced in those Courts before the date on which they were invested with that jurisdiction.</p>
            <blockList id="section-32.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendment</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.2.list2.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 32, for the words and figures “Chapters III and IV”, substitute the words and figures “Chapters III, IV and IV-A”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act and Code to Court so invested as to two Courts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Court invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes, with respect to the exercise of that jurisdiction, and the same Court, with respect to the exercise of its jurisdiction in suits of a civil nature which are not cognizable by a Court of Small Causes, shall, for the purposes of this Act and the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882) be deemed to be different Courts.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Modification of Code as so applied.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything in the last two foregoing sections,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>when, in exercise of the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes, a Court invested with that jurisdiction sends a decree for execution to itself as a Court having jurisdiction in suits of a civil nature which are not cognizable by a Court of Small Causes, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when a Court, in the exercise of its jurisdiction in suits of a civil nature which are not cognizable by a Court of Small Causes, sends a decree for execution to itself as a Court invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the documents mentioned in section224 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882) shall not be sent with the decree unless in any case the Court, by order in writing, requires them to be sent.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of proceedings of abolished Courts.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a Court of Small Causes, or a Court invested with the jurisdiction of a Court of Small Causes, has from any cause ceased to have jurisdiction with respect to any case, any proceeding in relation to the case, whether before or after decree, which, if the Court had not ceased to have jurisdiction, might have been therein, may be had in the Court which, if the suit out of which the proceeding has arisen were about to be instituted, would have jurisdiction to try the suit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section applies to cases from which special provision is made in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882), as extended to Courts of Small Causes, or in any other enactment for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Indian Limitation Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Publication of certain orders.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All orders required by this Act to be made in writing by the</p>
            <p>State Government shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
            <p>The Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887</p>
            <p>THE FIRST SCHEDULE—Enactments repealed.—</p>
            <p>Rep. by Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), sec. 2 and Sch. I.</p>
            <p>The Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1The">
        <num>1The.</num>
        <heading>Second Schedule</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1The.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(See section 15)</p>
            <p>Suits Excepted from the Cognizance of a Court of Small Causes</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1The.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit concerning any act done or purporting to be done by or by order of the Central Government, the Crown Representative or the State Government; tc "(1) a suit concerning any act done or purporting to be done by or by order of the Central Government, the Crown Representative or the State Government;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit concerning an act purporting to be done by any person in pursuance of a judgment or order of a Court or of a judicial officer acting in the execution of his office; tc "(2) a suit concerning an act purporting to be done by any person in pursuance of a judgment or order of a Court or of a judicial officer acting in the execution of his office;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit concerning an act or order purporting to be done or made by any other officer of the Government in his official capacity, or by a Court of Wards, or by an officer of a Court of Wards in the execution of his office; tc "(3) a suit concerning an act or order purporting to be done or made by any other officer of the Government in his official capacity, or by a Court of Wards, or by an officer of a Court of Wards in the execution of his office;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the possession of immoveable property or for the recovery of an interest in such property; tc "(4) a suit for the possession of immoveable property or for the recovery of an interest in such property;"</p>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra. tc "Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra."</p>
            <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961). tc "Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961)."</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (4) shall be omitted. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (4) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985). tc "Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)."</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, for clause (4), substitute the following clause, namely:— tc "Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, for clause (4), substitute the following clause, namely\:—"</p>
            <p>“(4) a suit for the possession of immoveable property or for the recovery of an interest in such property, but not including a suit by a lessor for the eviction of a lessee from a building after the determination of his lease, and for the recovery from him of compensation for the use and occupation of that building after such determination of lease. tc " “(4) a suit for the possession of immoveable property or for the recovery of an interest in such property, but not including a suit by a lessor for the eviction of a lessee from a building after the determination of his lease, and for the recovery from him of compensation for the use and occupation of that building after such determination of lease."</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this Article, the expression ‘building’ means a residential or non-residential roofed structure, and includes any land (including any garden), garages, out-houses, appurtenant to such building, and also includes any fittings and fixtures affixed to the building for the more beneficial enjoyment thereof.” tc " Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this Article, the expression ‘building’ means a residential or non-residential roofed structure, and includes any land (including any garden), garages, out-houses, appurtenant to such building, and also includes any fittings and fixtures affixed to the building for the more beneficial enjoyment thereof.”"</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 37 of 1972, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 20-9-1972). tc "Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 37 of 1972, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 20-9-1972)."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the partition of immoveable property; tc "(5) a suit for the partition of immoveable property;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit by a mortgagee of immoveable property for the foreclosure of the mortgage or for the sale of the property, or by a mortgagor of immoveable property for the redemption of the mortgage; tc "(6) a suit by a mortgagee of immoveable property for the foreclosure of the mortgage or for the sale of the property, or by a mortgagor of immoveable property for the redemption of the mortgage;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the assessment, enhancement, abatement or apportionment of the rent of immoveable property; tc "(7) a suit for the assessment, enhancement, abatement or apportionment of the rent of immoveable property;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the recovery of rent, other than house rent, unless the Judge of the Court of Small Causes has been expressly invested by the State Government with authority to exercise jurisdiction with respect thereto; tc "(8) a suit for the recovery of rent, other than house rent, unless the Judge of the Court of Small Causes has been expressly invested by the State Government with authority to exercise jurisdiction with respect thereto;"</p>
            <p>State Amendments</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (8) shall be omitted. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (8) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985). tc "Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)."</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (8) shall be omitted. tc "Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (8) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954). tc "Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954). "</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit concerning the liability of land to be assessed to land revenue; tc "(9) a suit concerning the liability of land to be assessed to land revenue;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit is restrain waste; tc "(10) a suit is restrain waste;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the determination or enforcement of any other right to or interest in immoveable property; tc "(11) a suit for the determination or enforcement of any other right to or interest in immoveable property;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the possession of an hereditary office or of an interest in such an office, including a suit to establish an exclusive or periodically recurring right to discharge the functions of an office; tc "(12) a suit for the possession of an hereditary office or of an interest in such an office, including a suit to establish an exclusive or periodically recurring right to discharge the functions of an office;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to enforce payment of the allowance or fees respectively called malikana and hakk, or of ceases or other dues when the cesses or dues are payable to a person by reason of his interest in immoveable property or in an hereditary office or in a shrine or other religious institution; tc "(13) a suit to enforce payment of the allowance or fees respectively called malikana and hakk, or of ceases or other dues when the cesses or dues are payable to a person by reason of his interest in immoveable property or in an hereditary office or in a shrine or other religious institution;"</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (13), after the words “other religious institution” insert the words “but not including any such suit where the right is based on a contract reduced to writing.”</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to recover from a person to whom compensation has been paid under the Land Acquisition Act, 1870 (10 of 1870)3, the whole or any part of the compensation; tc "(14) a suit to recover from a person to whom compensation has been paid under the Land Acquisition Act, 1870 (10 of 1870)1, the whole or any part of the compensation;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the specific performance or rescission of a contract; tc "(15) a suit for the specific performance or rescission of a contract;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the rectification or cancellation of an instrument; tc "(16) a suit for the rectification or cancellation of an instrument;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to obtain in injunction; tc "(17) a suit to obtain in injunction;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit relating to a trust, including a suit to make good out of the general estate of a deceased trustee the loss occasioned by a breach of trust, and a suit by a co-trustee to enforce against the estate of a deceased trustee a claim for contribution; tc "(18) a suit relating to a trust, including a suit to make good out of the general estate of a deceased trustee the loss occasioned by a breach of trust, and a suit by a co-trustee to enforce against the estate of a deceased trustee a claim for contribution;"</p>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra. tc "Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra."</p>
            <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19</p>
            <p>(w.e.f. 4-11-1961). tc "Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19</p>
            <p>(w.e.f. 4-11-1961)."</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (18) for the words “relating to a trust”, substitute the words “to enforce a trust”. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (18) for the words “relating to a trust”, substitute the words “to enforce a trust”."</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (2) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1959); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3). tc "Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (2) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1959); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3)."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for a declaratory decree not being a suit instituted under section 283 or section 332 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882); tc "(19) a suit for a declaratory decree not being a suit instituted under section 283 or section 332 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882);"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1The.20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit instituted under 4section 283 or section 332 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882); tc "(20) a suit instituted under</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2section">
        <num>2section.</num>
        <heading>283 or section 332 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882);"</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2section.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra. tc "Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra."</p>
            <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961).</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (20), for the words “Code of Civil Procedure”, add the words “in respect of any immoveable property”. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (20), for the words “Code of Civil Procedure”, add the words “in respect of any immoveable property”."</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (3) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1959); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3). tc "Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (3) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1959); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3)."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2section.21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to set aside an attachment by a Court or a revenue-authority, or a sale, mortgage, lease or other transfer by a Court or a revenue-authority or by a guardian; tc "(21) a suit to set aside an attachment by a Court or a revenue-authority, or a sale, mortgage, lease or other transfer by a Court or a revenue-authority or by a guardian;"</p>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra. tc "Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra."</p>
            <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961).</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-2section.21.list8">
              <listIntroduction>In Second Schedule, in clause (21),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2section.21.list8.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>after the word ‘attachment’ add the words “of any immovable property”;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2section.21.list8.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>after the word ‘transfer’, add the words “of any such property”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (4) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3). tc "Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (4) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958,</p>
            <p>sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3)."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2section.22">
          <num>(22)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for property which the plaintiff has conveyed while insane; tc "(22) a suit for property which the plaintiff has conveyed while insane;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2section.23">
          <num>(23)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to alter or set aside a decision, decree or order of a Court or of a person acting in a judicial capacity; tc "(23) a suit to alter or set aside a decision, decree or order of a Court or of a person acting in a judicial capacity;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2section.24">
          <num>(24)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to contest an award; tc "(24) a suit to contest an award;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2section.25">
          <num>(25)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit upon a foreign judgment as defined in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882)5 or upon a judgment obtained in India; tc "(25) a suit upon a foreign judgment as defined in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882)1 or upon a judgment obtained in</p>
            <p>India;"</p>
            <p>State Amendment tc "State Amendment"</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (25) shall be omitted. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (25) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985). tc "Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2section.26">
          <num>(26)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to compel a refund of assets improperly distributed under 7section 295 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882); tc "(26) a suit to compel a refund of assets improperly distributed under</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3section">
        <num>3section.</num>
        <heading>295 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882);"</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3section.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (26) shall be omitted. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (26) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985). tc "Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)."</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (26) shall be omitted. tc "Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (26) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3(1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954). tc "Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3(1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954)."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3section.27">
          <num>(27)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit under the</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8Indian">
        <num>8Indian.</num>
        <heading>Succession Act, 1865 (10 of 1865), section 320 or section 321 or under the Probate and Administration Act, 1881 (5 of 1881), section 139 or section 140, to compel a refund by a person to whom an executor or administrator has paid a legacy or distributed assets. tc "(27) a suit under the</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4Indian">
        <num>4Indian.</num>
        <heading>Succession Act, 1865 (10 of 1865), section 320 or section 321 or under the Probate and Administration Act, 1881 (5 of 1881), section 139 or section 140, to compel a refund by a person to whom an executor or administrator has paid a legacy or distributed assets."</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.28">
          <num>(28)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for legacy or for the whole or a share of a residue bequeathed by a testator, or for the whole or a share of the property of an intestate; tc "(28) a suit for legacy or for the whole or a share of a residue bequeathed by a testator, or for the whole or a share of the property of an intestate;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.29">
          <num>(29)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4Indian.29.list1">
              <listIntroduction>a suit—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4Indian.29.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for a dissolution of partnership or for the winding up of the business of a partnership after its dissolution; tc " (a) for a dissolution of partnership or for the winding up of the business of a partnership after its dissolution;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.29.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for an account of partnership-transactions; or tc " (b) for an account of partnership-transactions; or"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.29.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for a balance of partnership-account, unless the balance has been struck by the parties or their agents; tc " (c) for a balance of partnership-account, unless the balance has been struck by the parties or their agents;"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.30">
          <num>(30)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for an account of property and for its due administration under decree; tc "(30) a suit for an account of property and for its due administration under decree;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.31">
          <num>(31)</num>
          <content>
            <p>any other suit for an account, including a suit by a mortgagor, after the mortgage has been satisfied, to recover surplus collections received by the mortgagee, and a suit for the profits of immoveable property belonging to the plaintiff which have been wrongfully received by the defendant; tc "(31) any other suit for an account, including a suit by a mortgagor, after the mortgage has been satisfied, to recover surplus collections received by the mortgagee, and a suit for the profits of immoveable property belonging to the plaintiff which have been wrongfully received by the defendant;"</p>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra. tc "Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra."</p>
            <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act, however, ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961).</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (31), for the words “and a suit for the profits on immovable property belonging to the plaintiff which have been wrongfully received by the defendant”, substitute the words “but not included a suit for mesne profits”. tc "Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (31), for the words “and a suit for the profits on immovable property belonging to the plaintiff which have been wrongfully received by the defendant”, substitute the words “but not included a suit for mesne profits”."</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 6 of 1930, sec. 3 (5) (w.e.f. 9-5-1930) read with Act 87 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 3).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.32">
          <num>(32)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for a general average loss or for salvage; tc "(32) a suit for a general average loss or for salvage;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.33">
          <num>(33)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for compensation in respect of collision between ships; tc "(33) a suit for compensation in respect of collision between ships;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.34">
          <num>(34)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit on a policy of insurance or for the recovery of any premium paid under any such policy; tc "(34) a suit on a policy of insurance or for the recovery of any premium paid under any such policy;"</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (34) shall be omitted.</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4Indian.35">
          <num>(35)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4Indian.35.list1">
              <listIntroduction>a suit for compensation— tc "(35) a suit for compensation—"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for loss occasioned by the death of a person caused by actionable wrong; tc " (a) for loss occasioned by the death of a person caused by actionable wrong;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for wrongful arrest, restraint or confinement; tc " (b) for wrongful arrest, restraint or confinement;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for malicious prosecution; tc " (c) for malicious prosecution;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for libel; tc " (d) for libel;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for slander; tc " (e) for slander;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for adultery or seduction; tc " (f) for adultery or seduction;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for breach of contract of betrothal or promise of marriage; tc " (g) for breach of contract of betrothal or promise of marriage;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4Indian.35.list1.h.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for inducing a person to break a contract made with the plaintiff; tc " (h) for inducing a person to break a contract made with the plaintiff;"</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.h.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>for obstruction of an easement or diversion of a water courses; tc " (i) for obstruction of an easement or diversion of a water courses;"</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.h.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>for an act which is, or, save for the provisions of Chapter IV of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) would be, an offence, punishable under Chapter XVII of the said Code; tc "</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.h.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>for an act which is, or, save for the provisions of Chapter IV of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) would be, an offence, punishable under Chapter XVII of the said Code;"</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>for illegal, improper or excessive distress, attachment or search, or for trespass, committed in, or damage caused by, the illegal or improper execution of any distress, search or legal process; tc "</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>for illegal, improper or excessive distress, attachment or search, or for trespass, committed in, or damage caused by, the illegal or improper execution of any distress, search or legal process;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4Indian.35.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>for improper arrest under 11Chapter XXXIV of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882) or in respect of the issue of an injunction wrongfully obtained under 2Chapter XXXV of that Code; or tc " (k) for improper arrest under</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2Chapter">
        <num>2Chapter.</num>
        <heading>XXXIV of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882) or in respect of the issue of an injunction wrongfully obtained under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2Chapter">
        <num>2Chapter.</num>
        <heading>XXXV of that Code; or"</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2Chapter.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2Chapter.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2Chapter.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>for injury to the person in any case not specified in the foregoing sub-clauses of this clause; tc " (l) for injury to the person in any case not specified in the foregoing sub-clauses of this clause;"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (35), sub-clause (ii) shall be omitted. tc "Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (35), sub-clause (ii) shall be omitted."</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954). tc "Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954)."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.36">
          <num>(36)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit by a Muhammadan for exigible (mu’ajjal) or deferred (mu’wajjal) dower; tc "(36) a suit by a Muhammadan for exigible (mu’ajjal) or deferred (mu’wajjal) dower;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.37">
          <num>(37)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for the restitution of conjugal rights,  for the custody of a minor, or for a divorce; tc "(37) a suit for the restitution of conjugal rights,</p>
            <p>*** for the custody of a minor, or for a divorce;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.38">
          <num>(38)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit relating to maintenance; tc "(38) a suit relating to maintenance;"</p>
            <p>State Amendments</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, in clause (38), after the words “relating to maintenance” add the words “but not including any suit where the rights is based on a contract reduced in writing”.</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 24 of 1982, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985).</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, for clause (38), substitute the following clauses, namely:—</p>
            <p>“(38) a suit relating to maintenance but not being a suit for recovery of arrears of maintenance based upon a decree or written agrrangement.”</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (2) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.39">
          <num>(39)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for arrears of land-revenue, village-expenses or other sums payable to the representative of a village community or to his heir or other successor in title; tc "(39) a suit for arrears of land-revenue, village-expenses or other sums payable to the representative of a village community or to his heir or other successor in title;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.40">
          <num>(40)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for profits payable by the representative of a village-community or by his heir or other successor in title after payment of land-revenue, village-expenses and other sums; tc "(40) a suit for profits payable by the representative of a village-community or by his heir or other successor in title after payment of land-revenue, village-expenses and other sums;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.41">
          <num>(41)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit for contribution by a sharer in joint property in respect of a payment made by him of money due from a co-sharer, or by a manager of joint property, or a member of an undivided family, in respect of a payment made by him on account of the property of family; tc "(41) a suit for contribution by a sharer in joint property in respect of a payment made by him of money due from a co-sharer, or by a manager of joint property, or a member of an undivided family, in respect of a payment made by him on account of the property of family;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.42">
          <num>(42)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit by one of several joint mortgagors of immoveable property for contribution in respect of money paid by him for the redemption of the mortgaged property; tc "(42) a suit by one of several joint mortgagors of immoveable property for contribution in respect of money paid by him for the redemption of the mortgaged property;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.43">
          <num>(43)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit against the Government to recover money paid under protest in satisfaction of a claim made by a revenue-authority on account of an arrear of land-revenue or of a demand recoverable as an arrear of land-revenue; tc "(43) a suit against the Government to recover money paid under protest in satisfaction of a claim made by a revenue-authority on account of an arrear of land-revenue or of a demand recoverable as an arrear of land-revenue;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.43A">
          <num>(43A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit to recover property obtained by an act which is, or save for the provisions of Chapter IV of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), would be, an offence punishable under Chapter XVII of the said Code; tc "(43A) a suit to recover property obtained by an act which is, or save for the provisions of Chapter IV of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), would be, an offence punishable under Chapter XVII of the said Code;"</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In Second Schedule, clause (43A) shall be omitted.</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch., Item 3 (1) (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2Chapter.44">
          <num>(44)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a suit the cognizance whereof by a Court of Small Causes is barred by any enactment for the time being in force. tc "(44) a suit the cognizance whereof by a Court of Small Causes is barred by any enactment for the time being in force."</p>
            <p>State Amendments tc "State Amendments"</p>
            <p>Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra. tc "Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>Same as that of Maharashtra."</p>
            <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961). tc "Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 and Gujarat A.L.O., 1960. The Act ceases to apply to the City of Ahmedabad—See Gujarat Act 19 of 1961, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 4-11-1961)."</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.—</p>
            <p>After the Second Schedule, insert the following Schedule, namely:—</p>
            <p>“The Third Schedule</p>
            <p>Form A</p>
            <p>(See section 27B)</p>
            <p>In the Court of Small Causes of ..................................</p>
            <p>A.B. ........................................................................................(Plaintiff)</p>
            <p>vs.</p>
            <p>C.D. ........................................................................................(Defendant)</p>
            <p>A.B., of ........................in the town of ........................maketh oath (or affirms) and saith that C.D. ........................ of ........................... is justly indebted to ........................ in the sum of Rs. ........................ for arrears of rent of the house and premises No. ........................ situated at ........................ in the town of/village ........................ due for ........................ months, to wit, from ........................ to ........................ at the rate of Rs. ........................ per mensem:</p>
            <p>Sworn (or affirmed) before me........................ day of ........................20.........</p>
            <p>Judge of the Court of Small Causes of........................</p>
            <p>Form B</p>
            <p>(See section 27C)</p>
            <p>In the Court of Small Causes of ........................</p>
            <p>Form of Warrant</p>
            <p>I hereby direct you to distrain the moveable property of C.D., on the house and premises at No. ........................, in the town/village of ........................ for the sum of Rs. ........................, and the costs of the distress, according to the provisions of Chapter IVA of the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887.</p>
            <p>Dated the ........................ day of ........................ 20.......</p>
            <blockList id="section-2Chapter.44.list25">
              <listIntroduction>Seal</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2Chapter.44.list25.Signature">
                <num>(Signature)</num>
                <p>To</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>F.F. Bailiff.</p>
            <p>Form c</p>
            <p>(See section 27-I)</p>
            <p>In the Court of Small Causes of ........................</p>
            <p>Form of Inventory and Notice</p>
            <p>(state particulars of property seized)</p>
            <p>Take notice that I have this day seized the moveable property contained in the above inventory for the sum of Rs. ........................, being the amount of ........................ months’ rent due to A.B., at ........................ last, and that unless you pay the amount thereof, together with the costs of this distress, within fifteen days from the date hereof, or obtain an order from the Court of Small Causes to the contrary, the same will be appraised and sold pursuant to the provisions of Chapter IVA of the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887.</p>
            <p>Dated the ........................ day of ........................20.......</p>
            <p>Signature</p>
            <p>Bailiff</p>
            <p>To</p>
            <p>C.D.</p>
            <p>Form D</p>
            <p>(See section 27N)</p>
            <p>In the Court of Small Causes of ........................</p>
            <p>Take notice that I have appraised the moveable property seized on the ........................day of ........................ under the provisions of Chapter IVA of the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887, of which seizure and property a notice and inventory were duly served upon you (or upon ........................ on your behalf, as the case may be) under date the ........................ and that the said property will be sold on the ........................ (two clear days at least after the date of the notice) at ........................ pursuant to the provisions of the said Act.</p>
            <p>Dated the ........................ day of........................ 20.........</p>
            <p>Signature</p>
            <p>Nazir and Appraiser.</p>
            <p>To</p>
            <p>C.D.</p>
            <p>Form E</p>
            <p>(See section 27P)</p>
            <p>In the Court of Small Causes of ........................</p>
            <p>Scale of Fees to be levied in distraints for house rent</p>
            <p>Sum Sued for</p>
            <p>Affidavits and Warrant to Sell</p>
            <p>Order to Sell</p>
            <p>Commission</p>
            <p>Total</p>
            <p>Rs.</p>
            <p>Rs.</p>
            <p>Rs. nP.</p>
            <p>Rs. nP.</p>
            <p>Rs. nP.</p>
            <p>Rs. nP.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-25</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-25</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-0">
        <num>0.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-0.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-75</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-25</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-25</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-75</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-60">
        <num>60.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-50</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-80">
        <num>80.</num>
        <heading>and under</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
            <p>upwards of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-00</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>per centum</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>.....</p>
            <p>The above scale includes all expenses, except in suits where the tenant disputes the landlord’s claim, and witnesses have to be summoned, in which case each summons must be paid for at twenty-five naya paise each for sums under rupees 40 and seventy-five naye paise each for sums above that amount; and also where peons are kept in charge of property distrained such fee not exceeding seventy-five naye paise per day as may be fixed by the Registrar of Small Cause Court must be paid per man.” tc "The above scale includes all expenses, except in suits where the tenant disputes the landlord’s claim, and witnesses have to be summoned, in which case each summons must be paid for at twenty-five naya paise each for sums under rupees 40 and seventy-five naye paise each for sums above that amount; and also where peons are kept in charge of property distrained such fee not exceeding seventy-five naye paise per day as may be fixed by the Registrar of Small Cause Court must be paid per man.”"</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 87 of 1958, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 15-10-1958); Act 11 of 1960, section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>This Schedule has been amended in its applications to the Bombay Presidency by sec. 2 of the Provicial Small Cause Courts (Bombay Amendment) Act, 1930 (Bombay Act 6 of 1930); and by sec. 2 of the Provincial Small Cause Courts (Bombay Amendment) Act, 1932 (Bombay Act 9 of 1932).</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for paragraph (1). tc " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for paragraph (1)."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>See now the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894). tc " 1. See now the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894)."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), Sch. I, Order XXI, rules 63 and 100, respectively.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, for “a Part A State or a Part C State”.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), section 73.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>See now the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), sections 360 and 361.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Ins. by Act 6 of 1914, sec. 2. tc " 1. Ins. by Act 6 of 1914, sec. 2."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 6 of 1914, sec. 2, for item (j). tc " 1. Subs. by Act 6 of 1914, sec. 2, for item (j)."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), Sch. I, Order XXXVIII and XXXIX, respectively, and section 95.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>The words “for the recovery of a wife” omitted by Act 10 of 1914, sec. 3 and Sch. II.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Ins. by Act 6 of 1914, sec. 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
