<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Immigrants (Expulsion From Assam) Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/10/eng@1950-03-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/10/eng@1950-03-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1950-03-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/10/eng@1950-03-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/10/eng@1950-03-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Immigrants (Expulsion From Assam) Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 10 OF 1950</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 1st March, 1950]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the expulsion of certain Immigrants from Assam.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Immigrants (Expulsion from Assam) Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Power to order expulsion of certain immigrants. If the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government is of opinion that any person or class of persons, having  been ordinarily resident in any place outside India, has or have.</p>
            <p>whether before or after the commencement of this Act, come into Assam  and that the stay of such person or class of persons in Assam is  detrimental to the interests of the general public of India or of any  section thereof or of any Scheduled Tribe in Assam, the Central</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Government may by order--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>direct such person or class of persons to remove  himself or themselves from India or Assam within such  time and by such route as may be specified in the  order; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>give such further directions in regard to his or their  removal from India or Assam as it may consider  necessary or expedient;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any person  who on account of civil disturbances or the fear of such disturbances  in any area now forming part of Pakistan has been displaced from or  has left his place of residence in such area and who has been  subsequently residing in Assam.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Delegation power. The Central Government may, by notification    in the Official Gazette, direct that the powers and duties  conferred or imposed on it by section 2 shall, subject to such  conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, be  exercised or discharged also by--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any officer subordinate to the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the   Government of Assam, Meghalaya] or Nagaland]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>or any officer subordinate to that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to give effect orders, etc. Any authority empowered by  or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act to exercise any power  may, in addition to any other action expressly provided for in this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, take or cause to be taken such steps, and use or cause to be used  such force, as may in its opinion be reasonably necessary for the  effective exercise of such power.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalties. Any person who--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the  contravention of any order made under section 2, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>fails to comply with any direction given by any such  order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>harbours any person who has contravened any order made  under section 2 or has failed to comply with any  direction given by any such order,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three years  and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Protection to persons acting under this Act. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for  anything which in good faith done or intended to be done under this</p>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Construction of references to Assam. In this Act, except in  section 3, references to Assam shall be construed as including also a  reference to  the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the Union  territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.]]</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
