<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1862/04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1862/04"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Markets And Fairs Act, 1862"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1862/04/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1862/04/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1862/04/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1862/04/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Markets And Fairs Act, 1862</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[1st November 2012]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. IV of 1862</p>
        <p>An Act for regulating the establishment and the closure of markets and fairs.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS, the establishment of new markets or fairs in the neighbourhood of places where markets or fairs have been previously established leads to disputes between the owners of the lands on which such new and previously established markets or fairs are held, and such disputes not unfrequently occasion breaches of peace and serious inconvenience to the frequenters of such markets or fairs;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS, it is expedient to provide also for the closure of existing markets or fairs in the interests of the general public; It is enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>(1) No new market or fair to be established without permission-</p>
        <p>No person shall establish a new market or fair without permission, in writing, from the Magistrate of the District. If any person shall attempt to establish a new market or fair without such licence he shall, on conviction by a Magistrate of the first class, be subject to a fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or in default of payment, to simple imprisonment for any period not exceeding two months.</p>
        <p>(2) Person desiring to establish to apply to Magistrate-</p>
        <p>When any person desires to establish a new market or fair, he shall make application, in writing, to the Magistrate of the district. The application shall specify-</p>
        <p>the name of the place at which it is proposed to establish such new market or fair ; the days on which it is be held;</p>
        <p>the name of the place where the nearest existing market or fair is held;</p>
        <p>and the days on which it is be held;</p>
        <p>the distance, in English miles, between the two places; and</p>
        <p>the reasons of the applicant for desiring to establish a new market or fair;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Procedure on application-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of the application, the Magistrate, subject to the provisions of this section and of section 5A, may issue a proclamation stating the desire of the applicant to establish a market or fair at the place named by him and the days on which it is proposed to be held and calling upon any person who may have any objection to the establishment of the market or fair to state his objection, in writing, within six weeks from the date of the proclamation:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Magistrate instead of issuing a proclamation may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, dismiss the application summarily.</p>
            <p>If a proclamation is issued, it shall be fixed] in a conspicuous place in the village or town in or near to which it is proposed that the new market or fair shall be held, and a copy of same shall be affixed at the police station within the jurisdiction of which the village or town is situated, and in the Court of the Magistrate.</p>
            <p>If it shall appear that any existing market or fair is held within a distance of six miles from the place where it is proposed that the new market or fair shall be established, the Magistrate shall cause a notice, to the effect of the proclamation to be served upon the owner of the land where such existing market or fair is held.</p>
            <p>The proclamation and notice (if any), shall be issued and served at the expense of Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Order permitting establishment-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, within the time specified in the proclamation and notice (if any), no objection is preferred to the establishment of the proposed market or fair, the Magistrate of the district shall pass an order permitting it to be established.</p>
            <p>If within the time specified any objection is preferred, the Magistrate of the district shall inquire into the objection, and pass such order as may appear proper under the circumstances of the case.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Alteration of days on which market to be held-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Magistrate may, upon application or otherwise and after such enquiry (if any) as he thinks necessary, change or add to or reduce the days on which a market or fair is permitted under section 4 to be held.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Magistrate to consult Director of Agricultural Marketing and Rural Finance or authorised officer before passing orders-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No order under sections 3, 4, 7 [5, 5C or 5D] shall be made by the Magistrate of the District except in consultation with the Director of Agricultural Marketing and Rural Finance referred to in the Bombay Agricultural Produce Markets Act, 1939, or any officer authorised by the Director in this behalf or in consultation with any other officer specified by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5B">
        <num>5B.</num>
        <heading>Refusal of permission if within 5 miles a market or fair is already established-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If there be a market or fair within a distance of five miles from the place where it is proposed that the new market or fair shall be established, the Magistrate shall refuse permission to establish such new market or fair.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5C">
        <num>5C.</num>
        <heading>Power to close existing market or fair in public interest-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The District Magistrate, on an application made to him under this Act for the closure of an existing market or fair, if he is satisfied that it is necessary so to do-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the prevention of breaches of the peace or serious inconvenience to the frequenters of such market or fair, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>because of the vicinity of any place of public religious worship, educational institution, hostel, hospital, nursing home, or other public place to the market or fair and the consequent nuisance caused to such public place by the holdings of the market or fair, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>on grounds of public health, public convenience or safety, or the proper regulation of traffic,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may, by order in writing, direct that, from such date as is stated therein, either permanently or for a period specified in the order, such market or fair shall be closed and shall not be held at such place:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order shall be made by the Magistrate, unless he has followed the procedure set out in section 5D.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5D">
        <num>5D.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for closure of existing market or fair-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application for the closure of an existing market or fair under the last preceding section shall specify-</p>
            <p>the name of the place at which the existing market or fair is held;</p>
            <p>the days on which it is held;</p>
            <p>the name of the place in the vicinity where any other market or fair is held or proposed to be held;</p>
            <p>the days on which that market or fair is held or is proposed to be held;</p>
            <p>the distance in miles between the two places; and</p>
            <p>the reasons for the closure of the existing market or fair.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of such application, the District Magistrate shall issue a proclamation, stating therein that an application has been made to him for the closure of an existing market or fair and the reasons urged therefor, and calling upon all persons who may be interested in the holding of the market or fair, or who may have any objection to such closure, to submit their objections in writing to the Magistrate, within six weeks from the date of the proclamation. The District Magistrate shall also cause a notice, setting out the matter contained in the proclamation, to be served upon the owner of the land upon which the market or fair to be closed is held, and also upon the owner of such market or fair, calling upon them to show cause, within six weeks from the date of the notice, why such market or fair should not be closed:</p>
            <p>Provided that the District Magistrate, instead of issuing a proclamation and notice as aforesaid, may for reasons to be recorded in writing, dismiss the application summarily.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a proclamation is issued, it shall be fixed in a conspicuous place in the village or town in or near to which the market or fair to be closed is held, and a copy of the same shall be affixed at the police station within the jurisdiction of which the village or town is situated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Proclamation and notice (if any) shall be issued and served at the expense of Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, within the time specified in the proclamation and notice, no objection is preferred to the closure of the market or fair, the District Magistrate may forthwith, and if within such time any objection is preferred, the District Magistrate shall enquire into the objection, and, pass such order as may appear proper under the circumstances of the case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Appeal-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every order passed by a District Magistrate under section 3, 4, 5, 5C or 5D shall within six weeks, be open to appeal to such officer as the State Government may specify in this behalf (hereinafter in this section referred to as “the appellate authority”). The order made by the District Magistrate, subject to an appeal to the appellate authority, and the decision of the appellate authority on appeal, shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravening, disobeying, or opposing, order-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every person who shall contravene, disobey or oppose any order duly made under this Act, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or, in default of payment, to imprisonment for any period not exceeding two months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Delegation-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate may delegate his powers under this Act to any officer not below the rank of a Mahalkari in respect of the whole or any part of the area within the jurisdiction of such officer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Extent-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall extend to the whole of the State of Maharashtra except Greater Bombay.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“market” includes a bazaar, but does not include-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a market belonging to, maintained, established or regulated by a local authority under any law relating to local authorities and for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an assemblage of people collected at, or concerned in, the inauguration of sacred edifices, or collected at or concerned in, any other religious festival or ceremonies not forming a part of a fair or market;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“a District Magistrate” or “Magistrate of the District” includes any other Magistrate, whom the State Government may, in respect of any area, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Saving of general powers of State Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Meaning of “Magistrate” Repealed by Bom. III of 1886.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
