<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1938/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1938/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Manceuvres, Field Firing And Artillerypractice Act, 1938"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1938/5/eng@1938-03-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1938/5/eng@1938-03-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1938-03-12" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1938/5/eng@1938-03-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1938/5/eng@1938-03-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Manceuvres, Field Firing And Artillerypractice Act, 1938</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 5 OF 1938</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 12th March, 1938.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide facilities for military manceuvres and for field  firing and artillery practice.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide facilities for military  manoeuvres and for field firing and artillery practice; It is hereby  enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the  manceuvres, Field Firing and Artillery Practice Act, 1938.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>MANCEUVRES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MANCEUVRES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to authorise manoeuvres.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>State Government may, by notification in the local Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>authorise the execution of military manoeuvres over any area specified  in the notification during a specified period not exceeding three  months:</p>
              <p>Provided that the same area or any part thereof shall not  ordinarily be so specified more than once in any period of three  years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall publish notice of its intention  to issue a notification under sub- section (1) as early as possible in  advance of the issue of the notification, and no such notification  shall be issued until the expiry of three months from the date of the  first publication of such notice in the local Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notice required by sub- section (2) shall be given by  publication in the local Official Gazette and shall also be given  throughout the area which it is proposed to specify in the  notification by publica-</p>
              <p>tion in the manner prescribed by rules made under section 13, and  shall be repeated by like publication one month and one week as nearly  as may be before the commencement of the manoeuvres.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Power exercisable for purposes of manoeuvres.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where a  notification under sub- section (1) of section 2 has been issued, such  persons as are included in the military forces engaged in the  manoeuvres may, within the specified limits and during the specified  periods,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>pass over, or encamp, construct military works of a  temporary character, or execute military manoeuvres on, the  area specified in the notification, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>supply themselves with water from any source of water  in such area:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that nothing herein contained shall authorise the  taking of water from any source of supply, whether belonging  to a private owner or a public authority, of an amount in  excess of the reasonable requirements of the military forces  or of such amount as to curtain the supply ordinarily  required by those entitled to the use of such water supply.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall not authorise entry  on or interference with any well or tank held sacred by any religious  community or any place of worship or ground attached thereto except  for the ligitimate purpose of offering prayers or any place or  building reserved or used for the disposal of the dead, or any  dwelling house or premises attached thereto or any educational  institution, factory, workshop or store or any premises used for the  carrying on of any trade, business or manufacture or any garden or  pleasure ground, or any ancient monument as defined in section 2 of  the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act, 1904. (7 of 1904.)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Duty of Officer Commanding to repair damage. The Officer in</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Command of the military forces engaged in the manoeuvres shall cause  all lands used under the powers conferred by this Chapter to be  restored, as soon and as far as practicable, to their previous  condition.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Right to compensation for damage caused by manoeuvres. Where  a notification issued under section 2 authorises the execution of  military manoeuvres compensation shall be payable from the Defence</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Estimates for any damage to person or property or interference with  rights or privileges arising from such manoeuvres including expenses  reasonably incurred in protecting person, property, rights and  privileges.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Method of assessing compensation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Collector of the  district in which any area utilised for the purpose of manoeuvres is  situated shall depute one or more Revenue Officers to accompany the  forces engaged in the manoeuvres for the purpose of determining the  amount of any compensation payable under section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Revenue Officer shall consider all claims for  compensation under section 5 and determine, on local investigation and  where possible after hearing the claimant, the amount of compensation,</p>
              <p>if any, which shall be awarded in each case; and shall disburse on the  spot to the claimant the compensation so determined as payable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any claimant, dissatisfied with a refusal of the Revenue</p>
              <p>Officer to award him compensation or with the amount of compensation  awarded to him by the Revenue Officer, may, at any time within fifteen  days from the communication to him of the decision of the Revenue</p>
              <p>Officer, give notice to the Revenue Officer of his intention to appeal  against the decision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any such notice has been given, the Collector of the  district shall constitute a commission consisting of himself as chair-</p>
              <p>man, a person nominated by the Officer Commanding the forces engaged  in the manoeuvres and two persons nominated by the District Board, and  the commission shall decide all appeals of which notice has been  given.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The commission may exercise its powers notwithstanding the  absence of any member of the commission, and the chairman of the  commission shall have a casting vote in the case of an equal division  of opinion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the commission shall be final and no suit  shall lie in any Civil Court in respect of any matter decided by the  commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No fee shall be charged in connection with any claim,</p>
              <p>notice, appeal, application or document filed before the Revenue</p>
              <p>Officer, Collector or the commission under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Offences. If, within the area and during the period  specified in a notification under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 2, any  person-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>wilfully obstructs or interferes with the execution of  the manoeuvres, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>without due authority enters or remains in any camp, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>without due authority interferes with any flag or mark  or any apparatus used for the purposes of the manoeuvres,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to ten rupees.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FIELD FIRING AND ARTILLERY PRACTICE</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FIELD FIRING AND ARTILLERY PRACTICE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Chapter-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" field firing" includes air armament practice;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" notified area" means an area defined in a  notification issued under sub- section (1) of section 9.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to authorise field firing and  artillery practice.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in  the local Official Gazette, define any area as an area within which  for a specified term of years the carrying out periodically of field  firing and artillery practice may be authorised.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the local</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, authorise the carrying out of field firing and  artillery practice throughout a notified area or any specified part  thereof during any period or periods specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before any notification under sub- section (2) is issued, the</p>
              <p>State Government shall publish notice of its intention to issue such  notification as early as possible in advance of the issue of the  notification, and no such notification shall be issued until the  expiry of two months from the date of the first publication of the  notice in the local Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notice required by sub- section (3) shall be given by  publication in the local Official Gazette and shall also be given  throughout the notified area by publication in some newspaper  circulating in and in the language commonly understood in that area  and by beat of drum and by affixation in all prominent places of  copies of the said notice in the language of the locality and in such  other manner as may be prescribed by rules made under section 13 and  shall be repeated by like publication one week as nearly as may be  before the commencement of the period or of each period specified in  the notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that the fact of the said beat of drum and affixation  shall be verified in writing by one headman and two other literate  inhabitants of the locality and provided further that such notice by  the beat of drum shall be given seven and two days as nearly as may be  before the commencement of such field firing and artillery practice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Powers exercisable for purposes of field firing and artillery  practice.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where a notification under sub- section (2) of section 9  has been issued, such persons as are included in the forces engaged in  field firing or artillery practice may, within the notified area or  specified part thereof during the specified period or periods,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>carry out field firing and artillery practice with  lethal missiles, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>exercise, subject to the provisions of sections 3 and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, any of the rights conferred by section 3 on forces engaged  in military manoeuvres:</p>
              <p>Provided that the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 3  shall not debar entry into, or interference with, any place specified  in that sub- section, if it is situated in an area declared to be a  danger zone under sub- section (2) of this section, to the extent that  may be necessary to ensure the exclusion from it of persons and  domestic animals:</p>
              <p>Provided further that in the case of a dwelling house occupied by  women adequate warning shall be given through a local inhabitant and  entry shall be effected after such warning in the presence of two  respectable inhabitants of the locality.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Officer Commanding the forces engaged in any such  practice may, within the notified area or specified part thereof,</p>
              <p>declare any area to be a danger zone, and thereupon the Collector  shall, on application made to him by the Officer Commanding the forces  engaged in the practice, prohibit the entry into and secure the  removal from such danger zone of all persons and domestic animals  during the times when the discharge of lethal missiles is taking place  or there is danger to life or health.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Compensation. The provisions of sections 5 and 6 shall apply  in the case of field firing and artillery practice as they apply in  the case of military manoeuvres:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the compensation payable under this section shall  include compensation for exclusion or removal from any place declared  to be a danger zone of persons or domestic animals, such compensation  to be disbursed at not less than the minimum rates prescribed by rules  made under section 13 before the exclusion or removal is enforced, and  shall also include compensation for any loss of employment or  deterioration of crops resulting from any such exclusion or removal.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Offences. If, during any period specified in a notification  issued under sub- section (2) of section 9, any person within a  notified area-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>wilfully obstructs or interferes with the carrying out  of field firing or artillery practice, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>without due authority enters or remains in any camp, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>without due authority enters or remains in any area  declared to be a danger zone at a time when entry thereto is  prohibited, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>without due authority interferes with any flag or mark  or target or any apparatus used for the purposes of the  practice,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to ten rupees.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>GENERAL.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>GENERAL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules. The State Government may, by  notification in the local Official Gazette, make rules-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>prescribing the manner in which the notices required by  sub- section (2) of section 2 and sub- section (3) of section 9  shall be published in the areas concerned;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>regulating the use under this Act of land for  manoeuvres or field firing and artillery practice in such  manner as to secure the public against danger and to enable  the manoeuvre, or practice, to be carried out without inter-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>ference and with the minimum inconvenience to the inhabitants  of the areas affected;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>regulating the procedure of the Revenue Officers and  commissions referred to in section 6 in such manner as to  secure due publicity regarding the method of making claims  for compensation and preferring appeals from original awards  of compensation, the expeditious settlement of claims and of  appeals and the payment of compensation so far as possible  direct to the claimants; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>defining the principles to be followed by the Revenue</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Officers and commissions referred to in section 6 in assess-</p>
              <p>ing the amount of compensation to be awarded.</p>
              <p>The Indian Naval Reserve Forces (Discipline) Act, 1939. Rep.</p>
              <p>by the Navy Act, 1957 (62 of 1957), s. 186 (w. e. f. 1. 1. 1958).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
