<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/62/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/62"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Reserve Bank (Transfer To Public Ownership) Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/62/eng@1948-09-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/62/eng@1948-09-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1948-09-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/62/eng@1948-09-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/62/eng@1948-09-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Reserve Bank (Transfer To Public Ownership) Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 62 OF 1948</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 23rd September 1948.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to bring the share capital of the Reserve Bank of India into  public ownership and to make consequential amendments in the Reserve</p>
        <p>Bank of India Act, 1934.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.- This Act may be called the Reserve Bank (Transfer   to Public Ownership) Act, 1948.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means such day  as the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Gazette, appoint;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India as constituted by  the principal Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" principal Act" means the Reserve Bank of India Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1934">
        <num>1934.</num>
        <heading>(2 of 1934.)</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of Bank shares.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the appointed day--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all shares in the capital of the Bank shall by virtue of  this Act be deemed to be transferred free of all  trusts, liabilities and encumbrances to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Government, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>as full compensation therefor, the Central Government  shall issue to every person who, immediately before the  appointed day, is registered as the holder of any such  shares, an amount calculated at the rate of one hundred  and eighteen rupees and ten annas per share, in  promissory notes of the Central Government bearing  interest at the rate of three per centum per annum  repayable at par on such date as may be specified in  this behalf by the Central Government:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the amount so calculated is  not an exact multiple of one hundred rupees the amount  in excess of the nearest lower multiple of one hundred  rupees shall be paid by cheque drawn on the Bank:</p>
            <p>Provided further that in respect of any share  obtained at par from the Central Government by any</p>
            <p>Director of</p>
            <p>the Bank in pursuance of sub- section (8) of section 4  of the principal Act as in force immediately before the  appointed day, the said amount shall be calculated at  the rate of one hundred rupees per share.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding the transfer of shares effected by this  section any shareholder who, immediately before the appointed day, is  entitled to payment of dividend on the shares held by him shall be  entitled to receive from the Bank--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all dividends accruing due on his shares in respect of  the year ending on the 30th day of June, 1948, or any  preceding year remaining unpaid on the appointed day;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>dividends calculated at the rate of four rupees per  annum per share in respect of the period from the 1st  day of July, 1948, to the appointed day.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Vacation of office by existing office bearers.- On the  appointed day any person who immediately before that day was holding  office as a Director of the Central Board otherwise than as Governor  or Deputy Governor or as a member of a Local Board of the Bank shall  vacate his office, and the Central Board and the Local Boards of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Bank shall thereafter be constituted in the manner prescribed by  sections 8 and 9 of the principal Act as amended by this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Interim arrangements.- Pending the constitution of the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Board under section 8 of the principal Act as amended by this Act, the</p>
            <p>Governor of the Bank, or in his absence a Deputy Governor of the Bank  duly nominated by him in this behalf, may, subject to such  restrictions and conditions as may from time to time be imposed by the</p>
            <p>Central Government, exercise all powers, and do all acts and things  which may be exercised or done by the Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Rule- making power.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 1 for the purpose of  giving effect to the objects of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the manner in which and the authority by which  compensation shall be paid under section 3; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the determination of persons to whom compensation is  so payable.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Amendment to Act II of 1934. Rep. by the Repealing and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Amending Act, 1950 (35 of 1950).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
