<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1871/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1871/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Pensions' Act, 1871"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1871-08-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Pensions' Act, 1871</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 23 OF 1871</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 8th August, 1871.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Pensions  and</p>
        <p>Grants by Government of money or land- revenue.</p>
        <p>Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend  the  law relating to pensions and grants by Government of money or land-</p>
        <p>revenue; it is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>I.- PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.- This Act may be called the' Pensions' Act, 1871.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Extent of Act.-  In so far as it relates to Union pensions, it  extends to the whole of India and in so far as it relates to other  pensions, it extends] to  the whole of India except  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States]].</heading>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Enactments repealed. Saving of Rules Rep. by the Repealing</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2 and Sch.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation- section.- In this Act, the expression" grant  of money or land- revenue" includes anything payable on the part of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government in respect of any right, privilege, perquisite or office.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3A">
          <num>3A.</num>
          <heading>Definition.- The expression" the appropriate Government"</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>means, in relation to  Union] pensions, the Central Government, and  in relation to other pensions, the State Government.]</p>
              <p>II.- RIGHTS TO PENSIONS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Bar of suits relating to pensions.- Except as hereinafter  provided no Civil Court shall entertain any suit relating to any  pension or grant of money or land- revenue conferred or made by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government or by any former Government, whatever may have been the  consideration for any such pension or grant and whatever may have  been the nature of the payment, claim or right for which such pension  or grant may have been substituted.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Claims to be made to collector or other authorized officer.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person having a claim relating to any such pension or grant may  prefer such claim to the Collector of the District or Deputy</p>
              <p>Commissioner or other officer authorized in this behalf by the    appropriate Government] and such Collector, Deputy Commissioner or  other officer shall dispose of such claim in accordance with such  rules as the Chief Revenue authority may, subject to the general  control of the  appropriate Government], from time to time prescribe  in this behalf.</p>
              <p>(II.- Rights to Pensions. III. Mode of Payment. IV.- Miscellaneous)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Civil Court empowered to take cognizance of such claims.- A</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Civil Court, otherwise competent to try the same, shall take  cognizance of any such claim upon receiving a certificate from such</p>
              <p>Collector, Deputy Commissioner or other officer authorized in that  behalf that the case may be so tried, but shall not make any order or  decree in any suit whatever by which the liability of Government to  pay any such pension or grant as aforesaid is affected directly or  indirectly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Pensions for lands held under grants in perpetuity.- Nothing  in sections 4 and 6 applies to-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>any inam of the class referred to in section 1 of Madras Act</p>
              <p>No. IV of 18621;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>pensions heretofore granted by Government in the territories  respectively subject to the Lieutenant- Governors of Bengal and the</p>
              <p>North- Western Provinces, either wholly or in part as an indemnity for  loss sustained by the resumption by a Native Government of lands held  under sanads purporting to confer a right in perpetuity. Such  pensions shall not be liable to resumption on the death of the  recipient, but every such pension shall be capable of alienation and  descent, and may be sued for and recovered in the same manner as any  other property.</p>
              <p>III.- MODE OF PAYMENT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Payment to be made by Collector or other authorized  officer.- All pensions or grants by Government of money or land- revenue  shall be paid by the Collector or the Deputy Commissioner or other  authorized officer, subject to such rules as may, from time to time,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>be prescribed by the Chief Controlling Revenue- authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Saving of rights of grantees of land- revenue.- Nothing in  sections 4 and 8 shall affect the right of a grantee of land- revenue,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>whose claim to such grant is admitted by Government, to recover such  revenue from the persons liable to pay the same under any law for the  time being in force for the recovery of the rent of land.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Commutation of pensions.- The  appropriate Government] may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>with the consent of the holder, order the whole or any part of his  pension or grant of money or land- revenue to be commuted for a lump  sum on such terms as may seem fit.</p>
              <p>IV.- MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Exemption of pension from attachment.- No pension granted or  continued by Government on political considerations, or on account of  past services or present infirmities or as a compassionate allowance,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>and no money due or to become due on account of any such pension  or allowance,</p>
              <p>shall be liable to seizure, attachment or sequestration by  process of any Court at the instance of a creditor, for any demand  against the pensioner, or in satisfaction of a decree or order of any  such Court.</p>
              <p>This section applies  also to pensions granted or continued",</p>
              <p>after the separation of Burma from India, by the Government of Burma.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Assignments, etc., in anticipation of pension, to be void.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All assignments, agreements' orders, sales, and securities of every  kind made by the person entitled to any pension, Pay or allowance  mentioned in section 11, in respect of any money not payable at or  before the making thereof, on account of any such pension, Pay or  allowance, or for giving or assigning any future interest therein, are  null and void.</p>
              <p>(IV.- Miscellaneous.)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12A">
          <num>12A.</num>
          <heading>Nomination by Pensioner to receive moneys outstanding on  account of pension.-.-. Notwithstanding anything contained in section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>or in any other law for the time being in force,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any person to whom any pension mentioned in  section 11 is payable by the Government of India or out of  the Consolidated Fund of India (such person being hereinafter   referred to as the pensioner) may nominate any other person</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(hereinafter referred to as the nominee), in such manner and  in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government  by rules, to receive after the death of the pensioner, all  moneys payable to the pensioner on account of such pension  at, before or after the date of such nomination and which  remain unpaid immediately before the death of the pensioner;</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the nominee shall be entitled, on the death of the  pensioner, to receive, to the exclusion of all other persons,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>all such moneys which have so remained unpaid:</p>
              <p>provided that if the nominee predeceases the pensioner, the  nomination shall, so far as it relates to the right conferred upon the  said nominee, become void and of no effect:</p>
              <p>provided further that where provision has been duly made in the  nomination, in accordance with the rules made by the Central</p>
              <p>Government, conferring upon some other person the right to receive all  such moneys, which have so remained unpaid, in the event of the  nominee predeceasing the pensioner, such right shall, upon the decease  as aforesaid of the nominee, pass to such other person.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Reward to informers.- Whoever proves to the satisfaction of  the.  appropriate Government] that any pension is fraudulently or  unduly received by the person enjoying the benefit thereof shall be  entitled to a reward equivalent to the amount of such pension for the  period of six months.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-" In each State the Chief Controlling</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Revenue Authority may, with the consent of the appropriate</p>
              <p>Government, from time to time make rules consistent with this Act  respecting all or any of the following matters:-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the place and times at which, and the person to whom, any  pension shall be paid;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>inquiries into the identity of claimants;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>records to be kept on the subject of pensions;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>transmission of such records;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>correction of such records;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>delivery of certificates to pensioners;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>registers of such certificates;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>reference to the Civil Court, under section 6, of persons  claiming a right of succession to, or participation in, pensions or  grants of money or land- revenue payable by Government;</p>
              <p>and generally for the guidance of officers under this Act.</p>
              <p>All such rules shall be published in the Official Gazette, and shall  thereupon have the force of law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.- The Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, make rules to  provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner and form in which any nomination may be made  under section 12A and the manner and form in which such nomination may  be cancelled or varied by another nomination;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which provision may be made, for the purposes  of the second proviso to section 12A, in any such nomination for  conferring on some person other than the nominee the right to receive  moneys payable to the nominee if such nominee predeceases the  pensioner,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(IV- Miscellaneos. Schedule)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Laying of rules.- Every rule made by the Central Government  under this Act and every rule made under section 14 by a Chief</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Controlling Revenue Authority with the consent of the Central</p>
              <p>Government, shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before  each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period  of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-repbytherepealingact19381of1938s2andsch">
      <doc name="repbytherepealingact19381of1938s2andsch">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1871/23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1871/23"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Rep. by the repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2 and Sch."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1871/23/eng@1871-08-08"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="repbytherepealingact19381of1938s2andsch"/>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
