<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Opium And Revenue Laws (Extension Of Application) Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/33/eng@1950-04-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/33/eng@1950-04-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1950-04-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/33/eng@1950-04-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/33/eng@1950-04-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Opium And Revenue Laws (Extension Of Application) Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 33 OF 1950</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th April, 1950.] B</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the extension of certain opium and revenue laws  to certain parts of India.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Opium and Revenue Laws</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Extension of Application) Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Extension of certain opium and revenue laws to certain parts  of India.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The following Acts, namely,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the Opium Act, 1857 (13 of 1857),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the Opium Act, 1878 (1 of 1878),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the Revenue Recovery Act, 1890 (1 of 1890),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the Government Trading Taxation Act, 1926 (3 of 1926),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1930 (2 of 1930),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>the Taxation on Income (Investigation Commission) Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1947">
        <num>1947.</num>
        <heading>(30 of 1947), and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1947.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list0.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>the Payment of Taxes (Transfer of Property) Act, 1949</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>(22 of 1949),</p>
            <p>and all rules and orders made thereunder, which are in force  immediately before the commencement of this Act in certain parts of</p>
            <p>India, are hereby extended to and shall be in force in, the rest of</p>
            <p>India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1947.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amendments specified in the Schedule shall be made in the  aforesaid Acts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Modifications in State laws relating to income- tax  investigation. If immediately before the commencement of this Act  there is in force in any Part B State other than Jammu and Kashmir any  law (hereinafter in this section referred to as" the State law")</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>corresponding to the Taxation on Income (Investigation Commission)</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act, 1947 (30 of 1947), that law shall continue to remain in force  with the following modifications, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all cases referred to or pending before the State</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Commission (by whatever name called) in respect of  matters relating to taxation on income other than  agricultural income</p>
            <p>shall stand transferred to the Central Commission for  disposal:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Central Commission shall not, by reason  merely of the transfer of any case under the provisions  of this section, be bound to recall or rehear any  witness who has given evidence in the case, and may act  on the evidence already recorded by or produced before  the Commission which was originally investigating into  the case;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the disposal of cases transferred to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Commission under clause (a), it shall have and exercise  the same powers as it has and exercises in the  investigation of cases referred to it under the</p>
            <p>Taxation on Income (Investigation Commission) Act, 1947</p>
            <p>(30 of 1947), and shall be entitled to act for the  same term as under sub- section (3) of section 4 of that</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list11.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>any decision given, whether before or after the  commencement of this Act, by the Chief Revenue</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Authority of Travancore or of Travancore- Cochin in the  exercise or purported exercise of any powers conferred  on it by any law for the time being in force in the</p>
            <p>State shall be deemed to be a decision given by the</p>
            <p>Income- tax authority for the purposes of sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 8 of the Travancore Taxation on Income</p>
            <p>(Investigation Commission) Act, 1124;] (Travancore Act</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>XIV of 1124)</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any reference in the State Law, by whatever form of  words, to the State Government or the State Commission  shall, in relation to income other than agricultural  income, be construed as a reference to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government or the Central Commission, as the case may  be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the report of the Central Commission shall be submitted  to the Central Government, and the Central Government  may, by order in writing, direct that such proceedings  as it thinks fit under the law in force in the State  relating to income- tax, super- tax or excess profits tax  or any other law, shall be taken against the person to  whose case the report relates in respect of his income  other than agricultural income, and upon such a  direction being given, all such proceedings may be  taken and completed under the appropriate law  applicable in the State, as if the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>direction had been given and the proceedings had been  instituted thereunder;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list7.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>where under any law in force in the State the  agricultural income of an assessee is to be included in  his total income for the purpose of determining the tax  payable by him, the tax payable in respect of his  income other than agricultural income shall be an  amount bearing to the total amount of tax which would  have been payable under the appropriate law in force in  the State if a combined assessment had been made, the  same proportion as such income bears to the total  income including the agricultural income:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that for this purpose any reduction of tax allowed  on the agricultural income by the appropriate law in  force in the State shall not be taken into account.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- In this section," Central Commission" means the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Investigation Commission constituted under the Taxation on</p>
            <p>Income (Investigation Commission) Act, 1947 (30 of 1947).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Repeals and savings. If immediately before the commencement of  this Act there is in force in any Part B State, other than Jammu and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Kashmir, or in the merged territory of Cooch Behar any law  corresponding to any of the Acts specified in section 2, other than  the Taxation on Income (Investigation Commission) Act, 1947 (30 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1947">
        <num>1947.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1947.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), that law shall, upon the commencement of this Act, stand  repealed:</p>
            <blockList id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such repeal shall not affect--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the previous operation of that law, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in  respect of any offence committed against that law,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in  respect of any such penalty, forfeiture or  punishment;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be  instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or  punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:</p>
            <p>Provided further that anything done or any action taken under any  provision of that law shall be deemed to have been done or taken under  the corresponding provision of the Central Act as now extended to the</p>
            <p>State and shall continue in force accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Removal of difficulties. If any difficulty arises in giving  effect to the provisions of any of the Acts, rules or orders now  extended to any part of India in</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>which they were not in force before the commencement of this Act, the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>make such provision or give such direction as appears to it to be  necessary for removing the difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
