<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1912/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1912/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delhi Laws Act, 1912"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1912-09-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delhi Laws Act, 1912</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 13 OF 1912</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th September, 1912.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the application of the law in force in the</p>
        <p>Province of Delhi and for the extension of the enactments thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS by Proclamation  published in Notification No. 911,</p>
        <p>dated the seventeenth day of September, 1912, the Governor- General in</p>
        <p>Council, with the sanction and approbation of the Secretary of State  for India, has been pleased to take under his immediate authority and  management the territory mentioned in Schedule A, which was formerly  included within the Province of the Punjab, and to provide for the  administration thereof by a Chief Commissioner as a separate Province  to be known as the Province of Delhi;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the application of the  law in force in the said territory, and for the extension of other  enactments thereto; It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Delhi Laws Act, 1912; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the first day of October, 1912.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Saving of territorial application of enactments. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Proclamation referred to in the preamble shall not be deemed to have  effected any change in the territorial application of any enactment  notwithstanding that such enactment may be expressed to apply or  extend to the territories for the time being under any particular  administration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Construction of certain enactments in force in the territories  mentioned in Schedule A. All enactments made by any authority in</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>India] and all notifications, orders, schemes, rules, forms and by-</p>
            <p>laws issued, made or prescribed under such enactments which  immediately before the commencement of this Act were in force in, or  prescribed for, any of the territory mentioned in Schedule A, shall in  their application to that territory be construed as if references  therein to the authorities, or gazette mentioned in cloumn I of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleB">
      <doc name="scheduleB">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1912/13/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1912/13"/>
              <FRBRalias value="were references to the authorities, or gazette respectively  mentioned or referred to opposite there to in column 2 of that"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1912/13/eng@1912-09-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleB">
            <heading>Schedule.</heading>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Powers of Courts and State Government for purposes of  facilitating application of enactments. For the purpose of  facilitating the application to the territory mentioned in Schedule A</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>or any part thereof of any enactment passed</p>
                  <p>before the commencement of this Act or of any notification, order,</p>
                  <p>scheme, rule, form or by- law issued, made or prescribed under any such  enactment--</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-4.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any Court may, subject to the other provisions of this</p>
                  <p>Act, construe the enactment, notification, order,</p>
                  <p>scheme, rule, form or by- law with such alterations not  affecting the substance as may be necessary or proper  to adapt it to the matter before the Court, and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the State Government may, subject to the other  provisions of this Act, by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette direct by what officer any power or duty shall  be exercised or discharged, and any such notification  shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Vesting of powers of separate officers in single officer.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A notification issued under section 4, sub- section (2), may direct  that any powers or duties vested in separate officers may be  consolidated and vested in, and discharge by, a single officer.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where by such a notification appellate powers are  consolidated and vested in a single officer, the period of limitation  for the consolidated appeal shall be the longest period provided in  the case of an appeal to any of the officers whose powers are so  consolidated.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Pending proceedings. Nothing in this Act shall affect any  proceeding which at the commencement thereof is pending in respect of  any of the territory mentioned in Schedule A, and every such  proceeding shall be continued as if this Act had not been passed:</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Provided that all proceedings which at the commencement of this</p>
                  <p>Act are pending before the Commissioner of the Division or any other  authority within the territory mentioned in Schedule A shall be  transferred to, and disposed of by, such authorities in the State of</p>
                  <p>Delhi as the State Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, direct.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Power to extend enactments in force in other Provinces with  modifications and restrictions. Rep. by the Part C States (Laws) Act,</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1950">
              <num>1950.</num>
              <heading>(30 of 1950), s. 4.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
