<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Public Debt Act, 1944"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/18/eng@1944-11-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/18/eng@1944-11-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1944-11-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/18/eng@1944-11-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/18/eng@1944-11-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Public Debt Act, 1944</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 18 OF 1944</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd November, 1944.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Government</p>
        <p>Securities  and to the management by the Reserve Bank of</p>
        <p>India of the public debt of  the Government].</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating  to Government securities  and to the management by the Reserve</p>
        <p>Bank of India of the public debt of  the Government];</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Public Debt  Act, 1944.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date' as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint in  this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1A">
        <num>1A.</num>
        <heading>Securities to which this Act applies. This Act applies to</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government securities created and issued Whether before or after the  commencement of this Act by the Central Government or a State</p>
            <p>Government .]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in  the subject or context,-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" the Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" the Government" in relation to any Government  security means the Central or State Government issuing the  security;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" Government security" means-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a security, created and issued,  by the Government]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>for the purpose of raising a public loan, and having one of  the following forms, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>stock transferable by registration in the books of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Bank; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a promissory note payable to order; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list5.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>a bearer bond payable to bearer; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list5.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>a form prescribed in this behalf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other security created and issued by  the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government] in such form and for such of the purposes of this</p>
            <p>Act as may be prescribed;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" promissory note" includes a treasury bill.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of Government securities.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the  provisions of section 5, a transfer of a Government security shall be  made only in the manner prescribed for the making of transfers of  securities of the class to which it belongs, and no transfer of a</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Government security which-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>is made after the 30th April, 1946, in the case of a  security issued by the Central Government,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>is made after the 31st March, 1949, in the case of a  security issued by the Government of a Part A State,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>is made after the 14th October, 1956, in the case of  a security issued by the Government of a Part B State other  than Jammu and Kashmir,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>is made on or after the 1st day of November, 1956,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>in the case of a security issued on or after that day by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government of any State other than Jammu and Kashmir,  and]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list5.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>is made on or after the 1st day of September, 1972,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>in the case of a security issued on or after that day by the</p>
            <p>Government of the State of Jammu and Kashmir,]</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>shall be valid if-]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list9.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>it does not purport to convey the full title to the  security, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list9.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>it is of such a nature as to affect the manner in which  the security was expressed by  the Government] to be held,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall affect any order made by the</p>
            <p>Bank under this Act, or any order made by a Court upon the Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Transferor of Government securities not liable for amount  thereof. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Negotiable Instru-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ments Act, 1881 (26 of 1881), a person shall not, by reason only of  his having transferred a Government security, be liable to pay any  money due either as principal or as interest thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Holding of Government securities by holders of public offices.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of any public office to which  the Government] may,</p>
            <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, declare this subsection to  apply, a Government security in the form of stock or of a promissory  note may be held in the name of the office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Government security is so held, it shall be deemed to  be transferred without any or further endorsement or transfer deed  from each holder of the office to the succeeding holder of the office  on and from the date on which the latter takes charge of the office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the holder of the office transfers to a party not being  his successor in office a Government security so held, the transfer  shall be made by the signature of the holder of the office and the  name of the office in the manner and subject to the conditions laid  down in section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section applies as well to an office of which there are  two or more joint holders as to an office of which there is a single  holder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Notice of trust not receivable.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No notice of any trust in  respect of any Government security shall be receivable by  the</p>
            <p>Government], nor shall  the Government] be bound by any such notice  even though expressly given, nor shall  the Government] be regarded  as a trustee in respect of any Government security.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>Bank may, as an act of grace and without any liability to the Bank or  to  the Government], record in its books such directions by the  holder of stock for the payment of interest on, or of the maturity  value of, or the transfer of, or such other matters relating to, the  stock as the Bank thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Persons whose title to a Government security of a deceased sole  holder may be recognised by the Bank. Subject to the provisions of  section 9 the executors or administrators of a deceased sole holder of  a Government security and the holder of a succession certificate  issued under Part X of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925),</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>shall be the only persons who may be recognise by the Bank as having  any title to the Government security:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall bar the recognition  by the Bank of the manager or the sole surviving male member of a</p>
            <p>Hindu undivided family governed by the Mitakshara Law as having a  title to a Government security, when the security appears to the Bank  to stand in the name of a deceased member of the family and an  application is made by such manager or sole surviving member for  recognition of his title and is supported by a certificate signed by  such authority and after such inquiry as may be prescribed to the  effect that the deceased belonged to a Hindu undivided family governed  by the Mitakshara Law, that the Government security formed Dart of the  joint property of the family, and that the applicant is the managing  or sole surviving male member of the family.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- The expression" Hindu undivided family governed by  the Mitakshara Law" shall, for the purposes of this section, be  deemed to include a Malabar tarwad.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Right of survivors of joint holders of several payees.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 45 of the Indian</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872),-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>When a Government security is held by two or more persons  jointly and either or any of them dies, the title to the  security shall vest in the survivor or survivors of those  persons, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when a Government security is payable to two or more</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Persons severally and either or any of them dies, the  security shall be payable to the survivor or survivors of  those persons or to the representative of the deceased or to  any of them:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect any  claim which any representative of a deceased person may have against  the survivors or survivors under or in respect of any security to  which this section applies.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section I a body  incorporated or deemed to be incorporated under the Companies Act,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1956">
        <num>1956.</num>
        <heading>(1 of 1956), or the I Co- operative Societies Act, 1912 (2 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1912">
        <num>1912.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1912.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), or any other enactment for the time 2 being in force whether  whether or without  India], relating to the incorporation of  associations of individuals, shall be deemed to die when it is  dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Summary procedure on death of holder of Government securities  not exceeding five thousand rupees face value. Notwithstanding  anything contained in section 7, if within six months of the death of  a person who was the holder of a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government security or securities the face value of which does not in  the aggregate exceed five thousand rupees, probate of his will or  letters of administration of his estate or a succession certificate  issued under Part X of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), is  not produced to the Bank, or proof to the satisfaction of the Bank that  proceedings have been instituted to obtain one of these is not  furnished, the Bank may determine who is the person entitled to the  security or securities, or to administer the estate of the deceased  and may make an order vesting the security or securities in the person  so determined.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Government securities not exceeding five thousand rupees face  value belonging to minor or in same person. When a Government security  or securities belong to a minor or a person who is insane and  incapable of managing his affairs and the face value of the security  or securities does not in the aggregate exceed five thousand rupees,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>the Bank may make such order as it thinks fit for the vesting of such  security or securities in such person as it considers represents the  minor or insane person.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Issue of duplicate securities and of new securities and of new  securities on conversion, consolidation, sub- division or renewal.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person entitled to a Government security applies to the Bank  alleging that the security has been lost, stolen or destroyed, or has  been defaced or mutilated, the Bank may, on proof to its satisfaction  of the loss, theft, destruction, defacement or mutilation of the  security, subject to such conditions and on payment of such fees as  may be prescribed, order the issue of a duplicate security payable to  the applicant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person entitled to a Government security applies to  the Bank to have the security converted into a security of another  form, or into a security issued in connection with another loan or to  have it consolidated with other like securities, or to have it sub-</p>
            <p>divided, or to have it renewed, the Bank may, subject to such  conditions and on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, cancel  the security and order the issue of a new security or securities.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person to whom a duplicate security or a new security is  issued under this section shall be deemed for the purposes of section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>to have been recognised by the Bank as the holder of the security;</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and a duplicate security or new security so issued to any person shall  be deemed to constitute a new contract between  the Government] and  such person and all persons deriving title thereafter through him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Summary determination by the Bank of title to Government  security in case of dispute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Bank is of opinion that a  doubt exists as to the title to a Government security, it may proceed  to determine the person who shall for the purposes of the Bank be  deemed to be the person entitled thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bank shall give notice in writing to each claimant of  whom it has knowledge stating the names of all other claimants and the  time when and the officer of the Bank by whom the determination of the</p>
            <p>Bank will be made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bank shall give notice in writing to each claimant of the  result of the determination so made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the expiry of six months from the issue of the notices  referred to in sub- section (3), the Bank may make an order vesting in  the person, found by the Bank to be entitled to the security, the  security and any unpaid interest thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Law applicable in regard to Government securities.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding that as a matter of convenience  the Government] may  have arranged for payments on a Government</p>
            <p>security to be made elsewhere than in  India], the rights of all  persons in relation to Government securities shall be determined in  connection with all such questions as are dealt with by this Act by  the law and in the Courts of  India].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Recording of evidence.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of making any order  which it is empowered to make under this Act, the Bank may request a</p>
            <p>District Magistrate  to record or to have recorded the whole or  any part of such evidence as any person whose evidence the Bank  requires may produce. A District Magistrate so requested may himself  record, or may direct any Magistrate of the first class subordinate to  him or any Magistrate of the second class subordinate to him and  empowered in this behalf by general or special order of the State</p>
            <p>Government to record the evidence, and shall forward a copy thereof to  the Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of making a vesting order under this Act the</p>
            <p>Bank may direct one of its officers to record the evidence of any  person whose evidence the Bank requires or may receive evidence upon  affidavit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Magistrate or an officer of the Bank acting in pursuance  of this section may administer an oath to any witness examined by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Postponement of payments and registration of transfers pending  the making of a vesting order. Where the Bank contemplates making an  order under this Act to vest a Government security in any person, the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Bank may suspend payment of interest on or the maturity value of the  security or postpone the making of any order under section 11 or the  registration of any transfer of the security until the vesting order  has been made.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power of Bank to require bonds.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before making any order  which it is empowered to make under this Act, the Bank may require the  person in whose favour the order is to be made to execute a bond with  one or more sureties in such form as may be prescribed or to furnish  security not exceeding twice the value of the subject- matter of the  order, to be held at the disposal of the Bank, to pay to the Bank or  any person to whom the Bank may assign the bond or security in  furtherance of sub- section (2) the amount thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Court before which a claim in respect of the subject-</p>
            <p>matter of any such order is established may order the bond or  security to be assigned to the successful claimant who shall thereupon  be entitled to enforce the bond or realise the security to the extent  of such claim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Publication of notices in Official Gazette. Any notice  required to be given by the Bank under this Act may be served by post,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>but every such notice shall also be published by the Bank in  the</p>
            <p>Gazette of India or the Official Gazette of the State, according as  the notice relates to a security, issued by the Central Government or  a State Government, and on such publication shall be deemed to have  been delivered to all persons for whom it is intended.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Scope of vesting order. An order made by the Bank under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act may confer the full title to a Government security or may confer a  title only to the accrued and accruing interest on the security  pending a further order vesting the full title.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Legal effect of orders made by the Bank. No recognition by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Bank of a person as the holder of a Government security, and no order  made by the Bank under this Act shall be called in question by any</p>
            <p>Court so far as such recognition or order affects the relations of    the Government] or the Bank with the person recognised by the Bank  as the holder of a Government security or with any person claiming an  interest in such security: and any such recognition by the Bank of any  person or any order by the Bank vesting a Government security in any  person shall operate to confer on that person a title to the security  subject only to a personal</p>
            <p>liability to the rightful owner of the security for money had and  received on his account.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Stay of proceedings on order of Court. Where the Bank  contemplates making with reference to any Government security any  order which it is empowered to make under this Act, and before the  order is made the Bank receives from a Court in  India] an order to  stay the making of such order, the Bank shall either-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>hold the security together with any interest unpaid or  accruing thereon until the further orders of the Court are  received, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>apply to the Court to have the security transferred to  the official Trustees appointed for the State in which such</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Court is situated, pending the disposal of the proceedings  before the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Cancellation by the Bank of vesting proceedings. Where the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Bank contemplates making an order under this Act vesting a Government  security in any person the Bank may, at any time before the order is  made, cancel any proceedings already taken for that purpose and may,</p>
            <p>on such cancellation, proceed anew to the making of such order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Discharge in respect of interest on Government securities.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in the terms of a Government  security, no person shall be entitled to claim interest on such  security in respect of any period which has elapsed after the earliest  date on which demand could have been made for the payment of the  amount due on such security.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Discharge in respect of bearer bonds.  The Government] shall  be discharged from all liability on a bearer bond or on any interest  coupon of such a bond on payment to the holder of such bond or coupon  on presentation on or after the date when it becomes due of the amount  expressed therein, unless before such payment an order of a Court in</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>India has been served on  the Government] restraining it from  making payment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Period of limitation of Central Government' s liability in  respect of interest. Where no shorter period of limitation is fixed by  any law for the time being in force, the liability of  the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government] in respect</p>
            <p>of any interest payment due on a Government security shall terminate  on the expiry of six years from the date on which the amount due by  way of interest became payable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Inspection of documents. No person shall be entitled to  inspect, or to receive information derived from any Government  security in the possession or custody of  the Government] or from any  book, register, or other document kept or maintained by or on behalf  of  the Government] in relation to Government securities or any</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government security, save in such circumstances and manner and subject  to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>The Bank and its Officers to be deemed public officers. For  the purposes of section 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1872">
        <num>1872.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1872.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), the provisions of Part IV of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908,</p>
            <p>(5 of 1908), relating to suits by or against public officers in their  official capacity, and the provisions of rule 27 of Order V, and rule</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>of Order XXI of the said Code, the Bank and any officer of the Bank  acting in his capacity as such shall be deemed to be a public officer.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person, for the purpose of obtaining for  himself or for any other person any title to a Government security,</p>
            <p>makes to any authority under this Act in any application made under  this Act or in the course of any inquiry undertaken in pursuance of  this Act any statement which is false and which he either knows to be  false or does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine  or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall take cognisance of any offence under sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) except on the complaint of the Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, subject  to the condition of previous publication, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, make rules  to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power such rules may provide for all or any of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the forms in which Government securities may be issued;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the form of the obligations referred to in clause (iv)</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>of sub- clause (a) of clause (2) of section 2;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which Government securities  may be issued to the  Rulers of former Indian States];</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which different forms of Government  securities may be transferred;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the holding of Government securities in the form of  stock by the holders of offices other than public offices,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and the manner in which and the conditions subject to which</p>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Government securities so held may be transferred;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the manner in which payment of interest in respect of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Government securities is to be made and acknowledged;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conditions governing the grant of duplicate,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list10">
              <listIntroduction>renewed, converted, consolidated and sub- divided Government  securities;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list10.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the fees to be paid in respect of the issue of  duplicate Government securities and of the renewal,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list12">
              <listIntroduction>conversion, consolidation and sub- division of Government  securities;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list12.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the form in which receipt of a Government security  delivered for discharge, renewal, conversion, consolidation  or sub- division is to be acknowledged;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list12.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the manner of attestation of documents relating to</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list14">
              <listIntroduction>Government securities in the form of stock;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list14.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the manner in which any document relating to a</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list16">
              <listIntroduction>Government security or any endorsement on a promissory note  issued by  the Government] may, on the demand of a person  who from any cause is unable to write, be executed on his  behalf;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list16.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the form of the bonds referred to in sub- section (1) of  section 16.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list16.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the circumstance and the manner in which and the condi-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>tions subject to which inspection of Government securities,</p>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list19">
              <listIntroduction>books, registers and other documents may be allowed or  information therefrom may be given under section 25;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list19.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in making vesting orders;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list19.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the authority by whom the certificate referred to in  the proviso to section 7 is to be granted and the manner of  making the inquiry therein mentioned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list19.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the persons in whose favour  nominations may be made under section 9B, the manner in which  and the conditions and restrictions subject to which such  nominations may be made, the registration, variation or can-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list21">
              <listIntroduction>cellation of such nominations and the fees that may be levied  for such registration, variation or cancellation;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list21.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>the manner in which any person may be appointed for the  purposes of sub- section (4) of section 9B.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Certain laws not to apply to Government securities. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Indian securities Act, 1920 (10 of 1920), and any law corresponding to  that law in force in any Part B State immediately before the commence-</p>
            <p>ment of the Public Debt (Amendment) Act, 1956 (57 of 1956), shall  cease to apply to Government securities to which this Act applies and  to all matters for which provision is made by this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that any such corresponding law shall continue to apply  to or in relation to any securities created and issued by the</p>
            <p>Government of Hyderabad, Saurashtra or Travancore- Cochin on or before  the 31st day of March, 1953, for such period not exceeding one year  from the commencement of the Public Debt (Amendment) Act, 1956 (57 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1956">
        <num>1956.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, specify.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Construction of reference to laws not in force before 1st</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>April, 1951 in Part B States. Any reference in this Act to any law  which did not extend to any Part B State or any part of such State  before the commencement of</p>
            <p>the Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951 (3 of 1951), shall wherever neces-</p>
            <p>sary, be construed as including a reference to the corresponding law,</p>
            <p>if any, in force in that State, or, as the case may be, any part  thereof, before the said date.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Construction of references to laws not in force in jammu and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Kashmir. Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in  the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall, wherever necessary, be construed  as including a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force in  that State.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
