<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/69/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/69"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Carriage By Air Act, 1972"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/69/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/69/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/69/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/69/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Carriage By Air Act, 1972</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Carriage by Air Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification is the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. —In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“amended Convention” means the Convention as amended by the Hague Protocol on the 28th day of September, 1955;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>“Convention” means the Convention for the unification of certain rules relating to international carriage by air signed at Warsaw on the 12th day of October, 1929.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>“Montreal Convention” means the Convention for the unification of certain rules for international carriage by air signed at Montreal on the 28th day of May, 1999;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>“Annexure” means the Annexure annexed to this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of Convention to India. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rules contained in the First Schedule being the provisions of the Convention relating to the rights and liabilities of carriers, passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, have the force of law in India in relation to any carriage by air to which those rules apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing the carriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of this Act, the High Contracting Parties to the Convention and the date of enforcement of the said Convention shall be such as are included in Part I of the Annexure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in the First Schedule to the territory of any High Contracting Party to the Convention shall be construed as a reference to all the territories in respect of which he is a party.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in the First Schedule to agents of the carrier shall be construed as including a reference to servants of the carrier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, having regard to the objects of this Act, and if it considers necessary or expedient so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, add to, or, as the case may be, omit from, Part I of the Annexure, any High Contracting Party and on such addition, or as the case may be, omission, such High Contracting Party shall be or shall cease to be, a High Contracting Party.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application of amended Convention to India. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rules contained in the Second Schedule, being the provisions of the amended Convention relating to the rights and liabilities of carriers, passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons, shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, have the force of law in India in relation to any carriage by air to which those rules apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing the carriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of this Act, the High Contracting Parties to the amended Convention and the date of enforcement of the said amended Convention shall be such as are included in Part II of the Annexure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, having regard to the objects of this Act, and if it considers necessary or expedient so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, add to, or, as the case may be, omit from, Part II of the Annexure, any High Contracting Party and on such addition, or, as the case may be, omission, such High Contracting Party shall be or shall cease to be, a High Contracting Party.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in the Second Schedule to the territory of any High Contracting party to the amended convention shall be construed as a reference to all the territories in respect of which he is a party.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in the Second Schedule to agents of the carrier shall be construed as including a reference to servants of the carrier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Application of Montreal Convention to India. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rules contained in the Third Schedule, being the provisions of the Montreal Convention relating to the rights and liabilities of carriers, passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons, shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, have the force of law in India in relation to any carriage by air to which those rules apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing the carriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of this Act, the State Parties to the Montreal Convention and the date of enforcement of the said Montreal Convention shall be such as are included in Part III of the Annexure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in the Third Schedule to the territory of any State Party to the Montreal Convention shall be construed as a reference to all the territories in respect of which he is party.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in the Third Schedule to agents of the carrier shall be construed as including a reference to servants of the carrier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, having regard to the objects of this Act, and if it considers necessary or expedient so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, add to, or, as the case may be, omit from, Part III of the Annexure, any State Party and on such addition, or, as the case may be, omission, such State Party shall be or shall cease to be, a State Party.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Liability in case of death. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Fatal Accidents Act, 1855 or any other enactment or rule of law in force in any part of India, the rules contained in the First Schedule, the Second Schedule and the Third Schedule shall, in all cases to which those rules apply, determine the liability of a carrier in respect of the death of a passenger.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The liability shall be enforceable for the benefit of such of the members of the passenger's family as sustained damage by reason of his death.</p>
            <p>Explanation .—</p>
            <p>In this sub-section, the expression “member of a family” means wife or husband, parent, step-parent, gand parent, brother, sister, half-brother, half-sister, child, step-child and grand-child:</p>
            <p>Provided that in deducing any such relationship as aforesaid any illegitimate person and any adopted person shall be treated as being or as having been, the legitimate child of his mother and reputed father or, as the case may be, of his adopters.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An action to enforce the liability may be brought by the personal representative of the passenger or by any person for whose benefit the liability is under sub-section (2) enforceable, but only one action shall be brought in India in respect of the death of any one passenger, and every such action by whomsoever brought shall be for the benefit of all such persons so entitled as aforesaid as either are domiciled in India or not being domiciled there express a desire of take the benefit of the action.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (5), the amount recovered in any such action after deducting any costs not recovered from the defendant, shall be divided between the persons entitled in such proportion as the Court may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court before which any such action is brought may, at any stage of the proceedings make any such order as appears to the Court to be just and  equitable in view of the provisions, the First Schedule or the Second Schedule or the Third Schedule, as the case may be, limiting the liability of a carrier and of any proceedings which have been or are likely to be commenced outside India in respect of the death of the passenger in question.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Conversion of francs.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any sum in francs mentioned in rule 22 of the First Schedule or of the Second Schedule, as the case may be, shall, for the purpose of any action against a carrier, be converted into rupees at the rate of exchange prevailing on the date on which the amount of damages to be paid by the carrier is ascertained by the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Conversion of Special Drawing Rights. —Any sum in Special Drawing Rights mentioned in rules 21 and 22 of the Third Schedule shall, for the purpose of any action against a carrier, be converted into rupees at the rate of exchange prevailing on the date on which the amount of damages to be paid by the carrier is ascertained by the Court in accordance with the provisions of rule 23 of the said Third Schedule.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Provisions regarding suits against High Contracting Parties who undertake carriage by air.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every High Contracting Party to the Convention or the amended Convention, as the case may be, who has not availed himself of the provisions of the Additional Protocol thereto shall, for the purposes of any suit brought in a Court in India in accordance with the provisions of rule 28 of the First Schedule, or of the Second Schedule, as the case may be, to enforce a claim in respect of carriage undertaken by him, be deemed to have submitted to the jurisdiction of that Court and to be a person for the purposes of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The High Court may make rules of procedure providing for all matters which may be expedient to enable such suits to be instituted and carried on.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall authorise any Court to attach or sell any property of a High Contracting Party to the Convention or to the amended Convention.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to carriage by air which is not international. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply the rules contained in First Schedule and any provision of section 3 or section 5 or section 6 to such carriage by air, not being international carriage by air as defined in the First Schedule, as may be specified in the notification, subject, however, to such exceptions, adaptations and modifications, if any, as may be so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply the rules contained in the Second Schedule and any provisions of section 4 or section 5 or section 6 to such carriage by air, not being international carriage by air as defined in the Second Schedule, as may be specified in the notification, subject, however, to such exceptions, adaptations and modifications, if any, as may be so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply the rules contained in the Third Schedule and any provision of section 4A or section 5 or section 6A to such carriage by air, not being international carriage by air as defined in the Third Schedule, as may be specified in the notification, subject, however, to such exceptions, adaptations and modifications, if any, as may be so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1978 (38 of 1978), sec. 2 (w.e.f.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-11-1978).</p>
            <p>THE CARRIAGE BY AIR ACT, 1972</p>
            <p>The First Schedule</p>
            <p>(See section 3)</p>
            <p>Rules</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Scope—Definitions</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These rules apply to all international carriage of persons, luggage or goods performed by aircraft for reward. They apply also to such carriage when performed gratuitously by an air transport undertaking.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In these rules, “High Contracting Party” means a High Contracting Party to the Convention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of these rules the expression, “international carriage” means any carriage in which according to the contract made by the parties, the place of departure and the place of destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two High Contracting Parties, or within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, if there is an agreed stopping place within a territory subject to the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of another Power, even though that Power is not a party to the Convention. A carriage without such an agreed stopping place between territories subject to the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of the same High Contracting Party is not deemed to be international for the purposes of these rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A carriage to be performed by several successive air carriers is deeemd, for the purposes of these rules to be one undivided carriage, if it has been regarded by the parties as a single operation, whether it has been agreed upon under the form of a single contract or of a series of contracts, and it does not lose its international character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be performed entirely within a territory subject to the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of the same High Contracting Party.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These rules apply to carriage performed by the State or by legally constituted public bodies provided it falls within the conditions laid down in rule 1.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These rules do not apply to carriage performed under the terms of any international postal Convention.t</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Documents of Carriage</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-I">
          <num>I</num>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-I.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Passenger Ticket</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <section id="section-3">
            <num>3.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-3.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>For the carriage of passengers the carrier must deliver a passenger ticket which shall contain the following particulars:—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the place and date of issue;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the place of departure and of destination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the agreed stopping places, provided that the carrier may reserve the right to alter the stopping places in case of necessity, and that if he exercises that right, the alteration shall not have the effect of depriving the carriage of its international character;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>the name and address of the carrier or carriers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>a statement that the carriage is subject to the rules relating to liability contained in this Schedule.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-3.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The absence, irregularity or loss of the passenger ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall nonetheless be subject to these rules. Nevertheless, if the carrier accepts a passenger without a passenger ticket having been delivered he shall not be entitled to avail himself of those provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit his liability</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </part>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-II">
          <num>II</num>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-II.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Luggage Ticket</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <section id="section-4">
            <num>4.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-4.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the carriage of luggage, other than small personal objects of which the passenger takes charge himself, the carrier must deliver a luggage ticket.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-4.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The luggage ticket shall be made out in duplicate, one part for the passenger and the other part for the carrier.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-4.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>The luggage ticket shall contain the following particulars:—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the place and date of issue;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the place of departure and of destination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the name and address of the carrier or carriers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>the number of the passenger ticket;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>a statement that delivery of the luggage will be made to the bearer of the luggage ticket;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <p>the number and weight of the packages;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.g">
                    <num>(g)</num>
                    <p>the amount of the value declared in accordance with rule 22(2);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.h">
                    <num>(h)</num>
                    <p>a statement that the carriage is subject to the rules relating to liability contained in this Schedule.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-4.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The absence, irregularity or loss of the luggage ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall nonetheless be subject to these rules. Nevertheless if the carrier accepts luggage without a luggage ticket having been delivered, or if the luggage ticket does not contain the particulars set out at (d), (f) and (h) of sub-rule (3), the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of those provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit his liability.t</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </part>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-III">
          <num>III</num>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-III.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Air Consignment Note</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <section id="section-5">
            <num>5.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-5.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every carrier of goods has the right to require the consignor to make out and hand over to him a document called an “air consignment note”; every consignor has the right to require the carrier to accept this document.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-5.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The absence, irregularity or loss of this document does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, subject to the provisions of Rule 9, be nonetheless governed by these rules.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-6">
            <num>6.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-6.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The air consignment note shall be made out by the consignor in three original parts and be handed over with the goods.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The first part shall be marked “for the carrier” and shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the carrier and shall accompany the goods. The third part shall be signed by the carrier and handed by him to the consignor after the goods have been accepted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The carrier shall sign an acceptance of the goods.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The signature of the carrier may be stamped; that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at the request of the consignor, the carrier makes out the air consignment note, he shall be deemed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-7">
            <num>7.</num>
            <heading>The carrier of goods has the right to require the consignor to make out separate consignment notes when there is more than one package.</heading>
          </section>
          <section id="section-8">
            <num>8.</num>
            <heading>The air consignment note shall contain the following particulars:—</heading>
            <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the place, date of its execution;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the place of departure and of destination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the agreed stopping places, provided that the carrier may reserve the right to alter the stopping places in case of necessity, and that if he exercises that right the alteration shall not have the effect of depriving the carriage of its international character;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>the name and address of the consignor;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>the name and address of the first carrier;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <p>the name and address of the consignee, if the case so requires;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                    <num>(g)</num>
                    <p>the nature of the goods;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.h">
                    <num>(h)</num>
                    <p>the number of the packages, the method of packing and the particular marks or numbers upon them;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the weight, the quantity and the volume or dimensions of the goods;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.j">
                    <num>(j)</num>
                    <p>the apparent condition of the goods and of the packing;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.k">
                    <num>(k)</num>
                    <p>the freight, if it has been agreed upon, the date and place of payment, and the person who is to pay it;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                    <num>(l)</num>
                    <p>if the goods are sent for payment on delivery, the price of the goods, and if the case so requires, the amount of the expenses incurred;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.m">
                    <num>(m)</num>
                    <p>the amount of the value declared in accordance with rule 22(2);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.n">
                    <num>(n)</num>
                    <p>the number of parts of the air consignment note;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.o">
                    <num>(o)</num>
                    <p>the documents handed to the carrier to accompany the air consignment note;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.p">
                    <num>(p)</num>
                    <p>the time fixed for the completion of the carriage and a brief note of the route to be followed, if these matters have been agreed upon;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.q">
                    <num>(q)</num>
                    <p>a statement that the carriage is subject to the rules relating to liability contained in this Schedule.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section id="section-9">
            <num>9.</num>
            <heading>If the carrier accepts goods without an air consignment note having been made out, or if the air consignment note does not contain all the particulars set out in rule 8(a) to (i) inclusive and (q), the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit his liability.</heading>
          </section>
          <section id="section-10">
            <num>10.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-10.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and statements relating to the goods which he inserts in the air consignment note.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-10.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consignor will be liable for all damage suffered by the carrier or any other person of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the said particulars and statements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-11">
            <num>11.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-11.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The air consignment note is prima facie evidence of the conclusion of the contract, of the receipt of the goods and of the conditions of carriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-11.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The statements in the air consignment note relating to the weight, dimensions and packing of the goods, as well as those relating to the number of packages, are prima facie evidence of the facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and condition of the goods do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far as they both have been, and are stated in the air consignment note to have been, checked by him in the presence of the consignor, or relate to the apparent condition of the goods.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-12">
            <num>12.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-12.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to his liability to carry out all his obligations under the contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the goods by withdrawing them at the aerodrome of departure or destination, or by stopping them in the course of the journey on any landing or, by calling for them to be delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the journey to a person other than the consignee named in the air consignment note or by requiring them to be returned to the aerodrome of departure. He must not exercise the right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the carrier or other consignors and he must repay any expenses occasioned by the exercise of this right.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-12.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If it is impossible to carry out the orders of the consignor the carrier must so inform him forthwith.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-12.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the carrier obeys the orders of the consignor for the disposition of the goods without requiring the production of the part of the air consignment note delivered to the latter, he will be liable, without prejudice to his right of recovery from the consignor, for any damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in possession of that part of the air consignment note.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-12.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The right conferred on the consignor ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with rule 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the consignment note or the goods, or if he cannot be communicated with, the consignor resumes his right of disposition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-13">
            <num>13.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-13.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except in the circumstances set out in rule 12, the consignee is entitled, on arrival of the goods at the place of destination, to require the carrier to hand over to him the air consignment note and to deliver the goods to him, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the conditions of carriage set out in the air consignment note.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-13.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the goods arrive.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-13.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the carrier admits the loss of the goods, or if the goods have not arrived at the expiration of seven days after the date on which they ought to have arrived, the consignee is entitled to put into force against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of carriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-14">
            <num>14.</num>
            <heading>The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights given to them by rules 12 and 13, each in his own name, whether he is acting in his own interest or in the interest of another, provided that he carries out the obligations imposed by the contract.</heading>
          </section>
          <section id="section-15">
            <num>15.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-15.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Rules 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor or the consignee, with each other or the mutual relations of third parties whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-15.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of rules 12, 13 and 14 can only be varied by express provisions in the air consignment note.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-16">
            <num>16.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-16.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consignor must furnish such information and attach to the air consignment note such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of customs, octroi or police before the goods can be delivered to the consignee. The consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned by the absence, insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or documents, unless the damage is due to the fault of the carrier or his agents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-16.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The carrier is under no obligation to enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or documents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </part>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Liability of the Carrier</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the death or wounding of a passenger or any other bodily injury suffered by a passenger, if the accident which caused the damage so sustained took place on board the aircraft or in the course of any of the operations of embarking or disembarking.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the destruction or loss of, or of damage to, any registered luggage or any goods, if the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place during the carriage by air.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The carriage by air within the meaning of sub-rule (1) comprises the period during which the luggage or goods are in charge of the carrier, whether in an aerodrome or on board an aircraft, or, in the case of a landing outside an aerodrome in any place whatsoever.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of the carriage by air does not extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by river performed outside an aerodrome. If, however, such a carriage takes place in the performance of a contract for carriage by air, for the purpose of loading, delivery or transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by air.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>The carrier is liable for damage occasioned by delay in the carriage by air of passengers, luggage or goods.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The carrier is not liable if he proves that he and his agents have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage or that it was impossible for him or them to take such measures.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the carriage of goods and luggage the carrier is not liable if he proves that the damage was occasioned by negligent pilotage or negligence in the handling of the aircraft or in navigation and that, in all other respects, he and his agents have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>If the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the negligence of the injured person the Court may exonerate the carrier wholly or partly from his liability.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the carriage of passengers the liability of the carrier for each passenger is limited to the sum of 1,25,000 francs. Where damages may be awarded in form of periodical payments, the equivalent capital value of the said payments shall not exceed 1,25,000 francs. Nevertheless, by special contract the carrier and the passenger may agree to a higher limit of liability.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the carriage of registered luggage and of goods, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of 250 francs per kilogramme, unless the consignor has made, at the time when the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of the value at delivery and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless he proves that that sum is greater than the actual value to the consignor at delivery.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As regards objects of which the passenger takes charge himself the liability of the carrier is limited to 5,000 francs per passenger.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The sums mentioned in this rule shall be deemed to refer to the French franc consisting of sixty-five and a half miligrammes gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Any provision tending to relieve the carrier of liability or to fix a lower limit than that which is laid down in these rules shall be null and void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the whole contract which shall remain subject to the provisions of this Schedule.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the cases covered by rules 18 and 19 any action for damage, however founded, can only be brought subject to the conditions and limits set out in this Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the cases covered by rule 17, the provisions of sub-rule (1) also apply, without prejudice to the questions as to who are the person who have the right to bring suit and what are their respective rights.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of this Schedule which exclude or limit his liability, if the damage is caused by his wilful misconduct or by such default on his part as is in the opinion of the Court equivalent to wilful misconduct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Similarly the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the said provisions, if the damage is caused as aforesaid by any agent of the carrier acting within the scope of his employment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Receipt by the person entitled to delivery of luggage or goods without complaint is prima facie evidence that the same have been delivered in good condition and in accordance with the document of carriage.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of damage, the person entitled to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of the damage, and, at the latest, within three days from the date of receipt in the case of luggage and seven days from the date of receipt in the case of goods. In the case of delay the complaint must be made at the latest within fourteen days from the date on which the luggage or goods have been placed at his disposal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every complaint must be made in writing upon the document of carriage or by separate notice in writing despatched within the times aforesaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Failing complaint within the times aforesaid, no action shall lie against the carrier, save in the case of fraud on his part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>In the case of the death of the person liable, an action for damages lies in accordance with these rules against those legally representing his estate.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>An action for damages must be brought at the option of the plaintiff either before the Court having jurisdiction whether the carrier is ordinarily resident, or has his principal place of business, or has an establishment by which the contract has been made or before the Court having jurisdiction at the place of destination.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>The right of damages shall be extinguished if an action is not brought within two years reckoned from the date of arrival at the destination, or from the date on which the aircraft ought to have arrived, or from the date on which the carriage stopped.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of carriage to be performed by various successive carriers and falling within the definition set out in sub-rule (4) of rule 1, each carrier who accepts passenger’s luggage or goods is subjected to the rules set out in this Schedule, and is deemed to be one of the contracting parties to the contract of carriage in so far as the contract deals with that part of the carriage which is performed under his supervision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of carriage of this nature, the passenger or his representative can take action only against the carrier who performed the carriage during which the accident or the delay occurred, save in the case where, by express agreement, the first carrier has assumed liability for the whole journey.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As regards luggage or goods, the passenger or consignor will have a right of action against the first carrier, and the passenger or consginee who is entitled to delivery will have a right of action against the last carrier, and further, each may take action against the carrier who performed the carriage during which the destruction, loss, damage or delay took place. These carriers will be jointly and severally liable to the passenger or to the consignor or consignee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provisions Relating to Combined Carriage</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of combined carriage performed partly by air and partly by any other mode of carriage, the provisions of this Schedule apply only to the carriage by air, provided that the carriage by air falls within the terms of rule 1.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Schedule shall prevent the parties in the case of combined carriage from inserting in the document of air carriage conditions relating to other modes of carriage, provided that the provisions of this Schedule are observed as regards the carriage by air.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>General and Final Provisions</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Any clause contained in the contract and all special agreements entered into before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the rules laid down by this Schedule, whether by deciding the law to be applied, or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void. Nevertheless for the carriage of goods arbitration clauses are allowed, subject to these rules, if the arbitration is to take place in the territory of one of the High Contracting Parties within one of the jurisdictions referred to in rule 28.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Nothing contained in this Schedule shall prevent the carrier either from refusing to enter into any contract of carriage, or from making regulations which do not conflict with the provisions of this Schedule.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>This Schedule does not apply to international carriage by air performed by way of experimental trial by air navigation undertaking with the view to the establishment of a regular line of air nagivation, nor does it apply to carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope of an air carrier’s business.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>The expression “days” when used in these rules means current days, not working days.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>When a High Contracting Party has declared at the time of ratification of or of accession to the Convention that sub-rule (1) of rule 2 of these rules shall not apply to international carriage by air performed directly by the State, its colonies, protectorates or mandated territories or by any other territory under its sovereignty, suzerainty or authority, these rules shall not apply to international carriage by air so performed.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>THE CARRIAGE BY AIR ACT, 1972</p>
              <p>The Second Schedule</p>
              <p>(See section 4)</p>
              <p>RULES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SCOPE -DEFINITION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These rules apply to all international carriage of persons, baggage or cargo performed by aircraft for reward. They apply equally to gratuitous carriage by aircraft performed by an air transport undertaking.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In these rules, “High Contracting Party” means a High Contracting Party to the amended Convention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of these rules, the expression “international carriage” means any carriage in which, according to the agreement between the parties, the place of departure and the place of destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two High Contracting Parties or within the territory of a single High Contracting Party if there is an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State, even if that State is not a High Contracting Party. Carriage between two points within the territory of a single High Contracting Party without an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State is not international carriage for the purposes of these rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Carriage to be performed by several successive air carriers is deemed, for the purposes of these rules, to be one undivided carriage if it has been regarded by the parties as a single operation, whether it had been agreed upon under the form of a single contract or of a series of contracts and it does not lose its international character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be performed entirely within the territory of the same State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These rules apply to carriage performed by the State or by legally constituted public bodies provided it falls within the conditions laid down in rule 1.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>These rules shall not apply to carriage of mail and post packages.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Documents of Carriage</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-I">
          <num>I</num>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-I.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Passenger Ticket</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <section id="section-3">
            <num>3.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-3.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>In respect of the carriage of passengers a ticket shall be delivered containing:</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>an indication of the place of departure and destination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>a notice to the effect that, if the passenger’s journey involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than the country of departure, the amended Convention may be applicable and that the amended Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of carriers for death or personal injury and in respect of loss of, or damage to, baggage.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-3.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The passenger ticket shall constitute prima facie evidence of the conclusion and conditions of the contract of carriage. The absence, irregularity or loss of the passenger ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, nonetheless, be subject to these rules. Nevertheless, if with the consent of the carrier, the passenger embarks without a passenger ticket having been delivered, or if the ticket does not include the notice required by sub-rule (1)(c) of this rule, the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of rule 22.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </part>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-II">
          <num>II</num>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-II.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Baggage Check</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <section id="section-4">
            <num>4.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-4.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>In respect of the carriage of registered baggage, a baggage check shall be delivered, which, unless combined with or incorporated in a passenger ticket which complies with the provisions of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 shall contain:</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>a notice to the effect that, if the carriage involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than the country of departure, the amended Convention may be applicable and that the amended Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of carriers in respect of loss of, or damage to baggage.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-4.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The baggage check shall constitute prima facie evidence of the registration of the baggage and of the conditions of the contract of carriage. The absence, irregularity or loss of the baggage check does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, nonetheless, be subject to these rules. Nevertheless, if the carrier takes charge of the baggage without a baggage check having been delivered or if the baggage check unless combined with or incorporated in the passenger’s ticket with the provisions of sub-rule (1)(c) of rule 3 does not include the notice required by sub-rule (1)(c) of this rule, he shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 22.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </part>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-III">
          <num>III</num>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-III.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Air Waybill</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <section id="section-5">
            <num>5.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-5.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out and hand over to him a document called as “air waybill”; every consignor has the right to require the carrier to accept this document.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-5.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The absence, irregularity or loss of this document does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, subject to the provisions of rule 9, be nonetheless governed by these rules.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-6">
            <num>6.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-6.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The air waybill shall be made out by the consignor in the three original parts and be handed over with the cargo.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The first part shall be marked “for the carrier”, and shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the carrier and shall accompany the cargo. The third part shall be signed by the carrier and handed by him to the consignor after the cargo has been accepted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The carrier shall sign prior to the loading of the cargo on board the aircraft.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The signature of the carrier may be stamped; that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-6.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at the request of the consignor, the carrier makes out the air waybill, he shall be deemed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-7">
            <num>7.</num>
            <heading>The carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out separate waybills when there is more than one package.</heading>
          </section>
          <section id="section-8">
            <num>8.</num>
            <heading>The air waybill shall contain:</heading>
            <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>a notice to the consignor to the effect that, if the carriage involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than the country of departure, the amended Convention may be applicable and that the amended Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of carriers in respect of loss of, or damage to, cargo.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section id="section-9">
            <num>9.</num>
            <heading>If, with the consent of the carrier, cargo is loaded on board the aircraft without an air waybill having been made out, or if the air waybill does not include the notice required by rule 8(c), the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 22.</heading>
          </section>
          <section id="section-10">
            <num>10.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-10.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and statements relating to the cargo which he inserts in the air waybill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-10.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consignor shall indemnify the carrier against all damage suffered by him, or by any other person to whom the carrier is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the particulars and statements furnished by the consignor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-11">
            <num>11.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-11.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The air waybill is prima facie evidence of the conclusion of the contract, of the receipt of the cargo and of the conditions of carriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-11.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The statements in the air waybill relating to the weight, dimensions and packing of the cargo, as well as those relating to the number of packages, are prima facie evidence of the facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and conditions of the cargo do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far they both have been, and are stated in the air waybill to have been checked by him in the presence of the consignor, or relate to the apparent conditions of the cargo.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-12">
            <num>12.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-12.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to his liability to carry out all his obligations under the contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the cargo by withdrawing it at the aerodrome of departure or destination, or by stopping it in the course of the journey on any landing, or by calling for it to be delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the journey to a person other than the consignee named in the air waybill, or by requiring it to be returned to the aerodrome of departure. He must not exercise this right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the carrier or other consignors and he must repay any expenses occasioned by the exercise of this right.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-12.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If it is impossible to carry out the orders of the consignor the carrier must so inform him forthwith.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-12.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the carrier obeys the orders of the consignor for the disposition of the cargo without requiring the production of the part of the air waybill delivered to the latter, he will be liable, without prejudice to his right of recovery from the consignor, for any damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in possession of that part of the air waybill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-12.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The right conferred on the consignor ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with rule 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the waybill or the cargo, or if he cannot be communicated with, the consignor resumes his right of disposition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-13">
            <num>13.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-13.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except in the circumstances set out in the preceding rule, the consignee is entitled on arrival of the cargo at the place of destination to require the carrier to hand over to him the air waybill and to deliver the cargo to him, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the conditions of carriage set out in the air way bill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-13.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the cargo arrives.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-13.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the carrier admits the loss of the cargo, or if the cargo has not arrived at the expiration of seven days after the date on which it ought to have arrived, the consignee is entitled to put into force against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of carriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-14">
            <num>14.</num>
            <heading>The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights given to them by rules 12 and 13, each in his own name, whether he is acting in his own interest or in the interest of another, provided that he carries out the obligations imposed by the contract.</heading>
          </section>
          <section id="section-15">
            <num>15.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-15.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Rules 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor or the consignee with each other or the mutual relations of third parties whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-15.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of rules 12, 13 and 14 can only be varied by express provision in the air waybill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-15.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in these rules prevents the issue of a negotiable air waybill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section id="section-16">
            <num>16.</num>
            <heading/>
            <subsection id="section-16.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consignor must furnish such information and attach to the air waybill such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of customs, octroi or police before the cargo can be delivered to the consignee. The consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned by the absence, insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or documents, unless the damage is due to the fault of the carrier or his servants or agents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="section-16.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The carrier is under no obligation to enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or documents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </part>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Liability of the carrier</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the death or wounding of a passenger or any other bodily injury suffered by a passenger if the accident which caused the damage so sustained took place on board the aircraft or in the course of any of the operations of embarking or disembarking.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the destruction or loss of, or of damage to, any registered baggage or any cargo, if the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place during the carriage by air.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The carriage by air within the meaning of the preceding sub-rule comprises the period during which the baggage or cargo is in charge of the carrier, whether in an aerodrome or on board an aircraft, or in the case of a landing outside an aerodrome, in any place whatsoever.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of the carriage by air does not extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by river performed outside an aerodrome. If, however, such a carriage takes place in the performance of a contract for carriage by air for the purpose of loading delivery or transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by air.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>The carrier is liable for damage occasioned by delay in the carriage by air of passengers, baggage or cargo.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>The carrier is not liable if he proves that he and his servants or agents have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage or that it was impossible for him or them to take such measures.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>If the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the negligence of the injured person the Court may in accordance with the provisions of its own law exonerate the carrier wholly or partly from his liability.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the carriage of persons the liability of the carrier for each passenger is limited to the sum of 2,50,000 francs. Where, in accordance with the law of the Court seized of the case, damages may be awarded in the form of periodical payments the equivalent capital value of the said payments shall not exceed 2,50,000 francs. Nevertheless, by special contract, the carrier and the passenger may agree to a higher limit of liability.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list0">
                <item id="section-22.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>In the carriage of registered baggage and of cargo, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of 250 francs per kilogramme, unless the passenger or consignor has made, at the time when the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of interest in delivery at destination and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless he proves that that sum is greater than the passenger’s or consignor’s actual interest in delivery at destination.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>In the case of loss, damage or delay of part of registered baggage or cargo, or of any object contained therein, the weight to be taken into consideration in determining the amount to which the carrier’s liability is limited shall be only the total weight of the package or packages concerned. Nevertheless, when the loss, damage or delay of a part of the registered baggage or cargo, or of an object contained therein, affects the value of other packages covered by the same baggage check or the same air waybill, the total weight of such package or packages shall also be taken into consideration in determining the limit of liability.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As regards objects of which the passenger takes charge himself the liability of the carrier is limited to 5,000 francs per passenger.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The limits prescribed in this rule shall not prevent the Court from awarding in accordance with its own law, in addition, the whole or part of the Court costs and of the other expenses of the litigation incurred by the plaintiff. The foregoing provision shall not apply if the amount of the damages awarded, excluded Court costs and other expenses of the litigation, does not exceed the sum which the carrier has offered in writing to the plaintiff within a period of six months from the date of the occurrence causing the damage, or before the commencement of the action, if that is later.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The sums mentioned in francs in this rule shall be deemed to refer to a currency unit consisting of sixty-five and a half miligrammes of gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred. These sums may be converted into national currencies in round figures. Convention of the sums into national currencies other than gold shall, in case of judicial proceedings, be made according to the gold value of such currencies at the date of the judgment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any provision tending to relieve the carrier of liability or to fix a lower limit than that which is laid down in these rules shall be null and void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the whole contract, which shall remain subject to the provisions of these rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Sub-rule (1) of this rule shall not apply to provisions governing loss or damage resulting from the inherent defect, quality or vice of the cargo carried.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the cases covered by rules 18 and 19 any action for damages, however founded, can only be brought, subject to the conditions and limits set out in these rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the cases covered by rule 17 the provisions of the preceding sub-rule also apply, without prejudice to the questions as to who are the persons who have the right to bring suit and what are their respective rights.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>The limits of liability specified in rule 22 shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the carrier, his servants or agents, done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result; provided that, in the case of such act or omission of a servant or agent, it is also proved that he was acting within the scope of his employment.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If an action is brought against a servant or agent of the carrier arising out of damage to which these rules relate, such servant or agent, if he proves that he acted within the scope of his employment, shall be entitled to avail himself of the limits of liability which that carrier himself is entitled to invoke under rule 22.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The aggregate of the amounts recoverable from the carrier, his servants and agents, in that case, shall not exceed the said limits.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) of this rule shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the servant or agent done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Receipt by the person entitled to delivery of baggage or cargo without complaint is prima facie evidence that the same has been delivered in good condition and in accordance with the document of carriage.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of damage, the person entitled to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of the damage, and, at the latest, within seven days from the date of receipt in the case of baggage and fourteen days from the date of receipt in the case of cargo. In the case of delay the complaint must be made at the latest within twenty-one days from the date on which the baggage or cargo have been placed at his disposal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every complaint must be made in writing upon the document of carriage or by separate notice in writing despatched within the time aforesaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Failing complaint within the times aforesaid, no action shall lie against the carrier, save in the case of fraud on his part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>In the case of the death of the person liable, an action for damages lies in accordance with the terms of these rules against those legally representing his estate.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An action for damages must be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, in the territory of one of the High Contracting Parties, either before the Court having jurisdiction where the carrier is ordinarily resident, or has his principal place of business, or has an establishment by which the contract has been made or before the Court have jurisdiction at the place of destination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Questions of procedure shall be governed by the law of the Court seized of the case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The right to damages shall be extinguished if an action is not brought within two years, reckoned from the date of arrival at the destination, or from the date on which the aircraft ought to have arrived, or from the date on which the carriage stopped.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The method of calculating the period of limitation shall be determined by the law of the Court seized of the case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of carriage to be performed by various successive carriers and falling within the definition set out in sub-rule (3) of rule 1, each carrier who accepts passengers, baggage or cargo is subjected to the rules set out in this Schedule, and is deemed to be one of the contracting parties to the contract of carriage in so far as the contract deals with that part of the carriage which is performed under his supervision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of carriage of this nature, the passenger or his representative can take action only against the carrier who performed the carriage during which the accident or the delay occurred save in the case where, by express agreement, the first carrier has assumed liability for the whole journey.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As regards baggage or cargo, the passenger or consignor will have a right of action against the first carrier, and the passenger or consignee who is entitled to delivery will have a right of action against the last carrier, and further, each may take action against the carrier who performed the carriage during which the destruction, loss, damage or delay took place. These carriers will be jointly and severally liable to the passenger or to the consignor or consignee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provisions Relating to Combined Carriage</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of combined carriage performed partly by air and partly by any other mode of carriage, the provisions of this Schedule apply only to the carriage by air, provided that the carriage by air falls within the terms of rule (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Schedule shall prevent the parties in the case of combined carriage from inserting in the document of air carriage conditions relating to other modes of carriage, provided that the provisions of the Schedule are observed as regards the carriage by air.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>General and Final Provisions</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Any clause contained in the contract and all special agreements entered into before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the rules laid down by this Schedule, whether by deciding the law to be applied, or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void. Nevertheless for the carriage of cargo arbitration clauses are allowed, subject to these rules, if the arbitration is to take place within one of the jurisdictions referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 29.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Nothing contained in this Schedule shall prevent the carrier either from refusing to enter into any contract of carriage, or from making regulations which do not conflict with the provisions of this Schedule.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>The provisions of rules 3 to 9 (inclusive) relating to documents of carriage shall not apply in the case of carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope of an air carrier’s business.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>The expression “days” when used in these rules means current days not working days.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
