<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2002/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Andhra Pradesh Compulsory Registration Of Marriages Act, 2002"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Andhra Pradesh Compulsory Registration Of Marriages Act, 2002</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 15 OF 2002.</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the compulsory registration of marriages in the state and for matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of the State of Andhra Pradesh in the Fifty-third year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title extent and Commence¬ment.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh Compulsory Registration of Marriages Act, 2002.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>ft extends to the whole of the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, appoint.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"Marriages" include all the marriages performed by persons belonging to any caste or religion and also the marriages performed as per any custom, practices or any traditions including the marriages performed in the tribal areas and the word "Marriage" also includes "remarriages".</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Local Authority" means the Grama Panchayat or the Municipality or the Municipal Corporation, as the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"Government" means the State Government of Andhra Pradesh;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"Notification" means any notification published in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette and the word "Notified" shall be construed accordingly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the Government under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"Public servant" means any employee of the Government, a local Gram Panchayat, Mandal Parishad; Zilla Parishad, Municipality or Municipal Corporation owned or controlled by the Government or any Government Agency;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"Register" means a register of marriages maintained under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"Memorandum" means a memorandum of marriage mentioned in Section 8;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>"Registrar" Means a Registrar of marriages appointed by the Government under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>"Marriage Officer" means an officer appointed under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>"Registrar General" means the Registrar General of Marriages appointed by the Government under this Act;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The expression "custom and tradition" signifies any custom or tradition which, having been continuously and uniformly observed for a long time, and prevalent in the force of law in any local area, tribal community etc;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>"Magistrate" means a Judicial Magistrate of First Class.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Application of other laws not barred</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any other law for the time being in force, except to the extent the provisions of other laws are inconsistent with any provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Registrar General of marriages</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint a person known as Registrar General of Marriages;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint such officers with such designations as it thinks fit for purpose of discharging under the superintendence and directions of the Registrar General of Marriages such functions of the Registrar General under this Act, as he may, think fit from time to time authorise and delegate them to discharge such functions as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>District Registrar of Marriages</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint a District Registrar of Marriages for each District and such number of Additional Deputy Registrars of Marriages as it thinks fit, who shall subject to the general control supervision and directions of the District Registrar, discharge such functions of the District Registrar, discharge such functions of the District Registrar as the District Registrar may, from time to time, authorise them to discharge;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The District Registrar of Marriages shall manage and supervise subject to the directions of the Registrar General of Marriages the registration of marriages in the district and shall be responsible for carrying into execution in the district the provisions of this Act, and the orders of the Registrar General of Marriages issued from time to time for the purpose of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Marriage Officer</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The local authority may appoint a Marriage Officer for each local area comprising the area within the jurisdiction of a Municipal Corporation, Municipality, Gram Panchayat or any other area or a combination of any two or more areas;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Marriage Officer shall, enter in the Register of Marriages maintained for the purpose, all information given to him under section 7 or section 8 and register the marriage;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Marriage Officer shall have an office in the local area for which he is appointed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Marriage Officer shall atend his office for the purpose of registering the marriages on such days at such hours as the Registrar General of Marriages or District Registrar of Marriages may direct and shall cause to be placed in some conspicuous place on or near the outer door of the office of the Marriage Officer, a Board bearing in the local language, his name with the addition of "Marriage Officer" for the local area for which he is appointed and the days and hours of his attendance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Registration of marriages</heading>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Every Marriage in State to be Registered.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the commencement of the Act, every marriage performed in the State shall be registered under this Act in the manner provided in section 8 notwithstanding the fact that the said marriage had been entered in the Marriage Registers governed by the any other personal laws of the bride or bridegroom or customs and traditions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act does not apply to the Marriages already registered with the Registrar of Marriages appointed by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Memorandum of marriage.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The parties to a marriage either bride or bridegroom or their parents or guardian shall inform the Marriage Officer about the factum of the Marriage to be registered in the Form as prescribed in the schedule duly signed by the said person, within 30 days from the date of the marriage in duplicate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Memorandum shall be signed by the bride and bridegroom and two witnesses on each side of bride and bridegroom before the Marriage Officer;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Marriage Officer shall maintain the Register of Marriages in the Form as provided in the Schedule and enter in the Register all the information supplied to him in the memorandum and obtain the signatures of the bride and bridegroom and two witnesses on each side;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of the memorandum of the factum of Marriage or the proposed Marriage and on payment of the such charges, the Marriage Officer may go to the place specified within his jurisdiction and obtain the signatures of the bride and bridegrom and two witnesses on each side.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Memorandum of marriages presented after 30 days.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The memorandum of Factum of marriage may be presented to the Marriage Officer after expiry o fa period of 30 "days as specified in sub-section (1) of section 8, and thereafter within a period of 60 days With the payment of Fee of Rs. 100/-(one hundred only)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Penalities</heading>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for neglecting to comply with the provisions of sections 8 and 9 or for making false statement in memorandum.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person who.-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilfully omits or neglects to get the marriage registered as required in sections 8 and 9 shall be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who makes any statement in the memorandum which is false in any material particulars and which he/she knows or has reason to believe to be false, shall be punished with imprisonment fora term which may extend to one year or fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for failing to register the marriage.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any Marriage Officer who fails to register a marriage pursuant to section 8 shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or fine which may extend to five hundred rupees or with both.</p>
              <p>CHAPTER - IV</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Marriage Certificate to be given to the couple.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Marriage Officer shall, as soon as the registration of marriage has been completed, give free of costs to the couple a Marriage Certificate in the Form as provided in the Schedule under his hand and seal;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such Certificate issued by the Marriage Officer shall be the conclusive proof of the factum of the said marriage.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Marriage Officer to keep registers in the prescribed form.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Marriage Officer shall keep in the prescribed form a Register of marriages for the registration area or any part thereof in relation to which he exercises jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar General shall cause to be printed and supplied sufficient number of registers for making entries of Marriages according to such form and instructions as he may, from time to time prescribe, a copy of such forms in the local language shall be pasted in some conspicuous place on or near the other door of office of every Marriage Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Search Marriages Register.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to any Rules made in this behalf by the State including the Rules relating to payment of fee, any person may:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Cause a search to be made by the Marriage Officer for any entry in the Register of Marriages; and,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>obtain an extract from such Register relating to Marriages.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All extracts given under this section shall be signed by the Marriage Officer or any other Officer authorised by the State Government to give such extracts and shall be admissible in evidence for the purpose of providing the marriage to which the entry relates.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Marriage Officers to send periodical returns to the District Registrar for compilation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Marriage Officer shall send to the District Registrar of Marriages or to any officer specified by him, at such intervals and in such form as may be prescribed, a return regarding the entries of marriages in the Register kept by such Marriage Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Non registration not to invalidate marriage</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No Marriage performed in this State to which this Act applies shall be deemed to be invalid solely by reason of the fact that it was not registered under this Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Offence under this Act triable summarily by a Magistrate.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>An offence under this Act shall be tried summarily by the Judicial Magistrate of First Class, in accordance with the procedure as laid down in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Sanction for prosecution.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No. prosecution for an offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted except by an officer authorised by Registrar General, by general or special order in this behalf without his prior sanction.</p>
              <p>l9. Registrars Mani age Officers to be deemed public servants.</p>
              <p>All Registrars of Marriages or Marriage Officers and other Officers appointed under this Act, shall while acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or any rule or Order made thereunder, shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government, the Registrar General, any Registrar or Marriage Officer or any person exercising any power of performing any duty under this Act, for anything in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or orders made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purpose of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the duties and powers of the Registrars of Marriages or Marriage officers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the forms and the manner in which the registers or records required to be kept by or under this Act shall be maintained;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the custody in which the registers and records are to be kept and the preservation of such registers and records; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the fee to be paid under the relevant provisions of the Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under the Act shall immediately after it is made, be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the State if it is in session, and if it is not in session, in the session immediately following for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and if before the expiration of the session in wiled) it is so laid or the session immediately following the Legislative Assembly agrees in making any modification in the rule or in the annulment of the rule, the rule shall, from the date on which the modification are annulment is notified, have effect only in such modified form or shall stand annulled, as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity or anything previously due under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2002/15"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2002/15/eng@2017-03-16"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-16" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>FORM - A</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>(See Section 12)</p>
                <p>MARRIAGE CERTIFICATE</p>
                <p>I........................,hereby certify that I have registered under the Compulsory Registration of Marriage Act, 2002, the marriage of bridegroom AB with bride CD on this day of 200.. in pursuance of the memorandum dated the day of ........... received by me and the same has been entered as Serial No.........in Page ...........of the Register of Marriages maintained by me for the year.</p>
                <p>Date:</p>
                <p>District Registrar of Marriages/Marriage Office of the Local Area.</p>
                <p>Address:</p>
                <p>MEMORANDUM OF MARRIAGE</p>
                <p>(See Section 8)</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="schedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of Marriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Place of marriage (With Sufficient particulars to locate the place.</p>
                <p>BRIDEGROOM'S PATICULARS.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="schedule.3.list0">
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Full Name of the bridegroom.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>Father's Name/Mother's Name.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>His age at the time of marriage.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Usual place of residence.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Address:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <p>Status of the bridegroom at the time of marriage. (Whether unmarried/widower/divorced).</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Signature of the Bridegroom.</p>
                <p>WITNESSES:</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="schedule.1.list0">
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Name.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>S/o. W/o. D/o.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>Age:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Usual place of residence.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Address:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Signature of the Witness.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="schedule.2.list0">
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Name</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>S/o, W/o Din</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>Age.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Usual place of residence</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Address.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Signature of the Witness.</p>
                <p>BRIDE'S PARTICULARS;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="schedule.3.list0">
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Full Name of the bride</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>Father's Name/Mother's Name</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>Her age at the time of marriage</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Usual place of residence.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Address:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.3.list0.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <p>Status of the bride at the time of marriage. (Whether unmarried/widow/Divorced)</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Signature of the Bride.</p>
                <p>WITNESSES:</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="schedule.1.list0">
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Name.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>S/o. W/o. D/o.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>Age.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Usual place of residence.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.1.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Address:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Signature of the Witness.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="schedule.2.list0">
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Name</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>Sio, Wlo, Di°.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>Age.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Usual place of residence.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="schedule.2.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Address:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Signature of the Witness.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
