<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1974/56/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1974/56"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The West Bengal Workmen's House-Rent Allowance Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1974/56/eng@2017-06-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1974/56/eng@2017-06-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1974/56/eng@2017-06-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1974/56/eng@2017-06-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The West Bengal Workmen's House-Rent Allowance Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[18th July, 1975]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[West Bengal Act No. LVI of 1974]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the payment of house-rent allowance to workmen employed in industry in West Bengal.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for the payment of house-rent allowance to workmen employed in industry in West Bengal;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent, commencement and application</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the West Bengal Workmen's House-rent Allowance Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall apply to every industry in which fifty or more workmen are employed.</p>
            <p>Provided that the State Government may, after giving not less than sixty days’ notice of its intention so to do, by notification, apply the provisions of this Act to any industry employing such number of workmen less than fifty as may be specified in the notification:</p>
            <p>Provided further that this Act, if it once applies to any industry, shall continue to apply to that industry even if the number of workmen employed in that industry falls below fifty or, as the case may be, below such number as may be specified in the notification under the first proviso.</p>
            <p>Explanation:-For computing the number of workmen employed in any industry for the purposes of this sub-section, the number of Workmen employed in all the units and the branches of the industry in and outside West Bengal, shall be taken into consideration, and if there is any dispute or difference in this regard, the decision of the State Government thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>***</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"controlling authority" means the authority appointed by the State Government under Section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"Employer" means in relation to any industry—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>belonging to, or under the control of, the State Government, a person or authority appointed by the State Government, for the supervision and control of workmen, or where no person or authority has been so appointed, the head of the department concerned, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>belonging to, or under the control of, any local authority, the person appointed by such authority for the supervision and control of workmen, or where no person has been so appointed, the chief executive officer of the local authority, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in any other case, the person who, or the authority which, has the ultimate control over the affairs of the industry and where the said affairs are entrusted to any other person, whether called a manager, managing director or by any other name, such person;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"industry" has the same meaning as assigned to it in clause (i) of section 2 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), but does not include a plantation as defined in clause (f) section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (69 of 1951);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"month" has the same meaning as assigned to it in Clause (27) of the General Clauses Act, 1899):</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"wages" has the same meaning as assigned to it in clause (rr) of section 2 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"Workman" has the same meaning as assigned to it in clause (s) of section 2 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Controlling authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, appoint any officer not below the rank of Labour Officer, to be the controlling authority who shall be responsible for the administration of this Act and different controlling authorities may be appointed for different areas.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Payment of house-rent allowance</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall be bound to pay to every workman house-rent allowance which shall be five per cent. of the wages payable to the workman for his service in the industry during a month, or rupees fifteen, whichever is higher:</p>
            <p>Provided that in the case of a workman employed purely on temporary basis or casual basis or as a budli, who renders service for less than six days in a month house-rent allowance shall be paid pro-rata.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The house-rent allowance payable to a workman under sub-section (1) shall be paid in such manner and within such time as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) a workman who is entitled to draw under the terms of his service house-rent allowance at a higher rate than that provided in sub-section (1) shall continue to draw the same at such higher rate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the workman in an industry is given house accommodation by the employer and a deduction is made therefore from his wages then,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the amount deducted for such house accommodation is higher than the house-rent allowance admissible under sub-section (1), the deduction shall</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>be reduced by the amount mentioned in that sub-section and no house-rent allowance shall be payable to the workman; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the amount deducted is less than the house-rent allowance admissible under sub-section (1), the said allowance shall be reduced by the amount deducted and the balance paid to the workman.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of house-rent allowance</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the house-rent allowance payable under this Act is not paid by the employer within the prescribed time, the workman or any other person authorised by him in writing in this behalf, or in the case of death of the workman, his legal representatives may, without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, make in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, an application to the controlling authority having jurisdiction over the. area in which the industry is situated, for the recovery of the house-rent allowance due to him :</p>
            <p>Provided that such application shall be made within one year from the date on which the house-rent allowance became due:</p>
            <p>Provided further that such application may be entertained after the expiry of the said period of one year if the controlling authority is satisfied that the workman had sufficient cause for not making the application in time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The controlling authority to whom an application under sub-. section (1) is made may, after giving the applicant and the employer concerned an opportunity of being heard and after making such further inquiry, as may be considered necessary, determine, in such manner as may be prescribed, the amount of house-rent allowance due to the applicant and may, by an order, direct, without prejudice to any other action which may under this Act or any other law lie against the employer, the payment to the applicant of the amount of house-refit allowance so determined.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount directed to be paid by an order under sub-section (2) may be recovered by any Magistrate to whom the controlling authority making the order makes application in this behalf as if it were a fine imposed by such Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie in the prescribed manner and within the prescribed time from an order of the controlling authority dismissing any application or giving any direction under sub-section (2), to the State Government or to such authority not below the rank of Assistant Labour Commissioner, as the State Government may, by notification, appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Reference of dispute under the Act</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any dispute arises between an employer and any workman with respect to the house-rent allowance payable under this Act or with respect to the application of this Act to an industry, such dispute shall be deemed to be an industrial dispute within the meaning of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, appoint such person as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and may define the limits within which they shall exercise jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) may, for the purpose of ascertaining whether any of the provisions of this Act has been complied with,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>require an employer to furnish such information as he may consider necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>at any reasonable time and with such assistance, if any, as he thinks fit, enter the place of any industry or any premises connected therewith and require any one found in charge thereof to produce before him for examination any accounts, books, registers and other documents relating to the employment of workmen or the payment of wages in the industry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>examine, with respect to any matter relevant to any of the purposes aforesaid, the employer, his agent or servant or any other person found in charge of the industry or any premises connected therewith or any person whom the Inspector has reasonable cause to believe to be or to have been a workman in the industry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>make copies of, or take extracts from, any book, register or other document maintained in relation to the industry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person required to produce any accounts, book, register or other document or to give information by an Inspector under sub--section (1) shall be legally bound to do so.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, if it thinks fit so to do in the public interest, by notification, exempt any class of industry from the provisions of this Act for such period and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of registers, records, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall prepare and maintain such registers, records, and other documents in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, for the purposes of avoiding any payment to be made by himself under this Act or enabling any other person to avoid such payment, knowingly makes or causes to be made any false statement or false representation shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine hid may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who contravenes, or makes default in complying with, any of the provisions of this Act shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act, save on a complaint made by or under the authority of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the controlling authority, an Inspector or any other person in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>manner and time of payment of house-rent allowance referred to in sub-section (2) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>form and manner of making application for, and manner of determining the amount of, house-rent allowance due, referred to in sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>manner in which and the time within which an appeal shall be filed under sub-section (4) of section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>other powers of Inspectors referred to in clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 7; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>form in which registers, records and other documents are to be prepared and manner in which they are to be maintained uncle section 9.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
