<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1884/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1884/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Agriculturists' Loans Act, 1884"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1884/12/eng@1884-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1884/12/eng@1884-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1884-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1884/12/eng@1884-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1884/12/eng@1884-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Agriculturists' Loans Act, 1884</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 12 OF 1884</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th July, 1884.] Preambl</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to amend and provide for the extension of the Northern India</p>
        <p>Takkavi Act, 1879.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Agriculturists'</p>
            <p>Loans Act, 1884; and</p>
            <p>Commencement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the first day of August, 1884.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Local extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section  extends to the whole of</p>
            <p>India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st</p>
            <p>November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rest of this Act extends in the first instance only to</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh, the Central Provinces, Assam and Delhi and the  territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were  comprised in the States of Bombay, Punjab and Ajmer.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>But any State Government may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette, extend the rest of this Act to  the</p>
            <p>whole or any part of  the territories to which this Act extends]</p>
            <p>under its administration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Act X of 1879, and sections 4 and 5 of Act XV of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1880">
        <num>1880.</num>
        <heading>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2 and Sch.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power for State Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State</p>
            <p>Government  or, in a State for which there is a Board of Revenue of</p>
            <p>Financial Commissioner, such Board or Financial Commissioner, subject  to the control of the State Government] may, from time to time,</p>
            <p>make rules as to loans to be made to owners and occupiers of arable  land, for the relief of distress, the purchase of seed or cattle, or  any other purpose not specified in the Land Improvement Loans Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1883">
        <num>1883.</num>
        <heading>(19 of 1883.), but connected with agricultural objects.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1883.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All such rules shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of Loans. Every loan made in accordance with such  rules, all interest (if any) chargeable thereon, and costs (if any)</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>incurred in making or recovering the same, shall, when they become  due, be recoverable from the person to whom the loan was made, or from  any person who has become surety for the repayment thereof, as if they  were arrears of land- revenue or costs incurred in recovering the same  due by the person to whom the loan was made or by his surety.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Liability of joint- borrowers as among themselves. When a loan  is made under this Act to the members of a village community or to any  other persons on such terms that all of them are jointly and severally  bound to the Government for the payment of the whole amount payable in  respect thereof, and a statement showing the portion of that amount  which as among themselves each is bound to contribute is entered upon  the order granting the loan and is signed, marked, or sealed by each  of them or his agent duly authorized in this behalf and by the officer  making the order, that statement shall be conclusive evidence of the  portion of that amount which as among themselves each of those persons  is bound to contribute.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
