<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2001/29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2001/29"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Council Of World Affairs Act, 2001"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2001/29/eng@2001-09-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2001/29/eng@2001-09-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2001-09-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2001/29/eng@2001-09-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2001/29/eng@2001-09-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Council Of World Affairs Act, 2001</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 29 OF 2001</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 3rd September, 2001.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the Indian Council of World Affairs to be an  institution of national importance and to provide for its  incorporation and matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Indian Council of World Affairs Act, 2001.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, it shall be deemed to have  come into force on the 1st day of September, 2000.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of the Indian Council of World Affairs as institution  of national importance.- Whereas the objects of the Indian Council of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>World Affairs, a society registered under the Societies Registration</p>
            <p>Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) are such as to make the nstitution one of  national importance, it is hereby declared that the institution, known  as the Indian Council of World Affairs, is an institution of national  importance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Governing Body;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Council" means the Indian Council of World Affairs incorporated  under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Director- General" means the Director- General of the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" existing Council" means the Indian Council of World Affairs, a  society registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1860">
        <num>1860.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>) and functioning as such immediately before the appointed day;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Fund" means the Fund of the Council referred to in section 18;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" Governing Body" means the Governing Body of the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" member" means a member of the Council and includes the President  and Vice- President;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" President" means the President of the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" regulations" means the regulations made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" rules" means the rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" Vice- Presidents" means the Vice- Presidents of the Council.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation of the Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Indian Council of World</p>
            <p>Affairs is hereby constituted as a body corporate by the name of the</p>
            <p>Indian Council of World Affairs and as such body corporate it shall  have perpetual succession and a common seal with ower, subject to the  provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both  movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by that name sue and  be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The head office of the Council shall be at Delhi and the Council  may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, establish  branches at other places in India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of assets and liabilities of the existing Council to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Council.-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On and from the appointed day,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all properties and other assets vested in the existing Council  immediately before that day, shall vest in the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all contracts  entered into and all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or  for the existing Council immediately before that day for or in  connection with the purposes of the existing Council, shall be deemed  to have been incurred, entered into and engaged to be done by, with or  for the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all sums of money due to the existing Council, immediately before  that day, shall be deemed to be due to the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or which could  have been instituted by or against the existing Council, immediately  before that day, may be continued or instituted by or against the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Council; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>every employee holding any office under the existing Council  immediately before that day, shall, on that day, hold his office or  service under the Council with the same rights and privileges as to  pension, gratuity and other matters as would have bee admissible to  him if there had been no such vesting; and shall continue to do so  unless and until his employment under the Council is duly terminated  or until his remuneration and other conditions of service are duly  altered by the Council.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1947">
        <num>1947.</num>
        <heading>(14 of 1947) or in any other law for the time being in force, the  absorption of any employee by the Council in its regular service under  this section shall not entitle such emplo ee to any compensation under  that Act or any other law and no such claim shall be entertained by  any court, tribunal or other authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Obligation to transfer property or assets.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person having  possession, custody or control of property forming part of the  properties and other assets referred to in clause (a) of sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 5 shall deliver forthwith such proper y to the</p>
            <p>Director- General.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person incharge of the property and other assets of the  existing Council immediately before the commencement of this Act  shall, within ten days from that day, furnish to the Director- General  a complete inventory of all properties and assets (incl ding   particulars of book debts and investments and belongings) immediately  before the commencement of this Act and also of all agreements entered  into by the existing Council or any person on its behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Composition of the Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from the 1st day of</p>
            <p>September, 2001 and until the appointment of date under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, the Council shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Vice- President of India, who shall be President, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Prime Minister of India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the speaker of the Lok Sabha;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Leader of the House, Rajya Sabha;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Leader of the Opposition, Lok Sabha;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the Leader of the Opposition, Rajya Sabha.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from such date as may be appointed by the Central</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Government by notification in the Official Gazette which shall not be  later than three months from the date of assent by the President of  the Indian Council of World Affairs Bill, 2001, the Cou cil shall  consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Vice- President of India, who shall be the President, ex  officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>three Vice- Presidents as may be nominated by the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>a Director- General to be nominated by the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>five members of the Lok Sabha to be nominated by the Speaker of  the Lok Sabha and three members of the Rajya Sabha to be nominated by  the Chairman of the Rajya Sabha;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>seven members, who are distinguished in the field of diplomacy,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>international affairs, international law, Multilateral or United</p>
            <p>Nations affairs, security and disarmament to be nominated by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>seven members, who are representatives (of which at least two   shall be the Vice- Chancellors) of Universities or research  institutions of higher learning from amongst experts in the fields of  history, economics and other social sciences to be nominate by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>seven members, who are either media personalities or  representatives of organisations such as India International Centre,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Centre for Policy Research, Indian Council of Social Science Research,</p>
            <p>Institute of Defence Studies and Analyses, Indian Council of Cultural</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Relations, and interested in the work and objectives of the Council to  be selected by the Governing Body of the Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list12.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>five members who are representatives of Business or Chambers of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Commerce, Federation of Indian Chambers of Commerce and Industry,</p>
            <p>Confederation of Indian Industry, Associated Chambers of Commerce and</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list16">
              <listIntroduction>Industry of India, Federation of Indian Export Or anisations to be  nominated by the Governing Body of the Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list16.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>three members from the Ministry of External Affairs, ex officio</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Foreign Secretary, Financial Advisor, and Dean (Foreign Service</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list19">
              <listIntroduction>Institute), to be nominated by the Chairperson of the Governing Body;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list19.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>five members to be nominated by the Central Government to  represent respectively the Ministries of the Central Government  dealing with Education, Culture, Urban Development, Science and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Technology and Defence, ex officio.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is hereby declared that the office of the member of the Council  shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for being, a</p>
            <p>Member of either House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being nominated or selected as  a member if he-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence  which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral  turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Term of office and vacancies among members.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise  provided in this section, the term of office of a member shall be  three years from the date of his nomination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of the member nominated to fill a casual  vacancy shall continue for remainder of the term of the member in  whose place he is nominated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member shall, unless the Central Government otherwise directs,</p>
            <p>continue in office until another person is nominated as a member in  his place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall remove a member if he-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in  sub- section (4) of section 7; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is, without obtaining leave of absence from the Council, absent  from three consecutive meetings of the Council; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.4.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>in the opinion of the Central Government, has so abused his  position as to render his continuance in office detrimental to the  public interest:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no member shall be removed under this clause unless he  has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member shall, unless disqualified under sub- section (4) of  section 7, be eligible for re- nomination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member may resign from his office by writing under his hand  addressed to the Central Government but shall continue in his office  until his resignation is accepted by that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The manner of filling vacancies among members shall be such as may  be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Powers and functions of President.- The President shall exercise  such powers and discharge such functions as are laid down in this Act  or as may be prescribed by rules.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Powers and functions of Vice- Presidents.- The Vice- Presidents  shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the functions of  the President as may be prescribed by rules or as may be delegated to  him by the President.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Allowances of members.- Members shall receive such allowances, if  any, from the Council as may be prescribed by rules.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of Council.- The Council shall hold its first meeting at  such time and place as may be appointed by the Central Government and  shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of  business at the first meeting as may be laid own by that Government;</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and thereafter the Council shall meet at such times and places and  observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of  business at its meetings as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Objects of Council.- The objects of the Council shall be-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to promote the study of Indian and international affairs so as to  develop a body of informed opinion on international matters;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to promote India' s relations with other countries through study,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>research, discussion, lectures, exchange of ideas and information with  other organisations within and outside India engaged in similar  activities;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to serve as a clearing house of information and knowledge  regarding world affairs;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to publish books, periodicals, journals, reviews, papers,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>pamphlets and other literature on subjects covered under clauses (a)</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>and (b);</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to establish contacts with organisations promoting objects  mentioned in this section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to arrange conferences and seminars to discuss and study the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Indian policy towards international affairs; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to undertake such other activities for the promotion of ideas and  attainment of the above- mentioned objects.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Governing Body and other committees of Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall  be a Governing Body of the Council which shall be constituted by the</p>
            <p>Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Governing Body shall be the executive committee of the Council  and shall exercise such powers and discharge such functions as the</p>
            <p>Council may, by regulations made in this behalf, confer or impose upon  it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from such date as may be appointed by the Central</p>
            <p>Government by notification in the Official Gazette, the Vice- President  of India, ex officio shall be the Chairperson of the Governing Body  and shall exercise such powers and discharge such func ions as may be  prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be followed by the Governing Body in the exercise  of its powers and discharge of its functions and the term of office  of, and the manner of filling vacancies among the members of the</p>
            <p>Governing Body, shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be prescribed by  rules, the Council may constitute as many standing committees and as  many ad hoc committees as it thinks fit for exercising any power or  discharging any function of the Council or for i quiring into, or  reporting or advising upon, any matter which the Council may refer to  them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson and members of the Governing Body or a standing  committee or an ad hoc committee shall receive such allowances as may  be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Staff of Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a chief executive officer of  the Council who shall be designated as the Director- General and shall  be appointed by the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director- General shall act as the Secretary to the Council as  well as to the Governing Body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director- General shall exercise such powers and discharge such  functions as may be prescribed by regulations or as may be delegated  to him by the Council or the President or the Governing Body or the</p>
            <p>Chairperson.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Financial Advisor of the Ministry of External Affairs shall be  the Financial Advisor of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the Council  may appoint such number of other officers and employees as may be  necessary for the exercise of its powers and efficient discharge of  its functions and may determine the designations an grades of such  other officers and employees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the</p>
            <p>Director- General and other officers and employees of the Council shall  be entitled to such salary and allowances and shall be governed by  such conditions of service in respect of leave, pension gratuity,</p>
            <p>provident fund and other matters, as may be prescribed by regulations  made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Council.- The Council shall undertake various plans  to promote, organise and implement various programmes for efficiently  achieving the objects of the Council specified in section 13 and shall  also perform such other functions as the Cent al Government may, by  rules, prescribe.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Payment to Council.- The Central Government may, after due  appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Council in each financial year such sums as may be considered  necessary for the exercise of powers and efficient discharge of  functions of the Council under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Fund of Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Council shall maintain a Fund to which  shall be credited to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all moneys received from the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Council by way of grants, gifts,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Council in any other manner or from any  other source.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All moneys credited to the Fund shall be deposited in such banks  or invested in such manner as the Council may, subject to the approval  of the Central Government, decide.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the administrative and  other expenses of the Council, including expenses incurred in the  exercise of its powers and discharge of its functions under section 16  or in relation to any of the activities referred to therein or for  anything relatable thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Budget of Council.- The Council shall prepare, in such form and at  such time every year, as may be prescribed by rules, a budget in  respect of the financial year next ensuing, showing the estimated  receipts and expenditure of the Council and shall for ard to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government such number of copies thereof as may be prescribed  by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by rules, prescribe and in accordance wi h such  general directions as may be issued by that Government, in  consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Council shall be audited by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by him in  connection with such audit shall be payable by the Council to the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
            <p>Council shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor General of</p>
            <p>India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and,</p>
            <p>in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
            <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect the office or offices of t e Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Council as certified by the Comptroller and</p>
            <p>Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this  behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded  annually to the Central Government and that Gover ment shall cause the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.- The Council shall prepare every year, in such form  and at such time as may be prescribed by rules, an annual report  giving a true and full account of its activities during the previous  year and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the entral Government  and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House  of Parliament.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Authentication of orders and instruments of Council.- All orders  and decisions of the Council shall be authenticated by the signature  of the President or the Vice- President and all other instruments  issued by the Council shall be authenticated by the ignature of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Director- General or any other officer of the Council authorised by the</p>
            <p>Council in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Vacancy, etc. not to invalidate proceedings of the Council.- No  act or proceeding of the Council, Governing Body or any standing or ad  hoc committee under this Act shall be invalid merely by reason of-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Council;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member of  the Council; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Council not affecting the  merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Reports, returns and information.- The Council shall furnish to  the Central Government such reports, returns and other information as  that Government may require from time to time.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Power to make rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner of filling vacancies among members under sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 8;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.7.list3">
              <listIntroduction>President and the Vice- Presidents under sections 9 and 10, as the case  may be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.7.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the allowances to be paid to the members under section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.7.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the control and restrictions in relation to the constitution of  standing and ad hoc committees under sub- section (5) of section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.7.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the number of other officers and employees that may be appointed  by the Council and the manner of such appointment under sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 15;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.5.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the salaries and allowances payable to the Director- General and  other officers and employees of the Council under sub- section (6) of  section 15;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.5.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>such other functions to be performed by the Council under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the time at which the budget shall be  prepared by the Council and the number of copies thereof to be  forwarded to the Central Government under section 19;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the form in which an annual statement of accounts including the  balance- sheet shall be prepared by the Council under sub- section (1)</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>of section 20;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the time at which the annual report of the  activities of the Council shall be submitted to the Central Government  under section 21;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council may make regulations  consistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules to carry out  the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the summoning and holding of meetings, other than the first  meeting of the Council, the time and place where such meetings are to  be held and the transaction of business at such meetings under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Governing Body and the Chairperson under sub- sections (2) and (3) of  section 14;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the Governing Body in exercise of  its powers and discharge of its functions and the term of office of,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Governing Body under sub- section (4) of section 14;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the allowances to be paid to the Chairperson and members of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Governing Body, standing and ad hoc committees under sub- section (6)</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>of section 14;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list9.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Director- General under sub- section (3) of section 15;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list11.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service of the Director- General and other  officers and employees of the Council under sub- section (6) of section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed by  regulations.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the first  regulations under this Act shall be made by the Governing Body and any  regulations so made may be altered or rescinded by the Council in  exercise of its powers under sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.- Every rule  and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may  be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in  session, for a total period of thirty days wh ch may be comprised in  one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or regulat on or both Houses agree that the  rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be w thout prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions  not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act s may appear to be  necessary for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the  expiry of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may  be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Indian Council of World Affairs</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list1.Second">
                <num>(Second)</num>
                <p>Ordinance, 2001 (Ord. 3 of 2001) is hereby repealed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the repeal of the said Ordinance, anything done or  any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been  done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            <p>SUBHASH C. JAIN,</p>
            <p>Secy. to the Govt. of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
