<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1881/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1881/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Obstructions In Fairways Act, 1881"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1881/16/eng@1881-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1881/16/eng@1881-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1881-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1881/16/eng@1881-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1881/16/eng@1881-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Obstructions In Fairways Act, 1881</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 16 OF 1881</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 15th March, 1881.] Preamb</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to empower the Government to remove or destroy obstructions in  fairways, and to prevent the creation of such obstructions.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>short title. This Act may be called the Obstructions in</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Fairways Act, 1881;</p>
            <p>But nothing herein contained shall apply to vessels  belonging  to, or hired by a contract made on behalf of, the Government].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Central Government empowered to remove or destroy obstruction  in fairway. Whenever, in any fairway leading to any port in  the  territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were  comprised in Part A States and Part C States], any vessel in sunk,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>stranded or abandoned, or any fishing- stake, timber or other thing is  placed or left,  the Central Government] may, if in its opinion such  thing is, or is likely to become, an obstruction or danger to  navigation,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cause such thing or any part thereof to be removed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if such thing is of such a description or so situate  that,  in the opinion of the Central Government], it  is not worth removing, cause the same or any part  thereof to be destroyed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of 1962,</p>
            <p>s. 3 and Sch.</p>
            <p>Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>10. 1967): vide Reg. 8 of 1965, s. 3 and Sch.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Central Government entitled to expenses incurred in removing  obstruction. Whenever anything is removed under section 2,  the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government] shall be entitled to receive a reasonable sum,</p>
            <p>having regard to all the circumstances of the case, for the expenses  incurred in respect of such removal.</p>
            <p>Dispute concerning such expenses.</p>
            <p>Any dispute arising concerning the amount due under this section,</p>
            <p>in respect of anything so removed, shall be decided by the District</p>
            <p>Magistrate or Presidency Magistrate having jurisdiction at the place  where such thing is, upon application to him for that purpose by  either of the disputing parties; and such decision shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Notice of removal to be given by Central Government. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government] shall, whenever anything is removed under  section 2, publish in the Official Gazette a notification containing a  description of such thing, and the time at which and the place from  which the same was so removed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Things removed may, in certain cases, be sold. If after  publishing such notification, such thing is unclaimed, or if the person claiming the same fails to pay the amount due  for the said expenses and any customs- duties or other  charges properly incurred by the  Central Government]</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>in respect thereof,</p>
            <p>the  Central Government] may sell such thing by public  auction, if it is of a perishable nature, forthwith,</p>
            <p>and if it is not of a perishable nature, at any time  not less than six months after publishing such  notification as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Proceeds how applied. On realizing the proceeds of such sale,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>the amount due for expenses and charges as aforesaid, together with  the expenses of the sale, shall be deducted therefrom, and the surplus</p>
            <p>(if any) shall be paid to the owner of the thing sold, or, if no such  person appear and claim such surplus, shall be held in deposit for  payment, without interest, to any person thereafter establishing his  right to the same:</p>
            <p>Provided that he makes the claim within one year from the date of  the sale.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>" Vessel" to include tackle, cargo, etc. For the purposes of  this Act, the term" vessel" shall be deemed to include also every  article or thing or collection of things being or</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>forming part of the tackle, equipment, cargo, stores or ballast of a  vessel; and any proceeds arising from the sale of a vessel, and of the  cargo thereof, or of any other property recovered therefrom, shall be  regarded as a common fund.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules to regulate and prohibit the placing of  obstructions in fairways. The Central Government may, from time to  time, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to regulate  or prohibit, in any fairway leading to a port in  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</heading>
      </section>
      <part id="part-A">
        <num>A</num>
        <heading>States and Part C States] the placing of fishing- stakes, the  casting or throwing of ballast, rubbish, or any other thing likely to  give rise to a bank or shoal, or the doing of any other act which  will, in its opinion, cause, or be likely to cause, obstruction or  danger to navigation.</heading>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for breach of such rules. Whoever is guilty of any act  or omission in contravention of the rules made under section 8, may be  tried for such offence in any district or presidency- town in which he  is found, and shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may  extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred  rupees, or with both.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Compensation payable in certain cases for damage caused under  this Act. Whenever the maintenance or creation of an obstruction in  any fairway has become lawful by long usage or otherwise, and such  obstruction is removed or destroyed under section 2, or its creation  is regulated or prohibited under section 8, any person having a right  to maintain or create such obstruction shall be entitled to receive  from the  Central Government] reasonable compensation for any damage  caused to him by such removal, destruction, regulation or prohibition.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every dispute arising concerning the right to such compensation,</p>
              <p>or the amount thereof, shall be determined according to the law for  the time being in force relating to like disputes in the case of land  needed for public purposes  and not otherwise; and for the purposes  of such law the fairway from or in which such obstruction was removed  or destroyed, or in which its creation was regulated or prohibited,</p>
              <p>shall be deemed to be a part of the presidency- town or district in  which the port to which such fairway leads is situate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Certain action of the Government previous to passing of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act to be deemed to have been taken hereunder. Whenever any  obstruction in a fairway leading to a port in  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-A">
        <num>A</num>
        <heading>States and Part C States] has been removed or destroyed, or  whenever the creation of any such obstruction has been regulated or  prohibited, by an order of the Central Government or a State</heading>
        <paragraph id="part-A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government, previous to the passing of this Act, such removal,</p>
            <p>destruction, regulation or prohibition shall be deemed to have been  effected under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Saving of other powers possessed by Central Government.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing herein contained shall be deemed to prevent the exercise by    the Central Government] of any other powers possessed by it in this  behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Application to fairways in inland waterways. All  references in this Act to the Central Government shall, in relation to  fairways in inland waterways, be construed as references to  State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government]].</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
