<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/51/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/51"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Railway Companies (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/51/eng@1951-09-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/51/eng@1951-09-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-09-14" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/51/eng@1951-09-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/51/eng@1951-09-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Railway Companies (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 51 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 14th September, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make provision for the proper management and administration  of railway companies in certain special cases.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and application.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Railway Companies (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1951.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It applies to every railway company in respect of which a  notified order has been issued under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Companies Act" means the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7   of 1913.);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" directors" means the directors appointed under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" notified order" means an order notified in the Official</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Gazette;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" railway company" means any company registered under the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Companies Act or any law repealed thereby for the  purpose of making and working or making or working a  railway, whether alone or in conjunction with other  purposes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to apply Act to any railway  company and to appoint directors thereof.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Central</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Government is of opinion that a situation has arisen in the affairs of  a railway company which--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has prejudicially affected the convenience of persons  using the railway administered by the railway company,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has caused serious dislocation in any trade or industry  using the railway, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>has caused serious unemployment amongst a section of the  community,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>or when, in the opinion of the Central Government, it is necessary in  the national interest the Central Government may, by notified</p>
            <p>The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. 1963 vide Reg. 7 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1963">
        <num>1963.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, s. 3 and Sch. I.</p>
            <p>order, apply the provisions of this Act to the railway company and  appoint as many persons as it thinks fit to be directors of the  railway company for the purpose of taking over its management and  administration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1963.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The power to appoint directors under this section includes  the power to appoint any individual, firm or company to be the  managing agent of the railway company on such terms and conditions as  to the Central Government may seem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Effect of notified order appointing directors or managing  agents. On the issue of a notified order under section 3,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all persons holding office as directors of the railway  company immediately before the issue of the notified  order shall be deemed to have vacated their offices as  such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any contract of management between the railway company  and any managing agent thereof holding office as such  immediately before the issue of the notified order  shall be deemed to have terminated;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the managing agent, if any, appointed under this Act  shall be deemed to have been duly appointed in  pursuance of the Companies Act and the memorandum and  articles of association of the railway company, and the  provisions of the Companies Act and of the memorandum  and articles shall, subject to the other provisions  contained in this Act, apply accordingly, but no such  managing agent shall be removed from office except with  the previous consent of the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the directors shall take such steps as may be necessary  to take into their custody or under their control all  the property, effects and actionable claims to which  the railway company is, or appears to be, entitled, and  all the property and effects of the railway company  shall be deemed to be in the custody of the directors  as from the date of the notified order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the directors shall be for all purposes the directors of  the railway company duly constituted under the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Companies Act, and shall alone be entitled to exercise  all the powers of the directors of the railway company,</p>
            <p>whether such powers are derived from the Companies Act  or from the memorandum or articles of association of  the railway company or from any other source.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of directors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the control of  the Central Government, the directors shall take such steps as may be  necessary for the purpose of efficiently managing the business of the  railway company and, in</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>particular, the directors shall have power, notwithstanding anything  contained in the Companies Act or in the memorandum or articles of  association of the railway company,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to choose one of their number to be the chairman, and to  delegate to him or to any one or more of the directors  all or any of their powers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>with the previous approval of the Central Government and  subject to such conditions as that Government may think  fit to impose, to raise funds in such manner and offer  such security therefor as they think fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to carry out such repairs as may be necessary in respect  of any machinery, rolling- stock, buildings, works or  other property in their custody;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to do all acts necessary for making, maintaining,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>altering or repairing and using the railway of the  railway company;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to employ such persons as may be necessary for enabling  them to efficiently discharge their duties, and define  the conditions of service of such employees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The directors may, with the previous sanction of the Central</p>
            <p>Government, cancel or vary, either unconditionally or subject to such  conditions as they think fit to impose, any contract or agreement  entered into between the railway company and any other person at any  time before the issue of the notified order under section 3, if such  contract or agreement had been entered into in bad faith and is  detrimental to the interests of the railway company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Statement of affairs to be made to directors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the issue  of a notified order under section 3, there shall be made out and  submitted to the directors a statement as to the affairs of the  railway company, verified by affidavit and containing the following  particulars, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the assets of the railway company, stating separately  the cash balance in hand and at the bank, if any;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the debts and liabilities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the names, residences and occupations of the creditors,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>stating separately the amount of secured debts and  unsecured debts and, in the case of secured debts, the  particulars of the securities, their value and the  dates when they were given;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the debts due to the railway company and the names,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>residences and occupations of the persons from whom  they are due and the amount likely to be realised  therefrom;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>such other particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The statement shall be submitted by one or more of the  persons who was or were holding office as a director or as directors  of the railway company immediately before the issue of the notified  order under section 3 or by the secretary, manager or other chief  officer of the railway company who was holding office as such before  the issue of the notified order as the directors may require in each  case, and the statement shall be submitted within such time as may be  so required.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person, without any reasonable excuse, knowingly and  wilfully makes default in complying with the requirements of this  section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to  three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or  with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Statements by beneficial owners of shares of railway company.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who has any interest in any share of the railway company  which stands in the name of another person in the register of  shareholders of the railway company shall, within such period as may  be specified by the Central Government by notified order, make a  declaration in such form as may be prescribed (which shall be   countersigned by the person in whose name the share is registered) to  the railway company declaring his interest in the share, and  notwithstanding anything contained in any other law or in any contract  to the contrary, a person who fails to make a declaration as aforesaid  in respect of any share shall be deemed to have no right or title  whatsoever in or to that share:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall affect the right of  any person who has an interest in any such share to establish in a</p>
            <p>Court his right thereto if the person in whose name the share is  registered refuses to sign that declaration as required by this  section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power of directors to institute proceedings against past  directors, etc., for damages.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The directors may, if they are  satisfied that it is necessary in the interests of the railway company  or in the public interest so to do, institute in the name of the  railway company such proceedings as they think fit for the recovery of  damages for any fraud, misfeasance or other misconduct in connection  with the management of the affairs of the railway company committed by  any person before the issue of the notified order under section 3 or  for the recovery of any property of the railway company which has been  misapplied or wrongfully retained by any person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No director shall be personally liable for any costs or  expenses incurred in connection with any proceedings instituted by  virtue of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalties. If any person wilfully destroys or fails to deliver  to the directors when required any books of account, registers or any  other documents</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>in his custody relating to the business of the railway company or  retains any property of the railway company, he shall be punishable  with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which  may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Filling up of vacancies among directors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Casual vacancies  occurring in the body of directors, whether caused by death,</p>
            <p>resignation or otherwise, shall be filled by nomination by the Central</p>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act of the directors shall be called in question on the  ground merely of the existence of any vacancy among the directors or  any defect in the appointment of any of them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>No right to compensation for termination of contract of  managing agent or any other contract.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Companies Act or in any other law for the time being  in force, no managing agent shall be entitled to any compensation for  the premature termination under this Act of any contract of management  entered into by him with the railway company, and no person shall be  entitled to compensation in respect of the cancellation or variation  under this Act of any other contract or agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect the right  of any such managing agent or person to recover from the railway  company moneys recoverable otherwise than by way of such compensation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Cancellation of appointment of directors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any time  it appears to the Central Government that the purpose of the notified  order appointing the directors has been fulfilled or that for any  other reason it is unnecessary that the notified order should remain  in force, the Central Government may, by notified order, cancel the  appointment of directors made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the cancellation of any such appointment as is referred to  in sub- section (1), the Central Government may--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>direct that all the property, effects and actionable  claims of the railway company shall revest in the  persons in whom they were vested before the issue of  the notified order under section 3; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>reconstitute by fresh appointment a new body of persons  to take charge of the management and administration of  the whole affairs of the railway company, whether as  directors or managers or in any other capacity:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no such direction or fresh appointment shall be  made except in pursuance of a resolution passed by the shareholders of  the railway company at a meeting called for the purpose by the  directors appointed under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, at any time before the issue of  the notified order under sub- section (1), take such action as may be</p>
            <p>necessary under clause (b) of sub- section (2) for the purpose of  making any fresh appointments.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Companies Act.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Companies Act or in the memorandum or  articles of association of the railway company, but subject to the  other provisions contained in this Act,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of the  railway company or any other person to nominate or  appoint any person to be a director of the railway  company;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders  of the railway company shall be given effect to unless  approved by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>no proceeding for the winding- up of the railway company  or for the appointment of a receiver in respect thereof  shall lie in any Court, unless by or with the sanction  of the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1) and to  the other provisions contained in this Act and subject to such  exceptions, restrictions and limitations as the Central Government may  by notified order specify, the Companies Act shall continue to apply  to the railway company in the same manner as it applied thereto before  the issue of the notified order under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act and  of any notified order made thereunder shall have effect  notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith in any other law for  the time being in force or in the memorandum or articles of  association of the railway company or in any other instrument having  effect by virtue of any law other than this Act, but save as aforesaid  the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in  derogation of, any other law for the time being applicable to the  railway company.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Directors to be public servants. Every director appointed  under section 3 shall be deemed to be a public servant within the  meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860)</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by notified  order, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it under  this Act, except the powers given to it under section 3 to apply the  provisions of this Act to any railway company or the powers given to  it under section 12 or section 18, may be exercised by any State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government, and where any powers are so delegated, they shall be  exercised subject to such directions as the Central Government may  issue from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under Act.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit,</p>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any director  in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done in pursuance of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the</p>
            <p>Central Government or any State Government or any director for any  damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good  faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to acquire railway of railway  company.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where under any instrument, having effect by virtue of  any law other than this Act or by virtue of an agreement arrived at  between the parties, provision is made for the purchase by a person or  local authority or the State Government of a railway which is the  property of a railway company on payment of the value thereof  calculated in the manner and subject to the conditions specified in  the instrument, the Central Government shall also have the same right  to purchase the railway on the same terms and subject to the same  conditions as the person, local authority or the State Government has  under the instrument.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If in respect of any railway the Central Government exercises  its right of purchase under this section, any person, local authority  or State Government, in whom or in which a similar right is vested  under the instrument, shall be deemed to have become disentitled to  exercise the same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may by  notified order, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, any rules made under sub- section (1) may provide for-</p>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which or the conditions subject to which  the directors or managing agents of a railway company  may exercise their powers under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the additional particulars which a statement under  section 6 should contain;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form in which a declaration under section 7 may be  made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of a Railway Local Advisory Committee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which books of account shall be maintained  by the directors and audited;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the submission of specified or periodical returns and  reports by the directors to any specified authority in  connection with the affairs of the railway company;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conduct of business of the directors appointed by  notified order and for the recruitment and employment  of officers and staff.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the year session or  the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should  not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Ordinance 2 of 1951. The Railway Companies</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Emergency Provisions) Ordinance, 1951 (2 of 1951.) is hereby  repealed:</p>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the repeal shall not affect--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the previous operation of the said Ordinance, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in  respect of any offence committed against the said</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinance, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect  of any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment, and any  such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be  instituted, continued or enforced, and any such  penalty, forfeiture, or punishment may be imposed as if  this Act had not been passed:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything  done or any action taken (including any notified order issued,</p>
            <p>appointment made or direction given under the said Ordinance) shall be  deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provision of  this Act and shall continue in force accordingly, unless and until  superseded by anything done or any action taken under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
