<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/52/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/52"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Veterinary Council Act, 1984"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1984-08-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Veterinary Council Act, 1984</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 52 OF 1984</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th August, 1984.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- fifth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to regulate veterinary practice and to provide, for that  purpose, for the establishment of a Veterinary Council of India and</p>
        <p>State Veterinary Councils and the maintenance of registers of the  veterinary practitioners and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to make provision for the regulation of  veterinary practice and to provide, for that purpose, for the  establishment of a Veterinary Council of India and State Veterinary</p>
        <p>Councils and the maintenance of registers of persons qualified to  engage in veterinary practice for the whole of India and for matters  connected therewith or ancillary thereto;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS</p>
        <p>Parliament has no power to make laws for the States  with respect to any of the matters aforesaid except as provided in  articles 249 and 250 of the Constitution;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS in pursuance of clause (1) of article 252 of the</p>
        <p>Constitution, resolutions have been passed by all the Houses of the</p>
        <p>Legislatures of the States of Haryana, Bihar, Orissa, Himachal Pradesh  and Rajasthan to the effect that the matters aforesaid should be  regulated in those States by Parliament by law;</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Indian Veterinary Council Act, 1984.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends, in the first instance, to the whole of the States  of Haryana, Bihar, Orissa, Himachal Pradesh and Rajasthan and to all</p>
              <p>Union territories; and it shall also extend to such other States as  may adopt this Act by resolution passed in that behalf in pursuance of  clause (1) of article 252 of the Constitution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force in a State or Union territory to  which it extends, or may become extended in future, on such date  as  the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>appoint and different dates may be appointed for different provisions  of this Act or for different States or Union territories.</p>
              <p>The provisions of this Act shall come into force in the following</p>
              <p>States Union territories on the dates mentioned against each of them:-</p>
              <p>Name of State U. T. Date on which  provisions of Notification No,</p>
              <p>the Act shall and Date  come into force</p>
              <p>Haryana</p>
              <p>Bihar</p>
              <p>Orissa</p>
              <p>Himachal Pradesh</p>
              <p>Rajasthan</p>
              <p>Delhi</p>
              <p>Andman and Nicobar Islands 27. 6. 1985 S. O. 3248, dt. 27. 6. 1985</p>
              <p>Lakshadweep</p>
              <p>Dadra and Nagar Haveli</p>
              <p>Goa, Daman and Diu</p>
              <p>Pondicherry</p>
              <p>Chandigarh</p>
              <p>Mizoram</p>
              <p>Arunnachal Pradesh</p>
              <p>Sikkim</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Council" means the Veterinary Council of India  established under section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" President" means the President of the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" recognised veterinary qualification" means any of the  veterinary qualifications included in the First Schedule or the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Second Schedule;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" register" means a register maintained under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" registered veterinary practitioner" means a person  whose name is for the time being duly registered in a register;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" regulation" means a regulation made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" State Veterinary Council" means a Veterinary Council  established under section 32 and includes a Joint State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Veterinary Council established in accordance with an agreement  under section 33;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" veterinary institution" means any University or other  institution within or without India which grants degrees,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>diplomas or licences in veterinary science and animal husbandry;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" veterinary medicine" means modern scientific veterinary  medicine in all its branches and includes veterinary surgery and  obstetrics;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" Vice- President" means the Vice- President of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Council.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>INDIAN VETERINARY COUNCIL</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>INDIAN VETERINARY COUNCIL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and composition of the Council.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect  from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a</p>
              <p>Council to be called the Veterinary Council of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid,</p>
              <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire,</p>
              <p>hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to  contract and shall by the said name sue or be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Council shall consist of the following members, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>five members to be nominated by the Central Government  from amongst Directors of Animal Husbandry (by whatever name   called) of those States to which this Act extends;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>four members to be nominated by the Central Government  from amongst the heads of veterinary institutions in the States  to which this Act extends;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>one member to be nominated by the Indian Council of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Agricultural Research;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Animal Husbandry Commissioner, Government of India,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>one member to be nominated by the Central Government to  represent the Ministry of the Central Government dealing with  animal husbandry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>one member to be nominated by the Indian Veterinary</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Association;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list7.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>eleven members to be elected from amongst themselves by  persons enrolled in the Indian veterinary practitioners register;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>one member to be nominated by the Central Government  from amongst the Presidents of the State Veterinary Councils of  those States to which this Act extends;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>one member to be nominated by the Central Government  from amongst the Presidents of the State Veterinary Associations  of those States to which this Act extends;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list7.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>Secretary, Veterinary Council of India, ex officio.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President and Vice- President shall be elected by the  members from amongst themselves in such manner as may be provided by  regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever there is a vacancy in the office of the President,</p>
              <p>the Vice- President shall discharge the functions of the President.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The names of persons nominated or elected as members shall be  notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall not be qualified for nomination or election to  the Council unless he holds a recognised veterinary qualification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Mode of election of members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An election under clause (g)</p>
              <p>of sub- section (3) of section 3 shall be conducted by the Central</p>
              <p>Government in accordance with such rules as may be made by it in this  behalf and any rule so made may provide that pending the preparation  of the Indian veterinary practitioners register in accordance with the  provisions of this Act, the members referred to in that clause may be  nominated by the Central Government instead of being elected as  provided therein.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any dispute arises regarding any election to the</p>
              <p>Council, it shall be referred to the Central Government for its  decision which shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Term of office of President, Vice- President and members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President or Vice- President shall hold office for a term not  exceeding three years and not extending beyond the expiry of his term  as a member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this section, a member, other  than an ex officio member, shall hold office for a term of three years  from the date of his election or nomination to the Council or until  his successor shall have been duly elected or nominated, whichever is  longer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Members of the Council shall be eligible for re- nomination or  re- election.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the term of three years is about to expire in respect  of any member, a successor may be nominated or elected at any time  within three months before the said term expires, but, he shall not  assume office until the said term has expired.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Cessation of membership.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A member shall be deemed to have  vacated his office--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he is absent without excuse, sufficient in the  opinion of the Council, from three consecutive meetings of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he ceases to hold the post from which he has been  nominated;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a member elected under clause (g) of sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>section (3) of section 3, if he ceases to be a person enrolled in  the register;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>if he has been convicted of an offence involving moral  turpitude and punishable with imprisonment;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a  competent court.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the occurrence of a vacancy referred to in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the President shall forthwith report the fact of such vacancy to  the Central Government and thereafter that Government may, subject to  the proviso to section 7, take necessary steps to fill such vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Casual vacancies.- A casual vacancy in the Council shall be  filled by nomination or election, as the case may be, and the person  nominated or elected to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for  the remainder of the term for which the member whose place he takes  was nominated or elected:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that no such casual vacancy occurring within three  months of the date of expiry of the normal term of office of a  nominated or an elected member need be filled under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Resignation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President or Vice- President may at any  time resign his office by notice in writing addressed to the Council  and delivered to the Secretary and the resignation shall take effect  from the date on which it is accepted by the Council or on the expiry  of ninety days from the date of receipt of the resignation by the</p>
              <p>Secretary, whichever is earlier.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member may at any time resign his office by notice in  writing addressed to the President and every such resignation shall  take effect from the date on which it is accepted by the President or  on the expiry of ninety days from the date of receipt of the  resignation by the President, whichever is earlier.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Council.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall meet at least  twice in a year at such time and place as may be appointed by the</p>
              <p>Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The quorum necessary for the transaction of business at a  meeting of the Council shall be nine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President when present shall preside at every meeting of  the Council and in his absence the Vice- President and in the absence  of both any other member elected by the members present from amongst  themselves shall preside at such meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all questions which  come up before any meeting of the Council shall be decided by a  majority of the members present and voting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of an equality of votes, the President shall have  a casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (1) to (5), the</p>
              <p>Council shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to transaction  of business at its meetings as may be provided by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Secretary and other officers or servants.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government,</p>
              <p>appoint a Secretary (who shall also act as Treasurer unless the</p>
              <p>Council appoints any other person as Treasurer) and may appoint such  other officers and employees as it may deem necessary to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the Secretary, other  officers and employees appointed by the Council shall be such as may  be provided by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Secretary, officers and other employees of the Council  shall be deemed to the public servants within the meaning of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All orders and decisions and other instruments of the Council  shall be authenticated by the signature of the Secretary or any other  officer of the Council duly authorised by it in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Executive Committee and other Committees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council  shall appoint from among its members an Executive Committee and may  constitute other Committees for such general or specific purposes as  the Council considers necessary and may co- opt any person or persons  specially qualified to advise on any matter to any Committee other  than the Executive Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Committee constituted under this section shall meet at such  time and at such places and shall observe such rules of procedure in  regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be  provided by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Fees and allowances.- The President and other members and the  members of the Committees (other than the members of the Council)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>shall be paid such fees and allowances for attending the meetings of  the Council and the Committees as may be provided by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Information to be furnished by the Council and publication  thereof.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its  minutes, abstract of its accounts and other information to the Central</p>
              <p>Government as that Government may require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may publish in such manner as it may  think fit any report, copy, abstract or other information furnished to  it under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Recognition of veterinary qualifications granted by  veterinary institutions in India.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The veterinary qualifications  granted by any veterinary institution in India which are included in  the First Schedule shall be recognised veterinary qualifications for  the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any veterinary institution in India which grants a veterinary  qualification not included in the First Schedule may apply to the</p>
              <p>Central Government to have such qualification recognised and the</p>
              <p>Central Government, after consulting the Council, may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, amend the First Schedule so as to include  such qualification therein and any such notification may also direct  that an entry shall be made in the last column of the First Schedule  against such veterinary qualification declaring that it shall be a  recognised veterinary qualification only when granted after a  specified date.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Recognition of veterinary qualifications granted by  veterinary institutions in countries with which there is a scheme of  reciprocity.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The veterinary qualifications granted by veterinary  institutions outside India which are included in the Second Schedule  shall be recognised veterinary qualifications for the purposes of this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may enter into negotiations with the authority in  any country outside India which by the law of such country is  entrusted with the maintenance of a register of veterinary  practitioners, for the setting of a scheme of reciprocity for the  recognition of veterinary qualifications, and in pursuance of any such  scheme, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, amend the Second Schedule so as to include therein the  veterinary qualification which the Council has decided should be  recognised, and any such notification may also direct that an entry  shall be made in the last column of the Second Schedule against such  veterinary qualification declaring that it shall be a recognised  veterinary qualification only when granted after a specified date.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government, after consultation with the Council,</p>
              <p>may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Second</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleby">
      <doc name="scheduleby">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/52/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/52"/>
              <FRBRalias value="directing that an entry be made therein in respect of any  veterinary qualification declaring that it shall be a recognised  veterinary qualification only when granted before a specified date."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/52/eng@1984-08-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleby">
            <subsection id="scheduleby.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where the Council has refused to recommend any veterinary  qualification which has been proposed for recognition by any authority  referred to in sub- section (2) and the authority applies to the</p>
                <p>Central Government in this behalf, the Central Government, after  considering such application and after obtaining from the Council a  report, if any, as to the reasons for any such refusal, may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Second Schedule so as  to include such qualification therein and the provisions of sub-</p>
                <p>section (2) shall apply to such notification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Special provisions in certain cases for recognition of  veterinary qualifications granted by veterinary institutions in  countries with which there is no scheme of reciprocity.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-17.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The</p>
                  <p>Central Government, after consultation with the Council, may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the veterniary  qualifications granted by veterinary institutions in any country  outside India in respect of which a scheme of reciprocity for the  recognition of veterinary qualifications is not in force shall be  recognised veterinary qualification for the purposes of this Act or  shall be so only when granted after a specified date:</p>
                  <blockList id="section-17.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that veterinary practice by persons possessing such  qualifications--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-17.1.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>shall be permitted only if such persons are enrolled as  veterinary practitioners in accordance with the law regulating  the registration of veterinary practitioners for the time being  in force in that country;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-17.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>shall be limited to the institution to which they are  attached for the time being for the purpose of teaching, research  work, charitable work; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-17.1.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>shall be limited to the period specified in this behalf  by the Central Government by general or special order.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In respect of any such veterinary qualification, the Central</p>
                  <p>Government, after consultation with the Council, may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, direct that it shall be a recognised  veterinary qualification only when granted before a specified date.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Power to require information as to courses of study and  examinations.- Every veterinary institution in a State which grants a  recognised veterinary qualification shall furnish such information as  the Council may from time to time require as to the courses of study  and examinations to be undergone in order to obtain such  qualification, as to the ages at which such courses of study and  examinations are required to be undergone and such qualification is  conferred and generally as to the requisites for obtaining such  qualification.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Inspection of veterinary institutions and examinations.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A</p>
                  <p>Committee constituted under section 12 may, subject to regulations, if  any, made by the Council, appoint such number of veterinary inspectors  as it may deem requisite to inspect any veterinary institution or any  college or other institution where veterinary education is given or to  attend any examination held by any veterinary institution for the  purpose of recommending to the Central Government recognition of  veterinary qualification granted by that veterinary institution.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The veterinary inspectors shall not interfere with the  conduct of any training or examination, but shall report to the</p>
                  <p>Committee on the adequacy of the standards of veterinary education  including staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other  facilities prescribed by regulations for giving veterinary education  or on the sufficiency of every examination which they attend.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Committee shall forward a copy of any such report to the  veterinary institution concerned and shall also forward a copy with  remarks, if any, of the said institution thereon, to the Central</p>
                  <p>Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>Appointment of visitors.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-20.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Council may appoint such  number of visitors as it may deem requisite to inspect any veterinary  institution or any college or other institution where veterinary  education is given or to attend any examination held by any veterinary  institution for the purpose of granting any recognised veterinary  qualification.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any person, whether he is a member or not, may be appointed  as a visitor under this section, but a person who is appointed as an  inspector under section 19 for any inspection or examination shall not  be appointed as a visitor for the same inspection or examination.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The visitors shall not interfere with the conduct of any  training or examination, but shall report to the President on the  adequacy of the standards of veterinary education including staff,</p>
                  <p>equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities prescribed by  regulations for giving veterinary education or on the sufficiency of  every examination which they attend.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The report of a visitor shall be treated as confidential  unless in any particular case the President otherwise directs:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the Central Government requires a copy of the  report of the visitor, the Council shall furnish the same.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>Withdrawal of recognition.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-21.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When upon report by the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-21.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Committee or the visitor, it appears to the Council--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-21.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>that the courses of study and examinations to be  undergone in, or the proficiency required from candidates at any  examination held by, any veterinary institution, are not in  conformity with the regulations made under this Act or fall short  of the standards required thereby, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-21.1.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>that the staff, equipment, accommodation, training and  other facilities for instruction and training provided in such  veterinary institution or in any college or other institution  affiliated to it do not conform to the standards prescribed by  the Council.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>the Council shall make a representation to that effect to the Central</p>
                  <p>Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-21.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>After considering such representation, the Central Government  may send it to the State Government of the State in which the  veterinary institution is situated and the State Government shall  forward it along with such remarks as it may choose to make to the  veterinary institution, with an intimation of the period within which  that institution may submit its explanation to the State Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-21.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On receipt of the explanation or, where no explanation is  submitted within the period fixed, then on the expiry of that period,</p>
                  <p>the State Government shall make its recommendation to the Central</p>
                  <p>Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-21.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government, after making such inquiry, if any, as  it may deem fit, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct  that an entry shall be made in the appropriate Schedule against the  said veterinary qualification declaring that it shall be a recognised  veterinary qualification only when granted before a specified date or  that the said veterinary qualification if granted to students of a  specified college or institution affiliated to any veterinary  institution shall be a recognised veterinary qualification only when  granted before a specified date or, as the case may be, that the said  veterinary qualification shall be a recognised veterinary  qualification in relation to a specified college or</p>
                  <p>institution affiliated to any veterinary institution only when granted  after a specified date:</p>
                  <p>Provided that before issuing such notification the Central</p>
                  <p>Government may consult the Indian Council of Agricultural Research.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Minimum standards of veterinary education.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-22.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Council  may, by regulations, specify the minimum standards of veterinary  education required for granting recognised veterinary qualifications  by veterinary institutions in those States to which this Act extends.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Copies of the draft regulations and of all subsequent  amendments thereof shall be furnished by the Council to the State</p>
                  <p>Government concerned and the Council shall, before submitting such  regulations or any amendments thereof, as the case may be, to the</p>
                  <p>Central Government for approval, take into consideration the comments  of the State Government received within three months from the  furnishing of the copies as aforesaid.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, before approving such regulations  or any amendments thereof, consult the Indian Council of Agricultural</p>
                  <p>Research.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Committee constituted under section 12 shall from time to  time report to the Council on the efficacy of the regulations and may  recommend to the Council such amendments thereof as it may think fit.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>INDIAN VETERINARY PRACTITIONERS REGISTER</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>INDIAN VETERINARY PRACTITIONERS REGISTER</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-23">
                <num>23.</num>
                <heading>Indian veterinary practitioners register.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-23.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Council  shall, as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, cause to  be maintained in such form and in such manner as may be provided by  regulations a register of veterinary practitioners to be known as the</p>
                    <p>Indian veterinary practitioners register which shall contain the names  of all persons who possess the recognised veterinary qualifications  and who are for the time being enrolled on a State veterinary register  of the State to which this Act extends.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-23.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>It shall be the duty of the Secretary of the Council to keep  the Indian veterinary practitioners register in accordance with the  provisions of this Act and of any orders made by the Council, and from  time to time to revise the register and publish it in the Gazette of</p>
                    <p>India or in such other manner as may be provided by regulations.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-23.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Such register shall be deemed to be a public document within  the meaning of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), and may be  proved by a copy published in the Gazette of India.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-23.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Each State Veterinary Council shall furnish to the Council  six printed copies of the State veterinary register as soon as may be  after the 1st day of April of each year and each State Veterinary</p>
                    <p>Council shall inform the Council without delay of all additions to,</p>
                    <p>and other amendments in, the State veterinary register made from time  to time.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-24">
                <num>24.</num>
                <heading>Registration in the Indian veterinary practitioners register.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>The Secretary of the Council may, on receipt of the report of  registration of a person in a State veterinary register or on an  application made in such form and in such manner, as may be provided  by regulations, by any such person, enter his name in the Indian  veterinary practitioners register:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Secretary is satisfied that the person  concerned possesses a recognised veterinary qualification.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-25">
                <num>25.</num>
                <heading>Issue of certificate of registration.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-25.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person whose  name has been entered in the Indian veterinary practitioners register  shall, on an application made in this behalf in such form and in such  manner and on payment of such fees, not exceeding fifteen rupees, as  may be provided by regulations, be entitled to a certificate of  registration.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-25.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On receipt of an application under sub- section (1), the</p>
                    <p>Council shall grant to the applicant a certificate of registration in  such form as may be provided by regulations:</p>
                    <p>Provided that on the removal of his name from a register, such  certificate shall cease to be valid.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-25.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where it is shown to the satisfaction of the Secretary of the</p>
                    <p>Council that a certificate of registration has been lost or destroyed,</p>
                    <p>the Secretary may, on payment of such fees, not exceeding ten rupees,</p>
                    <p>as may be specified by regulations, issue a duplicate certificate in  such form as may be specified in the regulations.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-26">
                <num>26.</num>
                <heading>Registration of additional qualifications.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-26.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any person  whose name is entered in the Indian veterinary practitioners register  obtains any post- graduate degree or diploma in veterinary science in  addition to his recognised veterinary qualification, he shall, on an  application made in this behalf in such form and in such manner and on  payment of such fees, not exceeding fifteen rupees, as may be provided  by regulations, be entitled to have an entry stating such degree or  diploma made against his name in such register in addition to any  entry previously made.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-26.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The entries in respect of any such person in a State  veterinary register shall be altered in accordance with the  alterations made in the Indian veterinary practitioners register.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Removal of names from the Indian veterinary practitioners  register.- If the name of any person enrolled on a State veterinary  register is removed therefrom in pursuance of any power conferred  under this Act, the Council shall direct the removal of the name of  such person from the Indian veterinary practitioners register.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Person enrolled on Indian veterinary practitioners register  to notify change of place of residence or practice.- Every person  registered in the Indian veterinary practitioners register shall  notify any transfer of the place of his residence or practice to the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Council and the State Veterinary Council within ninety days of such  transfer, failing which his right to participate in the election of  members of the Council or a State Veterinary Council shall be liable  to be forfeited by order of the Central Government either permanently  or for such period as may be specified therein.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>PRIVILEGES OF REGISTERED VETERINARY PRACTITIONERS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PRIVILEGES OF REGISTERED VETERINARY PRACTITIONERS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Privileges of persons, who are enrolled on the Indian  veterinary practitioners register.- Subject to the conditions and  restrictions laid down in this Act, every person whose name is for the  time being borne on the Indian</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>veterinary practitioners register shall be entitled according to his  qualifications to practise as a veterinary practitioner and to recover  in due course of law in respect of such practice any expenses, charges  in respect of medicaments and other appliances or any fees to which he  may be entitled.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Right of persons who are enrolled on the Indian veterinary  practitioners register.- No person, other than a registered veterinary  practitioner, shall--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-30.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>hold office as veterinary physician or surgeon or any  other like office (by whatever name called) in Government or in  any institution maintained by a local or other authority;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>practise veterinary medicine in any State:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that the State Government may, by order, permit a person  holding a diploma or certificate of veterinary supervisor, stockman or  stock assistant (by whatever name called) issued by the Directorate of</p>
                    <p>Animal Husbandry (by whatever name called) of any State or any  veterinary institution in India, to render, under the supervision and  direction of a registered veterinary practitioner, minor veterinary  services.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-30.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.--" Minor veterinary services" means the rendering of  preliminary veterinary aid, like, vaccination, castration, and  dressing of wounds, and such other types of preliminary aid or the  treatment of such ailments as the State Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>be entitled to sign or authenticate a veterinary health  certificate or any other certificate required by any law to be  signed or authenticated by a duly qualified veterinary  practitioner;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>be entitled to give evidence at any inquest or in any  court of law as an expert under section 45 of the Indian Evidence</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Act, 1872, (1 of 1872.) on any matter relating to veterinary  medicine.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>DISCIPLINE</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>DISCIPLINE</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Professional conduct.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-31.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Council may, by regulations,</p>
                    <p>specify standards of professional conduct and etiquette and a code of  ethics for veterinary practitioners.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-31.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Regulations made by the Council under sub- section (1) may  specify which violations thereof shall constitute infamous conduct in  any professional respect, that is to say, professional misconduct, and  such provisions shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained  in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>STATE VETERINARY COUNCILS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>STATE VETERINARY COUNCILS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Establishment and composition of State Veterinary Councils.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-32.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Except where a Joint State Veterinary Council is established in  accordance with an agreement made under section 33, the State</p>
                    <blockList id="section-32.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Government shall establish a State Veterinary Council consisting of  the following members, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-32.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>four members elected from among themselves by veterinary  practitioners registered in the State veterinary register;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-32.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the heads of veterinary institutions, if any, in the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-32.1.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>State, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-32.1.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>three members nominated by the State Government;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-32.1.list4.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the Director of Veterinary Services of the State (by   whatever name called), ex officio;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-32.1.list4.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>one member to be nominated by the State Veterinary</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-32.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Association, if any;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-32.1.list6.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>Registrar of the State Veterinary Council, ex officio.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The names of persons nominated or elected as members shall be  notified by the State Government in the Official Gazette.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person shall not be qualified for nomination or election as  a member of the State Veterinary Council unless he holds a recognised  veterinary qualification.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Inter- State agreements.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-33.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Two or more State Governments may  enter into an agreement to be in force for such period and to be  subject to renewal for further periods, if any, as may be specified in  the agreement to provide--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>for the establishment of a Joint State Veterinary</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-33.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Council for all participating States; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>for the State Veterinary Council of one State to serve  the needs of the other participating States.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-33.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-33.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In addition to such matters as are in this Act specified, an  agreement under this section may--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>provide for the apportionment between the participating</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>States of the expenditure in connection with the State Veterinary</p>
                    <blockList id="section-33.2.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Council or Joint State Veterinary Council;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.2.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>determine which of the participating State Governments  shall exercise the several functions of the State Government  under this Act and the references in this Act to the State</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-33.2.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Government shall be construed accordingly;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.2.list6.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>provide for consultation between the participating State</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-33.2.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>Governments either generally or with reference to particular  matters arising under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.2.list8.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>make such incidental and ancillary provisions not  inconsistent with this Act as may be deemed necessary or  expedient for giving effect to the agreement.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-33.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An agreement under this section shall be published in the</p>
                    <p>Official Gazettes of the participating States.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Compostion of Joint State Veterinary Councils.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-34.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Joint</p>
                    <p>State Veterinary Council shall consist of the following members,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-34.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>two members elected from among themselves by veterinary  practitioners registered in the register of each of the  participating States;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the heads of veterinary institutions, if any, in the  participating States, ex officio;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>two members nominated by each participating State</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-34.1.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list5.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the Director of Veterinary Services of each of the  participating States, by whatever name called, ex officio;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list5.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>one nominee of the State Veterinary Associations, if  any, of each of the participating States;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list5.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>Registrar of the Joint State Veterinary Council, ex  officio.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The names of the persons nominated or elected as members  shall be notified by the State Governments in the Official Gazettes of  the States.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person shall not be qualified for nomination or election as  a member of the Joint State Veterinary Council unless he holds a  recognised veterinary qualification.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Incorporation of State Veterinary Councils.- Every State</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Veterinary Council shall be a body corporate by such name as may be  notified by the State Government in the Official Gazette or, in the  case of a Joint State Veterinary Council, as may be determined in the  agreement, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power to  acquire and hold property, both movable and immovable, and shall by  the said name sue or be sued.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>President.- The President of the State Veterinary Council  shall be elected by the members of that Council from amongst  themselves in such manner as may be prescribed.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Mode of elections.- The election under this Chapter shall be  conducted in the prescribed manner and where any dispute arises  regarding any such election, it shall be referred to the State</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government for its decision.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Terms of office and causal vacancies.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-38.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the  provisions of this section, a member of the State Veterinary Council,</p>
                    <p>other than an ex officio member, shall hold office for a term of three  years from the date of his election or nomination to the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council or until his successor has been duly elected or  nominated, whichever is longer:</p>
                    <p>Provided that a member of the State Veterinary Council nominated  under clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 32 or clause (c) of  sub- section (1) of section 34, shall hold office during the pleasure  of the authority nominating him.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Members of the State Veterinary Council shall be eligible for  re- election or re- nomination, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An elected or nominated member of the State Veterinary</p>
                    <blockList id="section-38.3.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Council shall be deemed to have vacated his office--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-38.3.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if he is absent without excuse, sufficient in the  opinion of the State Veterinary Council, from three consecutive  meetings of the State Veterinary Council;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-38.3.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if he ceases to hold the office from which he has been  nominated;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-38.3.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>in the case of a member whose name is required to be  included in any State veterinary register, if his name is removed  from the register;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-38.3.list2.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>if he has been convicted of an offence involving moral  turpitude and punishable with imprisonment;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-38.3.list2.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-38.3.list2.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a  competent court.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No act done by the State Veterinary Council shall be called  in question on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy, or  defect, in the establishment of, the State Veterinary Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A casual vacancy in the State Veterinary Council shall be  filled by fresh election or nomination, as the case may be, and the  person elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only  for the remainder of the term for which the member whose place he  takes was elected or nominated.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Veterinary Council shall observe such rules of  procedure in regard to transaction of business at its meetings as may  be prescribed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-39">
                <num>39.</num>
                <heading>Resignation.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-39.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The President of the State Veterinary</p>
                    <p>Council may at any time resign his office by notice in writing  addressed to the State Veterinary Council and delivered to the</p>
                    <p>Registrar and the resignation shall take effect from the date on which  it is accepted by that Council or on the expiry of ninety days from  the date of receipt of the resignation by the Registrar, whichever is  earlier.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-39.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A member of the State Veterinary Council may at any time  resign his office by notice in writing addressed to the President of  the State Veterinary Council and every such resignation shall take  effect from the date on which it is accepted by the President or on  the expiry of ninety days from the date of receipt of the resignation  by the President, whichever is earlier.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-40">
                <num>40.</num>
                <heading>Executive and other Committees.- Subject to such conditions  and restrictions as may be prescribed, the State Veterinary Council  may constitute an Executive Committee and other Committees for  exercising any power or discharging any duty of the State Veterinary</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Council or for inquiring into, reporting with respect to, or advising  on, any matter which the State Veterinary Council may refer to them.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-41">
                <num>41.</num>
                <heading>Fees and allowances.- The President and other members of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>State Veterinary Council and the members of the Committees (other than   the members of the State Veterinary Council) shall be paid such fees  and allowances for attending the meetings of the State Veterinary</p>
                    <p>Council and the Committees as may be prescribed.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-42">
                <num>42.</num>
                <heading>Appointment of Registrar and other officers or servants.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-42.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Veterinary Council may, with the previous sanction of the</p>
                    <p>State Government, appoint a Registrar who shall also act as Treasurer  unless the State Veterinary Council appoints any person as Treasurer  and may appoint such other officers and employees as it may deem  necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The terms and conditions of service of the Registrar, and of  the other officers and employees appointed by the State Veterinary</p>
                    <p>Council shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Registrar and other officers and employees of the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council shall be deemed to be public servants within the  meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All orders and decisions and other instruments of the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council shall be authenticated by the signature of the</p>
                    <p>Registrar or any other officer of the State Veterinary Council duly  authorised by it in this behalf.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), for  the first two years from the first constitution of the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council the Registrar of the State Veterinary Council shall  be a person appointed by the State Government, who shall hold office  during the pleasure of the State Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43">
                <num>43.</num>
                <heading>Information to be furnished by State Veterinary Council.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-43.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Veterinary Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its  minutes and of the minutes of the Executive Committee and abstract of  its accounts to the State Government as the State Government may from  time to time require and shall forward to the Council copies of all  material so furnished to the State Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Government may publish in such manner as it thinks  fit any report, copy or abstract furnished to it under this section.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>REGISTRATION</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>REGISTRATION</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-44">
                <num>44.</num>
                <heading>Preparation and maintenance of State veterinary practitioners  register.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-44.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Government shall as soon as may be cause to be  prepared in the manner hereinafter provided a register of veterinary  practitioners to be known as the State veterinary register for the</p>
                    <p>State.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Veterinary Council shall on its establishment  assume the duty of maintaining the State veterinary register in  accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State veterinary register shall contain the names of the  persons possessing the recognised veterinary qualifications.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-44.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The State veterinary register shall include the following  particulars, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-44.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the full name, nationality and residential address of  the registered person;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-44.4.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the date of his admission in the State veterinary  register;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-44.4.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>his qualification for registration and the date on which  he obtained such qualification and authority which conferred it;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-44.4.list1.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>his professional address; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-44.4.list1.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>such further particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-45">
                <num>45.</num>
                <heading>First preparation of register.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-45.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the purpose of first  preparing the State veterinary register, the State Government shall,</p>
                    <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Registration</p>
                    <p>Tribunal consisting of three persons holding recognised veterinary  qualifications and shall also appoint a Registrar who shall act as</p>
                    <p>Secretary of the Tribunal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Government shall, by the same or a like  notification, appoint a date on or before which application for  registration, which shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee, not  exceeding twenty- five rupees, shall be made to the Registration</p>
                    <p>Tribunal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Registration Tribunal shall examine every application  received on or before the appointed date, and, if it is satisfied that  the applicant is qualified for registration under section 46, shall  direct the entry of the name of the applicant on the register.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The register so prepared shall thereafter be published in  such manner as the State Government may direct, and any person  aggrieved by a decision of the Registration Tribunal expressed or  implied in the register as so published may, within sixty days from  the date of such publication, appeal to an authority appointed by the</p>
                    <p>State Government in this behalf by notification in the Official</p>
                    <p>Gazette.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Registrar shall amend the register in accordance with the  decisions of the authority appointed under sub- section (4) and shall  thereupon issue to every person whose name is entered in the register  a certificate of registration in the prescribed form.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Upon the establishment of the State Veterinary Council, the  register shall be given into its custody, and the State Government may  direct that all or any specified part of the application fees for  registration in the first register shall be paid to the credit of the</p>
                    <p>State Veterinary Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-46">
                <num>46.</num>
                <heading>Qualifications for entry on preparation of register.- A person  shall be entitled, on payment of the prescribed fee not exceeding  twenty- five rupees, to have his name entered on the State veterinary  register if he resides in the State and if he holds a recognised  veterinary qualification.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-47">
                <num>47.</num>
                <heading>Scrutiny of applications for registration.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-47.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>After the date  appointed for the receipt of applications for registration under sub-</p>
                    <p>section (2) of section 45, all applications for registration shall be  addressed to the Registrar of the State Veterinary Council and shall  be accompanied by the prescribed fee not exceeding twenty- five rupees.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If upon such application the Registrar of the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council is of the opinion that the applicant is entitled to  have his name entered on the State veterinary register, he shall enter  thereon the name of the applicant:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no person, whose name has under the provisions of  this Act been removed from the State veterinary register of any State,</p>
                    <p>shall be entitled to have his name entered on the State veterinary  register of another State except with the approval of the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council from whose register his name was removed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person whose application for registration is rejected by  the Registrar of the State Veterinary Council may, within three months  from the date of such rejection, appeal to the State Veterinary</p>
                    <p>Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person aggrieved by the decision of the State Veterinary</p>
                    <p>Council under sub- section (3) may, within sixty days from the  communication to him of such decision, appeal to the State Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Upon entry in the State veterinary register of a name under  this section, the Registrar of the State Veterinary Council shall  issue a certificate of registration in the prescribed form.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>Renewal fees.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-48.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, direct that for the retention of a name in  the State veterinary register, there shall be paid in every five years  to the State Veterinary Council, such renewal fee, not exceeding  fifteen rupees, as may be prescribed and where such direction has been  made, such renewal fee shall be due to be paid before the 1st day of</p>
                    <p>April of the year to which it relates.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-48.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where a renewal fee is not paid within the said period, the</p>
                    <p>Registrar of the State Veterinary Council shall remove the name of the  defaulter from the State veterinary register:</p>
                    <p>Provided that a name so removed may be restored to the said  register on payment of renewal fee in such manner as may be  prescribed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-48.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On payment of the renewal fee, the Registrar of the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council shall issue a certificate of renewal and such  certificate shall be proof of renewal of registration.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-49">
                <num>49.</num>
                <heading>Removal from the register.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-49.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-49.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of  this section, the State Veterinary Council may order that the name of  any person shall be removed from the State veterinary register where  it is satisfied after giving that person a reasonable opportunity of  being heard and after such further inquiry, if any, as it may think  fit to make--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-49.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>that his name has been entered in the State veterinary  register by error or on account of mis- representation or  suppression of a material fact, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-49.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>that he has been convicted of an offence involving moral  turpitude and punishable with imprisonment or has been guilty of  any infamous conduct in any professional respect or has violated  the standards of professional conduct and etiquette or the code  of ethics which in the opinion of the State Veterinary Council  renders him unfit to be kept in the said register.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-49.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An order under sub- section (1) may direct that any person  whose name is ordered to be removed from the State veterinary register  shall be ineligible for registration under this Act, either  permanently or for such period of years as may be specified.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-49.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An order under sub- section (1) shall not take effect until  the expiry of three months from the date thereof or until an appeal,</p>
                    <p>if any on such order is finally disposed of, whichever date is later.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-49.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person aggrieved by an order under sub- section (1) may,</p>
                    <p>within sixty days from the communication to him of such order, appeal  to the Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-49.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person aggrieved by the decision of the Council under sub-</p>
                    <p>section (4) may, within sixty days from the communication to him of  such decision, appeal to the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-49.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person whose name has been removed from the register under  this section or under sub- section (2) of section 48 shall forthwith  surrender his certificate of registration and certificate of renewal,</p>
                    <p>if any, to the Registrar of the State Veterinary Council and the name  so removed shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-49.7">
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person whose name has been removed from the State  veterinary register under this section or sub- section (2) of section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>shall not be entitled to have his name registered in the State  veterinary register or in any other State veterinary register, except  with the approval of the State Veterinary Council from whose register  his name has been removed.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-50">
                <num>50.</num>
                <heading>Restoration to State veterinary register.- The State</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Veterinary Council may, at any time for reasons appearing to it  sufficient and subject to approval of the Council, order that upon  payment of the prescribed fee not exceeding twenty- five rupees, the  name of a person removed from a State veterinary register shall be  restored thereto.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Printing of State veterinary register.- As soon as may be  after the 1st day of April each year, the Registrar of the State</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Veterinary Council shall cause to be printed copies of the State  veterinary register as it stood on the said date and such copies shall  be made available to persons applying therefor on payment of the  prescribed charge not exceeding ten rupees and shall be evidence that  on the said date the persons whose names are entered therein were  registered veterinary practitioners.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
              <num>VIII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading>Transfer of registration.- Where a registered veterinary  practitioner of one State is practising veterinary medicine in another</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>State, he may, on payment of prescribed fee which shall not exceed the  renewal fee for registration in such other State, make an application  in the prescribed form to the Council for the transfer of his name  from the State veterinary register of the State where he is registered  to the State veterinary register of the State in which he is  practising veterinary medicine, and on receipt of any such  application, the Council shall, notwithstanding anything contained  elsewhere in this Act, direct that the name of such person be removed  from the first- mentioned State veterinary register and entered in the</p>
                    <p>State veterinary register of the second- mentioned State and the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Councils concerned shall comply with such direction:</p>
                    <p>Provided that such a person shall be required to produce a  certificate to the effect that all dues in respect of his registration  in the former State have been paid:</p>
                    <p>Provided further that where any such application for transfer is  made by a veterinary practitioner against whom any disciplinary  proceeding is pending or where for any other reason it appears to the</p>
                    <p>Council that the application for transfer has not been made bona fide  and the transfer should not be made, the Council may, after giving the  veterinary practitioner a reasonable opportunity of making a  representation in this behalf, reject the application.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-53">
                <num>53.</num>
                <heading>Bar of jurisdiction.- No order refusing to enter a name in a  register or removing a name from a register shall be called in  question in any court.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-54">
                <num>54.</num>
                <heading>Issue of duplicate certificates.- Where it is shown to the  satisfaction of the Registrar of the State Veterinary Council that a  certificate of registration or a certificate of renewal has been lost  or destroyed, the Registrar may, on payment of the prescribed fee, not  exceeding ten rupees, issue a duplicate certificate in the prescribed  form.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-55">
                <num>55.</num>
                <heading>Penalty for falsely claiming to be registered.- If any person  whose name is not for the time being entered in a register falsely  represents that it is so entered or uses in connection with his name  or title any words or letters reasonably calculated to suggest that  his name is so entered, he shall be punishable on first conviction  with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and on any  subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months  or with fine not exceeding one thousand rupees or with both.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-56">
                <num>56.</num>
                <heading>Misuse of titles. If any person,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-56.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>not being a person registered in a register, takes or  uses the description of a veterinary practitioner, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>not possessing a recognised veterinary qualification,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>uses a degree or a diploma or a licence or an abbreviation  indicating or implying such qualification,</p>
                    <p>he shall be punishable on first conviction with fine which may extend  to one thousand rupees, and on any subsequent conviction with  imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine not exceeding  five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-57">
                <num>57.</num>
                <heading>Practice by unregistered persons.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-57.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>After the expiry of one  year from the date appointed under sub- section (2) of section 45, no  person, other than a registered veterinary practitioner or a person  permitted by the State Government under the proviso to clause (b) of  section 30 shall practise veterinary medicine or render minor  veterinary services, as the case may be, in that State.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-57.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any person contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1),</p>
                    <p>he shall be punishable on first conviction with fine which may extend  to one thousand rupees, and on any subsequent conviction with  imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine not exceeding  five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-58">
                <num>58.</num>
                <heading>Failure to surrender certificate of registration.- If any  person whose name has been removed from a register fails without  sufficient cause forthwith to surrender his certificate of  registration or certificate of renewal, or both, he shall be  punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and in  case of a continuing offence with an additional fine which may extend  to ten rupees per day after the first day during which the offence  continues.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-59">
                <num>59.</num>
                <heading>Cognizance of offence.- No court shall take cognizance of any  offence punishable under this Act except upon complaint made by order  of the State Government or State Veterinary Council.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-60">
                <num>60.</num>
                <heading>Bar of suit and other legal proceedings.- No suit or other  legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government or the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>State Government or the Council or a State Veterinary Council in  respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done  in pursuance of this Act, or of any rules, regulations or orders made  thereunder.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-61">
                <num>61.</num>
                <heading>Payment of part of fees to Council.- The State Veterinary</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Council shall, before the end of June in each year, pay to the Council  a sum equivalent to one- fourth of the total fees realised by the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council under this Act during the period of twelve months  ending on the 31st day of March of that year.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-62">
                <num>62.</num>
                <heading>Accounts and audit.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-62.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Council shall maintain  appropriate accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual  statement of accounts including the balance sheet, in accordance with  such general directions as may be issued and in such form as may be  specified by the Central Government in consultation with the</p>
                    <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The accounts of the Council shall be audited annually by the</p>
                    <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any person appointed by  him in this behalf and any expenditure incurred by him or any person  so appointed in connection with such audit shall be payable by the</p>
                    <p>Council to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
                    <p>Council shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
                    <p>India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books of  accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect the office of the Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The accounts of the Council as certified by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India or any person appointed by him in this  behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded  annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-62.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A copy of the accounts of the Council as so certified  together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded  simultaneously to the Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-63">
                <num>63.</num>
                <heading>Appointment of Commission of Inquiry.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-63.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Whenever it appears  to the Central Government that the Council is not complying with any  of the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may appoint a</p>
                    <p>Commission of Inquiry consisting of three persons, two of whom shall  be appointed by the Central Government, one being the Judge of a High</p>
                    <p>Court and one by the Council and refer to it the matter on which the  inquiry is to be made.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-63.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Commission shall proceed to inquire in a summary manner  and report to the Central Government on the matters referred to it  together with such remedies, if any, as the Commission may like to  recommend.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-63.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may accept the report or remit the  same to the Commission for modification or reconsideration.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-63.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>After the report is finally accepted, the Central Government  may order the Council to adopt the remedies so recommended within such  time as may be specified in the order and if the Council fails to  comply within the time so specified, the Central Government may pass  such order or take such action as may be necessary to give effect to  the recommendations of the Commission.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-63.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Whenever it appears to the State Government that the State</p>
                    <p>Veterinary Council is not complying with any of the provisions of this</p>
                    <p>Act, the State Government may likewise appoint a similar Commission of  inquiry in respect of the State Veterinary Council to make inquiry in  like manner and pass such orders or take such action as specified in  sub- sections (3) and (4).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-64">
                <num>64.</num>
                <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-64.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central</p>
                    <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to  carry out the purposes of Chapters II, III, IV and V.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-64.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule,</p>
                    <p>or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall,</p>
                    <p>thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                    <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-65">
                <num>65.</num>
                <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-65.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The State</p>
                    <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to  carry out the purposes of Chapters VI, VII and VIII.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-65.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the manner in which the President of the State</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-65.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Veterinary Council shall be elected under section 36;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the manner in which election under Chapter VI shall be  conducted;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the procedure to be observed by the State Veterinary</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-65.2.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Council at its meetings under sub- section (6) of section 38;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list5.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the conditions and restrictions with respect to the  constitution of Executive Committee and other Committees under  section 40;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list5.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>the fees and allowances for attending the meetings of  the State Veterinary Council and the Committees under section 41;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list5.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>the terms and conditions of appointment of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Registrar, other officers and employees of the State Veterinary</p>
                    <blockList id="section-65.2.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>Council under sub- section (2) of section 42;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list8.g">
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <p>the particulars to be included in the State veterinary  register under clause (e) of sub- section (4) of section 44;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.2.list8.h">
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <p>the fee which shall be accompanied by an application for  registration under sub- section (2) of section 45 and sub- section</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-65.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>of section 47;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the form of certificate of registration under sub-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-65.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>section (5) of section 45 and sub- section (5) of section 47;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list3.j">
                        <num>(j)</num>
                        <p>the fee payable under section 46, section 50, section 52  and section 54;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list3.k">
                        <num>(k)</num>
                        <p>the renewal fee under sub- section (1) of section 48;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list3.l">
                        <num>(l)</num>
                        <p>the manner of payment of renewal fee under the proviso  to sub- section (2) of section 48;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list3.m">
                        <num>(m)</num>
                        <p>the charge for supplying printed copies of the State  veterinary register under section 51;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list3.n">
                        <num>(n)</num>
                        <p>the form of duplicate certificate under section 54;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-65.1.list3.o">
                        <num>(o)</num>
                        <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed  under Chapters VI, VII and VIII.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-65.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature  where it consists of two Houses, or, where such Legislature consists  of one House, before that House.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-66">
                <num>66.</num>
                <heading>Power to make regulations.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-66.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Council may, with the  previous approval of the Central Government, make regulations, not  inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made under  section 64, to carry out the purposes of Chapters II, III, IV and V.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-66.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-66.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the manner in which the President and Vice- President  shall be elected under sub- section (4) of section 3;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the procedure to be observed respectively by the Council  and the Committee at their meeting under sub- section (6) of  section 9 and sub- section (2) of section 12;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the terms and conditions of appointment of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Secretary, other officers and employees of the Council under sub-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-66.2.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 11;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list4.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the fees and allowances for attending the meetings of  the Council and the Committees under section 13;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list4.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>the form and manner in which the Indian veterinary  practitioners register shall be maintained under sub- section (1)</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-66.2.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>of section 23;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list6.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>the manner of keeping the Indian veterinary  practitioners register under sub- section (2) of section 23;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list6.g">
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <p>the form and manner in which an application may be made  under section 24;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list6.h">
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <p>the form of application and the fee payable under sub-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-66.2.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>section (1) of section 25;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list8.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the form of certificate of registration under sub-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-66.2.list10">
                      <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 25;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list10.j">
                        <num>(j)</num>
                        <p>the fee payable under sub- section (3) of section 25;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list10.k">
                        <num>(k)</num>
                        <p>the form of duplicate certificate under sub- section (3)</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-66.2.list12">
                      <listIntroduction>of section 25;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list12.l">
                        <num>(l)</num>
                        <p>the form and manner in which an application may be made  and the fee payable under sub- section (1) of section 26;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list12.m">
                        <num>(m)</num>
                        <p>the standards of professional conduct and etiquette and  code of ethics to be observed by veterinary practitioners under  sub- section (1) of section 31;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-66.2.list12.n">
                        <num>(n)</num>
                        <p>any other matter for which under this Act provision may  be made by regulations.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-66.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every regulation shall, as soon as may be after it is made by  the Council, be forwarded to the Central Government and that</p>
                    <p>Government shall cause a copy of the same to be laid before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the  regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be  made, the regulation shall, thereafter, have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
                    <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-67">
                <num>67.</num>
                <heading>Repeal and saving.- As from the commencement of this Act in  any State, every other Act relating to any matter contained in this</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Act and in force in that State shall, to the extent to which that Act  or any provision contained therein corresponds, or is repugnant, to  this Act or any provision contained in this Act, stand repealed and  the provisions of section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1897">
                <num>1897.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1897.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>), shall apply to such repeal as if such other Act were a Central</p>
                    <p>Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
