<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/30"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Vice- President' S Pension Act, 1997"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/30/eng@1997-05-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/30/eng@1997-05-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1997-05-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/30/eng@1997-05-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/30/eng@1997-05-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Vice- President' S Pension Act, 1997</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 30 OF 1997</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 28th May, 1997.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the payment of pension and other facilities to  retiring Vice- Presidents.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- eighth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Vice- President' s Pension Act, 1997.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Pension to retiring Vice- Presidents.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to every person who ceases to hold officer as</p>
            <p>Vice- President, either by the expiration of his term of officer or by  resignation of his office, a pension of six thousand two hundred and  fifty rupees per month, for the remainder of his life:</p>
            <p>Provided that such person shall not be entitled to receive any pension  during the period he holds the office of the Prime Minister, a</p>
            <p>Minister or any other office or becomes a Member of Parliament and is  in receipt of salary and allowances which are defrayed out of the</p>
            <p>Consolidated fund of In dia or the Consolidated Fund of a State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, every such  person shall, for the remainder of his life, be entitled-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to the use of such furnished residence (including its   maintenance), without payment of rent, as a Union Deputy Minister is  entitled to during his tenure of office under the provisions of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Salaries and allowances of Ministers Act, 1952 (58 of 1952);</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to the use of similar telep hone facilities at his residence, as a  member of Parliament is entitled to under the provisions of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954 (30   of 1954);</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to secretarial staff; and office expense not exceeding rupees six  thousand per annum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to the same facilities for himself as respects medical attendance  and treatment and on the same conditions as a retired president is  entitled to under the provisions of the President' s Emoluments and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Pension Act, 1951 (30 of 1951);</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list7.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to the same facilities for his spouse and minor children as  respects medical attendance and treatment and on the same conditions  as the spouse of a retired President is entitled to under the  provisions of the President' s Emoluments and Pensions Act, 1951 (30 of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1951">
        <num>1951.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1951.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1951.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>); and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1951.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to travel anywhere in India, accompanied by his spouse, the  executive class by air, andthe highest class by rail.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Medical facilities to the family of deceased Vice- President.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, the spouse of a  person who dies while holding the office of Vice- Presidentshall, for  the remainder of life, be entitled to medical attendance and  treatment, free of charge.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Pension to be charged on the Consolidated Fund of India.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any sum payable under this Act shall be charged on the Consolidated</p>
            <p>Fund of India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazettee, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rules made by the Central Government under this Act, shall  be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
            <p>Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
            <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses  agree t hat the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter  have effect only in such modified from or be of no effect, as the case  may be; so, however, t hat any such modification or annulment shall  be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
