<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1961/05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1961/05"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Orissa Prevention Of Cow Slaughter Act, 1960"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1961/05/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1961/05/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1961/05/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1961/05/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Orissa Prevention Of Cow Slaughter Act, 1960</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[28th February 1961]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[ACT NO.5 of 1961]</p>
        <p>An act to prohibit and prevent the slaughter of cow and its progeny in the state of Orissa</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Orissa in the Eleventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Orissa Prevention of Cow Slaughter Act, 1960</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Orissa.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything-repugnant in the subject or context, -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"competent authority" means the person or persons appointed in this behalf by the Government by notification to exercise the powers and perform the functions of a competent authority under this Act or the rules made thereunder for such area or areas and for such period as may be specified in .the notification ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Cow" includes heifer or calf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government of Orissa;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Prescribed" means prescribed by- rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"Slaughter" means killing by any method whatsoever and includes maiming and inflicting of physical injury which in the ordinary course will cause death; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Uneconomic cow" includes an infirm cow or a cow which is permanently disabled or diseased.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of cow slaughters</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force or any usage or custom to the contrary and except as hereinafter provided, no person shall, at any place within the State, slaughter or cause to be slaughtered, or offer or cause to be offered for slaughter—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A cow, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>A bull or bullock, unless he has obtained a certificate in writing, from the competent authority of the area in which such bull or bullock is to be slaughtered 'certifying that it is fit for slaughter.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No bull or bullock, in respect of which a certificate has been issued under clause (b) of sub-section (I) shall be slaughtered at, any place other than the place indicated in the certificate or within thirty days of the date of issue of the certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A certificate under clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall be issued by the competent authority, only after he has, for reasons to be recorded in writing, certified that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The bull or bullock is over the age or fourteen years; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>In the case of a bull, it has become permanently unfit and unserviceable for the purpose of breeding and, in the case of a bullock, it has become permanently unfit and unserviceable for the purposes of draught and any kind of agricultural operation:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the permanent unfitness or unserviceability has not been caused deliberately.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The competent authority shall, before issuing the certificate under sub-section (3) or refusing to issue the same, record its order in writing. Any person aggrieved by the order of the competent authority, under this section may, within fifteen days of the date of the order, appeal against it to the Government or to such other authority as may be prescribed, who may pass such orders thereon as they may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may at any time, for the purposes of satisfying themselves as to the legality or propriety of the action taken under this section, call for and examine the record of any case and. may pass' such orders thereon as they may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions herein contained, any action taken under this section, shall be final and conclusive and shall not be called in question</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Section 3 not to apply to diseased, under experimentation cows, bulls or bullocks</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in Section 3 shall apply to the slaughter of a cow, bull or bullock –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>which is suffering from any contagious infectious disease notified as such by Government ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>which is subjected to experimentation in the interest of medical and public health research ;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>where the slaughtering is done in accordance with the conditions and circumstances to be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a cow, bull or bullock is slaughtered for the reasons stated in clause (a) of sub-section (1) the person who slaughters or causes to be slaughtered such cow, bull or bullock shall within twenty-four hours of the slaughter, lodge information of the same at the nearest police-station or before such officer or authority as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The carcase of the cow bull or bullock slaughtered under clause (a) of sub-section (1) shall be buried or disposed of in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of institution</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There may be established by the Government or by any Local Authority, wherever so directed by the Government. Institutions as may be necessary for taking care of uneconomic cows.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Levy of charges or fees</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government or a Local Authority, as the case may be, may levy such charges or fees as may be prescribed for keeping uneconomic cows in the institutions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner of the uneconomic cow shall be liable to pay the said charges or fees in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Dues payable under this section shall without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of section 3 shall be guilty of an offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever fails to lodge information in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 4 shall be guilty of an offence punishable with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend, to two hundred rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in any trial for an offence punishable under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) the accused pleads that the slaughtered cow, bull or bullock belonged to the class specified in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 4, the burden of proving the said fact shall be on the accused.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, an offence punishable under sub-section (1) of section 7 shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the conditions and the circumstances under which tows, bulls and bullocks are to be slaughtered under sub-section (1) of section 4</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>form of certificate, and the procedure for disposal of the applications and appeals under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which diseases shall be notified under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the information shall be lodged under sub-section (2) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the matters relating to the establishment, maintenance, management, supervision and control of institutions referred to in section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the duties of any officer or authority having jurisdiction under this Act, the procedure to be followed by such officer or authority; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
