<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1954/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1954/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Assam Prohibition Of Smoking In Passenger Vehicles Act, 1954"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1954/17/eng@2016-12-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1954/17/eng@2016-12-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1954/17/eng@2016-12-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1954/17/eng@2016-12-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Assam Prohibition Of Smoking In Passenger Vehicles Act, 1954</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 17 of 1954]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[12th May, 1954]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An</p>
      <p>Act to prohibit smoking in passenger vehicles.</p>
      <p>Whereas it is expedient in the public interest to prohibit smoking in passenger vehicles;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Assam Prohibition of Smoking in Passenger Vehicles, Act 1954.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of Assam.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act "passenger vehicle" means a motor vehicle having seating capacity for more than six persons, excluding the driver, which carries passengers for hire or reward at separate fares paid by or for individual passengers, either for the whole or for a stage of a journey.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for smoking in passenger vehicles</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever smokes in a passenger vehicle while such vehicle is carrying passengers shall be punishable with fine which for a first offence may extend to twenty rupees and for a second or subsequent offence to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The conductor of a passenger vehicle in whose presence a person commits an offence punishable under section 3, may request such person to desist from smoking, and if such person fails to comply with the request he may stop the vehicle and call for a police officer not below the rank of an Assistant Sub-Inspector of Police; and such police officer may arrest such person without warrant, if, when asked by the police officer to give his name and address, such person-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>refuses to give his name and address, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>gives a name or address which the police officer suspects to be false and such person refuses to accompany the police officer to a police station on being required to do so by the police officer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or proceeding shall lie against a conductor of a passenger vehicle or a police officer for, anything done or any arrest made, in good faith under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Warning to be painted or affixed</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The proprietor of every passenger vehicle shall cause to be painted or affixed in one or more conspicuous positions in such vehicle a warning that any person smoking while such vehicle is carrying passengers is liable under the law to arrest without warrant and to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the proprietor of a passenger vehicle fails to comply with the provisions of sub-section (1), within thirty days of the commencement of this Act, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to twenty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
