<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Departmental Inquiries (Enforcement Of Attendance Of Witnesses And Production Of Documents) Act, 1972"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/18/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/18/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/18/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/18/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Departmental Inquiries (Enforcement Of Attendance Of Witnesses And Production Of Documents) Act, 1972</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Departmental Inquiries (Enforce­ment of Attendance of Witnesses arid Production of Documents) Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
            <p>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES AND PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, 1972</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Departmental inquiries to which the Act shall apply.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions of Ibis Act shall apply to every departmental in­quiry made in relation to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>persons appointed to public services or posts in connection with the affairs of the Union;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>persons who, having been appointed to any public service or post in connection with the affairs of the Union, are in service or pay of,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any local authority in any Union territory,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any corporation established by or under a Central Act and owned or controlled by the Central Government,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any Government company within the meaning of sec­tion 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) in which not less than fifty-one per cent, of the paid-up share ‘capital is held by the Central Government or any company which is a subsidiary of such Gov­ernment company,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>any society registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1960), which is subject to the control of the Central Government</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES AND PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, 1972</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“departmental inquiry” means an inquiry held under and in accordance with—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any law made by Parliament or, any rule made there­under, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any rule made under the proviso to article 309, or continued under Article 313, of the Constitution of India,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>into any allegation of lack of integrity against any person to whom this Act applies;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“inquiring authority” means an officer or, authority appointed by the Central Government or by any officer or authority .subordinate to that Government to hold a departmental inquiry and includes any officer or authority who is empowered by or under any law or rule for the time being in force .to hold such inquiry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“lack of integrity” includes bribery or corruption.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES AND PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, 1972</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to authorise the exercise of powers specified in section 5.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Central Government is of opinion that for the purposes of any departmental inquiry it is necessary to summon as witnesses, or call for any document from, any class or category of persons, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, authorise the inquiring authority to exercise the power specified in section 5 in relation to any person with­in such class or category and thereupon the inquiring authority may exercise such power at any stage of the departmental inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The power conferred on the Central Government by sub-section (1) may also be exercised by such authority, not being an authority in­ferior to the appointing authority in relation to the person against whom the departmental inquiry is being held, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
            <p>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES AND PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, 1972</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of authorised inquiring authority to enforce attendance of witnesses and production of documents.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every inquiring authority authorised under section 4 (here­after referred to as the “authorised inquiring authority”) shall have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Pro­cedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any wit-end examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document or other material which is producible as evidence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the requisitioning of any public record from any court or office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the autho­rised inquiring authority shall not compel the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India, any subsidiary bank as defined in clause (k) of sec­tion 2 of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), or any corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Com­panies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to produce any books of account or other documents which the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India, the subsidiary bank or the corresponding new bank claims to be of a confidential nature, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to make any such books or documents a part of the record of the proceedings of the departmental inquiry, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to give inspection of any such books or documents, if produc­ed, to any party before it or to any other person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every process issued by an authorised inquiring authority for the attendance of any witness or for the production of any document shall be served and executed through the District Judge within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the witness or other person, on whom the process is to be served or executed, voluntarily resides or carries on business or personally works for gain, and, for the purpose of taking any action for the disobedience of any such process, every such process shall be deemed to be a process issued by the District Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every authorised inquiring authority making any departmental inquiry under this Act shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of sections 480 and 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).</p>
            <p>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES AND PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, 1972</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Territorial limits in which powers specified in section 5 may be exercised.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of exercising the powers specified in section 5, the territorial jurisdiction of every authorised inquiring authority shall extend to the limits of the territory to which this Act extends.</p>
            <p>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES AND PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, 1972</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each ‘House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that the modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything pre­viously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
