<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1912/03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1912/03"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bombay Race Courses Licensing Act, 1912"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1912/03/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1912/03/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1912/03/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1912/03/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bombay Race Courses Licensing Act, 1912</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[24th October 1974]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. III of 1912</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the licensing of race-courses in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS, it is expedient to make provision for the regulation, control and management of horse racing and all matters directly or indirectly connected therewith in the State of Maharashtra:</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short Title and extent-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Bombay Race-courses Licensing Act, 1912.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra. The rest of the Act extends only to such areas as the State Government may by notification in the Official Gazette direct:</p>
            <p>Provided that, on the commencement of the Bombay Race-courses Licensing and the Bombay Betting Tax Acts (Extension and Amendment) Act, 1958, the rest of the Act shall extend to those areas in which the Hyderabad Horse Racing and Betting Tax Regulation. 1358F., was in force immediately before such commencement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"horse-race" means any race in which any horse, mare or gelding runs or is made to run in connection with any other horse, mare or gelding for any prize of what nature or kind soever, or for any bet or wager made or to be made in respect of any such horse, mare or gelding or the riders thereof, and at which more than twenty persons shall be present;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"race-course" means any ground on which a horse race can be held.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition against horse-racing on unlicence race-courses</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No horse-race shall be held save on a race-course for which a licence for horse racing granted in accordance with the provisions of this Act is in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The terms of such licence shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application for License for Horse Racing</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner, lessee or occupier of any race-course may apply to the State Government for a licence for horse-racing on such race-course.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may withhold such licence or grant it subject to such conditions and for such period as it may think fit. Such conditions may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the payment of a licence fee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the amount of stakes which may be allotted for different kinds of horses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the measures to be taken for the training of persons to become jockeys; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>such other matters, whether directly or indirectly connected with horse racing for, which, in the opinion of the State Government, it is necessary of expedient to make provision in the licence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by such licence authorise the licence to grant, subject to such conditions as shall be specified by the State Government in such licence, a licence or permit to any book-maker to carryon his business or vocation or to act as a book-maker or turf commission agent in respect of horse races held on a racecourse, being a race-course which is situated in this State or outside it. The licence may be granted for such period not exceeding the period of the licence granted to the licensee as the licensee may think fit; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may at any time cancel any licence granted under this section in the event of any breach of the conditions subject to which it was granted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for taking part in horse race on unlicensed race course-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever takes part in any horse-race on any race course for which a licence granted in accordance with the provisions of section 4 is not in force shall be punishable with fine which may amount to two hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for owner. etc., allowing racing in unlicensed place-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any horse-race is held on any race-course for which a licence granted in accordance with the provisions of section 4 is not in force any person being the owner lessee or occupier of such race-course shall be punishable with fine which may amount to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravening conditions of license-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person to whom a licence has been granted in accordance with the provisions of section 4 contravenes any of the conditions subject to which such licence was granted, such person shall be punishable with fine which may amount to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person to whom a licence or permit has been granted by a licensee in pursuance of the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 4 contravenes any of the conditions subject to which such licence or permit was granted, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences under this Act-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or of a Magistrate of the First Class shall try an offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may from time to time by general or particular order published in the Official Gazette exempt any horse-race from the operation of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
