<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Burmah Shell (Acquisition Of Undertakings In India) Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1976-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Burmah Shell (Acquisition Of Undertakings In India) Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 2 OF 1976</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th January, 1976.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the right, title  and interest of the Burmah Shell Oil Storage and Distributing Company  of India Limited in relation to its undertakings in India with a view  to ensuring coordinated distribution and utilisation of petroleum  products distributed and marketed in India by the said company and for  matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Burmah Shell</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(Acquisition of Undertakings in India) Act, 1976.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Burmah Shell" means the Burmah Shell Oil Storage and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Distributing Company of India Limited, a foreign com-</p>
              <p>pany within the meaning of section 591 of the Companies</p>
              <p>Act, 1956, (1 of 1956.) incorporated in England in 1928  and having its registered office at Burmah House,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Pipers Way, Swindon, Wiltshire, England;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Government company" means a Government company as  defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956; (1   of 1956.)</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION OF THE UNDERTAKINGS IN INDIA OF BURMAH SHELL</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION OF THE UNDERTAKINGS IN INDIA OF BURMAH SHELL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Transfer and vesting in the Central Government of the under  takings of Burmah Shell in India. On the appointed day, the right,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>title and interest of Burmah Shell, in relation to its undertakings in</p>
              <p>India, shall stand transferred to, and shall vest in, the Central</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The undertaking referred to in  section 3 shall be deemed, save as otherwise provided in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, to include all assets, rights, powers, authorities and privileges  and all property, movable and immovable, cash balances, reserve funds,</p>
              <p>book- debts, investments and all other rights and interests in, or  arising out of, such property as were, immediately before the  appointed day, in the ownership, possession, power or control of</p>
              <p>Burmah Shell, in relation to its undertakings in India, and all books  of account, registers, records and all other documents of whatever  nature relating thereto and shall also be deemed to include all  borrowings, liabilities (including the liability for the payment of  any pension and other pensionary benefits to the persons employed in   relation to its undertakings in India) and obligations of whatever  kind then subsisting of Burmah Shell in relation to its undertakings  in India:</p>
              <p>Provided that remittance outside India of any money for the  payment of pension or other pensionary benefits shall be subject to  the rules and regulations for the time being in force in relation to  such remittance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The profits earned by Burmah Shell in relation to its  undertaking in India from the 1st day of January, 1975, shall be  payable to the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The undertakings referred to in sub- section (1) shall not  include the following, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any trade mark, and any right of Burmah Shell to use any  trade mark in India, as specified in the First</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-">
      <doc name="">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/2/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/2"/>
              <FRBRalias value=";"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/2/eng@1976-01-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="">
            <paragraph id=".paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id=".paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>all patents and designs registered in India in the name  of Burmah Shell;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the item described as" Loans in United Kingdom from  shareholders and or their associated companies" in the  accounts of Burmah Shell, filed pursuant to section 594  of the Companies Act, 1956, (1 of 1956.) as at 31st day  of December, 1974.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id=".4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise expressly provided by this Act, all deeds,</p>
                <p>bonds, agreements, powers of attorney, grants of legal representation  and other instruments of whatever nature in relation to the  undertakings of Burmah Shell in India, subsisting or having effect  immediately before the appointed day, and to which Burmah Shell is a  party or which are in favour of Burmah Shell shall be of as full force  and effect against or in favour of the Central Government and may be  enforced or acted upon as fully and effectually as if in the place of</p>
                <p>Burmah Shell the Central Government had been a party thereto or as if  they had been issued in favour of the Central Government.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id=".5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other  proceeding of whatever nature, in relation to the undertakings of</p>
                <p>Burmah Shell in India, which have been transferred to and vested in  the Central Government under section 3, is pending by or against</p>
                <p>Burmah Shell, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be, in any  way, prejudicially affected by reason of the transfer of the  undertakings of Burmah Shell or of anything contained in this Act, but  the suit, appeal or other proceedings may be continued, prosecuted and  enforced by or against the Central Government, or, where the  undertaking is directed under section 7 to vest in any Government  company, by or against the Government company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Central Government to be lessor or tenant under certain  circumstances.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any property is held in India by Burmah Shell  under any lease or under any right of tenancy, the Central Government  shall, on and from the appointed day, be deemed to have</p>
                  <p>become the lessee or tenant, as the case may be, in respect of such  property as if the lease or tenancy in relation to such property had  been granted to the Central Government, and thereupon all the rights  under such lease or tenancy shall be deemed to have been transferred  to, and vested in, the Central Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On the expiry of the term of any lease or tenancy referred to  in sub- section (1), such lease or tenancy shall, if so desired by the</p>
                  <p>Central Government, be renewed on the same terms and conditions on  which the lease or tenancy was held by Burmah Shell immediately before  the appointed day.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Removal of doubts.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby  declared that the provisions of sections 3, 4 and 5 shall apply to the  extent to which any property appertains to the business carried on by</p>
                  <p>Burmah Shell in India; and to the rights and powers acquired, and to  debts, liabilities and obligations incurred, and to contracts,</p>
                  <p>agreements and other instruments made, by Burmah Shell in India, and  to legal proceedings relating to those matters pending in any court or  tribunal in India.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any question arises as to whether any property appertains,</p>
                  <p>on the appointed day, to any business of Burmah Shell in India, or  whether any rights, powers, debts, liabilities or obligations were  acquired or incurred or any contract, agreement or other instrument  was made by Burmah Shell for the purposes of its business in India, or  whether any documents relate to those purposes, the question shall be  referred to the Central Government which shall, after giving an  opportunity of being heard to the persons interested in the matter,</p>
                  <p>decide it in such manner as it may think fit.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Power of Central Government to direct vesting of the  undertakings of the Burmah Shell in a Government company.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 3, 4 and 5, the Central</p>
                  <p>Government may, if it is satisfied that a Government company is  willing to comply, or has complied, with such terms and conditions as  that Government may think fit to impose, direct by notification, that  the right, title and interest and the liabilities of Burmah Shell in  relation to any of its undertakings in India shall, instead of  continuing to vest in the Central Government, vest in the Government  company either on the date of the notification or on such earlier or  later date (not being a date earlier than the appointed day) as may be  specified in the notification.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the right, title and interest and the liabilities of</p>
                  <p>Burmah Shell in relation to its undertakings in India vest in a</p>
                  <p>Government company under sub- section (1), the Government company  shall, on and from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have become  the owner, tenant or lessee, as the case may be, in relation to such  undertakings, and all the rights and liabilities of the Central</p>
                  <p>Government in relation to such undertakings shall, on and from the  date of such vesting, be deemed to have become the rights and  liabilities, respectively, of the Government company.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 5 shall apply to  a lease or tenancy, which vests in a Government company, as they apply  to a lease or tenancy vested in the Central Government, and reference  therein to the" Central Government" shall be construed as a reference  to the Government company.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Payment of amount.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the transfer and vesting in the</p>
                  <p>Central Government, under sections 3 and 4, of the right, title and  interest of Burmah Shell in relation to its undertakings in India, and  for the vesting in the Central Government, under section 5, of the  rights specified therein, there shall be paid by the Central</p>
                  <p>Government to Burmah Shell an amount of rupees twenty- seven crores and  seventy- five lakhs in such instalments and in such manner as are  specified in the Second Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Taxes, if any, payable in India by Burmah Shell by reason of  the payment of the amount specified in sub- section (1) shall be paid  by the Central Government to Burmah Shell in Indian currency, and any  amount received by Burmah Shell by way of refund of taxes so paid  shall be paid back by Burmah Shell to the Central Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount specified in sub- section (1) shall carry interest,</p>
                  <p>free of income- tax at the rate of eight per cent. per annum from the</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1st">
              <num>1st.</num>
              <heading>day of January, 1976, till the date of payment in the manner  specified in the Second Schedule.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-1st.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF BURMAH SHELL</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF BURMAH SHELL</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-9">
                <num>9.</num>
                <heading>Transfer of service of existing Employees of Burmah Shell.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-9.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every whole- time officer or other employee of Burmah Shell who was,</p>
                    <p>immediately before the appointed day, employed by Burmah Shell in  connection with its undertakings in India, and</p>
                    <p>every whole- time officer or other employee of Burmah Shell who was,</p>
                    <p>immediately before the appointed day, temporarily holding any  assignment outside India, shall, on the appointed day, become an  officer or other employee, as the case may be, of the Central</p>
                    <p>Government or the Government company in which the right, title and  interest of Burmah Shell in relation to its undertakings in India have  vested under this Act and shall hold office or service under the</p>
                    <p>Central Government or the Government company, as the case may be, on  the same terms and conditions and with the same rights to pension,</p>
                    <p>gratuity and other matters as would have been admissible to him if  there had been no such vesting and shall continue to do so unless and  until his employment under the Central Government or the Government  company is duly terminated or until his remuneration and conditions of  service are duly altered by the Central Government or the Government  company.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-9.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether any person was a whole-</p>
                    <p>time officer or other employee of Burmah Shell, or as to whether any  officer or other employee was employed wholly or mainly in connection  with the undertakings of Burmah Shell, in India immediately before the  appointed day, or whether any whole- time officer or other employee of</p>
                    <p>Burmah Shell was temporarily holding any assignment outside India, the  question shall be referred, within a period of two years from the  appointed day and not thereafter, to the Central Government which  shall, after giving an opportunity of being heard to the person  concerned in the matter, decide it in such manner as it thinks fit and  such decision shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-9.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
                    <p>Act, 1947, (14 of 1947.) the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972, (39 of</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1972">
                <num>1972.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1972.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>) or in any other law for the time being in force, the transfer  of the services of any officer or other employee under sub- section (1)</p>
                    <p>shall not entitle any such officer or other employee to any  compensation or gratuity under those Acts or such other law, and no  such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other  authority.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-10">
                <num>10.</num>
                <heading>Provident superannuation, welfare fund, etc.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-10.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Where a  provident, superannuation, welfare or other fund has been established  by Burmah Shell for the benefit of the persons employed by it in  connection with its undertakings in India, the moneys relatable to the  employees--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-10.1.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>whose services are transferred by or under this Act to  the Central Government or the Government company; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-10.1.list1.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>who are in receipt of pension or other pensionary  benefits immediately before the appointed day,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall, out of the moneys standing, on that day, to the credit of such  provident, superannuation, welfare or other fund stand transferred to,</p>
                    <p>and vested in, the Central Government or the Government company, as  the case may be, free from any trust that may have been constituted by</p>
                    <p>Burmah Shell in respect thereof.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-10.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The moneys which stand transferred, under sub- section (1), to  the Central Government or the Government company shall be dealt with  by the Central Government or that company, as the case may be, in such  manner as may be prescribed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-10.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Government company in which the undertakings of Burmah</p>
                    <p>Shell in India are directed to be vested shall, as soon as may be  after the date of vesting, constitute, in respect of the moneys and  other assets which are transferred to, and vested in, it under this  section, one or more trusts having objects as similar to the objects  of the existing trusts as in the circumstances may be practicable, so,</p>
                    <p>however, that the rights and interests of the beneficiaries of the  trust referred to in sub- section (1) are not, in any way, prejudiced  or diminished.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-10.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where all the moneys and other assets belonging to an  existing trust are transferred to and vested in the Central Government  or the Government company under this section, the trustees of such  trust shall, as from the date of such vesting, stand discharged from  the trust except as respects things done or omitted to be done before  the date of such vesting.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-11">
                <num>11.</num>
                <heading>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act shall  have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained  in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument  having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or in any  decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-12">
                <num>12.</num>
                <heading>Duty to deliver possession of properties, etc.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-12.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where any  property, appertaining to any undertaking of Burmah Shell in India has  been transferred to, and vested in, the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-12.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Central Government or the Government company under this Act--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>every person in whose possession, custody or control any  such property may be, shall, on a demand by the Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-12.1.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Government or the Government company, as the case may  be, deliver the property to the Central Government or  the Government company, as the case may be, forthwith;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12.1.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any person who, immediately before such vesting has in  his possession, custody or control any books, documents  or other papers relating to the undertakings of Burmah</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Shell in India, shall be liable to account for the said  books, documents and papers to the Central Government  or the Government company, as the case may be, and  shall deliver them up to the Central Government or that  company or to such person as the Central Government or  that company may authorise in this behalf.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-12.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Without prejudice to the other provisions contained in this  section, it shall be lawful for the Central Government or the</p>
                    <p>Government company to take all necessary steps for taking possession  of all properties which have been transferred to, and vested in, it  under this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-13">
                <num>13.</num>
                <heading>Contracts to continue unless terminated by Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-13.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every contract entered into by Burmah Shell for any  service, sale or supply in India, and in force immediately before the  appointed day, shall, unless terminated under sub- section (2) within  one year from the appointed day, continue to be of full force and  effect against or in favour of the Central Government or the</p>
                    <p>Government company in which the undertakings of Burmah Shell in India  have vested under this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, if it is satisfied that any  contract referred to in sub- section (1) is unduly onerous or has been  entered into in bad faith or is detrimental to the interests of that</p>
                    <p>Government or the Government company, by order in writing, either  terminate such contract or make such alterations or modifications  therein as it may think fit:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Central Government shall not terminate any  contract or make any alteration or modification therein except after  giving to the parties to the contract, a reasonable opportunity of</p>
                    <p>being heard and except after recording, in writing, its reasons for  such termination, alteration or modification, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-14">
                <num>14.</num>
                <heading>Penalties. Any person who,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>having in his possession, custody or control any  property forming part of any undertaking of Burmah</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Shell in India wrongfully withholds such property from  the Central Government or the Government company; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully obtains possession of or retains any property  forming part of any undertaking of Burmah Shell in</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>India; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Government or the Government company or any person  specified by the Central Government or that company,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>any books, documents or other papers relating to any  undertaking of Burmah shell in India which may be in  his possession, custody or control; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list7.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>fails to deliver to the Central Government or the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Government company, any assets, books of account,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list10">
                      <listIntroduction>registers or other documents in his possession, custody  or control relating to any undertaking of Burmah Shell  in India; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list10.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully removes or destroys any property pertaining  to any undertaking of Burmah Shell in India; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list10.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully uses any property forming part of the  undertakings of Burmah Shell in India,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-15">
                <num>15.</num>
                <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-15.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
                    <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-15.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer  of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer] shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-15.2.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-15.2.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-15.2.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>" director" in relation to a firm, means a partner in the  firm.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-16">
                <num>16.</num>
                <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
                    <p>Government or the Government company or any of its officers or other  employees for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done under this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-17">
                <num>17.</num>
                <heading>Cognizance of offences. Notwithstanding anything contained in  the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974.), no court shall take  cognizance of any offence against this Act except on a complaint, in  writing, made by the Central Government or any officer authorised in  this behalf by that Government.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-18">
                <num>18.</num>
                <heading>Indemnity. Every officer of the Central Government and every  officer or other employee of the Government company shall be  indemnified by the Central Government or the Government company, as  the case may be, against all losses and expenses incurred by him in,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>or in relation to, the discharge of his duties under this Act except  such as have been caused by his own wilful act or default.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-19">
                <num>19.</num>
                <heading>Power to remeve difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this act, the Central Government  may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>remove the difficulty:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-20">
                <num>20.</num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-20.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-20.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
                    <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both houses  agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
