<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Rehabilitation Finance Administration Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/12/eng@1948-03-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/12/eng@1948-03-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1948-03-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/12/eng@1948-03-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/12/eng@1948-03-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Rehabilitation Finance Administration Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 12 OF 1948</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 23rd March, 1948.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to establish the Rehabilitation Finance Administration.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to establish a Rehabilitation Finance</p>
        <p>Administration, for the purpose of giving financial assistance on  reasonable terms to displaced persons to enable them to settle in  business or industry;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Rehabilitation Fiance Administration Act, 1948.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in  this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context.--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Act" means the Rehabilitation Finance Administration</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act, 1948;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Administration" means the Rehabilitation Fiance</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Administration constituted under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" borrower" means an individual, company, association or  body of individuals, whether incorporated or not, to  whom a loan has been advanced under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" displaced person" means--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a person who, being displaced from any  area  now forming part of Pakistan] on account  of civil disturbances or fear of such  disturbances, has settled and is engaged or  intends to engage in any business or industry in</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>India, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a person in India who, having had his  business, industry or property, wholly or  partially  in any area</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>now forming part of Pakistan], has lost, wholly or  partially, such business, industry, or property on  account of civil disturbances or the fear of such  disturbances, and who is engaged, or intends to  engage in any business or industry in India;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>' loan' means a sum of money advanced by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Administration--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to a displaced person for the purpose of  any business or industry in which he is engaged or  intends to engage himself, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in respect of any business or industry,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>a substantial portion of which is owned by  displaced persons; and]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>' prescribed' means prescribed by rules made under  section 23 or regulations made under section 24.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment and incorporation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government  shall constitute  a Corporation called the Rehabilitation Finance</p>
            <p>Administration for giving financial assistance on reasonable terms to  displaced persons to enable them to settle in business and industry    or to any business or industry, a substantial portion of which is  owned by displaced persons].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Corporation shall be a body corporate by the name of the</p>
            <p>Rehabilitation Finance Administration having perpetual succession and  a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to  acquire, hold and transfer property, both movable and immovable, and  shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration shall have its head office at Delhi and  may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, open  branches at such places in India as it may consider necessary to  discharge effectively its functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Administration.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Administration  shall consist of the following members, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government  who shall be called the Chief Administrator;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>four] officials appointed by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>four] non- officials nominated by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act done by the Administration shall be called in question  on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy or any defect in  the constitution of the Administration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Advisory Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall constitute an</p>
            <p>Advisory Board to advise the Administration on matters of policy and  may where necessary constitute a Regional Committee to advise each  branch of the Administration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Advisory Board shall consist of such members, no  exceeding fifteen in number, as may be nominated by the Central</p>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Terms of office of the members of the Administration and the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Advisory Board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member appointed under clauses (a) and (b) of  sub- section (1) of section 4 shall hold office during the pleasure of  the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member nominated under clause (c) of sub- section (1) of  section 4 or sub- section (2) of section 5 shall hold office for a term  of two years from the date of his nomination and shall be eligible for  re- nomination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A nominated member may resign his membership by writing under  his hand addressed to the Central Government and he shall thereupon  cease to be a member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A casual vacancy created by resignation under sub- section (3)</p>
            <p>or by any other reason shall be filled by fresh nomination and the  person nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for the  remainder of the term for which the member whose place he takes was  nominated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Disclosure of interest.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No member of the Administration  shall have any interest, direct or indirect, in any business, industry  or concern to which any assistance under section 12 has been given or  is to be given and if any such member acquires such interest at any  time during the continuance of such assistance, he shall immediately  disclose it to the Administration and shall either resign his  membership or dispose of his interest in such manner and within such  time as he may be directed by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member of the Advisory Board who has any interest, direct  or indirect, in any business, industry or concern to which any  assistance under section 12 has been given or is to be given or  acquires such interest at any time during the continuance of such  assistance shall immediately disclose it to the Administration and  shall not participate in the proceedings of the Advisory Board  relating to such assistance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Removal from membership. Notwithstanding anything contained in  section 6, the Central Government may, for any reason which may appear  to it to be sufficient, remove any member at any time from the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Administration or the Advisory Board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>The Chief Administrator. The Chief Administrator shall be a  whole- time servant of the Administration and shall receive such  salaries and allowances and shall be subject to such terms and  conditions as may be determined by the Central Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Staff. The Administration may, in the manner prescribed</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>appoint a Deputy Chief nAdministrator and such other  officers and servants as may be required to enable it  to carry out the functions under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>fix the salary and allowances or other conditions of  service of the Deputy Chief Administrator, other  officers and servants;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>fix the remuneration and allowances payable to the  members of the Administration and of the Advisory</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Board:</p>
            <p>Provided that the appointment and the fixation of the  salary, allowances and other conditions of service of the Deputy</p>
            <p>Chief Administrator and such other officers as may be prescribed  by the Central Government, shall be subject to the previous  sanction of that Government.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Funds of the Administration.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government  may from time to time advance money to the Administration for its  business, the aggregate amount of which,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the purpose of enabling the Administration to  advance loans, shall not, save as hereinafter provided,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>exceed twelve crores and fifty lakhs of rupees; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the purpose of enabling the Administration to meet  any liability which it may incur in guaranteeing losses  in respect of loans advanced by scheduled banks, shall  no exceed two crores of rupees:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if, after the lapse of such period from the  commencement of this Act as the Central Government may think fit to  fix in this behalf, any sum of money earmarked for the purpose  specified</p>
            <p>in clause (b) is found not to have been actually advanced for that  purpose and is not, in the opinion of the Central Government, likely  to be required for the said purpose, the Central Government may  utilize the money for making advances from time to time to the</p>
            <p>Administration for the purpose specified in clause (a), and when any  such advance is made, the limit specified in clause (a) shall be  deemed to have been correspondingly increased.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any regulations that may be made in this  behalf, all moneys belonging to the Administration which are not  immediately required by the Administration for any purpose] shall be  deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or any agents thereof or  invested in such securities as may be approved by the Central</p>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration shall pay interest on the money so  advanced at the rate of 3 per cent. per annum to the Central</p>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Business of the Administration. The Administration may--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>subject to the provisions of section 13, advance loans;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>guarantee, on such terms and conditions as may be  agreed upon, losses which a scheduled bank may suffer  in respect of any loan advanced by it and approved by  the Administration:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the total amount which may be  guaranteed in respect of any scheduled bank and  the terms and conditions on which such guarantee  may be given shall be subject to the prior  approval of the Central Government:</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that the maximum liability  of the Administration under such guarantee shall  not exceed the amount for the time being available  under clause (b) of sub- section (1) of section 11;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>do all such acts and things as may be incidental to or  consequential upon the performance of its functions  under this Act including the running of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Administration.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Loans.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may prescribe the limits as  to amounts within which loans may be advanced by the Administration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of advancing any loan under sub- section (1),</p>
            <p>the Administration may call for any report either through its own  staff, or through the District Officer of the district in which the</p>
            <p>borrower resides or carries on business, or through any State</p>
            <p>Government, or through any Bank or any other appropriate agency.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration shall charge interest from the borrower at  such rate not exceeding 6 per cent, per annum as may be specified by  it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period of the loan shall not exceed  fifteen] years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The loan may be advanced either for fixed capital or working  capital or for both.</p>
            <p>The assets created from the loan shall, notwithstanding any law  or usage to the contrary, be deemed to be mortgaged to the</p>
            <p>Administration for the repayment of the loan together with the  interest thereon and the amount of the loan and the interest thereon  shall be first charge on such assets.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration may also take such further security for  any loan as it may consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to call for repayment before agreed period.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any agreement to the contrary, the Administration may,</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>be notice, require any borrower forthwith to repay in full with  interest thereon any loan borrowed from it,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if it appears to the Administration that false or  misleading information in any material particular was  given by the borrower for obtaining the loan or while  furnishing any information under section 17; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the borrower has failed to comply with the terms of  the contract with the Administration in the matter of  the loan; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if there is a reasonable apprehension that the borrower  is unable to pay his debts or that insolvency  proceedings or proceedings for liquidation may be  commenced against him; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if for any other reason it is necessary in the opinion  of the Administration to protect the interests of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Administration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Mode of recovery. If the amount of loan or any instalment  thereof or interest thereon which is due, in accordance with the terms  of the contract or under the provisions of section 14, has not been  repaid the Administration may,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>without prejudice to any other remedy provided by law,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>recover such loan, instalment or interests as arrears  of land revenue, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>take charge of the business or industry of the borrower  on such terms and conditions as it may deem fit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration shall maintain  proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual  statement of accounts including the profit and loss account and the  balance- sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the Central</p>
            <p>Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <p>India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Administration shall be audited annually  by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure  incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the</p>
            <p>Administration to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
            <p>Administration shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <p>India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
            <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect any of the offices of the Administration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Administration as certified by the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed  by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be  forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall  cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power of inspection.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Administrator or any other  officer authorized by him in writing in this behalf may, be order,</p>
            <p>require any borrower to furnish such information or to produce such  books of accounts and other documents for inspection at such time and  place as may be specified in the order and the borrower shall comply  with such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Administrator or such officer may inspect such  books of accounts or documents produced and take extracts therefrom.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Administrator or the officer making the inspection  or any person working under his order shall not communicate or allow  to be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any  information relating to the affairs of the borrower.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1)</p>
            <p>or sub- section (3) he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may  extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five thousand  rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Returns.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration shall furnish to the Central</p>
            <p>Government a half- yearly report together with accounts and such other  information within such time and in such manner as may be specified by  the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The report shall be laid before  Parliament] as soon as may  be after it is prepared.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to give direction. For the  purposes of this Act, the Central Government may, from time to time,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>give to the Administration such general or special directions as it  thinks fit, and the Administration shall, in the exercise of its  functions under this Act, comply with any such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from taxes. Notwithstanding anything contained in  the Indian Income- tax Act, 1922, (11 of 1922), or in any other  enactment for the time being in force relating to income- tax, super-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>tax or business profits tax, the Administration shall not be liable to  pay any income- tax, super- tax or business profits tax on any incomes,</p>
            <p>profits or gains.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Liquidation of the Administration.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No provision of law  relating to insolvency or to the winding up of companies or  corporation shall apply to the Administration and the Administration  shall not be placed in liquidation save by the order of the Central</p>
            <p>Government and in such manner as it may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event of the Administration being placed in  liquidation, the assets of the Administration, after meeting the  liabilities, if any, shall vest in the Central Government shall  thereupon have all the powers of the Administration in recovering the  loans remaining unpaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Delegation. The Administration may, by notification in the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Official Gazette, direct that any power or duty which under any of the  provisions of this Act is conferred or imposed upon the Administration  shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may  be specified in the direction, be exercised or discharged by the Chief</p>
            <p>Administrator, Deputy Chief Administrator or any other person  subordinate to the Administration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  for the purpose of  giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administration may, with  the previous sanction of the Central Government, make regulations, not  inconsistent with this Act or the rules made thereunder, to provide  for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the  purpose of giving effect tot he provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power such regulation may provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the conditions on which a person may be recognised as a  displaced person,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner and the time of the general meetings of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Administration, or Advisory Board or Regional Committee  and the procedure to the followed thereat and the  manner in which right of voting may be exercised,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the terms on which the Administration may grant loans.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>forms of returns and statements required under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Act,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the duties and conduct, salaries, allowances and  conditions of service of officers, servants and agents  of the Administration,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>manner and form of application for loans and contracts.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>manner in which accounts of the Administration shall be  kept and audited.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the conditions under which the  business or industry of a person to whom a loan has  been advanced may be taken charge of and administered  under section 15,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be or may be specified  under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All regulations made under this section shall be published in  the Official Gazette and shall came into force on such date as may be  specified therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Laying of rules and regulations before Parliament. Every  rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the  rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or regulation."]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
