<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/37/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/37"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Sonthal Parganas Act, 1855"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/37/eng@1855-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/37/eng@1855-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1855-12-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/37/eng@1855-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/37/eng@1855-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Sonthal Parganas Act, 1855</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 37 OF 1855</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd December, 1855.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to remove from the operation of the general Laws and</p>
        <p>Regulations certain districts inhabited by Sonthals and others,</p>
        <p>and to place the same under the superintendence of an officer to  be specially appointed for that purpose.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- WHEREAS the general Regulations and Acts of Government  now in force in the Presidency of Bengal are not adapted to the  uncivilized race of people called Sonthals, and it is therefore  expedient to remove from the operation of such laws the district  called the Damin- i- Koh, and other districts which are inhabited  principally by that tribe; it is enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Districts removed from operation of general Regulations.-- 2</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Clause 1.- The districts described in the Schedule to this Act are  hereby removed from the operation of the general Regulations of the</p>
            <p>Bengal Code and of the laws passed by the Governor- General of India in</p>
            <p>Council, except so far as is hereinafter provided; and  no</p>
            <p>Central Act passed before the commencement of Part III of the</p>
            <p>Government of India Act, 1935 26 Geo 5 c- 2,] shall be deemed to  extend to any part of the said districts, unless the same shall be  specially named therein:</p>
            <p>Proviso.-- Provided that nothing herein contained shall   remove any part of the said districts from the operation of</p>
            <p>Regulation 10 of 1804 of the Bengal Code; nor shall this Act affect  any revenue- settlement, nor any law relating to the recovery of  permanently- settled land- revenue due under the same, nor any law  relating to the sale of lands for arrears of revenue, or relating to  patni taluks or to the sale thereof for arrears of rent, nor any law  relating to mutations or batwara or to any other matter to which the</p>
            <p>State Government shall at any time notify in the  Official</p>
            <p>Gazette] that the general Laws and Regulations shall extend.</p>
            <p>Superintendence of districts.-- Clause 2.-- The said districts  shall be placed under the superintendence and jurisdiction of an  officer or officers  to be appointed in that behalf by the State</p>
            <p>Government and such officer or officers shall be subject to the  directions  and control of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Administration of justice and collection of revenue.-- The  administration of civil and criminal justice and the collection of the  revenue, not being permanently- settled land- revenue within the said  district, and hereby vested in the officer or officers to be so  appointed:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Suits exceeding value of one thousand rupees.--  Provided  that all civil suits in which the matter in dispute shall exceed the  value of one thousand rupees shall be tried and determined according  to the general laws and Regulations in the same manner as if this Act  had not been passed:</p>
            <p>Collection of permanently- settled land- revenue.-- Provided also  that all permanently- settled land- revenue shall be collected and paid  at the same places and in the same manner as if this Act had not been  passed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Administration of civil and criminal justice.-- In the  administration of civil and criminal justice the officer or officers  appointed under this Act  may hold his or their Courts either  within the said district or at any place or places that may be  appointed for that purpose by the State Government; and any person  liable to be imprisoned in any civil or criminal jail may be  imprisoned in any civil or criminal jail, as the case may be, which  the State Government may order, whether the same be in or out of the  said district.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Decisions final; confirmation of death- sentence; appeal;</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>procedure on references to Sadar Court. Rep. by the Sonthal Parganas</p>
            <p>Justice Regulation, 1893 (5 of 1893).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Saving of laws relating to European British subjects. Rep.,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ibid.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Commencement of Act. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1870">
        <num>1870.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1870.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
