<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Hindi Sahitya Sammelan Act, 1962"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/13/eng@1962-03-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/13/eng@1962-03-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1962-03-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/13/eng@1962-03-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/13/eng@1962-03-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Hindi Sahitya Sammelan Act, 1962</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 13 OF 1962</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 30th March, 1962.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the institution known as the Hindi Sahitya Sammelan  having its head office at Allahabad to be an institution of national  importance and to provide for its incorporation and matters connected  therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Hindi Sahitya Sammelan Act, 1962.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of the Hindi Sahitya Sammelan as an institution of  national importance. Whereas the objects of the institution known as  the Hindi Sahitya Sammelan which has its head Office at Allahabad are  such as to make the institution one of national importance, it is  hereby declared that the institution known as the Hindi Sahitya</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Sammelan, is an institution of national importance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the date on which this Act comes  into force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Sammelan" means the institution known as the Hindi</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Sahitya Sammelan, incorporated under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Society" means the Hindi Sahitya Sammelan which has  its head office at Allahabad and is registered under  the Societies Registration Act, 1860. (21 of 1860.)</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first members of the Sammelan and all  persons who may hereafter become members thereof in accordance with  the rules made in this behalf, so long as they continue to hold  membership thereof, are hereby constituted a body corporate by the  name of the Hindi Sahitya Sammelan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Sammelan shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire,</p>
            <p>hold and dispose of property and to contract and may by that name sue  and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The head office of the Sammelan shall be at Allahabad.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The first members of the Sammelan shall be--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all persons who, immediately before the appointed day,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>were members of the Society;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all persons who, before that day, have been Presidents  of the Society; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all persons who, before that day, were awarded the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Mangla Prasad Paritoshik by the Society.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Effect of incorporation of sammelan. On and from the appointed  day,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any reference to the Society in any law (other than   this act) or in any contract or other instrument shall  be deemed as a reference to the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all property, movable or immovable, of the Society  shall be the property of the Sammelan;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all rights and liabilities of the Society shall  be  the rights and liabilities of the sammelan; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>every person employed by the Society immediately before  the appointed day shall hold his office or service in  the Sammelan by the same tenure, at the same  remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and  with the same rights and privileges as to pension,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>leave, gratuity, provident fund and other matters as he  would have held the same if this Act had not been  passed, and shall continue to do so unless and until  his appointment is terminated or until his tenure or  terms and conditions are duly altered by the rules made  in this behalf;</p>
            <p>Provided that if the alteration so made is not acceptable to any  such employee, his employment may be terminated by the Sammelan in  accordance with the terms of the contract with the employee or, if no  provision is made therein in this behalf, on payment to him by the</p>
            <p>Sammelan of compensation equivalent to three months' remuneration in  the case of permanent employees and one month' s remuneration in the  case of other employees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Sammelan. Subject to the provisions of this Act  and the rules made thereunder, the Sammelan shall perform the  following functions, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to promote the spread of Hindi language and to develop  it and secure its enrichment in the manner indicated in  article 351 of the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to work for the promotion, development and advancement  of Hindi literature in India and foreign countries and  to print and publish such literature;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to work for the promotion, development and advancement  of Devanagari script, and to print and publish  literature of other Indian languages in Devanagari  script;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to arrange for the holding of examinations through the  medium of Hindi language and to confer degrees,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>diplomas and other academic distinctions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to establish and maintain schools, colleges and other  institutions for instruction in Hindi language and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Hindi literature and also to affiliate schools,</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>colleges and other institutions for its examinations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to affiliate institutions having for their object the  promotion of Hindi language and Hindi literature;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to award honorary degrees and other academic  distinctions to persons who may have rendered  distinguished service to the cause of Hindi;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to institute and award prizes (Paritoshiks) to  distinguished scholars in Hindi;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to promote and encourage research in Hindi language and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Hindi literature;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>to co- operate with other institutions having objects  similar to those of the Sammelan, in such manner as may  be conducive to their common objects;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>to receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions  from the Government and to receive bequests, donations  or transfers of movable and immovable properties from  testators, donors or transferors, as the case may be;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>to deal with any property belonging to or vested in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Sammelan in such manner as the Sammelan may deem fit  for advancing the objects of the Sammelan;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list9.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>with the approval of the Central Government, to borrow  on the security of the property of the Sammelan money  for the purposes of the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list9.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>to perform such other functions as may be deemed  necessary by the Sammelan for advancing the cause of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Hindi language and Hindi literature or as may be  necessary incidental or conducive to the performance of  all or any of the above functions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Governing Body.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The general superintendence, direction and  management of the affairs of the Sammelan shall vest in a Governing</p>
            <p>Body, by whatever name called.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Governing Body shall consist of such number of persons  not exceeding fifty- five as the Central Government may from time to  time determine, of whom not more than seven shall be nominated by the</p>
            <p>Central Government from among educationists of repute of eminent Hindi  scholars, and the remaining members shall be chosen in accordance with  the rules made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the powers and  functions of the Governing Body, the term of office of, and the  allowances, if any, payable to, members thereof, the procedure to be  followed by the Governing Body for the transaction of its business,</p>
            <p>the quorum necessary therefor and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among the members thereof shall be such as may be  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>First Governing Body and its duties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in section 7, the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, constitute the first Governing</p>
            <p>Body consisting of a Chairman, a Secretary, and thirteen other members  to be appointed by that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The thirteen members referred to in sub- section (1) shall be  chosen as follows:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>one member to represent the Ministry of the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Government dealing with education;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>one member to represent the Ministry of the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government dealing with finance;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list5.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>not more than three members from among the former</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>President of the Society; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list7.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the remaining number from among persons who are, in the  opinion of the Central Government, eminent in the field  of Hindi language or Hindi literature.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the first Governing Body of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Sammelan,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to perform all functions of the Sammelan and to carry  on the administration of the affairs of the Sammelan</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>until a Governing Body is constituted in accordance  with the provisions of section 7;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to make the rules with the approval of the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to determine the first members of the Sammelan within  the meaning of sub- section (4) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to take all necessary steps for the constitutions of  the Governing Body in accordance with such rules;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to perform such other function as it may consider  necessary.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Term of office and procedure of first Governing Body and  salary or allowances payable to members thereof.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the  provisions of section 14, the members of the first Governing Body  shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All questions at a meeting of the first Governing Body shall  be decided by a majority of the members present thereat, and in the  case of an equality of votes the Chairman or, in his absence, any  other person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The quorum to constitute a meeting of the first Governing</p>
            <p>Body shall be  five] members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members shall be paid out of the Fund of the Sammelan  such  salary or allowances or both] as may be prescribed and until  so prescribed, as may be specified by the Central Government in this  behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>First Governing Body to take over management of properties of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Sammelan. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any  other law for the time being in force or in any order of a court, the  first Governing Body shall take over the management, control and  administration of all the properties vested in the Sammelan.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Determination of first members.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Governing Body  shall, as soon as may be, cause to be prepared, subject to such  instructions, if any, as it may receive from the Central Government, a  list of all persons who are to be considered as first members of the</p>
            <p>Sammelan within the meaning of sub- section (4) of section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The list shall be published in such manner as may be directed  by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any time after the publication of the list of first  members under sub- section (2), it appears to the first Governing Body  that the name of any person has been wrongly omitted from, or wrongly  entered in, the list, it may order such name to be inserted or omitted  from that list and the list shall be amended accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order omitting the name of any person from the  list shall be made unless that person has been given a reasonable  opportunity of showing cause against such omission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No persons other than the persons named in the list prepared  under this section shall be considered as first members of the</p>
            <p>Sammelan within the meaning of sub- section (4) of section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Rules to be made by the first Governing Body.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Governing Body shall, as soon as may be, make rules in respect of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the matters relating to membership, including the  qualifications and disqualifications for membership of  the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions of the Governing Body; the  term of office of, and the allowances, if any, payable  to, members thereof; the procedure to be followed by  the Governing Body for the transaction of its business,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>the quorum necessary therefor and the manner of filling  casual vacancies among the members thereof;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conduct of elections for the constitution of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Governing body and the decisions on doubts and disputes  at or in connection with the said elections;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of an executive committee or any other  committee for carrying on the functions of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Governing body or of the Sammelan; the constitution,</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>powers and duties of such committees and the  allowances, if any, payable to the members thereof;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list9.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the procedure and the forms for the maintenance of  books of accounts and other registers and statements  for the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list9.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the appointment, control and other conditions of  service of the employees of the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list9.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conduct of correspondence, execution of documents  and contracts for or on behalf of the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list9.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the conduct prosecution of suits and proceedings by or  against the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list9.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the matters relating to the affiliation of schools,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list11">
              <listIntroduction>colleges, and other institutions with the Sammelan;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list11.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the matters relating to the award of degrees and  academic distinctions by the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list11.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <blockList id="section-12.1.list11.k.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the matters relating to the award of prizes</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-12.1.list11.k.list0.Paritoshiks">
                    <num>(Paritoshiks)</num>
                    <p>by the Sammelan;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list11.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the procedure for the amendment of the rules:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list11.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>such other matters as may be necessary for the  performance of the functions of the Sammelan.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A draft of the rules proposed to be made under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>shall be forwarded to the Central Government for approval and that</p>
            <p>Government may approve the same with or without modifications.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No rules made under this section shall have effect until they  are approved by the Central Government and are published by the first</p>
            <p>Governing Body in such manner as the Central Government may by order  direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of the rules so made shall be laid, as soon as may be  after they are made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Elections to Governing Body. The first Governing Body shall,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>within six months of its constitution or within such further period as  may be specified by the Central Government, arrange to hold elections  to the Governing Body in accordance with the provisions of the rules  made under section 12 and take such further steps as may be necessary  for its due constitution within the period specified as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution of first Governing Body. On the constitution of  the Governing Body under section 7 in accordance with the rules made  under section 12, the first Governing Body shall cease to exist and  stand dissolved.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Fund of the Sammelan</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The sammelan shall maintain a Fund  to which shall be Credited--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all fees and other charges received by the Sammelan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Sammelan by way of grants,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>gifts, donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers;</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Sammelan in any other manner  or from any other source.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the expenses of the</p>
            <p>Sammelan in the performance of its functions under this Act, including  allowances, if any, payable to the members of the Governing Body or of  any Committee and the salaries and allowances, if any, of the  employees of the Sammelan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Account and audit.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Sammelan shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as may be  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Sammelan shall, once at least in every  year, be audited by a chartered accountant in practice within the.</p>
            <p>meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949), to be  appointed annually by the Sammelan:</p>
            <p>Provided that no member of the Sammelan who is a chartered  accountant or a person who is in partnership with such member shall be  eligible for appointment as an auditor under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every auditor shall, in the performance of his duties, have  at all reasonable times access to the books, accounts and other  documents of the Sammelan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be practicable at the end of each year, the  audited accounts of the Sammelan together with the audit report shall  be forwarded to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Governing Body may, from time to  time, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act and such  rules may amend or repeal the rules made under section 12.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No rules made under this section shall have effect until they  are approved by the Central Government and are published by the</p>
            <p>Governing Body in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act of the Sammelan, or of the Governing Body, or of any other body  set up under the rules made in this behalf shall be invalid merely by  reason of--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy therein, or defect in the constitution  thereof, of or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect in the election, nomination or appointment  of a person acting as a member thereof, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the  merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provision  or give such direction not in consistent with the purposes of this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, as appears to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the  difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
