<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/2013/7"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' And Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Act, 2012"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' And Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Act, 2012</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 07 of 2013]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of a Welfare Fund for the welfare of the document writers, scribes and stamp vendors in the State of Kerala, to pay pension and other benefits to them and for other matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      <p>Whereas, it is expedient to provide for the constitution of a Welfare Fund for the welfare of the document writers, scribes and stamp vendors in the State of Kerala, to pay pension and other benefits to them and for other matters connected therewith or incidental thereto;</p>
      <p>Be it enacted in the Sixty-third Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Act, 2012.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 31st day of January, 2012.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act unless the context otherwise requires,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Board" means the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Board constituted under section 9;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"cessation of employment" means ceasing of employment of a licensee consequent to the cancellation or surrender of the licence obtained for doing the employment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"contribution" means the amount payable to the Welfare Fund by the members under sub-section (1) of section 4 and by the Government under sub-section (1) of section 26;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"dependent" means wife or husband, minor sons, unmarried or widowed or divorced daughters, mentally or physically disabled children, father mother who are solely dependent upon the member;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"Document Writer" means a person having a licence who is engaged in the profession of preparing documents including 'enquiry as to title, preparation of draft deeds and engrossing the deed on stamp paper for registration as per the Kerala Document Writers' Licence Rules, 1960;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Fund" means the Kerala Document Writers'. Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare fund constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the Government of Kerala;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"Inspector General of Registration" means the Inspector General of Registration of the Government of Kerala;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"member" means a Document Writer or a Scribe or a Stamp Vendor, who has been admitted as a member of the Welfare Fund under the provisions of this Act or who is continuing as a member of the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Scheme, 1991;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Kerala Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>"Registering Authority" means the District Registrar (General) of the district concerned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>"Scheme" means the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Scheme framed under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>"Scribe" means a person who assists a Document Writer in the preparation of documents and who possesses a valid scribe licence to transcribe the documents to be presented for registration as defined in sub-rule (5) of rule 3 of the Kerala Document Writers' Licence Rules, 1960;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>"Secretary" means the Secretary of the Board constituted as per this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>"stamp" means the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Wendors' Welfare Fund Stamp printed and distributed under section 24;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>"Stamp Vendor" means a person who has acquired a licence as per rule 35 of the Kerala Manufacture and Sale of Stamp Rules, 1960 and actively engaged in the profession of selling non-judicial stamps and stamp papers.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall, as soon as may be, after the commencement of this Act, by notification, frame a Scheme to be called the "Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Scheme" and after the framing of the Scheme, constitute a Fund to be called "the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund" in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Scheme may provide for all or any of the matters specified in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The following shall be credited to the Fund, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>contributions under sections 4 and 26;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>application fee realised under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any amount borrowed under section 15;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all amounts collected by way of sale of stamp under section 24;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any donation voluntarily made to the Fund by any association or institution or any other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any profit, interest, dividend or other income on any investment made of any part of the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any grants, loans or advances as may be given by the Government of India or the State Government or any other institution or organization;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>two per cent of the amount being received by the Stamp Vendors as commission;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>amount transferred under section 30;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>any fees levied under the Scheme;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other amount, to be credited to the Fund under the provisions of the Scheme;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>any amount raised by the Board from other sources to augment the resources of the Fund.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall vest in the Board and be administered by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The fund may be utilized for all or any of the following purposes, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the payment of a fixed amount and pension to a person, who had been a member and remitted contribution for not less than five years and ceased his employment or unable to continue in the employment due to ill health, at such rate as may be specified in the Scheme, based on the number of years in which he had remitted contribution;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation 1. The Board shall have the power to take decision regarding the eligibility of pensionary benefits payable to a member who could not continue his employment due to ill health.</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation 2. A person who had completed sixty-five years of age and who had been a Document Writer, Scribe or Stamp Vendor for twenty five years before the commencement of this Act shall become eligible for special pension if he becomes a member and remits contribution for a period of one year under the provisions of this Act.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the payment of family pension on the death of a member who had remitted contribution for not less than ten years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for the payment of financial assistance on the death of a member due to illness or accident;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for the repayment of the contribution amount remitted by the members with such interest, as may be specified in the Scheme, when they are incapacitated to do work due to permanent physical disability or on the cessation of their membership in the Welfare Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for the payment of financial assistance to meet the expense towards medical treatment of the members affected with serious ailment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for the payment of financial assistance to meet the marriage expense of the members and their daughters and for the maternity expense of the female members;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for the payment of financial assistance or loans or advances to the members for the purpose connected with their employment or for the construction of dwelling house or for the maintenance or renovation of the house or for the purchase of land for the construction of house or for the purchase of land and building and for the education, including higher education of the children of the members;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>for the payment of special relief to the members who suffer from physical disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.5.list4.i.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for any other purpose specified in the Scheme;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.5.list4.i.list0.J">
                    <num>(J)</num>
                    <p>for the day to day administrative expenses of the Board.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.-For the purpose of this sub-section the contribution remitted by a person who had been a member of the Kerala Document Writers, Scribes and Stamp Vendors Welfare Fund Scheme, 1991 and the number of years in which he had remitted contribution to the said Welfare Fund shall also be taken into account.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Scheme framed under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is framed, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in the Scheme or decides that the Scheme should not be issued, the Scheme shall, thereafter have effect only in such modified form ox be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Contribution to the Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Document Writer, Scribe and Stamp Vendor who is eligible to become a member shall pay one hundred rupees per month as contribution to the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, from time to time, revise the rate of contribution referred to in sub-section (1) up to a maximum limit of live hundred rupees, taking into account the amount required for the management of the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The contribution shall be paid in the name of the Secretary or officer authorised in this behalf, in the manner specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Membership in the Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person holding a valid licence of document writer or scribe under the Kerala Document Writers' Licence Rules, 1960 or a valid licence of a Stamp Vendor under the Kerala Manufacture and Sale of Stamp Rules, 1960, as the case may be, and is below the age of 65 years on the date of application may apply to the Board for admission as a member of the Fund in such form and manner as may be specified in the Scheme:</p>
            <p>Provided that, where the Fund under the Kerala Document Writers, Scribes and Stamp Vendors Welfare Fund Scheme, 1991 is transferred to the Fund under sub-section (1) of section 30, those who are members of the said Scheme shall be deemed to be the members of the Fund from the date of such transfer.</p>
            <p>Provided further that no person employed as a Document Writer, Scribe or Stamp Vendor after retiring from the service of the Central Government or any State Government or any public sector undertaking or local Authority with retirement benefits, shall be eligible for membership in the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On an application under sub-section (1), the Board may make such enquiry as it deem fit and cither admit the applicant to the Fund or for reasons to be recorded in writing reject the application:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order rejecting an application shall be passed unless the applicant has been given an opportunity of being heard:</p>
            <p>Provided further that any person aggrieved by an order rejecting any application for membership may prefer an appeal to the Government within such period as may be specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every applicant shall pay an application fee of one hundred rupees along with the application in such manner as may be specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member of the Fund, on completion of 65 years of age or on voluntarily applying for pension by surrendering his licence after 25 years of membership, shall cease to be a member of the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person who has been enrolled as member in the Fund shall be given a certificate of membership and a pass book recording the rate of contribution, details of enrolment in the register, date of birth, due date for payment of contribution etc., by the Registering Authority. The Registering Authority shall keep a register of the members coming under its jurisdiction and at the State level, the Secretary of Board shall keep a register of members enrolled in the Fund, showing the district-wise details of members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Cancellation of Membership</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The membership of a member shall be cancelled by the Registering Authority if it is found that a member has made manipulation of any kind or has given false information at any time in connection with the conditions for the membership or to obtain benefits as per the Scheme:</p>
            <p>Provided that, no order of cancellation of membership shall be passed unless the applicant has been given an opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Membership in the Fund shall automatically cease if a member commits default in payment of contribution for six months continuously.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Registering Authority is of the opinion that a member is not functioning as a Document Writer or Scribe or Stamp Vendor, as the case may be, his membership in the Fund shall be cancelled. The date of cancellation in such cases shall be, as may be fixed by the Registering Authority and shall be intimated to the members in writing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Appeal against the orders of the Registering Authority shall be filed before the Inspector General of Registration within such period as may be specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member may voluntarily retire from the Fund by submitting a letter addressed to the Registering Authority. In such case, the date of retirement shall be the date on which the member has submitted his letter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Revival of Membership</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The membership of a member which has been ceased under sub-section (2) of sect-ion f) may be revived on payment of arrears along with interest at twelve per cent per annum within six months from the date of cessation of such membership.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of the Scheme</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Government may by notification, amend the Scheme framed under this Act, cither prospectively or retrospectively.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification under sub-section (1) shall be laid as soon as may be, after it is issued, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid, or the session immediately following, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in the notification or decides that the notification should not be issued, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification with effect from such date as specified therein, constitute a Board to be called the "Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare fund Board" for the administration and management of the Fund and to implement and supervise connected activities.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name Kerala Document Writers, Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Board having perpetual succession and a common seal and shall by the said name, sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of seven official members representing the Government and five non-official members representing the beneficiaries of the Fund as may be nominated by the Government and as hereinafter provided, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Secretary to Government, Taxes Department he shall be the Chairman of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The Inspector General of Registration he shall be the Vice-Chairman of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>The Joint Inspector General of Registration. he shall be the Secretary of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>An officer of the Finance Department not below the rank of Deputy Secretary nominated by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>An officer of the Labour Department not below the rank of Deputy Secretary' nominated by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>An officer of the faxes Department not below the rank of Deputy Secretary nominated by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>An officer of the Law Department not below the rank of Deputy Secretary nominated by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>Five non-official members representing the Document Writers, Scribes and Stamp Vendors nominated by the Government, of whom one person shall be a woman.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall administer the Fund vested in it in such manner as specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the previous approval of the Government, delegate to the Chairman or to the Secretary such of its powers and functions under this Act or the Scheme as it may consider necessary, for the effective management of the Fund, subject to such restrictions and conditions, as it may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Meeting of the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall meet at least once in three months to transact its business.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Six members of the Board including at least four official members and two non-official members shall form the quorum for a meeting of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman or in his absence the Vice-Chairman, or in the absence of the Chairman and the Vice-Chairman, a member of the Board to be elected from among the members present at the meeting shall preside over the meeting of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any matter coming up before a meeting of the Board shall be decided by a majority of the members of the Board present and voting at the meeting and in the case of equality of votes, the Chairman or the Vice-Chairman or the member of the Board who presides over the meeting, shall have right for a casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Term of Office of members of the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The non-official members appointed under sub-section (3) of section 9 shall hold office for a period of three years from the date of publication of the notification constituting the Board in the Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any non-official member may resign his membership by giving notice in writing to the Government, but shall continue to hold office until his resignation is accepted by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may at any time, for reasons to be recorded in writing, remove from office any official member, if the Government are of opinion that, in public interest it is improper to allow such member to continue in office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Disqualification and removal of non-official members</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government may remove any non-official member of the Board from office.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he is of unsound mind;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he is adjudged as undercharged insolvent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if he, without the permission of the Board, has been absent from three consecutive meetings of the Board; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if in the opinion of the Government, he is not suitable or has become incapable of acting as a member of the Board or has so abused his position so as to render his continuance as member of the Board detrimental to public interest:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that before removing a member of the Board under this sub-section, he shall be given a reasonable opportunity to show cause why he should not be removed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A non-official member of the Board removed under clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall be disqualified for re-nomination as a member of the Board for a period of three years from the date of his removal unless otherwise ordered by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A non-official member of the Board removed under clause (d) of sub-section (1) shall not be eligible for re-nomination until he is declared by an order of the Government to be no longer ineligible.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Sitting fees, traveling allowance and daily allowance to members of the Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Sitting fees to the non-official members, traveling allowance and daily allowance to all members of the Board shall be at such rate as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Officers and Staff</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may appoint such officers and staff as they may deem necessary, in such manner as may be prescribed, on deputation from the Registration Department for assisting the Secretary in the performance of the functions of the Board under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Secretary of the Board shall be responsible for the implementation of the decisions of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power of the Board to borrow</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, from time to time, with the previous approval of the Government and subject to such terms and conditions as specified by the Government, borrow money for the purposes of the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Non-official Members of the Board to be public servants</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every non-official member of the Board shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act 45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other Legal proceedings shall lie against any member of the Board or any other person assisting the Board in the discharge of its functions and duties in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or under the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Directions by Government</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, from time to time, give directions to the Board, and the Board is bound to implement them.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to order enquiry</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, at any lime appoint an officer not below the rank of a Secretary to Government as enquiry officer to enquire into the working of the Board and to submit report to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall give the enquiry officer so appointed facilities for the proper conduct of the enquiry and furnish to such documents, accounts and informations in the possession of the Board as he may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Audit of Accounts of the Fund and appointment of auditors</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall appoint such auditors to audit the accounts of the Fund in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Fund shall be audited once in every year by such auditors.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Annual report and audited statement of accounts</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual report of the Fund shall be prepared under the direction of the Board and after approval by the Board, a copy of the report together with audited statement of accounts shall be submitted to the Government before the 31st of July every year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall, as soon as the annual report is received, cause the same together with the audited statement of accounts to be laid before the Legislative Assembly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Bar on jurisdiction of Civil Courts</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Civil Court shall have jurisdiction to settle, decide or deal with any question or to determine any matter which is by or under this Act or the Scheme required to be settled decided or dealt with or to be determined by the Government or the Board or the Secretary or any officer authorised by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Power to summon witness and take evidence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall, for the purposes of enquiry under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Central Act 5 of 1908) in respect of the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enforcing the attendance of any person or examining him on oath:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and the production of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavit; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>engaging Commission for the examination of witnesses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>The Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Stamp</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall get printed at the Government Press stamps of the value of fifty rupees inscribed as "the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Stamp", in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every document prepared by a licensed document writer and presented in any of the Sub-Registrar Offices in the State to be registered in book I, III or IV, as the case may be, shall be affixed with a stamp as specified in sub-section (1), in addition to the stamp duty chargeable under the Kerala Stamp Act 1959 (17 of 1959):</p>
            <p>Provided that this sub-section shall not apply to any document prepared and presented for registration on behalf of the Central Government or the State Government or Local Self Government Institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every stamp affixed as specified in sub-section (2) shall be cancelled in the manner provided for in section 12 of the Kerala Stamp Act, 1959 (17 of 1959).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The custody of the stamps printed under this section shall be with the Board and the supply and sale of stamps shall be in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Payment of money in case of default or disqualification</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In case of cessation of membership due to default or disqualification, the member or his nominee may apply for the amount remitted as contribution in the manner stated in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member whose membership has been ceased or his nominee shall not be eligible for any benefit from the Welfare Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The contribution if any remitted after the date of cessation of membership, shall be refunded in full without any interest thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount that has been received wrongly by a member or person nominated by him shall be recovered from such person by appropriate legal proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Contribution of the Government</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Ten per cent the total amount contributed by the members during a financial year of the expenses to be incurred under the head of pay and allowances of the staff including bonus and encashment of leave but excluding travelling allowance, assigned for the administration of the Welfare Fund, whichever is less, shall be given as Government contribution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At the end of every financial year, the Secretary shall calculate the expenses including bonus and encashment of leave but excluding travelling allowance, assigned for the administration of the Welfare Fund, under the head of account of pay and allowances of the staff and shall intimate the same to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the amount so calculated is found to be more than ten per cent of the yearly contribution of the members, the difference between this amount and ten per cent of the yearly contribution of the members, shall be withdrawn from the Welfare Fund and remitted to the head of account concerned fixed from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Act of Board not to be invalid by defect etc</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act done or proceedings taken under this Act or the rules or scheme made thereunder by the Board shall be invalid merely by reason of.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy or defect in the constitution of the Board; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect or irregularity in the nomination of any person as a member thereof; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any defect or irregularity in any act or proceedings of the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Removal of difficulties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government may,-by order published in the Gazette, make provisions which appear to them to be necessary and not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, for the purpose of removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be passed after the expiry of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The order issued under sub-section (1) shall be placed before the Legislative Assembly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, make rules either prospectively or retrospectively for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be alter it is made, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and, if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in the rule or decides that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Provision for the transfer of fund from the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund, Scheme, 1991</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, from the date to be notified by the Government, all amounts standing in the credit of the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Scheme, 1991 shall stand transferred to and credited to the Fund established under this Act and with effect from such date the liability of a member to pay contribution to the Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Scheme. 1991 shall cease.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All claims in respect of the said Fund may be determined by the Board constituted under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Kerala Document Writers', Scribes' and Stamp Vendors' Welfare Fund Ordinance, 2012 (48 of 2012) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or deemed to have been done or any action taken or deemed to have been taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/2013/7"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/2013/7/eng@2017-03-29"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-29" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>SCHEDULE</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>[See section 3(2)]</p>
                <p>MATTERS FOR WHICH PROVISION MAY BE MADE IN THE SCHEME</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which the Fund is to be administered by the Hoard.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>Registration of the members.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which the contribution and two per cent of the commission of Stamp Vendors shall be made to the Fund.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which the contribution from different sectors and the two per cent of the commission of Stamp Vendors may be recovered.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>The constitution of any committee for assisting the Board.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Duties of the Secretary.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which accounts shall be maintained, the investment of money belonging to the Fund in accordance with any direction issued or conditions specified by the Government, the preparation of budget, the audit of accounts and the submission of reports to the Government.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>The conditions under which withdrawal from the Fund may be permitted and any deduction or forfeiture may be made and the maximum amount of such deduction or forfeiture.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>The form in which a member shall furnish particulars about himself and his family whenever required.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>The nomination of a person to receive the benefits of a member from the Fund on his death and cancellation or verification of such nomination.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>The registers and records to be maintained with respect to members.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>The form of pass book, certificate and identity card and the procedure for their issue, custody and replacement.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>The fees to be levied for any of the purposes specified in the Schedule.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which the amount transferred under section 30 is to be transferred and credited to the Fund.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>The matters for which the Fund may be utilized for the welfare of the members or their dependents.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>The procedure for defraying the expenditure to be incurred in the administration of the Fund.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>The procedure for paying benefits, grants, advances etc., from the Fund.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Regularization of the rate of the amount from the Fund that may be given to the members who had ceased their employment or are unable to continue in employment due to ill health, based on the number of years of remittance of contribution, and pension.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>The manner and rate in which the contribution is to be refunded in the case of the members who have committed default.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>Any other matter which is necessary or proper for implementing the Scheme.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
