<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/36/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/36"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Andhra Pradesh And Mysore (Transfer Of Territory) Act, 1968"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1968-08-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Andhra Pradesh And Mysore (Transfer Of Territory) Act, 1968</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 36 OF 1968</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd August, 1968.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the transfer of certain territory from the</p>
        <p>State of Mysore to the State of Andhra Pradesh and for matters  connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Mysore (Transfer of Territory) Act, 1968.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the 1st day of October, 1968;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as  in the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1950">
        <num>1950.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>);</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" sitting member", in relation to either House of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a  person who, immediately before the appointed day, is a  member of that House;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" transferred territory" means the territory specified in  the Schedule and transferred from the State of Mysore  to the State of Andhra Pradesh by section 3.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of territory from Mysore to Andhra Pradesh.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As  from the appointed day, there shall be added to the State of Andhra</p>
            <p>Pradesh the territory specified in the Schedule which shall thereupon  cease to form part of the State of Mysore.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The transferred territory shall be included in, and form part  of the Hindupur taluk of Anantapur district in the State of Andhra</p>
            <p>Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to affect the  power of the State Government to alter, after the appointed day, the  name, extent or boundaries of any district or taluk in the State of</p>
            <p>Andhra Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the  appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the  heading" I. THE STATES",--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the entry against" I. Andhra Pradesh", the following  shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" The territories specified in sub- section (1) of  section 3 of the Andhra State Act, 1953, sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 3 of the States Reorganisation Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1956">
        <num>1956.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, the First Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and</p>
            <p>Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1959, and the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/36/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/36"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Andhra Pradesh and Mysore (Transfer of"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/36/eng@1968-08-22"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <heading>Territory) Act, 1968, but excluding the territories  specified in the Second Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh  and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1959."; and</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleto.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>in the entry against" 9. Mysore", after the words and  figures" States Reorganisation Act, 1956", the words,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>brackets and figures" but excluding the territory  specified in the Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and</p>
                <p>Mysore (Transfer of Territory) Act, 1968" shall be  inserted.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Extent of parliamentary and assembly constituencies. As from  the appointed day, the transferred territory shall cease to be part of</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Madhugiri parliamentary constituency and Bagepalli assembly  constituency in the State of Mysore as delimited in Order No. 11 of  the Delimitation Commission made under section 10 of the Delimitation</p>
                  <p>Commission Act, 1962 (61 of 1962), and shall form part of Hindupur  parliamentary constituency and Hindupur assembly constituency in the</p>
                  <p>State of Andhra Pradesh as delimited in Order No. 3 of the</p>
                  <p>Delimitation Commission made under the said section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Provision as to sitting members of Parliament and</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Legislative Assemblies.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The sitting members of the House of the</p>
                  <p>People representing Hindupur parliamentary constituency in the State  of Andhra Pradesh and Madhugiri parliamentary constituency in the</p>
                  <p>State of Mysore shall, notwithstanding the alteration in the extent of  those constituencies by virtue of the provisions of this Act, continue  to be members of the House of the People.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The sitting members of the Legislative Assemblies of Andhra</p>
                  <p>Pradesh and Mysore representing Hindupur assembly constituency and</p>
                  <p>Bagepalli assembly constituency respectively shall, notwithstanding  the alteration in the extent of those constituencies by virtue of the  provisions of this Act, continue to be members of the said Assemblies.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Extent of Council constituencies.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any reference in the</p>
                  <p>Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Andhra Pradesh) Order, 1957,</p>
                  <p>to Anantapur district shall be construed as including the territory  transferred to that district from the State of Mysore.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Any reference in the Delimitation of Council Constituencies</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list1.Mysore">
                      <num>(Mysore)</num>
                      <p>Order, 1951, to Kolar district shall be construed as  excluding the territory transferred from that district to the State of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Sitting members of Legislative Councils. Every sitting member  of the Legislative Council of Andhra Pradesh or of Mysore representing  a council constituency the extent of which is altered by virtue of  section 7 shall, as from the appointed day, be deemed to have been  elected to the said Council by that constituency as so altered.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Extension of jurisdiction of Andhra Pradesh High Court.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>As  from the appointed day,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Andhra Pradesh  shall extend to the transferred territory; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the High Court of Mysore shall have no jurisdiction in  respect of the said territory.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If, immediately before the appointed day, there is any  proceeding relatable to the transferred territory pending in the High</p>
                  <p>Court of Mysore, then, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-</p>
                  <p>section (1), such proceeding shall be heard and disposed of by that</p>
                  <p>High Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any order made by the High Court of Mysore in any proceeding  with respect to which that High Court exercises jurisdiction by virtue  of sub- section (2) shall, for all purposes, have effect, not only as  an order of the High Court of Mysore but also as an order made by the</p>
                  <p>High Court of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9.4.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.4.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Court of Mysore until that Court has disposed of all  issues between the parties, including any issues with  respect to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings  and shall include appeals, applications for leave to  appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9.4.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>petitions for revision and petitions for writs;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.4.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>references to a High Court shall be construed as  including references to a Judge or division court  thereof, and references</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>to an order made by a court or a Judge shall be  construed as including references to a sentence,</p>
                  <p>judgment or decree passed or made by that court or</p>
                  <p>Judge.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred  territory under existing Appropriation Acts. As from the appointed  day, any Act passed by the Legislature of Andhra Pradesh before that  day for the appropriation of any money out of the Consolidated Fund of  the State to meet any expenditure in respect of any part of the  financial year 1968- 69 shall have effect also in relation to the  transferred territory, and it shall be lawful for the State Government  to spend any amount for that territory out of the amount authorised by  such Act to be expended for any services in that State.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Assets and liabilities.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All land and all stores, articles  and other goods in the transferred territory belonging to the State of</p>
                  <p>Mysore shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State of Andhra</p>
                  <p>Pradesh.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression" land" includes  immovable property of every kind and any rights in or over such  property and the expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes  and currency notes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All rights, liabilities and obligations, whether arising out  of a contract or otherwise, of the State of Mysore in relation to the  transferred territory shall, as from the appointed day, be the rights,</p>
                  <p>liabilities and obligations, respectively, of the State of Andhra</p>
                  <p>Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>State Financial Corporations and State Electricity Boards. As  from the appointed day,--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the Financial Corporations constituted under the State</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951), for the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>States of Mysore and Andhra Pradesh, and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the State Electricity Boards constituted under the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948) for the  said States.</p>
                  <p>shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their  areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Extension of laws. All laws which, immediately before the  appointed day, extend to, or are in force in, the Hindupur taluk of</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Anantapur district in the State of Andhra Pradesh but do not extend  to, or are not in force in, the transferred territory, shall, as from  that day, extend to, or as the case may be, come into force in, the  transferred territory; and all laws which,</p>
                  <p>immediately before the appointed day, are in force in the transferred  territory but not in the Hindupur taluk of Anantapur district in the</p>
                  <p>State of Andhra Pradesh shall, on that day, cease to be in force in  the transferred territory, except as respects things done or omitted  to be done before that day.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.-- In this section," law" includes any enactment,</p>
                  <p>ordinance, regulation, order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or  other instrument having the force of law in the whole or in any part  of the State of Andhra Pradesh or Mysore.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Power to construe laws. Any court, tribunal or authority  required or empowered to enforce any law extended to the transferred  territory by section 13 may, for the purpose of facilitating its  application in relation to the transferred territory, construe the law  in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be necessary  or proper in regard to the matter before the court, tribunal or  authority.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed  day, the State of Mysore is a party to any legal proceedings with  respect to any property, rights or liabilities transferred to the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>State of Andhra Pradesh under this Act, the State of Andhra Pradesh  shall be deemed to be substituted for the State of Mysore as a party  to those proceedings, or added as a party thereto, as the case may be,</p>
                  <p>and the proceedings may continue accordingly.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Transfer of pending proceedings.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every proceeding pending  immediately before the appointed day before any court (other than a</p>
                  <p>High Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that  day falls within the State of Mysore shall, if it is a proceeding  relating exclusively to any part of the transferred territory, stand  transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer  in the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should  stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the</p>
                  <p>High Court of Mysore and the decision of that High Court shall be  final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-16.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In this section,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-16.3.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-16.3.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-16.3.list1.b.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in  the State of Andhra Pradesh means--</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-16.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                          <num>(i)</num>
                          <p>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in  which, or before whom, the proceeding would have lain  if the proceeding had been instituted after the  appointed day, or</p>
                        </item>
                        <item id="section-16.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                          <num>(ii)</num>
                          <p>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal,</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>authority or officer in that State as may be determined  after the appointed day by the Government of Andhra</p>
                  <p>Pradesh, or before the appointed day by the Government  of Mysore, to be the corresponding court, tribunal,</p>
                  <p>authority or officer.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act (including any difficulty  in relation to the transition under section 13 from one law to another   law), the President may by order do anything not inconsistent with any  such provision which appears to him to be necessary for the purpose of  removing the difficulty.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such  modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity  of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
