<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-man/act/1950/39/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-man/act/1950/39"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The West Bengal Collective Fines Act, 1950 [Manipur extension]"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-man/act/1950/39/eng@1950-11-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-man/act/1950/39/eng@1950-11-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1950-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-man/act/1950/39/eng@1950-11-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-man/act/1950/39/eng@1950-11-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The West Bengal Collective Fines Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 39 of 1950]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the imposition of collective fines.</p>
      <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for the imposition of collective fines in connection with acts prejudicially affecting the maintenance of public order;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the West Bengal Collective Fines Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Manipur.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1A">
        <num>1A.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Chief Commissioner" means the Chief Commissioner of the Union territory of Manipur; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Official Gazette" means the Manipur Gazette.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Imposition of collective fine on inhabitants of area</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If it appears to the Chief Commissioner that the inhabitants of any area are concerned in or abetting the commission of acts prejudicially affecting the maintenance of public order (which expression "public order" shall, without prejudice to the generality of its meaning, include public safety and communal harmony) or are harbouring persons concerned in the commission of such acts, or are failing to render all the assistance in their power to discover or apprehend such persons, or are suppressing material evidence of the commission of such acts, the Chief Commissioner may, by notification in the Official Gazette, impose a collective fine on the inhabitants of that area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Commissioner or any officer empowered in this behalf by the Chief Commissioner may, by general or special order, exempt any person or class or section of such inhabitants from liability to pay the whole or any part of the fine apportioned to them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate, after such enquiry as he may deem necessary by himself or some other officer deputed for the purpose, shall apportion such fine amongst the inhabitants who are liable collectively to pay it and such apportionment shall be made according to the judgment of the District Magistrate of the respective means of such inhabitants.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The portion of such fine payable by any person may be recovered--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the manner provided by the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), for the recovery of fines imposed by a Court:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Chief Commissioner may, in lieu of the rules referred to in sub-section (2) of section 386 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), make rules under this Act regulating the manner in which warrants under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of the said section of the said Code are to be executed, and for the summary determination of any claims made by any person other than the person liable to pay the fine in respect of any property attached in execution of the warrant; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>as arrears of land revenue.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Omitted</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the expression "inhabitants of an area" includes persons who themselves or by their agents or servants occupy or hold land or other immovable property within such area, and landlords who themselves or by their agents or servants collect rents from holders or occupiers of land in such area, notwithstanding that they do not actually reside therein.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Bar to legal proceedings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings whatsoever shall lie against any person for or in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Commissioner may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Savings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
