<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1994/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1994/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Kalakshetra Foundation Act, 1993"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1994/6/eng@1994-01-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1994/6/eng@1994-01-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1994-01-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1994/6/eng@1994-01-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1994/6/eng@1994-01-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Kalakshetra Foundation Act, 1993</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 6 OF 1994</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 4th January, 1994.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare Kal a kshett a of Madras to be an institution of  national importance to provide for the establishment and incorporation  of a Foundation for its administration, to make provisions for further  development of Kalakshetra in accordance with the aims and objects for  which Kalakshetra was founded and for matters connected therewith or  incide tal. thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Kalakshetra Foundation Act, 1993.-</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 29th day  of September, 1993.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of Kalakshetra as an institution of national  importance.- Whereas the objects of the institution known as</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Kalakshetra at Adyar, Madras in the State of Tamil Nadu, founded by  the late Thirumathi Rukmini Devi Atundale, are such as to make the</p>
              <p>Institution one of national importance, it is hereby declared that the  institution known as Kalakshetra is an institution of national  importance.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Academic Committee" means the Academic Committee  constituted under section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the date on which the Foundation  is established under sub- section (1) of section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Board of Trustees" means the Board of Trustees  managing the affairs of Kalakshetra under the' scheme writ'</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>approved by the Madras High Court in petition No. 716 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1985">
          <num>1985.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1985.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" constituent units" means the units of Kalakshetra  specified in the First Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Director" means the Director appointed under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>section (1) less of section 19,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Finance Committee" means the Finance Committee consti-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>tuted under sub- section (1) of section 17;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" Foundation" means the Kalakshetra Foundation  established under sub- section (1) of section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Fund" means the Fund of the Foundation referred to in  section 22;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" Governing Board means the Governing Board constituted  under section 11;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list5.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" Kalakshetra", means the institution known as, Kalakshetra  founded by the late Thirumathi Rukmini Devi Arundale, situated  at Adyar, Madras, and includes its constituent units;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list5.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list7.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" Member" means a Member of the Governing Board and in-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>cludes the Chairperson thereof;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list9.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list11">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list11.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>" regulations" means regulations made under section 32;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list11.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>" Schedule" means a Schedule annexed to this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list11.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>" State Government" means the Government of Tamil Nadu..</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE ASSETS AND PROPERTIES OF KALAKSHETRA</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE ASSETS AND PROPERTIES OF KALAKSHETRA</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Transfer to, and vesting in, the Central Government of the  assets and properties of Kalakshetra.- On the commencement of this Act  the right, title, and interest in relation to the assets and  properties of Kalakshetra specified in the Second Schedule and vested  in the Board of Trustees or any other body, in whatever capacity,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>shall Stand transferred to, and vest in, the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The right, title and  interest vested in the Central Government under section 4 shall be  deemed to include all the assets, rights, leaseholds, powers,</p>
              <p>authorities, licences and privileges; all property (movable and   immovable) including lands and buildings; musical instruments;</p>
              <p>equipments used in teaching, training and staging of performing arts;</p>
              <p>tools and facilities used in arts and crafts; costumes and  decorative items; books; stationery, furniture and other equipments  used in libraries and laboratories; works of art and artefacts;</p>
              <p>stores, automobiles and other vehicles; workshops; cash balances,</p>
              <p>funds including reserve funds, investments and all other rights and  interests arising out of such assets and properties as were  immediately before the commencement of this Act in the possession  ownership, power or control of the Board of Trustees or any other  body, in whatever capacity, and all books of account, registers, maps,</p>
              <p>plans and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All assets and properties as aforesaid which have vested in  the Central Government under section 4 shall, by force of such  vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage,</p>
              <p>charge, lien and all other encumbrances affecting them or of any  attachment, injunction, decree or order of any court or other  authority restricting the use of such assets or properties in any  manner, or appointing any receiver in respect of the whole or any part  of such assets and properties shall be deemed to have been withdrawn.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any licence, permission, authority, concession, facility,</p>
              <p>privilege, affiliation or any other instrument of similar nature  granted to the Board of Trustees or any other body, in whatever  capacity, in relation to the assets and properties of Kalakshetra or  any of its constituent units which has vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government under section 4, at any time before the commencement of  this Act and in force immediately before such commencement, shall  continue to be in force on and after such commencement in accordance  with its tenor in relation to, and for purposes of, such assets and  properties, or where the direction under section 6 has been issued,</p>
              <p>the Foundation shall be deemed to be substituted in such licence,</p>
              <p>permission, authority, concession, facility, privilege affiliation or  other instrument, as if it had been granted to the Foundation and the</p>
              <p>Foundation shall hold it for the remainder of the period for which the</p>
              <p>Board of Trustees or any other body, in whatever capacity, would have  held it under the terms thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on the commencement of this Act, any suit, appeal or  other proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any assets or pro-</p>
              <p>perties which have vested in the Central Government under section 4,</p>
              <p>instituted or preferred by the Board of Trustees is, pending, the same  shall not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially  affected by reason of such transfer and vesting, or of anything  contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be  continued, prosecuted or enforced, by the Central Government or where  the right, title and interest in relation to such assets and  properties are directed under section 6 to vest in the Foundation, by  the Foundation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Central Government to direct vesting of assets and  properties in the Foundation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained  in sections 4 and 5, the Central Government shall direct, by  notification, that the right, title and interest in relation to the  assets and properties of Kalakshetra, which had vested in it under  section 4, shall vest in the Foundation on such date, not being a date  earlier than the date of commencement of this Act, as may be specified  in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On and from the date of vesting of the right, title and  interest in relation to the assets, and properties of Kalakshetra in  the Foundation under sub- section (1)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Foundation shall be deemed to have become the owner  of the assets and properties; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the rights and liabilities of the Central Government,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>in relation to such assets and properties shall be deemed to  have become the rights and liabilities respectively of the</p>
              <p>Foundation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Duty of persons to deliver and to account for assets,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>properties, etc.-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting in the Central Government of the  assets and properties of Kalakshetra, all persons in charge of the  management of the said assets and properties immediately before the  date of such vesting, shall be bound to deliver to the Central</p>
              <p>Government or to the Foundation or to such person or body of persons  as the Central Government or the Foundation may specify in this  behalf, all assets, properties, books of account, registers or other,</p>
              <p>documents in their custody relating to the assets and properties of</p>
              <p>Kalakshetra.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who has, in his possession or control any  assets, properties, books, documents or other papers relating to</p>
              <p>Kalakshetra which have vested in the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>Foundation under this Act, and which belong to, Kalakshetra or would  have so belonged if Kalakshetra had not vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the Foundation, shall be liable to account for the said  assets, properties, books, documents and other papers to the</p>
              <p>Central Government or the Foundation, as the case may be, and  shall deliver them up to the Central Government or the Foundation  or to such person or body of persons as the Central Government or  the Foundation may specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall take or cause to be taken all  necessary steps for securing possession of assets and properties of</p>
              <p>Kalakshetra which have vested in it under section 4.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>KALAKSHETRA FOUNDATION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>KALAKSHETRA FOUNDATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and incorporation of foundation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With  effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification,</p>
              <p>appoint in this behalf there shall be established a Foundation to be  called the Kalakshetra Foundation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Foundation shall be a body corporate by the name afore-</p>
              <p>said, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to ac-</p>
              <p>quire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and  to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The office of the Foundation shall be located at</p>
              <p>Thiruvanmiyur, Madras.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>The object of foundation.- The objects of the Foundation shall  be,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to emphasise the essential unity of all true arts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to work for the recognition of the arts as vital to the  individual, national and international growth;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>to maintain the highest traditions of art and culture  in their pristine purity and in conformity with traditions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>to arrange for the training, research, study, teaching  and development of art and science, music, dance- drama, fine  arts, and Bharat- Natyam; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list0.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>to ensure that the principles of" education without  fear" and" art without vulgarity" are adhered to in the  activities of the Foundation and not to permit any deviation  from these high ideals.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Authorities of the Foundation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Foundation shall  consist of the following, authorities, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Governing Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Academic Committee; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Finance Committee.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discharge of functions and exercise of powers under  this Act, the authorities referred to in sub- section (1) shall be  guided by the objects specified in section 9.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>The Governing Board.- The Governing Board shall consist of-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairperson, who shall be a person of high eminence in  public life, to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>not more than twelve Members to be nominated by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government from amongst persons who-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>have rendered valuable service to Kalakshetra;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>have been connected with, or have knowledge of  art, culture, folk arts and crafts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>are eminent artistes; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>are patrons of art and culture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two persons, possessing one or more of the  qualifications referred to in sub- clauses (i) to (ii) of  clause (b), to be nominated by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>two officers of the Central Government, not below the  rank of a Deputy Secretary, to be nominated by that</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government, to represent the Ministry of the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government dealing with culture, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>one officer of the State Government, not below the rank  of Joint Secretary, to be nominated by that Government, to  represent the Department of Education of that Government, ex-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>officio; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the Director, ex officio.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Terms of office of Members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the</p>
              <p>Members shall be five years from the date of constitution of the</p>
              <p>Governing Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a casual Vacancy occurs in the office of a Member  nominated under clause (b) or clause (c) of section 11, whether by  reason of his death, resignation or inability to discharge his func-</p>
              <p>tions owing to illness or other incapacity, such vacancy shall be  filled by making fresh nomination and the Member so nominated shall  hold office for the remainder of the term of office of the Member in  whose place he is so nominated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing, Member shall be eligible for renomination,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Member may resign his office by writing under his hand  addressed to the Central Government but shall continue in office until  his resignation is accepted by that Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Members nominated under clauses (b) and (c) of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, shall be entitled to such allowances as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Governing Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governing Board shall  meet, at least twice in a year at Madras at such time as may be fixed  by the Chairperson of the Governing Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All decisions at the meeting of the Governing Board shall be  taken by majority of the Members present and voting:</p>
              <p>Provided that in the case of equality of votes the Chairperson of  the Governing Board shall have a casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governing Board shall observe such procedure in regard  to the transaction of its business at its meetings (including the   quorum at its meetings) as may be specified by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Governing Board shall be invalid  merely by reason of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Governing Board; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.4.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the nomination of a person acting as a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.4.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Member of the Governing Board; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.4.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Governing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Board not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Governing Board to be the supreme authority of Foundation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governing Board shall be the supreme authority of the</p>
              <p>Foundation and the general superintendence, direction and management  of the affairs of the Foundation shall vest in the Governing Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governing Board shall exercise such powers and discharge  such functions as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Academic Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Academic Committee shall  consist of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Director;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Heads of the constituent units;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>three distinguished persons in the field of art and  culture including dance, music, folk arts and crafts, to be  culture including dance, music, folk arts and crafts, to be</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>one person to be nominated by the State Government, re-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>presenting the Department of Education of that Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tenure of office and other terms and conditions of the  members of the Academic Committee shall be such as may be specified by  regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Academic Committee shall observe such procedure in  regard to the transaction of its business at its meetings (including   the quorum at the meetings) as may be specified by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of Academic Committee.- The Academic</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Committee shall be responsible for the maintenance of standards of  education, training and examination conducted by the constituent units  and shall exercise such other powers and perform such other functions  as may be assigned to it, from time to time, by the Governing Board.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Finance Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Finance committee shall consist  of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Financial Adviser to the Government of India or his  nominee in the Ministry of the Central Government dealing  with culture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an officer of the Central Government, not below the  rank of a Deputy Secretary, to be nominated by that</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>an officer of the State Government not below the rank  of a Deputy Secretary, to be nominated by that Government,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>representing the Department of Finance of that Government;</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Director.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Finance committee shall observe such procedure in regard  to the transaction of the business at its meetings as may be specified  by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of Finance Committee.- The Finance</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Committee shall-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>scrutinise the annual statement of accounts and budget  estimates of the Foundation prepared by the Director and make  recommendations to the Governing Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the limits of the recurring and non- recurring  expenditure of the Foundation for each financial year;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>review the financial position of the Foundation from  time to time and have an internal audit conducted; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>perform such other functions as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Appointment and duties of Director.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government shall, by notification, appoint a Direct- or who shall be  the principal executive officer of the Foundation and who shall be  responsible for the proper administration of the affairs of the</p>
              <p>Foundation and its day- to- day management and shall exercise such other  powers and perform such other duties as may be assigned to him by the</p>
              <p>Governing Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director shall prepare the annual statement of accounts  and budget estimates of the Foundation for scrutiny by the Finance</p>
              <p>Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director shall be a whole time employee of the</p>
              <p>Foundation and shall be entitled to such salary and allowances out of  the Fund and shall be subject to such conditions of service in respect  of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters, as may be  prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of service of existing employees.- On and from the  appointed day, every officer or other employee, employed immediately  before the appointed day in connection with the affairs of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Kalakshetra shall become an officer or other employee of the</p>
              <p>Foundation and shall hold office by the same tenure and remuneration  and on the same terms and conditions as to pension, gratuity and other  matters as he would have held under the Board of Trustees or any  other body, in whatever, capacity, if this Act had not been passed and  shall continue to do so, unless and until his employment in the</p>
              <p>Foundation is terminated or until his tenure, remuneration and other  terms and conditions are duly altered by the Foundation:</p>
              <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and other terms and condi-</p>
              <p>tions of service of any such officer or employee shall not be altered  to his disadvantage without the previous approval of Central</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Grants by Central Government to the Foundation.- For the  purpose of enabling the Foundation to discharge its functions  efficiently under this Act, the Central Government may, after due  appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Foundation in each financial year, such sums of money, on such terms  and conditions as that Government may determine, by way of grant, loan  or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Fund of the Foundation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Foundation shall have its  own Fund; and all sums which may, from time to time, be paid to it by  the Central Government and all receipts of the Foundation (including  any sum to which the State Government or any other authority or person   may pay to the Foundation) shall be credited to the Fund and all  payments by the Foundation shall be made therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All moneys belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in, such  banks or invested in such manner as may, subject to the approval of  the Central Government, be decided by the Governing Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Foundation may spend such sums as it may think fit for  performing its functions under this Act, and such sums shall be  treated as expenditure payable out of the Fund of the Foundation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Budget.- The Foundation shall prepare, in such form and at  such time each year, as may be prescribed, the budget in respect of  the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and  expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit of the Foundation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Foundation  shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare  an annual statement of accounts including the balance sheet in such  form as may be approved by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
              <p>India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Foundation shall be audited by the Comp-</p>
              <p>troller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by  him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Foundation  to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Foundation shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
              <p>India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts,</p>
              <p>and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of  books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and  to inspect the office of the Foundation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Foundation as certified by the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General India or any person appointed by him  in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be  forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall  cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Duty to furnish returns, annual reports, etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Foundation shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in  such form and in such manner, as may be prescribed, or as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may direct, such returns and statements and such  particulars in regard to any proposed or existing programme for the  promotion and development of the objects of the Foundation, as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, from time to time, direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
              <p>Foundation shall, as soon as possible after the end of each financial  year, submit to the Central Government an annual report in such form  and before such date as may be prescribed, giving a true and full  account of its activities and programmes during the previous year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be  laid, as soon as may be, after it is received, before each House of</p>
              <p>Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Prior approval of the Central Government for alienation of  property.- The Foundation shall not, except with the previous approval  of the Central Government, sell or otherwise dispose of any property  vested in the Foundation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to give directions to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Foundation.-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that  it is necessary so to do in the public interest, issue, for reasons to  be recorded and communicated to the Foundation, such directions as it  thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers,</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>such directions may include directions requiring the Foundation-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to make or amend any regulation within such period as  may be specified in the direction; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to give priority to the work undertaken or to be  undertaken by the Foundation in such manner as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government may think fit to specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any direction issued under this section shall have effect  notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in  force or in the memorandum or regulations of the Kalakshetra Society.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Dissolution of the Foundation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government  may, by notification and for reasons to be specified therein,</p>
              <p>dissolve, the Foundation from such date and for such period as may be  specified in the notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that before issuing any such notification, the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Foundation to  make representation against the proposed dissolution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When the, Foundation is dissolved under sub- section (1),-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all members of the Governing Board, Academic Committee  and the Finance Committee, notwithstanding that the terms of  their office had not expired, shall, from the date of  dissolution, vacate their offices as such members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all powers and duties of the Governing Board, Academic</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Committee and the Finance Committee shall, during the period  of dissolution, be exercised and performed by such person or  persons as the Central Government may appoint in this behalf;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all properties and assets vested in the Foundation  shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>as soon as the period of dissolution expires, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Foundation shall be reconstituted in accordance with the,</p>
              <p>provisions of this Act</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit  prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government or any officer of that Government or the Foundation or</p>
              <p>Member or Director or any officer of the Foundation for anything which  is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity.- Every Member of the Governing Board, Academic</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Committee and the Finance Committee and the Director of the Foundation  shall be indemnified by the Foundation against all losses and expenses  incurred by them in relation to the discharge of their duties, except  such as are caused by their wilful act or default.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the allowances to the Members under sub- section (5) of  section 12;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the powers which the Governing Board shall exercise and  the functions which it shall discharge under sub- section (2)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-31.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>of section 14;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>functions to be performed by the Finance Committee,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-31.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>under clause (iv) of section 18;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the salary and allowances and other terms and  conditions of service of the Director under sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 19;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form and the manner in which the budget is to be  prepared by the Governing Board under section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.3.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the form and the manner in which, and the time at which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-31.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>the returns, statements and the annual report shall be  prepared under section 25;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.3.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Foundation may make  thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its functions under this</p>
              <p>Act:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,</p>
              <p>such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the management of the properties and funds, affairs and  works of the Foundation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the procedure in regard to transaction of business of the  regard to transaction of business of the Governing Board</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Academic Committee (including quorum at their meetings) the  transaction of business of the Finance Committee under sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>section (3) of section 13, sub- section (3) of section 15 and  sub- section (2) of section 17;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>creation or abolition of posts and the procedure for  appointment of the professional, administrative and  ministerial staff;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the tenure of office and other terms and conditions of  the members of the Academic Committee under sub- section (2)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>of section 15; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list8.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of accounts, registers and other  records of the Foundation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No regulation made by the Foundation shall have effect until  it has been approved by the Central Government and published in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, and the Central Government, in approving the regula-</p>
              <p>tion, may make changes therein which appear to it to be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.- Every  rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be, compri-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>sed in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, be-</p>
              <p>fore the expiry of the session immediately following the session or  the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the  rule or regulation, should not be made, the rule or regulation shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises  in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act,</p>
              <p>remove the difficulty:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years, from the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid a soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Kalakshetra Foundation Ordinance,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1993">
          <num>1993.</num>
          <heading>(Ord. 31 of 1993.) is hereby repealed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1993.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the Ordinance so repealed, shall be deemed to have been  done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
