<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1965/14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1965/14"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Punjab Industrial Establishments (National And Festival Holidays And Casual And Sick Leave) Act, 1965 [Haryana Version]"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Punjab Industrial Establishments (National And Festival Holidays And Casual And Sick Leave) Act, 1965 [Haryana Version]</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>(PUNJAB ACT NO. 14 OF 1965)</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An  ACT to provide for the grant of National and Festival Holidays and  Casual and Sick Leave to persons employed in Industrial Establishments in the State of Haryana.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Punjab in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows :—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Punjab Industrial Establishments  (National and Festival Holidays and Casual and Sick Leave) Act, 1965.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Haryana.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the first day of July, 1965.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“day” means a period of twenty-four hours beginning at mid-night :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that in the case of a worker who works in a shift which extends beyond mid-night, such period of twenty-four hours shall begin when his shift ends.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“worker” means—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any person (including an apprentice) employed in any industrial establishment to do any skilled or unskilled, manual, supervisory, technical or clerical work for hire or reward, whether the terms of employment be expressed or implied; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any other person employed in any industrial establishment whom the Government may, by notification, declare to be a worker for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“employer”, when used in relation to an industrial establishment, means the person who has ultimate control over the affairs of the industrial establishment, and where the affairs of any industrial establishment are entrusted to any other person, whether called a managing agent, manager, superintendent or by any other name, such other person shall be deemed to be the employer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Government” means the Government of the State of Haryana;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>“industrial establishment” means—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any factory as defined in clause (m) of section 2 of the Factories Act, 1948 (Central Act 63 of 1948), or any place which is deemed to be a factory under sub-section (2) of section 85 of that Act; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any plantation as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (Central Act 69 of 1951);</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“Inspector” means an Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) of section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“wages” means all remuneration (whether byway of salary, allowances or otherwise) expressed in terms of money or capable of being so expressed which would, if the terms of employment, express or implied, were fulfilled, be payable to a worker in respect of his employment or of work done in such employment, but does not include—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any bonus;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the value of any house accommodation, supply of light, water, medical facilities or other amenity or of any service or of any concessional supply of foodgrains or other articles;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>any contribution paid or payable by the employer—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c.list2.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to any pension or provident fund, and the interest which may have accrued thereon; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c.list2.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>for the benefit of the worker under any law for the time being in force;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any travelling allowance or the value of any travelling concession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any sum paid to the worker to defray special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his employment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any gratuity payable on the termination of employment.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>National and festival holidays.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every worker shall, in each calendar year, be allowed in such manner and on such conditions as may be prescribed—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>three national holidays of one whole day each on the 26th January, 15th August and 2nd October; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>five other holidays on any of the festivals specified in the Schedule appended to this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that for purposes of clause (b), where at least ten per centum of the workers of an industrial establishment so desire, they may, in lieu of the festival holiday, avail of two half holidays on any of the festival days of their choice specified in such Schedule after settlement in this behalf has been made between the employer and the representatives of the workers in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may by notification add to the Schedule appended to this Act any festival, and thereupon the Schedule shall be deemed to be amended accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Casual and sick leave.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every worker shall in each calendar year, be allowed by the employer casual leave for seven days and sick leave for fourteen days in such manner and on such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
            <p>Explanation.— For purposes of this section, such conditions may provide that one kind of leave shall not be linked with another kind of leave, whether due under this Act, or under any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Wages.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any contract to the contrary, every worker shall,</p>
            <p>for each of the national and festival holidays and of the days of casual or sick leave, be paid by the employer wages at a rate equivalent to his average daily wage:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no worker shall be entitled to be paid such wages for any holiday or leave, other than a national holiday, if his name was not on the rolls of the industrial establishment continuously for a period of one month immediately preceding such holiday or leave;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where a worker is entitled to sickness benefit under the Employees’ State Insurance Act, 1948, or sickness allowance under the Plantations Labour Act, 1951, he shall not be entitled to be paid such wages for the days of sick leave allowed to him under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where a worker is not entitled to such sickness benefit or sickness allowance, he shall be paid wages for the days of sick leave allowed to him under this Act at a rate equivalent to one-half of his average daily wage.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a worker works on any holiday allowed under section 3, he shall, at his option, be entitled to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>twice his average daily wage for that day, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his average daily wage for that day and a substituted holiday with his average daily wage on any other day within ninety days from the day on which he so works.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.— For the purposes of this section, the average daily wage of a worker shall be computed on the basis of his total full-time wages during the preceding three calendar months, exclusive of any over-time wages, if any :</p>
            <p>Provided that the average daily wage of a worker who is paid wages by the day or at piece rate shall be computed on the basis of his wages for the days on which he actually worked during the month immediately preceding such holiday or leave.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Account of holidays and leave to be kept</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall keep in such form and manner as may be prescribed an account of festival holidays, casual leave and sick leave of every worker and every worker shall have access to such account.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, appoint such persons or class of persons as it may think fit to be Inspectors for carrying out the purposes of this Act for such areas as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power of Inspectors</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made by the Government in this behalf, an Inspector may, within the area for which he is appointed—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enter at all reasonable times any place which is, or which he has reason, to believe to be, an industrial establishment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>make such examination of the premises and of any prescribed registers, records and notices and take on the spot or otherwise the evidence of such person as he may deem necessary for carrying out the purposes of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>exercise such other powers as may be necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no one shall be required under this section to answer any question or give any evidence tending to incriminate himself.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any employer who contravenes any of the provisions of sections 3, 4, 5 and 6 shall be punishable, for the first offence, with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and for a second or subsequent offences, with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to recover wages</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a magistrate while convicting an employer under section 9 is satisfied that the worker has not been paid his due wages under this Act, the amount of which shall be determined by the magistrate, he shall direct the employer to pay such wages to the worker.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of wages determined under sub-section (1)shall, for the purposes of recovery be deemed to be a fine imposed under this Act, in addition to the penalty imposed under section 9 and shall be realised as such.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for obstructing inspector</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever willfully obstructs an Inspector in the exercise of any power conferred on him by or under this Act, or intentionally omits to produce on demand in writing by an Inspector any register, record or notice in his custody which may be required to be kept in pursuance of this Act or of any rule made thereunder shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act or the rules made thereunder except on a complaint in writing by an aggrieved person or an Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court below that of a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any worker drawing wages exceeding five hundred rupees per mensem and employed mainly in a managerial, administrative or supervisory capacity;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any worker employed in any industrial establishment under the control of the Government or Central Government or any State Government to whom the Civil Service Rules or any other similar rules or regulations notified in this behalf by the Government, Central Government or any State Government as the case may be, apply; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any mine or oil field.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may in public interest by notification exempt either permanently or for any specified period any class of industrial establishments from all or any of the provisions of this Act subject to such conditions as the Government may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Rights and privileges under other laws, etc., not affected.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall affect any rights or privileges which any worker is entitled to receive under any other law, award, contract, custom or usage, if such rights or privileges are more favourable to him than those to which he would be entitled under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification and after previous publication, make rules for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which, and the conditions which, national and other holidays shall be allowed to workers under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the number of days for which, the manner in which, and the conditions on which, casual and sick leave shall be allowed to workers under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which an account of festival holidays, casual leave and sick leave of workers shall be maintained by employers under section 6.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making a rule under this Act, the Government may provide that a contravention thereof shall be publishable with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before the House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of ten days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, the House agrees in making any modification in the rule or the House agrees that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of any thing previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1965/14/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1965/14"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1965/14/eng@2017-03-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-02" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>See section 3(1) (b)</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>New Year’s Day</p>
                <p>Basant Panchmi.</p>
                <p>Guru Ravi Dass’s Birthday.</p>
                <p>Shivratri.</p>
                <p>Holi.</p>
                <p>Hola.</p>
                <p>Id-ul-Fitr.</p>
                <p>Ram Naumi.</p>
                <p>Lord Mahavir’s Birthday.</p>
                <p>Good Friday.</p>
                <p>Baisakhi.</p>
                <p>Id-ul-Zuha.</p>
                <p>Guru Arjan Dev’s Martyrdom Day.</p>
                <p>Muharrum.</p>
                <p>Milad-ul-Nabi.</p>
                <p>Janam Ashatami.</p>
                <p>Dussehra.</p>
                <p>Maharishi Balmik’s Birthday.</p>
                <p>Diwali.</p>
                <p>Lala Lajpat Rai’s Death Anniversary.</p>
                <p>Guru Nank’s Birthday.</p>
                <p>Guru Teg Bahadur’s Martyrdom Day.</p>
                <p>Christmas Day.</p>
                <p>Jor Mela Fatehgarh Sahib.</p>
                <p>Guru Gobind Singh’s Birthday.</p>
                <p>Vishwa Karma Jainti.</p>
                <p>May Day.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
