<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Seaward Artilery Practice Act, 1949"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/8/eng@1949-02-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/8/eng@1949-02-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1949-02-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/8/eng@1949-02-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/8/eng@1949-02-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Seaward Artilery Practice Act, 1949</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 8 OF 1949</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 17th February, 1949.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide facilities for carrying out seaward artillery  practice.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide facilities for carrying out  seaward artillery practice;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and application.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Seaward Artillery Practice Act, 1949.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to all the State  which have a sea coast, and  applies also to, and to persons on, any vessel which is registered in</p>
            <p>India or which belongs to any person domiciled in India, wherever it  may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything  repugnant in the subject or context,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" notified area" means any part of the area of the sea  and the shores adjoining that area which may be specified in  this behalf by notification under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" seaward artillery practice" means artillery practice  or coastal firing towards the sea, whether within or beyond  the territorial waters and includes air armament practice;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" vessel" includes any ship, boat, country craft or any  other description of vessel.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government. to authorise seaward artillery  practice.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, authorise the carrying out of seaward artillery  practice</p>
            <p>over such area and during such period or periods as may be specified  in the notification:</p>
            <p>Provided that there shall be an interval of at least fourteen  days between the date of publication of such notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette and the date of carrying out of seaward artillery  practice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall, as soon as may be, after the  publication of a notification under sub- section (1), cause the  substance thereof to be published-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in some newspaper circulating in, and in the language  commonly understood in, the area specified in the noti-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>fication; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in such other manner as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises whether the substance of a  notification under sub- section (1) was published as required by sub-</p>
            <p>section (2), a certificate by the Collector of the district in which  the notified area is situate that the substance of the notification  was so published, shall be conclusive.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3A">
        <num>3A.</num>
        <heading>Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the power to issue  notifications under section 3 shall, subject to such conditions, if  any, as may be specified in the notification, be exercisable also by  such State Government as may be specified therein.]</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Powers exercisable for purpose of seaward artillery  practice.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>After a notification under sub- section (1) of section 3  has been issued, such persons as are included in the forces engaged in  seaward artillery practice may within the notified area and during the  period or periods specified in the notification-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>give directions prohibiting or restricting the use of  the notified area or any part thereof including the use of  any part of the area of the sea by any vessel, and take such  further measures as may be necessary to ensure that no  unauthorised person enters, passes over or remains in the  notified area or part thereof, as the case may be, during  such practice, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>carry out seaward artillery practice with lethal  missiles.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Officer Commanding the forces engaged in any such prac-</p>
            <p>tice may declare any portion of the notified area to be a danger zone,</p>
            <p>and thereupon the Collector shall, on application made to him by the</p>
            <p>Officer Commanding the forces engaged in the practice, prohibit the  entry into and secure, with the assistance of the naval or military  authorities concerned, the removal from such danger zone of any</p>
            <p>person, property or vessel during the times when the discharge of  lethal missiles is taking place or there is danger to life or  property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Compensation. Where by reason of a notification issued  under section 3 the carrying out of seaward artillery practice is  authorised in any notified area, compensation shall be payable for any  damage to person or property or interference with rights or privileges  arising from such practice, including expenses reasonably incurred in  protecting person, property, rights or privileges.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Method of assessing compensation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of  determining the amount of any compensation payable under section 5,</p>
            <p>the Collector of the district in which any notified area is situate  shall depute one or more Revenue Officers to accompany the forces  engaged in the practice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Revenue Officer so deputed shall consider all claims for  compensation under section 5 and determine, on local investigation and  after affording the claimant an opportunity of being heard, the amount  of compensation, if any, which shall be awarded in each case; and  shall disburse on the spot to the claimant compensation so determined  as payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Compensation payable under sub- section (2) shall include  compensation for the removal from any portion of a notified area  declared to be a danger zone of any person, property or vessel and for  any damage sustained in the course of any such removal. The compen-</p>
            <p>sation for removal will be disbursed on the spot at not less than the  minimum prescribed rates before the removal is enforced.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any claimant dissatisfied with the refusal of the Revenue</p>
            <p>Officer to award him compensation or with the amount of compensation  awarded to him by the Revenue Officer, may, at any time within one  month of the communication to him of the decision of the Revenue</p>
            <p>Officer, prefer an appeal to the Collector against the decision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Collector on such appeal shall be final  and no suit shall lie in any Civil Court in respect of any matter  decided by the Collector under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No fee shall be charged in connection with any claim,</p>
            <p>notice, appeal, application or document filed before the Revenue</p>
            <p>Officer or the Collector under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Offences. If within a notified area and during any period  specified in a notification issued under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 3,</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>any person-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>wilfully obstructs or interferes with the carrying out  of seaward artillery practice, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>without due authority enters or remains in any camp, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>without due authority enters or remains in any area  declared to be a danger zone at a time when entry thereto is  prohibited, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>without due authority interferes with any flag or mark  or target or buoy or any apparatus used for the purposes of  seaward artillery practice,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with fine which may extend to twenty rupees or  with imprisonment which may extend to fifteen days, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under this act.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit,</p>
            <p>procesution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for  anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in  pursuance of this Act or any rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except as otherwise provided in this Act, no suit or other  legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the State</p>
            <p>Government in respect of any damage caused or likely to be caused by  anything in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of  this Act or any rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for giving effect to  the provisions of this Act and different rules may be made for  different State or for different areas thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the substance of a notification  under section 3 may be published;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>regulating the use under this Act of the notified area  for seaward artillery practice in such manner as to secure  the public against danger, and to enable the practice to be  carried out with the minimum inconvenience to the inhabitants  of the area affected;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the minimum rates at which compensation shall be  payable under sub- section (3) of section 6, and generally  regarding the making of claims for compensation, the  procedure to be followed by the authorities granting the  compensation, the expeditious settlement of claims and the  filing of appeals from original awards of compensation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the principles to be followed in assessing the amount of  compensation to be awarded under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
