<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Companies (Profits) Surtax Act, 1964"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1964-05-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Companies (Profits) Surtax Act, 1964</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 7 OF 1964</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 2nd May, 1964.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to impose a special tax on the profits of certain  companies.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifteenth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Companies (Profits) Surtax Act, 1964.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Advance surtax" means the surtax payable under  section 7A;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>] assessee" means a person by whom surtax or any other  sum of money is payable under this Act and includes every  person in respect of whom any proceeding under this Act has  been taken for the assessment of his chargeable profits or</p>
            <p>, of the amount of refund due to him or of the chargeable  profits of any other person in respect of which he is  assessable or of the amount of refund due to such other  person;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>assessment" includes re- assessment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months  commencing on the 1st day of April, every year;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes  constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963;</p>
            <p>(54 of 1963).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" chargeable profits" means the total income of an  assessee computed under the Income- tax Act, 1961 (43 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1961">
        <num>1961.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1961.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>) for any previous year or years, as the case may be, and  adjusted in accordance with the provisions of the First</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-">
      <doc name="">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7"/>
              <FRBRalias value=";"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="">
            <subsection id=".6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, 1961; (43 of</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-1961">
              <num>1961.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1961.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-1961.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                  <p>Act;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1961.7A">
                <num>(7A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>" regular assessment" means an assessment made under  section 6;"]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1961.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>statutory deduction" means an amount equal to    fifteen per cent.] of the capital of the company as  computed in accordance with the provisions of the Second</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich">
      <doc name="oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", or an amount of two hundred thousand rupees, which-"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich">
            <heading>ever is greater:</heading>
            <paragraph id="oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Provided that where the previous year is longer or shorter  than a period of twelve months, the aforesaid amount of</p>
                <p>fifteen per cent.] or, as the case may be, of two hundred  thousand rupees shall be increased or decreased propor-</p>
                <p>tionately:</p>
                <p>Provided further that where a company has different previous  years in respect of its income, profits and gains, the  aforesaid increase or decrease, as the case may be, shall be  calculated with reference to the length of the previous year  of the longest duration; and</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="oranamountoftwohundredthousandrupeeswhich.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>all other words and expressions used herein but not  defined and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the  meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading/>
              <subsection id="section-3.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tax authorities. The income- tax authorities specified  in section 116 of the come- tax Act shall be the authorities for the  purpose of this the Act and every such authority shall exercise the  power and perform the functions of a tax authority under this Act in  respect of any company, and for this purpose his jurisdiction under  this Act shall be the same as he has under the Income- Tax Act by  virtue of orders or directions issued under section 120 of that Act</p>
                  <p>(Including orders or directions assigning concurrent jurisdiction) or  under any other provision of that Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-3.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board may, from time to time, issue such  orders, instructions and directions to other tax authorities as it may  deem fit for the proper administration of this Act, and such  authorities and all other persons employed in the execution of this</p>
                  <p>Act shall observe and follow such orders, instructions and directions  of the Board:</p>
                  <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be  issued-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>so as to require any tax authority to make a particular  assessment or to dispose of a particular case in a particular  manner; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>so as to interfere with the discretion of the Commis-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>sioner (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate  functions."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Charge of tax. Subject to the provisions contained in this Act,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>there shall be charged on every company for every assessment year  commencing on and from the first day of April, 1964,  but before the  first day of April, 1988"] a tax (in- this Act referred to as the   surtax) in respect of so much of its chargeable profits of the  previous year or previous years, as the case may be, as exceed the  statutory deduction, at the rate or rates specified in the Third</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in/act/1980/01/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in/act/1980/01"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Return of chargeable profit.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In the case of every  company whose chargeable profits assessable under this Act exceeded  during the previous year the amount of. statutory deduction, its  principal officer, or where in the case of a non- resident company any  person has been treated as its agent under section 163 of the Income-</p>
                  <p>tax Act, such person, shall furnish a return of the chargeable profits  of the company during the previous year in the prescribed form and  verified in the prescribed manner and setting forth such other  particulars as may be prescribed, before the 30th day of September of  the assessment year:</p>
                  <p>Provided that on an application made in this behalf, the Income-</p>
                  <p>tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for the furnishing  of the return.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In the case of any company which in the Income- tax Officer' s  opinion is assessable under this Act, the Income- tax Officer may,</p>
                  <p>before the end of the relevant assessment year, serve a notice upon  its principal officer, or where in the case of a non- resident company  any person has been treated as its agent under section 163 of the</p>
                  <p>Income- tax Act, upon such person, requiring him to furnish within  thirty days from the date of service of the notice a return of the  chargeable profits of the company during the previous year in the  prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner and setting  forth such other particulars as may be prescribed:</p>
                  <p>Provided that on an application made in this behalf, the Income-</p>
                  <p>tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for the furnishing  of the return.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any assessee who has not furnished a return during the time  allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or having furnished  a return under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) discovers any  omission or wrong statement therein, may furnish a return or a revised  return, as the case may be, at any time before the assessment is made.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Assessment.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the purposes of making an assessment under  this Act, the Income- tax Officer may serve on any, person who has  furnished a return under sub- section (1) of section 5 or upon whom a  notice has been served under' sub- section (2) of section 5 (whether a   return has been furnished or not) a notice requiring him on a date  therein to be specified, to produce or cause to be produced such  accounts or documents or evidence as the Income- tax officer may  require for the purposes of this Act and may from time to time serve  further notices requiring the production of such further accounts or  documents or other evidence as he may require.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Income- tax Officer, after considering such accounts,</p>
                  <p>documents or evidence, if any, as he has obtained under subsection (1)</p>
                  <p>and after taking into account any relevant material which he has  gathered, shall, by an order in writing, assess the chargeable profits  and the amount of the surtax payable on the basis of such assessment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Provisional assessment.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Income- tax Officer, before  proceeding to make an assessment under section 6 (in this section   referred to as the regular assessment) may, at any time after the  expiry of the period allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2)</p>
                  <p>of section 5 for the furnishing of the return and whether the return  has or has not been furnished, proceed to make in a summary manner a  provisional assessment of the chargeable profits and the amount of the  surtax payable thereon.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Before making such provisional assessment, the Income- tax</p>
                  <p>Officer shall give notice in the prescribed form to the person on whom  the provisional assessment is to be made of his intension to do so,</p>
                  <p>and shall with the notice forward a statement of the amount of the  proposed assessment, and the said person shall be entitled to deliver  to the Income- tax Officer at any time within fourteen days of the  service of the said notice a statement of his objections, if any, to  the amount of the proposed assessment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On expiry of the said fourteen days from the date of service  of the notice referred to in sub- section (2), or earlier, if the  assessee agrees to the proposed provisional assessment, the Income- tax</p>
                  <p>Officer may, after taking into account the objections, if any, made  under sub- section (2), make a provisional assessment, and shall  furnish a copy of the order of the assessment to the assessee:</p>
                  <p>Provided that assent to the amount of the provisional assessment,</p>
                  <p>or failure to make objection to it, shall in no way prejudice the  assessee in relation to the regular assessment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>There shall be no right of appeal against a provisional  assessment made under this section,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>After a regular assessment has been made, any amount paid or  deemed to have been paid towards the provisional assessment made under  this section shall be deemed to have been paid towards the regular  assessment; and where the amount paid or deemed to have been paid  towards the provisional assessment exceeds the amount payable under  the regular assessment, the excess shall be refunded to the assessee.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7A">
              <num>7A.</num>
              <heading>Advance payment of surtax.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-7A.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In this section,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7A.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>" chargeable amount", in relation to any previous year,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-7A.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>means so much of the chargeable profits of the previous year  as exceed the statutory deduction;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7A.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>" current chargeable amount", in relation to the advance  surtax payable by a company during any financial year, means  the chargeable amount of the company of the, period which  would be the previous year for the assessment year  immediately following that financial year.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Surtax shall be payable, in accordance' with the pro-</p>
                  <p>visions of-- this section, in advance during the financial  year in respect of the chargeable amount of the period which  would be the previous year for the immediately following  assessment year.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7A.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-7A.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The amount of advance surtax payable by an assessee in  the financial year shall be computed as follows:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7A.3.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the chargeable amount of the latest previous year in  respect of which the assessee has been assessed by way of  regular assessment shall first be ascertained;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7A.3.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in a case where the chargeable amount of the latest  previous year being a year later than the previous year  referred to in clause (a) on the basis of which a  provisional assessment has been made under section 7. exceeds  the chargeable amount referred to in clause, (a), the,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>chargeable, amount referred to in clause (a) shall be sub-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-7A.3.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>stituted by the chargeable amount on the basis of which such  provisional assessment has been made;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7A.3.list4.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>surtax shall be calculated on the chargeable amount  referred to in clause (a) or, as the case may be, in clause</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7A.3.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>, at the rates specified in the Third Schedule.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7A.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the provisions of this section, advance sur-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-7A.4.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>tax shall be payable in three equal instalments on the  following dates during the financial year, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7A.4.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the 15th day of June, the 15th day of September and the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15th">
              <num>15th.</num>
              <heading>day of December, in the case of an assessee whose chargeable amount to the extent of 75 per cent. thereof  or more is derived from a source or sources for which the  previous year (relevant to the assessment year next following   the financial year aforesaid) ends on or before the 31st day  of December;</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-15th.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-15th.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the 15th day of September, the 15th day of December  and the 15th day of March, in any other case.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that where, in respect of any class of assessees, the</p>
                  <p>Board has, in exercise of the powers conferred by the proviso to sub-</p>
                  <p>section (1) of section 211 of the Income- tax Act, authorised the  payment of the last instalment of advance tax on the 15th day of March  during the financial year instead of on the 15th day of December, the  last instalment of advance surtax in the case of such assessees shall  also be payable on the 15th day of March during the financial year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-15th.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.5.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Every company shall, in each financial year, on or before  the date on which the first instalment, or where it has not previously  been assessed by way of regular assessment under this Act, on or  before the date on which the last instalment, of advance surtax is due  in its case under sub- section (4), if it is likely to have any current  chargeable amount, send to the Income- tax Officer,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15th.5.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>where it has been previously assessed by way of regular  assessment under this Act, a statement of advance surtax  payable by it computed in the manner laid down in sub- section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>, or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15th.3.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-15th.3.list1.b.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>where it has not previously been assessed by way of  regular assessment under this Act, an estimate of--</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-15th.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                          <num>(i)</num>
                          <p>the current chargeable amount and</p>
                        </item>
                        <item id="section-15th.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                          <num>(ii)</num>
                          <p>the advance surtax payable by it on the amount  specified in (i) above calculated in the, manner laid  down in sub- section (3),</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.3.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>and shall pay such amount of advance surtax,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15th.3.list3.I">
                      <num>(I)</num>
                      <p>in a case falling under clause (a), as accords  with the statement in equal instalments on the dates  applicable in its case under sub- section (4); and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-15th.3.list3.II">
                      <num>(II)</num>
                      <p>in a case falling under clause (b), as accords  with the estimate in equal instalments on such of the  dates applicable in its case as have not expired, or in  one sum if only the last of such dates has not expired.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where a company which is required to send a statement under  clause (a) of sub- section (5) estimates on or before the date on which  the first instalment of advance surtax is due in its case under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (4) that, by reason of its current chargeable amount being  likely to be less than the chargeable amount on which advance surtax  is payable by it under subsection (5) or for any other reason, the  amount of advance surtax computed in the manner laid down in sub-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.6.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>section (3) on the current chargeable amount would be less than the  amount of advance surtax payable by it under sub- section (5), it may  send to the Income- tax Officer, in lieu of such statement, an estimate  of-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15th.6.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the current chargeable amount, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-15th.6.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the advance surtax payable by it on the current  chargeable amount calculated in the manner laid down in sub-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>section (3),</p>
                  <p>and shall pay such amount of advance surtax as accords with its  estimate in equal instalments on the dates applicable in its case  under sub- section (4).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where a company which has sent a statement under clause (a)</p>
                  <p>of subsection (5) estimates on or before the date on which the last  instalment of advance surtax is due in its case that, by reason of its  current chargeable amount being likely to be less than the chargeable  amount on which advance surtax is payable by it under sub- section (5)</p>
                  <p>or for any other reason, the amount of advance surtax computed in the  manner laid down in sub- section (3) on the current chargeable amount  would be less than the amount of advance surtax payable by it under-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.7.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>sub- section (5), it may, at its option, send to the Income- tax Officer  an estimate of--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15th.7.list4.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the current chargeable amount, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-15th.7.list4.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the advance surtax payable by it on the current  chargeable amount calculated in the manner laid down in sub-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>section (3),</p>
                  <p>and shall pay such amount of advance surtax as accords with its  estimate in equal instalments on such of the dates applicable in its  case under subsection (4) as have not expired, or in one sum if only  the last of such dates has not expired.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In the case of any company which is liable to pay advance  surtax under subsection (5) or sub- section (6) or, as the case may be,</p>
                  <p>sub- section (7), if, by reason of the current chargeable amount being  likely to be greater than the chargeable amount on which the advance  surtax so payable by it has been computed or for any other reason, the  amount of advance surtax computed in the manner laid down in sub-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-15th.8.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>section (3) on the current chargeable amount (which shall be estimated   by the company) exceeds the amount of advance surtax so payable by it  by more than twenty per cent. of the latter amount, it shall, on or  before the date on which the last instalment of advance surtax is  payable by it, send to the Income- tax Officer an estimate of-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15th.8.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the current chargeable amount, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-15th.8.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the advance surtax payable by it on the current  chargeable amount calculated in the manner laid down in sub-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>section (3),</p>
                  <p>and shall pay such amount of advance surtax as accords with its  estimate on such of the dates applicable in its case under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as have not expired, by instalment-. which may be revised  according to sub- section (9):</p>
                  <p>Provided that where in respect of any company the Commissioner  has, in exercise of the powers conferred by the first proviso to sub-</p>
                  <p>section (4) of section 209A, or the first proviso to sub- section (3A)</p>
                  <p>of section 212, of the Income- tax Act, extended the date for  furnishing the estimate referred to in the said sub- section (4) or, as  the case may be, the said sub- section (3A) and the company has paid  the advance surtax which it is liable to pay under sub- section (5) or  sub- section (6) or, as the case may be, sub- section (7) on or before  the date on which the last instalment of advance surtax is due in its  case, the company shall pay, on or before the date as so extended, the  amount by which the advance surtax already paid by It falls short of  the advance surtax payable in accordance with its estimate.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The company may send a revised estimate of the, advance  surtax payable by it on or before any one of the dates specified in  sub- section (4) and adjust any excess or deficiency in respect of any  instalment already paid in a subsequent instalment or in subsequent  instalments.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15th.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every statement or estimate under this section shall be sent  in the prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7C">
              <num>7C.</num>
              <heading>Interest payable by assessee.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7C.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where, in any financial  year, a company has paid advance surtax under section 7A on the basis  of its own estimate (including revised estimate), and the advance  surtax so paid is less than eighty- three, and one- third per cent of  the assessed surtax, simple interest at the rate of  fifteen per  cent. per annum from the 1st day of April next following the  said financial year up to the date of the regular assessment shall be  payable by the company upon the amount by which the advance surtax so  paid falls short of the assessed surtax,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7C.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where, on making the regular assessment, the Income- tax</p>
                  <blockList id="section-7C.2.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Officer finds-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7C.2.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>that any such company as is referred to in clause (a) of  sub- section (5) of section 7A has not sent the statement  referred to in that clause or the estimate in lieu of such  statement referred to in sub- section (6) of that section; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7C.2.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>that any such company as is referred to in clause (b) of  sub- section (5) of section 7A has not sent the estimate  referred to in that clause,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>simple interest at the rate of[ fifteen per cent] 2 per annum from  the 1st day of April next following the financial year, in which the  advance surtax was. payable in accordance with the said sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7C.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or sub-, section (6) up to the date of the regular assessment shall  be payable by the company upon the amount equal to the assessed  surtax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7C.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where, on making the regular assessment, the Income- tax</p>
                  <p>Officer finds that any company which is required,- to send an estimate  under sub- section (8) of section 7A has not sent the, estimate  referred to therein, simple interest at the rate of[ fifteen per  cent] 2 per annum from the 1st day of April next following the finan-</p>
                  <p>cial year in which the advance surtax was payable in accordance with  the' said sub- section (8) to the date of the regular assessment shall  be payable by the company upon the amount by which the advance surtax  paid by, it falls short of the assessed surtax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7C.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-7C.4.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>sections, where provisional assessment is made under section 7-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7C.4.list2.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>interest shall be calculated in accordance with the  provisions of sub- section (1) or subsection (2) or, as the  case may be, sub- section (3) up to the date on which the  surtax provisionally assessed is paid; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7C.4.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>thereafter interest shall be calculated at the rate of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>fifteen per cent 2 per annum on the amount by which the  surtax provisionally assessed falls short of the assessed  surtax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7C.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In such cases and under such circumstances as may be,</p>
                  <p>prescribed, the Income- tax Officer may reduce or waive the interest  payable by the company under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7C.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where, as a result of an order under section 11, or section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, or section 13, or section 17, or section 18 read with section 260  or section 262 of the Income- tax Act. the amount on which interest was  payable under this section' has been reduced, the interest shall be  reduced accordingly and the excess interest paid, if any, shall be  refunded.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-12.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In this section and section 9A," assessed surtax" mean.,;</p>
                  <p>the surtax determined on the basis of the regular assessment without  making any deduction therefrom.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7D">
              <num>7D.</num>
              <heading>Interest payable by assessee in case of underestimate, etc.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-7D.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>where, on making the regular assessment, the Income- tax Officer finds  that any company has under section 7A underestimated the advance  surtax payable by it and thereby reduced the amount payable in either  of the first two instalments, he may direct that the company shall pay  simple interest at  fifteen per cent.] per annum for the period  during which the payment was deficient, on the difference between the  amount paid in each such instalment and the amount which should have  been paid, having regard to the aggregate advance surtax actually paid  during the year.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, any instalment due  before the expiry of six months from the commencement of the previous  year in respect of which it is to be paid shall be deemed to have  become, due fifteen days after the expiry of the said six months."]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Profits escaping assessment. If-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the Income- tax Officer has reason to believe that by  reason of the omission or failure on the part of the assessee  to make a return under section 5 for any assessment year or  to disclose fully and truly all material facts necessary for  his assessment for any assessment year, chargeable profits  for that year have escaped assessment or have been under-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>assessed or assessed at too low a rate or have been made the  subject of excessive relief under this Act, or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>notwithstanding that there has been no omission or  failure as mentioned in clause (a) on the part of the  assessee, the Income- tax Officer has in consequence of  information in his possession reason to believe that  chargeable profits assessable for any assessment year have  escaped assessment or have been under- assessed or assessed at  too low a rate or have been the subject of excessive relief  under this Act,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>he may, in cases falling under clause (a) at any time, and in cases  falling under clause (b) at any time within four years of the end of  that assessment year, serve on the assessee a notice containing all or  any of the requirements which may be included in a notice under  section 5, and may proceed to assess or re- assess the amount charge-</p>
                  <p>able to surtax, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as may  be, apply as if the notice were a notice issued under that section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Penalties. If the Income- tax, Officer, in the course of any  proceedings under this Act, is satisfied that any person has, without  reasonable cause, failed to furnish' the return required under section</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, or to produce or cause to be produced the accounts, documents or  other evidence required by the Income- tax Officer under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>of section 6, or has concealed the particulars of the chargeable  profits or has furnished inaccurate particulars of such profits, he  may direct that such person shall pay, by way of penalty, in addition  to the amount of surtax payable, a sum not exceeding-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>where the person has failed to furnish the return  required under section 5, the amount of  surtax chargeable  under the Provisions of this Act."];</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in any other case, the amount of surtax which would  have been avoided if the return made had been accepted as  correct:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the Income- tax Officer shall not impose any penalty  under this section without the previous authority of the Inspecting</p>
                  <p>Assistant Commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9A">
              <num>9A.</num>
              <heading>False estimate of, or failure to pay, advance surtax.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>If the Income- tax Officer, in the course of any proceedings in  connection with the regular assessment for any assessment year, is  satisfied that any assessee-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>has furnished under clause (a) of sub- section (5) of  section 7A a statement of advance surtax payable by him which  he knew or had reason to believe to be untrue, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish a  statement of the advance surtax payable by him in accordance  with the provisions of clause (a) of sub- section (5) of  section 7A,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>he may direct that such assessee shall, in addition to the  amount of surtax, if any, payable by him, pay by way of  penalty a sum-,</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a  half times the amount by which the surtax actually paid  during the financial year immediately preceding the  assessment year under the provisions of section 7A falls  short of--</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>eighty- three and one- third percent of the assessed  surtax, or</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount which would have been payable by way of advance  surtax if the assessee had furnished a correct and complete  statement in accordance with the provisions of clause (a) of  sub- section (5) of section 7A,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.2.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>whichever is less;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.2.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a  half times of eighty- three and one- third per cent, of the  assessed surtax.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>If the Income- tax Officer, in the course of any  proceedings in connection with the regular assessment for any  assessment year, is satisfied that any assessee-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>has furnished under clause (b) of sub- section (5) or  sub- section (6) or sub- section (7) or sub- section (9) of  section 7A, an estimate of the advance surtax payable by him  which he knew or had reason to believe to be untrue, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>has furnished under sub- section (8) of section 7A, an  estimate of the advance surtax payable by him which he knew  or had reason to believe to be untrue, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.2.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish an  estimate of the advance surtax payable by him in accordance  with the provisions of clause (b) of sub- section (5) of  section 7A, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.2.list1.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish an  estimate of advance surtax payable by him in accordance with  the provisions of sub- section (8) of section 7A,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>he may direct that such assessee shall, in addition to the  amount of surtax, if any, payable by him, pay by way of  penalty a sum-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.2.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a  half times the amount by which the surtax actually paid  during the financial year immediately preceding the  assessment year under the provisions of section 7A falls  short of-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the assess-</p>
                  <p>ed surtax, or</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>where a statement under clause (a) of sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of section 7A was furnished by the assessee, the  amount payable under such statement,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.5.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>whichever is less;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.5.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a  half times the amount by which the surtax actually paid  during the financial year immediately preceding the  assessment year under the provisions of section 7A falls  short of eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the assessed  surtax;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.5.list2.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (c), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a  half times of eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the  assessed surtax; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.5.list2.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (d), shall not be  less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a half times the  amount of surtax payable in accordance with a statement under clause</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.5.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>or an estimate under clause (b) of sub- section (5) of section 7A</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>or an estimate in lieu of a statement under sub- section (6) of that  section falls short of eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the  assessed surtax.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- Where the Commissioner has, in exercise of the  powers conferred by the first proviso to sub- section (4) of section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-209A">
              <num>209A.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-209A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, or the first proviso to sub- section (3A) of section 212, of the</p>
                  <p>Income- tax Act, extended the date for furnishing the estimate referred  to in the said sub- section (4) or, as the case may be, the said sub-</p>
                  <p>section (3A) and the date so extended falls beyond the financial year  immediately preceding the assessment year, then, the amount of surtax  paid by the assessee on or before the date so extended shall, for the  purposes of clause (ii) of subsection (2) also be regarded is surtax  actual paid during that financial year."]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Opportunity of being heard. No order imposing a penalty under  section 9  or section 9A] shall be made unless the assessee has been  given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Appeals to the Appellate Assistant Commissioner.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any  person objecting to the amount of surtax for which he is liable as  assessed by the Income- tax Officer or denying his liability to be  assessed under this Act, or objecting to any penalty or fine imposed  by the Income- Tax Officer,  or objecting to the interest levied by  the Income- Tax Officer under section 7D,"] or to the amount allowed by  the Income- tax Officer by way of any relief under any provisions of  this Act, or to any refusal by the Income- tax officer to grant relief  or to an order of rectification or amendment having the effect of  enhancing the assessment or reducing the refund, or to an order  refusing to allow the claim made by the assessee for a rectification  under section 13 or amendment under section 14 may appeal to the</p>
                  <p>Commissioners Appeals]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be  verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the  following date, that is to say-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>where the appeal relates to assessment or penalty or  fine, the date of service of the notice of demand relating to  the assessment or penalty or fine, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in any other case, the date on which the intimation of  the order sought to be appealed against is served:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the  Commissioners Appeals may admit an appeal  after the expiration of the said period if he is satisfied that the  appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting it within that  period.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The  Commissioner (Appeals)] shall hear and determine the  appeal and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass such orders as  he thinks fit and such orders may include an order enhancing the  assessment or penalty:</p>
                  <p>Provided that an order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall  not be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a  reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The procedure to be adopted in the hearing and determination  of the appeals shall, with any necessary modification, be in  accordance with the procedure applicable in relation to income- tax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11A">
              <num>11A.</num>
              <heading>Transfer of certain pending appeals. Every appeal under  this Act which is pending immediately before the appointed day before  an Appellate Assistant commissioner or a Commissioner and any matter  arising Out of or connected with such appeal and which Is so pending  shall stand transferred on that day to the Commissioner, (Appeals) and  the Commissioner (Appeals) may Proceed with such appeal or matter  from, the stage at which it was on that day:</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Provided that the appellant may demand that before Proceeding  further with the appeal or matter the previous Proceeding or any part  thereof be reopened or that he be re- heard.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- In this section," appointed day" means the date  appointed under section 39 of the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1977.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any assessee aggrieved by  an order passed by a Commissioner under section 16, or an order passed  by  a Commissioner (Appeals)]</p>
                  <p>under any provision of this Act, may appeal to the Appellate Tribunal  against such order.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commissioner may, if he objects to any order passed by  the  Commissioner (Appeals)] under any provision of this Act, direct  the Income- tax Officer to appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against the  order.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every appeal under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall  be filled within sixty days of the date on which the order sought to  be appealed against is communicated to the assessee or to the Commis-</p>
                  <p>sioner, as the case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Income- tax Officer, or the assessee, as the case may be,</p>
                  <p>on receipt of notice that an appeal against the order of the</p>
                  <p>Commissioner (Appeals)] has been preferred under sub- section (1) or  sub- section (2) by the other party may, notwithstanding that he may  not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, within  thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file, a memorandum of cross  objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part of the  order of the  Commissioner Appeals] and such memorandum shall be  disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal, as if it were an appeal  presented within the time specified in sub- section (3).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the  filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the  relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if  it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it  wit within that period.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the  prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and,</p>
                  <p>shall, except in the case of in appeal referred to in sub- section (2)</p>
                  <p>or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in sub- section (4). be  accompanied by  a fee of  two hundred rupees].</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, in hearing and making  an order on any appeal under this section. the Appellate Tribunal  shall exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it  exercises and follows hearing and making an order on any appeal under  the Income- tax Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Rectification of mistakes.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-13.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>With a view to rectifying any  mistake apparent from the record, the Commissioner, the Income- tax</p>
                  <p>Officer, the  Commissioner (Appeals] and the Appellate Tribunal may,</p>
                  <p>its, own motion or on an application by the assessee in this behalf  amend any order passed by him or it in any proceeding under this Act    within four years from the end of the financial year in which such  order was passed."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the assess-</p>
                  <p>ment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability of the  assessee shall not be made under this section unless the authority  concerned has given notice to the assessee of its intention so to do  and has allowed the assessee a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where an amendment is made under this section, the order  shall be passed in writing by the authority concerned.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, where any such  amendment has the effect of reducing the assessment, the Income- tax</p>
                  <p>Officer shall make any refund which may be due to such assessee.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the  assessment or reducing the refund already made, the Income- tax Officer  shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the prescribed form  specifying the sum payable.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Other amendments. Where as a result of any order made under    section 154, 155, 250, 254, 260, 262, 263 or 264] of the Income- tax</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Act, it is necessary to recompute the chargeable profits determined in  any assessment under this Act, the Income- tax Officer may proceed to  recompute the chargeable profits, and determine the surtax payable or  refundable on the basis of such recomputation and make the necessary  amendment and the provisions of section 13 shall, so far as may be,</p>
                  <p>apply thereto, the period of four years specified in sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-14.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of that section being reckoned  from the end of the financial year  in which the order under the aforesaid sections of the Income- tax Act  was passed"]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Surtax deductible in computing distributable income under</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Income- tax Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (i) of  section 109 of the Income- tax Act, in computing the distributable  income of a company for the purposes of Chapter XID of that Act, the  surtax payable by the company any for any assessment year shall be  deductible from the total income of the company assessable for that  assessment year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Revision of orders prejudicial to revenue.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The</p>
                  <p>Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any proceeding  under this Act, and if he considers that any order passed therein by  the Income- tax Officer Is erroneous in so far as it is prejudicial to  the interests of the revenue, he, may, after giving the assessee an  opportunity of being heard and after making or causing to be made such  inquiry as he deems necessary, pass such order thereon as the  circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or  modifying the assessment, or cancelling the assessment and directing a  fresh assessment.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that, for the purposes of this sub- section, an order passed by the</p>
                  <p>Income- Tax Officer shall include an order passed by the Inspecting</p>
                  <p>Assistant Commissioner in exercise of the powers or in performance of  the functions of an Income- tax Officer conferred on, or assigned to,</p>
                  <p>him under clause (a) of sub- section (1) of section 125 or under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (1) of section 125A of the Income- tax Act as applied by  section 18 of this Act."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No order shall be made under sub- section (1) after the  expiry of two years from the end of the financial year in which the  order sought to be revised was passed."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), an  order in revision under this section may be passed at any time in the  case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to give  effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the</p>
                  <p>Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- In computing the period of limitation for the pur-</p>
                  <p>poses of sub- section (2), any period during which any proceeding under  this section is stayed by an order or injunction of any court shall be  excluded.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Revision of orders by Commissioner.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-17.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commissioner may,</p>
                  <p>either of his own motion or on an application by the assessee for  revision, call for the record of any proceeding under this Act which  has been taken by an Income- tax Officer subordinate to him and may  make such inquiry or cause such inquiry to be made and, subject to the  provisions of this Act, may pass such order thereon, not being an  order prejudicial to the assessee, as he thinks fit.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commissioner shall not of his own motion revise any  order under this section if the order has been made more than one year  previously.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In the case of an application for revision under this  section by the assessee, the application shall be made within one  year from the date on which the order in question was communicated to  him or the date on which he otherwise came to know of it, whichever is  earlier:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the  assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application  within, that period admit an application made after the expiry of that  period.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-17.4.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Commissioner shall not revise any order under this  section in the following cases-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-17.4.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-17.4.list1.a.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>where an appeal against the order lies to the Commissioner</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-17.4.list1.a.list0.Appeals">
                          <num>(Appeals)</num>
                          <p>but has not been made and the time within which such appeal  may be made has not expired, or the assessee has not waived his right  of appeal; or</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-17.4.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where the order has been made the subject of an appeal to  the Commissioner (Appeals).]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every application by an assessee for revision under this  section shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty- five rupees.</p>
                  <p>Explanation 1.- An order by the Commissioner declining to inter-</p>
                  <p>fere shall, for the purposes of this section be deemed not to be an  order prejudicial to the assessee.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Application of provisions of Income- tax Act. The provisions of  the following sections and Schedules of the Income- tax Act and the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Income- tax (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, 1962, as in force from  time to time, shall apply with such modifications, if any, as may be  prescribed, as if the said provisions and the rules referred to surtax  instead of to income- tax :--</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-18.44">
                <num>(44)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>] 18  116, 117, 118, 119, 120, 129], 131, 132, 132A</p>
                  <p>, 132 B] 133 to 136 (both inclusive)], 138, 140, 156, 160,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-161">
              <num>161.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-161.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, 162, 163, 166, 167, 170, 173, 175, 176, 178, 179,  218  to 229] (both inclusive), 231, 232, 233, 237 to 242 (both   inclusive), 244, 245, 254 to 262 (both inclusive), 265, 266,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-268">
              <num>268.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-268.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, 269, 281,  281B] 282, 284,  287, 288, 288A, 288B, 289  to 293 (both inclusive)], the Second Schedule and the Third</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1964/7/eng@1964-05-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>Provided that references in the said provisions and the rules to  the" assessee" shall be construed as references to an assessee as  defined in this Act.</heading>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Income- tax papers to be available for the purpose of this Act.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax be Act, all  information contained in any statement or return made or furnished  under the provisions of that Act or obtained or collected of for the  purposes of that Act may be used for the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All information' contained in any statement or return made  or furnished under the provisions of this Act or obtained or collected  for the purposes of this Act may be used for the purposes of the</p>
                  <p>Income- tax Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>Failure to deliver returns, etc. If any person fails without  reasonable cause to furnish in due time any return, under sub- section</heading>
              <subsection id="section-20.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of section 5, or to produce, or cause to be produced, any accounts  or documents, required to be produced under section 6, he shall be  punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and with  a further fine which may extend to ten rupees for every day during  which the default continues.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>False statements. If a person makes in any return furnished  under section 5, any statement which is false, and which he either  knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to be true, he  shall be punishable with simple imprisonment which may extend to six  months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with  both.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Abatement of false returns, etc. If a person makes or induces  in any manner another person to make and deliver any account,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>statement or declaration relating to chargeable profits liable to  surtax which is false and which he either knows to be false or does  not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with simple  imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may  extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Institution of proceedings and composition of offences.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-23.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A</p>
                  <p>person shall not be proceeded against for an offence under section 20  or section 21 or section 22 or under the Indian Penal Code except at  the instance of the Commissioner. (45 of 1860).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commissioner may, either before or after the institution  of proceedings, compound any offence punishable under section 20 or  section 21 or section 22.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Power to make exemption, etc., in relation to certain Union  territories. If the Central Government considers it necessary or  expedient so to do for avoiding any hardship or anomaly or removing an  difficulty that may arise as a result of the application of this Act  to the Union territories of Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Goa, Dam and Diu  and Pondicherry, the Central Government may, by general or special  order, made an exemption, reduction in rate or other modification in  respect of surtax in favour of any class of assessees or in regard to  the whole or any part of the chargeable profits of any class of  assessees.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24A">
              <num>24A.</num>
              <heading>Agreement with foreign countries. The Central</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-24A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Government may enter into an agreement with the Government of any  country outside India-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>for the granting of relief in respect of chargeable  profits on which have been paid both surtax under this Act  and tax of a similar character or income- tax on such profits  in that country, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>for the avoidance of double taxation of chargeable  profit under this Act and under any law relating to the  taxation of income or profits in force in that country, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>for exchange of information for the prevention of eva-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>sion or avoidance of surtax chargeable under this Act or the  chargeable under the corresponding law in force in that  country or investigation of cases of such evasion or  avoidance, or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>for recovery of tax under this Act and under any law  relating to the taxation of income or profits in force that  country,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>and may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such provision  as may be necessary for implementing the agreement."]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24AA">
              <num>24AA.</num>
              <heading>Power to make exemption, etc., in relation to  participation in the business of prospecting for, extraction, etc., of  mineral oils.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-24AA.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is  necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make in exemption, reduction in  rate or other modification in respect of surtax in favour of any class  of foreign companies specified in sub- section (2) or in regard to the  whole or any part of the profits chargeable of such class of companies.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes, of this sub- section," foreign  company" shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (4) of  section 80B of the Income- Tax Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24AA.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-24AA.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The foreign companies referred to in sub- section (1) are the  following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-24AA.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>foreign companies with whom the Central Government has  entered into agreements for the association or participation  of that Government or any person authorised by that</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-24AA.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Government in any business consisting of the prospecting for  or extraction or production of mineral oils; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-24AA.2.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>foreign companies providing any services or facilities  or supplying any ship, aircraft, machinery or plant (whether   by way of sale or hire) in connection with any business  consisting of the prospecting for or extraction or production  of mineral oils carried on by that Government or any person  specified by that Government in this behalf by notification  in the Official Gazette.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24AA.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification issued under this section shall be laid  before each House of Parliament,</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," mineral oil"</p>
                  <p>includes petroleum and natural gas.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-25.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board may, subject to the control  of the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                  <p>make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-25.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the form in which returns under section 5 may be  furnished and the manner in which they may be verified;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the form in which notice for making provisional  assessment shall be given;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.2.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the form in which appeals under section 11 or section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>may be filed and the manner in which they shall be  verified;</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.cc">
                      <num>(cc)</num>
                      <p>the circumstances in which, the conditions subject to  which and the manner in which,' the  Commissioner (Appeals)]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>may permit an appellant to produce evidence which he did not  produce or which he was- not allowed to Produce before the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Income- tax Officer;]</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.d.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>the procedure to be followed on applications for  rectification of mistakes and applications for refunds;</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.d.list0.dd">
                          <num>(dd)</num>
                          <p>the procedure to be followed in calculating interest  payable by assessees or interest payable by the Government to  assessees under this Act, including the rounding off the  period for which such interest is to be calculated in cases  where such period includes a fraction of a month, and  specifying the circumstances in which and the extent to which  petty amounts of interest payable by assessees may be  ignored;]</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which by this Act is to be, or may be,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-12.2A">
                <num>(2A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The power to make rules conferred by this section shall  include the power to give retrospective effect, form a date not  earlier than the date of commencement of this Act, to the rules or any  of them and, unless the contrary is permitted (whether expressly   or by necessary implication), no retrospective effect shall be given  to any rule so as to Prejudicially affect the interests of  assessees."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under this  section to be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each</p>
                  <p>House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of  thirty days, which may be comprised in one session  or in two or  more successive sessions] and if, before the expiry of the session    immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid"] both Houses agree in</p>
                  <p>making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule  should not be made, that rule shall thereafter have effect only in  such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however  that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Saving. Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to any  company Saving. which has no share capital.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
