<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Haryana Essential Services Maintenance Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/40/eng@2017-03-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/40/eng@2017-03-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/40/eng@2017-03-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/40/eng@2017-03-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Haryana Essential Services Maintenance Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>(HARYANA ACT No. 40 OF 1974)</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>AN ACT to provide for the maintenance of essential services in the State of Haryana and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Haryana in the Twenty fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Haryana Essential Services Maintenance Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Haryana.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"employment" includes employment of any nature whether paid or unpaid</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the Government of the State of Haryana;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under. this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"strike" means the cessation of work by a body of persons employed in any employment or class of employment to which this Act applies, acting in combination, or a concerted refusal, or a refusal under a common understanding, of any number of persons, who arc or have been so employed to continue to work or to accept employment, and includes—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>mass casual leave in pursuance of a common understanding among the persons who avail themselves of such leave, or under the direction of any other person or persons;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>refusal to work overtime where such work is necessary for the maintenance of work in any employment to which this Act applies; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any other conduct which is likely to result in, or results in, cessation or• substantial retardation of work in any employment to which this Act applies.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Employment to which Act applies.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>This Act shall apply—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to all employment under the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to any other employment or class of employment which the Government, being of the opinion that such employment or class of employment is essential for securing the public safety, the maintenance of public order, health or sanitation, or for maintaining supplies or services necessary for the life of the community, may, by notification, declare.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to order persons engaged in certain employment to remain in specified areas.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government or an officer authorised by it in this behalf may, in respect of any employment or class of employment to which section 3 applies, by general or special order, direct that any person or persons engaged in such employment shall not depart out of such area or areas may be specified in such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made under sub-section (1) shall be published in such manner as the Government or the officer making the order considers fit to bring it to the notice of persons affected thereby.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Power to prohibit strike</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Government is satisfied that in the public interest it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may by general or special order, prohibit strikes in any employment or class of employment to which this Act applies.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made under sub-section (1) shall be published in such manner as the Government considers sufficient to bring it to the notice of the persons affected by the order and shall remain in force for a period of six months :</p>
            <p>Provided that the Government may by a like order extend if for any period not exceeding six months, if it is satisfied that in the public interest it is necessary or expedient so to do.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Upon the issue of the order under sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no person employed in any employment or class of employment to which this Act applies and to whom the order relaters shall go , or remain on strike; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any strike declared or commenced, whether before or after the issue of the order persons employed in any such employment shall be illegal.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Offences.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person engaged in any employment or class of employment to which this Act applies who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>disobeys any lawful order given to him in the course of such employment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>without reasonable excuse abandons such employment or absents himself from work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>departs from any area specified in an order made under sub-section (1) of section 4 without the consent of the authority making the order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>himself takes part in instigates or incites other person to take part in, or otherwise acts in furtherance of, any illegal strike; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>knowingly expends or supplies any money in furtherance or support of any illegal strike.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be guilty of an offence under this Act.</p>
            <p>Explanation 1.—The fact that a person apprehends that by continuing in his employment he will be exposed to increased physical danger is not a reasonable excuse within the meaning of clause (b);</p>
            <p>Explanation 2.— A person abandons his employment within the meaning of clause (b) who, notwithstanding that is an express or implied term of his contract of employment that he may get his employment terminated on giving notice to his employer of his intention to do so, abandons his employment without the previous consent of his employer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any employer of a person engaged in an employment or class of employment declared under section 3 to be an employment to which this Act applies, who without reasonable cause—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>discontinues the employment of such person; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by closing an establishment in which such person is engaged causes the discontinuance of his employment;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be guilty of an offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Regulation of wages and conditions of service.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules regulating or empowering a specified authority to regulate wages and other conditions of service of persons or any class of persons engaged in any employment or class of employment declared as such under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any such rules have been made or when any directions regulating wages or conditions of service have been given by an authority empowered by such rules to give such directions, any person falling to comply with them shall be guilty of an offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalties and procedure.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person found guilty of an offence under this Act shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person incharge of, or responsible to, the company</p>
            <p>for the conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be liable to the proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of or that the commission of the offence is attributable to any neglect on the part of, a director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary "or other officer shall also be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.—For the purposes of this section,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"company" means any body corporate, and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The offences under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any magistrate or bench of magistrates empowered for the time being to try in a summary manner the offences specified in sub-section (1) of section 260 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 may, if such magistrate or bench of magistrates thinks fit, on an application made, in this behalf, by the complainant, try any offence under this Act in accordance with the provisions contained in sections 262 to 265 of the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Indemnity</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Over riding effect of orders, rules, etc. made under the Act.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any declaration, order, rule or regulation made and any direction given under this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Repeal</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The East Punjab Essential Services (Maintenance) Act, 1947 (East Punjab Act 13 of 1947), in its application to the State of Haryana, is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
