<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1876/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1876/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Oudh Laws Act, 1876"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1876/18/eng@1876-10-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1876/18/eng@1876-10-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1876-10-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1876/18/eng@1876-10-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1876/18/eng@1876-10-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Oudh Laws Act, 1876</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 18 OF 1876</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 10th October, 1876.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare and amend the laws to be administered in Oudh.</p>
        <p>Preamble.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to declare and amend the laws to be  administered in Oudh; It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Oudh Laws Act, 1876.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Local extent.</p>
              <p>It extends only to  Oudh;</p>
              <p>Commencement.</p>
              <p>And it shall come into force on the passing thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Repeal of enactments. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1938">
          <num>1938.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1938.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), s. 2 and Sch.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>GENERAL LAWS TO BE ADMINISTERED IN OUDH</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>GENERAL LAWS TO BE ADMINISTERED IN OUDH</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Statutory law to be administered in Oudh. The law to be  administered by the Courts of Oudh shall be as follows:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the laws for the time being in force regulating the  assessment and collection of land- revenue;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in questions regarding succession, special property of  females, betrothal, marriage, divorce, dower, adoption,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>guardianship, minority, bastardy, family relations,</p>
              <p>wills, legacies, gifts, partitions or any religious  usage or institution, the rule of decision shall be--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>any custom applicable to the parties  concerned which is not contrary to justice, equity  or good conscience, and has not been, by this or  any other enactment, altered or abolished, and has  not been declared to be void by any competent  authority;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>the Muhammadan law in cases where the  parties are Muhammadans, and the Hindu law in  cases where the parties are Hindus, except in so  far as such law has been, by this or any other  enactment, altered or abolished, or has been  modified by any such custom as is above referred  to:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the rules contained in this Act:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the rules published in the Official Gazette as provided  by section 40, or made under any other Act for the time  being in force in Oudh:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the Regulations and Acts specified in the second  schedule hereto annexed, subject to the provisions of  section 4, and to the modifications mentioned in the  third column of the same schedule:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>subject to the modifications hereinafter mentioned, all  enactments for the time being in force and expressly,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>or by necessary implication, applying to  the  territories which, immediately before the 1st November,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, were comprised in Part A States and Part C</p>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>States] or Oudh, or some part of Oudh:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>in cases not provided for by the former part of this  section, or by any other law for the time being in  force, the Courts shall act according to justice,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>equity and good conscience.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Validity of local customs and mercantile usages. All local  customs and mercantile usages shall be regarded as valid, unless they  are contrary to justice, equity or good conscience, or have, before  the passing of this Act, been declared to be void by any competent  authority.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>PART</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>DOWER AMONG MUHAMMADANS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </part>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>DOWER AMONG MUHAMMADANS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Muhammadan dower contracts how to be enforced. Where the  amount of dower stipulated for in any contract of dower by a</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Muhammadan is excessive with reference to the means of the husband,</p>
              <p>the entire sum provided in the contract shall not be awarded in any  suit by decree in favour of the plaintiff, or by allowing it by way of  set- off, lien or otherwise to the defendant; but the amount</p>
              <p>of the dower to be allowed by the Court shall be reasonable with  reference to the means of the husband and the status of the wife.</p>
              <p>Rule applicable after husband' s death.</p>
              <p>This rule shall be applicable whether the suit to enforce the  contract be brought in the husband' s life time or after his death.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PRE- EMPTION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRE- EMPTION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Right of pre- emption. The right of pre- emption is a right of  the persons hereinafter mentioned or referred to, to acquire, in the  cases hereinafter specified, immovable property in preference to all  other persons.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Presumption as to its existence. Unless the existence of any  custom or contract to the contrary is proved, such right shall,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>whether recorded in the settlement- record or not, be presumed--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to exist in all village- communities, however  constituted, and whether proprietary or under-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>proprietary, and in the cases referred to in section 40  of the Oudh Land- revenue Act,  (17 of 1876) and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to extend to the village- site, to the houses built upon  it, to all lands and shares of lands within the  village- boundary, and to all transferable rights  affecting such lands.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Its existence in towns to be proved. The right of pre- emption  shall not be presumed to exist in any town or city, or any sub-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>division thereof, but may be shown to exist therein and to be  exercisable therein by such persons and under such circumstances as  the local custom prescribes.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Devolution of right when property to be sold or foreclosed is  a proprietary or under- proprietary tenure. If the property to be sold  or foreclosed is a proprietary or under- proprietary tenure, or a share  of such a tenure, the right to buy or redeem such property belongs, in  the absence of a custom to the contrary,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>First, to co- sharers of the sub- division (if any) of the  tenure in which the property is comprised, in order of  their relationship to the vendor or mortgagor;</p>
              <p>Secondly, to co- sharers of the whole mahal in the same order;</p>
              <p>Thirdly, to any member of the village- community; and</p>
              <p>Fourthly, if the property be an underproprietary tenure, to the  proprietor.</p>
              <p>Where two or more persons are equally entitled to such right, the  person to exercise the same shall be determined by lot.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9A">
          <num>9A.</num>
          <heading>When a suit for pre- emption lies. No suit shall lie for  enforcing a right of pre- emption under this Act in respect of a  portion only of the property sold or foreclosed:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that, where the plaintiff has a right of pre- emption in  respect of only a portion of the property sold or foreclosed, then  notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any enactment a  suit for the pre- emption of that portion only shall lie and the  plaintiff shall have to pay the proportionate price or the  proportionate amount due in respect of such mortgage for such portion  of the property, as the case may be.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Notice to pre- emptors. When any person proposes to sell any  property, or when he forecloses a mortgage upon any property, in  respect of which any persons have a right of pre- emption, he shall  give notice to the persons concerned of the price at which he is  willing to sell such property, or of the amount due in respect of such  mortgage, as the case may be:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that, where a person has a right of pre- emption in  respect of a portion only of the property proposed to be sold or  foreclosed, the notice to such person shall specify the proportionate  amount of the price or the proportionate amount due in respect of such  mortgage at which the person proposing to sell or foreclose is willing  to sell or redeem such portion of the property, as the case may be.]</p>
              <p>Such notice shall be given through the Court within the local  limits of whose jurisdiction the property or any part thereof is  situate, and shall be deemed sufficiently given if it be stuck up on  the chaupal or other public place of the village or city in which the  property is situate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Loss of right of pre- emption. Any person having a right of  pre- emption in respect of any property proposed to be sold shall lose  such right, unless within three months from the date of such notice he  or his agent pays or tenders the price  specified in the notice  given under the preceding section] to the person so proposing to sell.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Right of pre- emptor on foreclosure. When the right of pre-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>emption arises in respect of the foreclosure of a mortgage  or a  portion of the mortgage], any person entitled to such right may, at  any time within three months after the</p>
              <p>giving of the notice required by section 10, pay or tender to the  mortgagee or his successor in title the amount specified in such  notice, and shall thereupon acquire a right to purchase the property,</p>
              <p>or a portion thereof, as the case may be].</p>
              <p>On completion of the purchase the person exercising the right of  pre- emption shall be bound to pay to the mortgagee or his successor in  title the amount specified in such notice, together with interest on  the principal sum secured by the mortgage  or the proportionate  amount of such principal sum in respect of the portion of the property  in which he possesses the right of pre- emption, as the case may be],</p>
              <p>at the rate specified by the instrument of mortgage, for any time  which has elapsed since the date of the notice, and any additional  costs which may have been properly incurred by the mortgagee or his  successor in title.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Suit to enforce right of pre- emption. Any person entitled to  a right of pre- emption may bring a suit to enforce such right on any  of the following grounds (namely):--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that no due notice was given as required by section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that tender was made under section 11 or section 12 and  refused;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a sale, that the price stated in the  notice was not fixed in good faith;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a mortgage, that the amount claimed by  the mortgagee was not really due on the footing of the  mortgage and was not claimed in good faith, and that it  exceeds the fair market- value of the property  mortgaged,  or the portion of the property mortgaged  in respect of which he possesses the right of pre-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>emption, as the case may be].</p>
              <p>If, in the case of a sale, the Court finds that the price was not  fixed in good faith, the Court shall fix such price as appears to it  to be the fair market- value of the property sold,  or the portion of  the property sold in respect of which he possesses the right of pre-</p>
              <p>emption, as the case may be].</p>
              <p>If, in the case of a mortgage, the Court finds that the amount  claimed by the mortgagee was not really due on the footing of the  mortgage, and that it was not claimed in good faith and that it  exceeds the fair market- value of the property mortgaged  or the  portion of the property mortgaged in respect of which he possesses the  right of</p>
              <p>pre- emption, as the case may be], the amount to be paid to the  mortgagee shall not exceed what the Court finds to be such market-</p>
              <p>value.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Decree to fix time for payment. If the Court find for the  plaintiff, the decree shall specify a day on or before which the  purchase- money or the amount to be paid to the mortgagee shall be  paid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Effect of non- payment of purchase- money. If such purchase-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>money or amount is not paid into Court before it rises on that day,</p>
              <p>the decree shall become void, and the plaintiff shall, so far only as  relates to such sale or mortgage, lose his right of pre- emption over  the property to which the decree relates.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROCEDURE OF THE COURTS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROCEDURE OF THE COURTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Rule of limitation. The Judicial Commissioner' s Circular No.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-104">
          <num>104.</num>
          <heading>of July, 1860, shall be held to have been a notification within  the meaning of section 24 of Act 14 of 1859,  and such Act shall be  deemed to have been in force in Oudh from the fourth day of July,</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1862">
          <num>1862.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1862.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>; and all orders and decrees passed under the rules contained in  the said Circular, or under the said Act, shall be deemed to have been  passed under a law in force for the time being.</p>
              <p>Nothing in his section affects the provisions of sections 102,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-104">
          <num>104.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-104.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, 105, 106, 107 and 108 of the Oudh Rent Act (XIX of 1868)  with  regard to the limitation of suits under that Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Act 32 of 1871, s. 28 to cease in any district from date of  notification that it is no longer under settlement. Act 32 of 1871,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>s. 28, to cease in any district from date of notification that it is  no longer under settlement. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1891">
          <num>1891.</num>
          <heading>(12 of 1891).</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Recognized agents. Recognized agents. Rep., ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Rules for taking evidence.  Section 172 of Act No. 8 of</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1859">
          <num>1859.</num>
          <heading>is hereby repealed, so far as the province of Oudh is concerned,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1859.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>and the following section is substituted therefor:--</p>
              <p>" On the day appointed for the hearing of the suit, or on some  other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the evidence of the</p>
              <p>witnesses in attendance shall be taken orally in open Court in the  presence and hearing and under the personal direction and  superintendence of the Judge.</p>
              <p>" A note of the essential points of the evidence of each witness  is to be taken at the time, and in the course of oral examination, by  the officer who tries the case, in his own language, or in English if  he is sufficiently acquainted with that language, and such note shall  be filed, and shall form part of the record of the case.</p>
              <p>" If the evidence be taken down in a different language from that  in which it has been given, and the witness does not understand the  language in which it is taken down, the witness may require his  deposition as taken down to be interpreted to him in the language in  which it was given.</p>
              <p>" It shall be in the discretion of the Court to take down, or  cause to be taken down, any particular question and answer, if there  appear any special reason for so doing, or any party or his pleader  requires it.</p>
              <p>" If any question put to a witness be objected to by either of the  parties or their pleaders, and the Court allow the same to be put, the  question and the answer shall be taken down, and the objection and the  name of the party making it shall be noticed in taking down the  depositions, together with the decision of the Court upon the  objection.</p>
              <p>" The Court shall record such remarks as it may think material  respecting the demeanour of the witness while under examination.</p>
              <p>The note as above required may be written and signed by the</p>
              <p>Judge with his own hand or typed to his dictation in open Court and  singned by him with his own hand, and such note shall form part of the  record."]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Execution- sale of ancestral and acquired property in land.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>So much of section 60 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1908">
          <num>1908.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1908.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), as renders land liable to sale in execution of a decree shall  be subject to the following restriction:-- No ancestral land shall be  sold in satisfaction of a decree without the permission of the State</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
              <blockList id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- In this section the words" ancestral land" mean--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>land forming a mahal or share in or portion of a mahal,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>which has been owned continuously from the conclusion  of the first regular settlement by the proprietor,</p>
              <p>which term shall include an under- proprietor as defined  in</p>
              <p>section 4, clause (15), of the United Provinces Land-</p>
              <blockList id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>revenue Act, 1901 (U. P. 3 of 1901), or by the person  or persons from whom such proprietor has directly or  indirectly inherited such land;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list8.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>land forming an estate or part of an estate as defined  in the Oudh Estate Act, 1969 (1 of 1969);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list8.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>land conferred by the British Government as a reward for  services rendered to the State on the owner or on a  person from whom such owner has directly or indirectly  inherited such land; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list8.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the interest of the holder of a grant of land revenue  conferred by the British or any former Government on  him or on a person from whom he has directly or  indirectly inherited such interest.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of manager of land attached. Rep. by the Oudh</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Civil Courts Act, 1879 (13 of 1879).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Service of process within jurisdiction of Lucknow Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court. Notwithstanding anything contained in the said Code, any Civil</p>
              <p>Court sitting within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the</p>
              <p>Lucknow Civil Court, but exercising jurisdiction beyond such limits,</p>
              <p>may cause summonses, warrants, notices and other processes to be  served within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Lucknow</p>
              <p>Civil Court without causing the same processes to be served through  such Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Section substituted for Act 19 of 1868, s. 109. Rep. by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Oudh Rent Act, 1886 (22 of 1886).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Section substituted for Act 19 of 1868, s. 118. Rep., ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Right of occupancy in judgment- debtor' s sir- land. Rep. by  the Oudh Rent Act, 1886, Amendment Act, 1901 (U. P. 4 of 1901).</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Revenue- agents authorized to appear, etc., in rent- suits.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in Act No. XX of 1865  all  persons duly admitted and enrolled as Revenue- agents under that Act in</p>
              <p>Oudh may appear, plead and act in suits under the Oudh Rent Act</p>
              <p>(19 of 1868)  in the Courts of officers exercising the powers of (19   of 1868.)</p>
              <p>Assistant Collectors, Deputy Collectors, Collectors and Commissioners  under the same Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules for custody and sale of attached  property. With the sanction of the State Government, the  High</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Court] may from time to time make rules consistent with this Act and  with the Code of Civil Procedure --</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the custody and sale of movable property attached in  execution of decrees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for the levy of a fee or commission on the sale of  attached property and the disposal of the funds  accruing from such fees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>as to the appointment and remuneration of persons</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(not being persons in the service of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government)] by whom property is to be attached, kept  in custody and sold;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>as to the appointment and remuneration of persons</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(not being persons in the service of the</p>
              <p>Government)] by whom local investigations under section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-180">
          <num>180.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-180.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, and investigations and adjustments of accounts  under section 181, of the Code of Civil Procedure   are to be made.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to revise decrees and orders of subordinate Courts.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Rep. by the Oudh Civil Courts Act, 1879 (13 of 1879).</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>VILLAGE AND ROAD- POLICE</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>VILLAGE AND ROAD- POLICE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Right to nominate village- policemen. The nomination to the  post of village- policeman shall be made by the zamindar of the  village, or, where there are more zamindars than one, by the lambardar  as their representative; and, where there are more lambardars than  one, the opinion of the majority (unless there is some special   provision to the contrary in the village administration- paper) shall  prevail.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Obligation to nominate. Every person authorized to nominate  to the office of village- policeman shall, within fifteen days after  the occurrence of a vacancy in such office, nominate a proper person  to the vacant post, and communicate the nomination to the Magistrate  of the district.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Discretion to appoint or reject nominee. The person so  nominated shall, after due enquiry into his age, character and  ability, be appointed or rejected by the State Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Power to Government to appoint. In default of such nomination  within the said fifteen days, the State Government shall appoint such  person as it thinks fit to the vacancy.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure in case of rejection of nominee.</p>
              <p>If the nomination has been made within the said fifteen days, but  the nominee is rejected, the person authorized to nominate shall,</p>
              <p>within fifteen days from the date of such rejection, nominate another  person to the vacant post; and in default of such nomination, or if  such nomination has been made but the nominee is again rejected, the</p>
              <p>State Government shall appoint such person as it thinks fit to the  vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of road- police. Subject to the rules to be framed  under section 39 and for the time being in force, the State Government  may from time to time appoint persons to be  road- police].</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Duties of village and road policemen. Every village- policeman  and every road- policeman shall perform the following duties:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he shall give immediate information to the officer in  charge of the police- station appointed for his village  or beat--</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of every unnatural, suspicious or sudden  death occurring in the village of which he is  chaukidar, or within his beat;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of each of the following offences  occurring in such village or on such beat (that is   to say), murder, culpable homicide, rape, dacoity,</p>
              <p>theft, robbery, mischief by fire, house- breaking,</p>
              <p>counterfeiting coin, causing grievous hurt, riot,</p>
              <p>harbouring a proclaimed offender, exposure of a  child, concealment of birth, administering  stupefying drugs, kidnapping, lurking house-</p>
              <p>trespass; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of all attempts and preparations to  commit, and abetments of, any of the said  offences:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>he shall keep the police informed of all disputes which  are likely to lead to any riot or serious affray:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>he shall arrest all proclaimed offenders, and all  persons whom he may find in the act of committing any  offence specified in paragraph (a), clause (2), of this  section:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>he shall observe and from time to time report to the  officer in charge of the police- station within the  jurisdiction of which his village or beat may be  situate, the movements of all bad characters in or on  such village or beat:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>he shall report to the officer in charge of such police-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-34.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>station the arrival of suspicious characters in the  neighbourhood:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.3.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>he shall supply to the best of his ability any local  information which a Magistrate or any officer of police  may require, and shall promptly execute all orders  issued to him by competent authority.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on arrest by village or roadpoliceman. Whenever a  village- police- man or road- policeman arrests any person, he shall take  him as soon as possible to the police- station within the jurisdiction  of which his village or beat is situate.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Dismissal of village or roadpoliceman. The Magistrate of  the district may dismiss any village- police- man or road- policeman for  any misconduct or neglect of duty.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where any village- policeman is guilty of neglect of duty or other  misconduct, the person authorized to nominate to his office may report  him for dismissal to the Magistrate of the district; and such</p>
              <p>Magistrate shall dismiss him accordingly, unless the Magistrate has  reason to think that such dismissal would be improper.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Acts punishable. Every village- policeman and road- policeman  guilty of any wilful misconduct in his office, or of neglect of duty,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>such misconduct or neglect not being an offence within the meaning of  the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
              <p>or withdrawing from the duties of his office without permission  and without having given at least two months' notice of his intention  to withdraw from such duties to the persons authorized to nominate or  appoint under sections 29, 32 and 33 (as the case may be),</p>
              <p>or offering any unnecessary personal violence to any person in  his custody,</p>
              <p>Penalty.</p>
              <p>shall be liable, on conviction before a Magistrate, to a penalty  not exceeding three months' pay, or to imprisonment for a period not  exceeding three months, or to both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Fines to be credited to such fund as Government appoints. All  fines levied under this Act on village- policemen or road- policemen  shall be credited to such fund as the State Government from time to  time appoints.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>SUBSIDIARY RULES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SUBSIDIARY RULES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules. The State Government may, from time to  time,  make rules consistent with this Act as to--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-39.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the discipline and remuneration of the village and road-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-39.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>police and the regulation of their number, location and  duties;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the disposal of unclaimed property under Act No. 5 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1861">
          <num>1861.</num>
          <heading>(for the regulation of police), sections 25, 26  and 27;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1861.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1861.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1861.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>public health and conservancy at fairs and other large  public assemblies, and the maintenance of a proper  watch and ward at such fairs and assemblies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1861.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>imposing  taxes for those purposes only;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1861.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the keeping and custody of civil, criminal and  revenue records.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Publication of rules. All rules made by the State Government  under section 39, and all rules made by the  High Court] under  section 27, shall be published in the Official Gazette, and shall  thereupon have the force of law.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Continuance of prior rules as to matters for which rules may  be made under the Act. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1891</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(12 of 1891).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for breach of rules. Whoever breaks any rule made or  continued under this Act, not being a rule made by the  High Court],</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punishable with fine  which may extend to fifty rupees, or with imprisonment for a term  which may extend to six months, or with both.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            <p>Honorary Civil Jurisdiction</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Power to invest taluqdars with civil jurisdiction. Rep. by  the Oudh Civil Courts Acts, 1879 (13 of 1879.)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Honorary police- officers</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Honorary police- officers. The State Government may, from time  to time, confer on any person whom it thinks fit any power which may  be exercised by a police- officer under any Act for the time being in  force, and withdraw any power so conferred.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Creation and alteration of districts and sub- divisions</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Power to create new districts. Power to form sub- divisions  of districts. Rep. by the United Provinces Act, 1890 (20 of 1890), s.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading/>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
