<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1888/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1888/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Reserve Forces Act, 1888"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1888/4/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1888/4/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1888/4/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1888/4/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Reserve Forces Act, 1888</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Indian Reserve Forces Act, 1888; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such day as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf.</p>
            <p>The Act has now been extended* to the Union Territories of—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Regn. 6 of 1963 (1-7-1965);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Pondicherry by Regn. 7 of 1963 (1-10-1963);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands by Regn. 8 of 1965 (1-10-1967).</p>
            <p>These Islands are now known as Lakshadweep—see Act 34 of 1973, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-11-1973).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Division of Reserve Forces into Regular and Supplementary Reserves.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Indian Reserve Forces shall consist of the Regular Reserve and the Supplementary Reserve.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Locality of service of Reserves.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>*** A person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces shall be liable to serve beyond the limits of India} as well as within those limits.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules for regulation of Reserve Forces.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>[</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may make rules and orders for the Government, discipline and regulation of the Indian Reserve Forces.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule and every order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or order or both Houses agree that the rule or order should not be made, the rule or order shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or order.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Liability of Reserve Forces to military law.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to *** such rules and orders as may be made under section 4, a person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces shall, as an office, or soldier, as the case may be, be subject to military law in the same manner and to the same extent as a person belonging to the</p>
            <p>the Regular Army.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Punishment of certain offences by persons belonging to Reserve Forces.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>when required by or in pursuance of any rule or order under this Act to attend at any place, fails without reasonable excuse to attend in accordance with such requirement, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>fails without reasonable excuse to comply with any such rule or order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>fraudulently obtains any pay or other sum contrary to any such rule or order,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>he shall be liable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>on conviction by a Court-martial, to such punishment other than death, transportation or imprisonment for a term exceeding one year as such Court is by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Army Act, 1950 empowered to award, or</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Army Act, 1950 empowered to award, or"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>on conviction by a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class, to imprisonment for a term which may extend, in the case of a first offence under this section, to six months, and, in the case of any subsequent offence thereunder, to one year.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces is required by or in pursuance of any rule or order under this Act to attend to any place, a certificate purporting to be signed by an officer appointed by such rule or order in this behalf, and stating that the person so required to attend failed to do so in accordance with such requirement, shall, without proof of the signature or appointment of such officer, be evidence of the matters stated therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person charged with an offence under this section may be taken into and kept in either military or civil custody, or partly into and in one description of custody and partly into and in the other, or be transferred from one description of custody to the other.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Reinstatement in civil employ of persons belonging to Reserve Forces on termination of period of training, muster or army service.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces is, during the period of his employment under an employer, called up for training, muster or army service in pursuance of his liability under any rule or order under this Act, it shall be the duty of every such employer to reinstate the person in his employment on the termination of the period of his training, muster or army service in an occupation and under conditions not less favourable to him than those which would have been applicable to him had his employment not been so interrupted:</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that if the employer refuses to reinstate such person or denies his liability to reinstate such person, or if for any reason reinstatement of such person is represented by the employer to be impracticable, either party may refer the matter to the authority prescribed in this behalf by rules made under this Act, and that authority shall, after considering all matters which may be put before it and after making such further inquiry into the matter as may be prescribed in the said rules, pass an order—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>exempting the employer from the provisions of this section, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the employer to re-employ such person on such terms as the authority thinks suitable, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>requiring the employer to pay to such person by way of compensation for failure or inability to re-employ, a sum not exceeding an amount equal to six months’ remuneration at the rate at which his last remuneration was payable to him by the employer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any employer fails to obey the order of any such authority as is referred to in the proviso to sub-section (1); he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and the Court by which an employer is convicted under this section shall order him (if he has not already been so required by the said authority) to pay to the person whom he has failed to re-employ a sum equal to six months’ remuneration at the rate at which his last remuneration was payable to him by the employer, and any amount so required to be paid either by the said authority or by the Court shall be recoverable as if it were a fine imposed by such Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any proceeding under this section it shall be a defence for an employer to prove that the person formerly employed did not apply to the employer for reinstatement within a period of two months from the termination of the period of his training, muster or army service.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The duty imposed by sub-section (1) upon an employer to reinstate in his employment a person such as is described in that sub-section shall attach to an employer who, before such person is actually called up for training, muster or army service, terminates his employment in circumstances such as to indicate an intention to evade the duty imposed by that sub-section, and such intention shall be presumed until the contrary is proved, if the termination takes place after the issue of orders calling him up for training, muster or army service under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Preservation of certain rights of persons belonging to Reserve Forces when called up for training, muster or army service.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When any person belonging to the Indian Reserve Forces and called up for training, muster or army service in pursuance of his liability under any rule or order under this Act has any rights under any provident fund or superannuation fund or other scheme for the benefit of employees maintained in connection with the employment he relinquishes, he shall continue, so long as he is engaged in training, muster or army services and if he is reinstated, until such reinstatement under the provisions of this Act, to have in respect of such fund or scheme such rights as may be prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
