<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1903/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1903/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Victoria Memorial Act, 1903"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1903/10/eng@1903-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1903/10/eng@1903-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1903-03-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1903/10/eng@1903-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1903/10/eng@1903-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Victoria Memorial Act, 1903</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 10 OF 1903</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 20th March, 1903.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the erection and management of the Victoria</p>
        <p>Memorial at Calcutta.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is intended to erect at Calcutta a building as a  memorial of the life and reign of Her late Majesty Victoria of the</p>
        <p>United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, Queen, Empress of India,</p>
        <p>and for this purpose large sums of money have been subscribed by the  princes and people of India;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS at a meeting of subscribers held in Calcutta certain  persons were appointed a Provisional Executive Committee to take the  custody of the said moneys;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient to make provision for the erection,</p>
        <p>maintenance and management of the memorial and for the appointment of  a permanent body of Trustees;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Short title. This Act may be called the Victoria</p>
            <p>Memorial Act, 1903;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Trustees. The Trustees of the Victoria Memorial</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>(hereinafter called the Trustees) shall be the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Governor of West Bengal, ex officio Chairman;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Chief Justice of the High Court of West Bengal, ex  officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>three persons to be nominated by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government, one of whom shall be a representative of commerce  and industry, chosen in consultation with the State</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government of West Bengal and two others chosen from among  persons who, in the opinion of the Central Government, have  expert knowledge of the exhibits in the Victoria Memorial or  are museologists, historians or art historians;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a representative of the Central Government in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Ministry concerned with matters relating to the Victoria</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Memorial, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list8.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>a representative of the Central Government in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Ministry of Finance, Department' of Expenditure, concerned  with matters relating to the Victoria Memorial, ex officio;</p>
            <p>the Mayor of the Corporation of Calcutta and where the Cor-</p>
            <p>poration of Calcutta is superseded, the Administrator of that</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Corporation, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list13.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>an officer, not below the rank of the Accountant-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>General nominated by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list16">
              <listIntroduction>India, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list16.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the Secretary to the Government of West Bengal in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list18">
              <listIntroduction>Department of Education, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list18.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>four persons (of whom one at least shall be from the   general body of subscribers), to be nominated by the Trustees  from among persons, who, in the opinion of the Trustees, have  expert knowledge of the exhibits in the Victoria Memorial or  are museologists, historians or art historians, with the  approval of the Central Government.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees shall be a body corporate, with perpetual  succession by the name of" The Trustees of the Victoria Memorial" and  a common seal, and in that name shall sue and be sued, and shall have  power to acquire and hold property, to enter into contracts, and to do  all acts necessary for and consistent with the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All acts done by a majority of those present and voting at  a meeting of the Trustees, and all acts done in pursuance of a  majority decision of the Trustees obtained by circulation to the</p>
            <p>Trustees of the matter requiring decision, shall be deemed to be acts  of the Trustees.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3A">
          <num>(3A)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.3A.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any of the Trustees referred to in clauses (b), (d),</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.3A.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>, (f), (g) and (h) of sub- section (1) is unable to attend any  meeting of the Trustees, he may, with the previous approval of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chairman, authorise in writing a person to do so.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act of the Trustees shall- be deemed to be invalid merely  by reason of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the  body of the Trustees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of ex officio Trustees the person for the time  being performing the duties of any of the offices mentioned in sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) shall act as a Trustee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees may appoint a person to act as their Secretary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Orders for the payment of money on behalf of the Trustees  shall be deemed to be sufficiently authenticated if signed by two</p>
            <p>Trustees and countersigned by the Secretary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Property vested in Trustees. All sums of money now in the  custody ofthe said Provisional Executive Committee and all other  property, whether movable or immovable, which have been or may  hereafter be given, bequeathed or otherwise transferred for the  purposes of the said Memorial or acquired for the said purposes by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Trustees shall vest in the Trustees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Officers and servants to be public servants. All officers and  servants employed by the Trustees shall be deemed to be public  servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860):</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that this section shall not apply to persons in the  service of any contractor employed by the Trustees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may  by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette,] make rule 2 to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the manner in which Trustees, other than ex officio</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Trustees, shall be appointed, and for the periods of time for  which such Trustees shall hold office;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.2.list3.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for the manner in which meetings of the Trustees shall  be convened, the quorum necessary for the transaction of  business, and the procedure at such meetings;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.2.list3.b.list0.bb">
                    <num>(bb)</num>
                    <p>for the manner in which a majority decision of the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Trustees shall be obtained by circulation to the Trustees of  the matter requiring decision;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for the appointment of Committees of the Trustees, and  the powers of expenditure and control which may be delegated  to such Committees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for the erection, maintenance and management of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Memorial, the care and custody of the objects deposited  therein, and the conditions under which the public shall have  access thereto;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list7.da">
                <num>(da)</num>
                <p>for the fees to be levied for admission to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Victoria Memorial;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list9.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for the form of accounts to be kept by the Trustees and  for the audit and publication of such accounts .</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this  section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power of Trustees to make regulations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees may,</p>
            <p>with the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification  in the Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this</p>
            <p>Act and the rules made thereunder, for enabling the body to discharge  its functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the conditions and restrictions subject to which  articles and things vested in the Trustees may be given on  loan;-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the recruitment and conditions of service of the  employees of the Victoria Memorial.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation shall, as soon as may be, after it is made  by the Trustees, be forwarded to the Central Government and that</p>
            <p>Government shall cause a copy of the same to be laid before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty  days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the  regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be  made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
