<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1974/45/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1974/45"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Interest- Tax Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1974-09-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Interest- Tax Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 45 OF 1974</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 23rd September. 1974]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fifth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to impose a special tax on interest in certain cases.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Interest- tax Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" assessee" means a person by whom interest- tax or any other  sum of money is payable under this Act and includes-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>every person in respect of whom any proceeding under  this Act has been taken for the assessment of his chargeable  interest or of the amount of refund due to him or of the  chargeable interest of any other person in respect of which  he is assessable or of the amount of refund due to such other  person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every person who is deemed to be an assessee in default  under any provision of this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" assessment" includes reassessment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months  commencing on the 1st day of April, every year;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes constituted  under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963; (54 of 1963.)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" chargeable interest" means the total amount of interest  referred to in section 5, computed in the manner laid down in section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6.5A">
          <num>(5A)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.5A.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" credit institution" means,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.5A.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a banking company to which the Banking Regulation Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1949">
        <num>1949.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1949.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, applies (including any bank or banking institution   referred to in section 51 of at Act )</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a public financial institution as defined in section of  the Companies Act, 1956;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>a State financial corporation established under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>or section 3A or an institution notified under section 46  of the State Financial Corporations Act, 1951; and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>any other financial company;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.5B">
          <num>(5B)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.5B.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" financial company" means a company, other than a company  referred to in sub- clause (i), (ii) or (iii) of clause (5A), being-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5B.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a hire- purchase finance company, that is to say, a  company which carries on, as its principal business, hire-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.5B.list3">
              <listIntroduction>purchase transactions or the financing of such  transactions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5B.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>an investment company, that is to say, a company which  carries on, as its principal business, the acquisition of  shares, stock, bonds, debentures, debenture stock or  securities issued by the Government or a local authority, or  other marketable securities of a like nature;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5B.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>a housing finance company, that is to say, a company  which carries on, as its principal business, the business of  financing of acquisition or construction of houses, including  acquisition or development of land in connection therewith;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5B.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>a loan company, that is to say, a company not being a  company referred to in sub- clauses (i) to (iii) which  carries on, as its principal business, the business of  providing finance, whether by making loans or advances or  otherwise;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5B.list3.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>a mutual benefit finance company, that is to say, a  company which carries on, as its principal business, the  business of acceptance of deposits from its members and which  is declared by the Central Government under section 620A of  the Companies Act, 1956, to be a Nidhi or Mutual Benefit</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.5B.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Society;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5B.list5.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>a miscellaneous finance company, that is to say, a  company which carries on exclusively, or almost exclusively,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>two or more classes of business referred to in the preceding  sub- clauses;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, 1961; (43 of 1961.)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" interest" means interest on loans and advances made in</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.7.list2">
              <listIntroduction>India and includes-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.7.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>commitment charges on unutilised portion of any credit  sanctioned for being availed of in India; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.7.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>discount on promissory notes and bills of exchange drawn  or made in, India,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.7.list4">
              <listIntroduction>but does not include-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.7.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>interest referred to in sub- section (1B) of the Reserve</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.7.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Bank of India Act, 1934;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.7.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>discount on treasury bills;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.7.list6.va">
                <num>(va)</num>
                <p>a residuary non- banking company other than a financial  company referred to in sub- clause (i), (ii), (iii), (iv), or (v)</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>that is to say, a company which receives any deposit under any scheme  or arrangement, by whatever name called, in one lumpsum or in  instalments by way of contributions or subscriptions or by sale of  units or certificates or other instruments or in any other manner; or]</p>
            <p>--- Subject to the provisions of this Act, the chargeable interest  any previous year of a credit institution shall be the total amount of  interest (other than interest on loans and advances made to other   credit institutions)  or to any cooperative society engaged in  carrying on the business of banking]</p>
            <p>Provided that any interest in relation to categories of had or  doubtful debts referred to in section 43D of the Income- tax Act  shall be deemed to accrue or arise to the credit institution in the  previous year in which it is credited by the credit institution to its  profit and loss account for that year or, as the case may be, in which  it is actually received by the credit institution, whichever is  earlier.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>all other words and expressions used herein but not defined  and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the meanings respec-</p>
            <p>tively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Tax authorities.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The income- tax authorities specified  in section 116 of the income- tax Act shall be the interest- tax  authorities for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such authority shall exercise the powers and perform  the functions of an interest- tax authority under this Act in respect  of any person within his jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1B">
          <num>(1B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The jurisdiction of an interest- tax authority under this Act  shall be the same as he has under the Income- tax Act by virtue of  orders or directions issued under section 120 of that Act (including   orders or directions assigning the concurrent jurisdiction) or under  any other provision of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1C">
          <num>(1C)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The interest- tax authority having jurisdiction in relation  to a credit institution which has no income assessable to income- tax  under the Income- tax Act shall be the interest- tax authority having  jurisdiction in respect of the area in which that institution carries  on its business or has its principal place of business.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1D">
          <num>(1D)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Section 118 of the Income- tax Act and any notification  issued thereunder shall apply- in relation to the control of interest-</p>
            <p>tax authorities as they apply in relation to the control of the cor-</p>
            <p>responding income- tax authorities, except to the extent to which the</p>
            <p>Board may, by notification in the Official Gazette, otherwise direct  in respect of any interest- tax authority-:]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All officers and persons employed in the execution of this-</p>
            <p>Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions  of the Board:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be  issued-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>so as to require any tax authority to make a Particular  assessment or to dispose of a particular case in a particular  manner; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>so as to interfere with the discretion of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Commissioner (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate  functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Income- tax Officer or Assistant Commissioner 9  employed in the execution of this Act shall observe and follow the  orders, instructions and directions issued for his guidance by the</p>
            <p>Director 9 or by the Commissioner or by the Additional Commissioner  of Income- tax or the Deputy Commissioner 9 within whose  jurisdiction he performs his functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Charge of tax.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act,</p>
            <p>there shall be charged on every scheduled bank for every assessment  year commencing on or after the 1st day of April, 1975, a tax (in this</p>
            <p>Act referred to as interest- tax) in respect of its chargeable interest  of the previous year at the rate of seven per cent. of such chargeable  interest:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) but  subject to the other provisions of this Act, there shall be charged  on every credit institution for every assessment year commencing on  and from 1st day of April, 1992, interest- tax in respect of its  chargeable interest of the previous year at the rate of three per  cent of such chargeable interest.]</p>
            <p>Provided that the rate at which interest- tax shall be charged  in respect of any chargeable interest accruing or arising after the</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31st">
        <num>31st.</num>
        <heading>day of March, 1983, shall be three and a half per cent. of such  chargeable interest.]</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Computation of chargeable interest.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the  provisions of sub- section (2), in computing the chargeable interest of  a previous year, there shall be allowed from the total amount of  interest (other than interest on loans and advances made to  credit   institutions]) accruing or arising to the assessee in the previous  year, a deduction in respect of the amount of interest which is  established to have become a bad debt during the previous year:</p>
            <p>Provided that such interest has been taken into, account in  computing the chargeable interest of the assessee of an earlier  previous year and the amount has been written off as irrecoverable in  the accounts of the assessee for the previous year during which it is  established to have become a bad debt.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that in computing the chargeable interest of a previous year, no  deduction, other than the deduction specified in this sub- section,</p>
            <p>shall be allowed from the total amount of interest accruing or arising  to the assesses.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In computing the chargeable interest of a previous year, the  amount of interest which accrues or arises to the assessee ' during  the period commencing on the 1st day of April, 1985 and ending with  the 30th day of September, 1991"].  before the 1st day of</p>
            <p>August, 1974 or during the period commencing on the 1st day of March,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1978">
        <num>1978.</num>
        <heading>and ending with the 30th day of June, 1980.] shall not be  taken into account.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Return of chargeable interest."</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of every  credit institution, its principal officer, or where in the case of a  non- resident credit institution any person has been treated as its  agent under section 163 of the Income- tax Act, such person, shall  furnish a return of the chargeable interest of the credit institution  of the previous year in the prescribed form and verified in the  prescribed manner and setting forth such other particulars as may be  prescribed, before the 31st day of December of the assessment year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>Assessing Officer may, before the end of the relevant assessment year,</p>
            <p>serve a notice upon the principal officer of any credit institution,</p>
            <p>or where in the case of a non- resident credit institution any person  has been treated as its agent under section 163 of the Income- tax Act,</p>
            <p>upon such person, requiring him to furnish within thirty days from the  date of service of the notice a return of the chargeable interest of  the credit institution of the previous year in the prescribed form and  verified in the prescribed manner and setting forth such other  particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any assessee who has not furnished a return within the time  allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or having furnished  a return under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) discovers any  omission or wrong statement therein, may furnish a return or a revised  return, as the case may be, at any time  before the expiry of one  year from the end of the relevant assessment year or before the  completion of the assessment, whichever is earlier]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Assessment.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of making an assessment  under this Act, the  Assessing officer] may serve on any person who  has furnished a return under section 7 or upon whom a notice has been  served under sub- section (2) of section 7 (whether a return has been   furnished or not) a notice requiring him on a date therein to be  specified, to produce or cause to be produced such accounts or  documents or evidence as the  Assessing officer]  Assessing officer]</p>
            <p>may require for the purposes of this Act and may, from time to time,</p>
            <p>serve further notices requiring the production of such further  accounts or documents or other evidence as he may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Assessing officer], after considering such accounts,</p>
            <p>documents or evidence, if any, as he has obtained under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and after taking into account any relevant material which he has  gathered, shall, by an order in writing assess the chargeable interest  and the amount of the interest- tax payable on the basis of such  assessment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>fails to make a return as required under sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 7 and has not made a return or a revised  return under sub- section (3) of that section, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>falls to comply with all the terms of notice under sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>section (2) of that section,</p>
            <p>the Assessing Officer shall, after taking into account all the  relevant material which he has gathered and after giving the assessee  an opportunity of being heard, make the assessment of the total  chargeable interest to the best of his judgment and determine the sum  payable by the assessee on the basis of such assessment:</p>
            <p>Provided that such opportunity shall be given by the Assessing</p>
            <p>Officer by serving a notice calling upon the assessee to show cause,</p>
            <p>on a date and time to be specified in the notice, why the assessment  should not be completed to the best of his judgment:</p>
            <p>Provided further that it shall not be necessary to give such  opportunity in a case where a notice under sub- section (1) has been  issued prior to the making of an assessment under this section.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Self- assessment.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where interest- tax is payable on the  basis of any return required to be furnished under section 7 or  section 10, after taking into account the amount of interest- tax, if  any, already paid under any provision of this Act, the assessee shall  be liable to pay such interest- tax, together with interest payable  under any provision of this Act for any delay in furnishing the return  or any default or delay in payment of advance interest- tax, before  furnishing the return and the return shall be accompanied by proof of  payment of such interest- tax and interest.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- Where the amount paid by the assessee under' this  sub- section falls short of the aggregate of the interest- tax and  interest as aforesaid, the amount so paid shall first be adjusted  towards the interest payable as aforesaid and the balance, it any,</p>
            <p>shall be adjusted towards the interest- tax payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the assessment under section 8 has been made, any  amount paid under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have been paid  towards such assessment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any assessee fails to pay the whole or any part of  interest- tax or interest or both in accordance with the provisions of  subsection (1), he shall, without- prejudice to any other consequences  which he may incur, be deemed to be an assessee in default in respect  of the interest- tax or interest or both remaining unpaid, and all the  provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Interest escaping assessment. If-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Assessing officer 2 has reason to believe that by  reason of the omission or failure on the part of the assessee  to make a return under section 7 for any assessment year or  to disclose fully and truly all material facts necessary for  his assessment for any assessment year, chargeable interest  for that year has escaped assessment or has been under-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>assessed or has been made the subject of. excessive relief  under this Act, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>notwithstanding that there has been no omission or  failure as mentioned in clause (a) on the part of the  assessee, the  Assessing officer] has, in consequence of  information in his possession, reason to believe that  chargeable interest assessable for any assessment year has  escaped assessment or has been under- assessed or has been the  subject of excessive relief under this Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he may, in cases falling under clause (a), at any time, and in cases  falling under clause (b), at any time within four years of the end of  that assessment year, serve on the assessee a notice containing all or  any of the requirements which may be included in a notice under  section 7, and may proceed to assess or reassess the amount chargeable  to interest- tax, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as may  be, apply, as if the notice were a notice issued under that section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Time limit for completion of assessments and  reassessments.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order of assessment shall be made under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>any time after the expiry of two years from the end of the  assessment year in which the interest was first assessable.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order of assessment or reassessment shall be made under  section 10 after the expiry of two years from the end of the  financial year in which the notice under that section was served.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, an order of fresh assessment in pursuance of an order passed  under section 15, section 16, section 19 or section 20, setting aside  or cancelling an' assessment, may be made at any time before the  expiry of two' years from the end of the financial year in which the  order under section 15 or section 16 is received by the Commissioner  or, as the case may be, the order under section 19 or section 20 is  passed by the Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) shall not apply  to the assessment or reassessment made in consequence of, or to give  effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order under  section 15 or section 16 or section 19 or section 20 of this Act or  section 256 or section 260 of the Income- tax Act as applicable to this</p>
            <p>Act by virtue of section 21 of this Act or in an order of any court in  it proceeding otherwise than by way of appeal or reference under this</p>
            <p>Act and such assessment or reassessment may, subject to the provisions  of sub- section (3), be completed at any time.</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.4.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation 1- In computing the period of limitation for the  purposes of this section-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.4.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the time taken in reopening the whole or any part of  the proceeding; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.4.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the period during which the assessment proceeding is  stayed by an order or injunction of any court,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be excluded.</p>
            <p>Explanation 2.--- Where, by an order referred to in sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, any interest is excluded from the chargeable interest for an  assessment year in respect of an assessee, then, an assessment of such  interest for another assessment year shall, for the purposes of  section 10 and this section, be deemed to be one made in consequence  of, or to give effect to, any finding or direction contained in the  said order.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Advance payment of interest- tax.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Interest- tax shall  be payable in advance during the-- year in respect of the  chargeable interest for the assessment year immediately following that  financial year in accordance---- the provision of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Interest- tax shall be payable in advance in three  instalments during each financial year, the due date of, and the  amount payable in, each such instalment being as specified in the  following Table:</p>
            <p>TABLE</p>
            <p>Due date of instalment Amount payable</p>
            <p>On or before the 15th September Not less than twenty per cent.</p>
            <p>of such interest- tax payable  in advance.</p>
            <p>On or before the 15th December Not less than fifty per cent.</p>
            <p>of such interest- tax payable  in advance, as reduced by  the amount, if any, paid in  the earlier instalment.</p>
            <p>On or before the 15th March The whole amount of such interest-</p>
            <p>tax payable in advance as reduced  by the amount or amount, if any,</p>
            <p>paid in the earlier instalment  or instalments</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Opportunity of being heard. No order imposing a penalty  under section 12 or section 13 shall be made unless the assessee has  been heard, or has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to the Commissioner Appeals.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person  objecting to the amount of interest- tax for which he is assessed by  the  Assessing Officer] or denying his liability to be assessed  under this Act, or objecting to any penalty or fine imposed by the</p>
            <p>Assessing Officer], or to the amount allowed by the  Assessing</p>
            <p>Officer] refusal by the  Assessing Officer] to grant relief or to an  order of rectification having the effect of enhancing the assessment  or reducing the refund, or to an order refusing to allow the claim  made by the assessed for a rectification under section 17, may appeal  to the  Commissioner (Appeals)].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be  verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the  following date, that is to say,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the appeal relates to assessment or penalty or  fine, the date of service of the notice of demand relating to  the assessment or penalty or fine or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any other case, the date on which the intimation of  the order sought to be appealed against is served:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the  Commissioner (Appeals)] may admit an appeal after  the expiration of the said period if he is satisfied that the  appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting it within that  period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Commissioner (Appeals)] shall hear and determine the  appeal and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass such orders as  he thinks fit and such orders may include an order enhancing the  assessment or penalty:</p>
            <p>Provided that an order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall  not be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a  reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be adopted in the hearing and determination  of the appeals shall, with any necessary modification, be in  accordance with the procedure applicable in relation to income- tax.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any assessee aggrieved by  an order passed by a Commission under section 19, or an order passed  by  a Commissioner (Appeals)] under any provision of this Act, may  appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner may, if he objects to any order passed by  the  Commissioner (Appeals)] under any provision of this Act, direct  the Assessing Officer 4 to appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against  the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under subsection (1) or sub- section (2) shall  be filed within sixty days of the date on which the order sought to be  appealed against is communicated to the assessee or to the</p>
            <p>Commissioner, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Assessing Officer or the assessee, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>on receipt of notice that an appeal against the order of the</p>
            <p>Commissioner (Appeals)] has been preferred under sub- section (1) or  sub- section (2) by the other party may, notwithstanding that he may  not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, within  thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file a memorandum of cross-</p>
            <p>objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part of the  order of the  Commissioner (Appeals)] and such memorandum shall be  disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an appeal  presented within the time specified in sub- section (3).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the  filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the  relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if  it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it  within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the  prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and,</p>
            <p>shall, except in the case of an appeal referred to in sub- section (2)</p>
            <p>or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in sub- section (4), be  accompanied by a fee of one hundred and twenty five two hundred  rupees 2</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, in hearing and making  an order on any appeal under this section, the Appellate Tribunal  shall exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it  exercises and follows in hearing and making an order on any appeal  under the Income- tax Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Rectification of mistakes.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With a view to rectifying any  mistake apparent from the record, the Commissioner, the  Assessing</p>
            <p>Officer] the Commissioner (Appeals) and the Appellate Tribunal may,</p>
            <p>of his, or its, own motion or on an application by the assessee in  this behalf, amend any order passed by him or it in any proceeding  under this Act  within four years from the end of the financial year  in which such order was passed]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the  assessment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability  of the assessee shall not be made under this section unless the  authority concerned has given notice to the assessee of its intention  so to do and has allowed the assessee a reasonable opportunity of  being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an amendment is made under this section, the order  shall be passed in writing by the authority concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, where any such  amendment has the effect of reducing the assessment, the  Assessing</p>
            <p>Officer] shall make any refund which may be due to such assessee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the  assessment or reducing the refund already made, the  Assessing</p>
            <p>Officer] shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the  prescribed form specifying the sum payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Interest- tax deductible in computing total income under  the Income- tax Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>tax Act, in computing the income of a credit institution chargeable to  income- tax under the head" Profits and gains of business or  profession" or under the head" Income from other sources", the  interest- tax payable by the credit institution for any assessment year  shall be deductible from the income, under the respective heads, of  the credit institution assessable for that assessment year.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Revision of order prejudicial to revenue.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any proceeding  under this Act, and if he considers that any order passed therein by  the  Assessing Officer] is erroneous in so far as it is prejudicial  to the interests of the revenue, he may, after giving the assessee an  opportunity of being heard and after making or causing to be made such  enquiry as he deems necessary, pass such order thereon as the  circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or  modifying the assessment, or cancelling the assessment and directing a  fresh assessment.</p>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that, for the purposes of this sub- section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" record" shall include and shall be deemed always to  have included all records relating to any proceeding under  this Act available at the time of examination by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Commissioner;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where any order referred to in this sub- section is the  subject matter of any appeal, the power of the Commissioner  under this subsection shall extend to all such matters as had  not been considered and decided in such appeal.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order shall be made under sub- section (1) after the  expiry of two years from the end of the financial year in which the  order sought to be revised was passed."]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), an  order in revision under this section may be passed at any time in the  case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to give  effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the</p>
            <p>Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- In computing the period of limitation for the  purposes of sub- section (2)  the time taken in giving an opportunity  to the assessee to be re- heard under the priviso to section 129 of the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Act, as applicable to this Act by virtue of section 21 of  this Act, and"] any period during which any proceeding under this  section is stayed by an order or injunction of any court shall be  excluded,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Revision of Order by Commissioner.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner may,</p>
            <p>either of his own motion or on an application by the assessee for  revision, call for the record of any proceeding under this Act which  has been taken by an Income- tax Officer  subordinate to him and  may, make such enquiry or cause such enquiry to be made and, subject  to the provisions of this Act, may pass such order thereon, not being  an order prejudicial to the assessee, as he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner shall not of his own motion revise any.</p>
            <p>order under this section if the order has been made more than one year  previously.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of an application for revision under this</p>
            <p>' section by the assessee, the application shall be made within one  year from the date on which the order in question was communicated to  him or the date on which he otherwise came to know of it, whichever is  earlier:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the  assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application  within that period, admit an application made after the expiry, of  that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commissioner shall not revise any order under this  section in the following cases-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where an appeal against the order lies to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-20.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Commissioner (Appeals) or to the Appellate Tribunal but has  not been made and the time within which such appeal may be  made has not expired, or the assessee has not waived his  right of appeal; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the order has been made the subject of an appeal    to the Commissioner (Appeals) or to the Appellate Tribunal]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every application by an assessee for revision under this  section shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty- five rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation 1.- An order by the Commissioner declining to  interfere shall, for the purposes of this section, be deemed not to be  an order prejudicial to the assessee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Application of provisions of Income- tax Act. The provisions  of the following sections and Schedule of the Income- tax Act and the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Income- tax (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, 1962 as in force from time  to time, shall apply with necessary modifications as if the said  provisions and the rules referred to interest- tax instead of to  income- tax;--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-2.44">
          <num>(44)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, 129, 131, 132, 132A, 132B, 133 to 136 (both   inclusive), 138, 140, 145, 156, 160, 161, 162, 163, 166, 167,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-170">
        <num>170.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-170.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, 173, 175 176, 178, 179, 220 to 227 (both inclusive),</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-228A">
        <num>228A.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-228A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, 229, 232, 237 to 245 (both inclusive), 254 to 262 (both   inclusive), 265, 266, 268, 269, 281, 281B, 282, 284, 287,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-288">
        <num>288.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-288.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, 288A, 288B, 289 to 293 (both inclusive), the Second</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleand">
      <doc name="scheduleand">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1974/45/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1974/45"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Third Schedule.]"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1974/45/eng@1974-09-23"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleand">
            <paragraph id="scheduleand.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Provided that references in the said provisions and the rules  to the" assessee" shall be construed as references to an,</p>
                <p>assessee as defined in this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Income- tax papers to be available for the purposes of this</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Act.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-22.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, all  information contained in any statement or return made or furnished  under the provisions of that Act or obtained or collected for the  purposes of that Act may be used for the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All information contained in any statement or return made or  furnished under the provisions of this Act or obtained or collected  for the purposes of this Act may be used for the purposes of the</p>
                  <p>Income- tax Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Failure comply with notices. If any person fails,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>without reasonable cause, to produce or cause to be produced, any  accounts or documents required to be produced tinder section 8, he  shall pay by way of penalty, a sum which shall not be less than one  thousand rupees, but which may extend to twenty- five thousand rupees,</p>
                  <p>for each such failure,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>False statements. If a person makes a statement in any  verification under this Act or any rule made thereunder, or delivers  an account or statement which is false, and which he either knows or  believes to be false or does not believe to be true, he shall be  punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be  less than three months but which may extend Lo sever. years and with  fine.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Wilful attempt to evade tax, etc. If a person wilfully  attempts in any manner whatsoever to evade any interest- tax, penalty  or interest chargeable or impassable, under this Act, he shall,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>without prejudice to any penalty that may be impassable on him under  any other provision of this Act, be punishable with' rigorous  imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months but  which may extend to seven years and with fine.</p>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, a wilful attempt  to evade any' interest- tax, penalty or interest chargeable or  impassable under this Act or the payment thereof shall include a case  where any person-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>has in his possession or control any books of account  or other documents (being books of account or other documents   relevant to any proceeding under this Act) containing a false  entry or statement; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>makes or causes to be made any false entry or statement  in such books of account or other documents; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>wilfully omits or causes to be omitted any relevant  entry or statement in such books of account or other  documents; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>causes any other circumstances to exist which will have  the effect of enabling such per- son to evade any interest-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>tax, penalty or interest chargeable or impassable under this</p>
                  <p>Act or the payment thereof.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Abetment of false returns, etc. If a person abets or  induces in any manner another person to make and deliver any account  or a statement or declaration relating to any chargeable interest  which is false and which he either knows or believes to be false or  does not believe to be true or to commit an offence under section 25,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>he shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which  shall not be less than three months but which may extend to seven  years and with fine.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26A">
              <num>26A.</num>
              <heading>Offences by credit institutions.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-26A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where an offence under  this Act has been committed by a credit institution, every person who,</p>
                  <p>at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was  responsible to, the credit institution or the conduct of the business  of the credit institution as well as the credit institution shall be  deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded  against and punished accordingly:</p>
                  <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence  was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due  diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1),</p>
                  <p>tution and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the</p>
                  <p>---- any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the credit  institution, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall  also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be  proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," director", in  relation to a co- operative society, means any member controlling the  affairs thereof.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26B">
              <num>26B.</num>
              <heading>Institution of proceedings and composition of offences.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-26B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A person shall not be proceeded against for any offence under section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>or section 25 or section 26 or for any offence under the Indian</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Penal Code, except with the previous sanction of the Commissioner or</p>
                  <p>Commissioner (Appeals):</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Chief Commissioner or, as the case may be,</p>
                  <p>Director General may issue such instructions or directions to the  aforesaid interest- tax authorities as he may deem fit for institution  of proceedings under this sub- section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-24.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any offence under the sections referred to in sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may, either before or after the institution of proceedings, be  compounded by the Chief Commissioner or Director General.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that the power of the Board to issue orders, instructions or direc-</p>
                  <p>tions under this Act shall include the power to issue instructions or  directions (including instructions or directions to obtain the pre-</p>
                  <p>vious approval of the Board) to other interest- tax authorities for the  proper composition of offences under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26C">
              <num>26C.</num>
              <heading>Power of credit institutions to vary certain agreements.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26C.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any agreement under which any  term loan has been sanctioned by the credit institution before the 1st  day of October, 1991, it shall be lawful for the credit institution to  vary the agreement, so as to increase the rate of interest stipulated  therein to the extent to which such institution is liable to pay the  interest- tax under this Act in relation to the amount of interest on  the term loan which is due to the credit institution.</p>
                  <p>Explanation- For the purposes of this section," term loan" means  a loan which is not repayable on demand-]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-27.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board my, subject to the  control of the Central Government, by notification in the official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the form in which returns under section 7 may be  furnished and the manner in which they may be Verified;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the form in which appeals under section 15 or section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>may be filed and the manner in which they may be verified</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the procedure to be followed on applications for  rectification of mistakes and applications for refunds-,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which by this Act is to be, or may be,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-16.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The power to make rules conferred by this section shall on  the first occasion of the exercise thereof include the power to give  retrospective effect to the rules or any of them from a date not  earlier than the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under  this section to be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made before  each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree In making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Power to exempt. Where the Central Government is of the  opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do either in the  public interest or having regard to the peculiar circumstances of the  case, it may, by notification, and subject to conditions, if any, as  may be specified in the notification, exempt  any credit institution  or any class of credit institutions or any interest on any category of  loans advances] levy of interest- tax:</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Provided that no such exemption shall be made except on the  recommendation of the Reserve Bank of India.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulty.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-29.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>] If any difficulty  arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, Central</p>
                  <p>Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this</p>
                  <p>Act, remove the difficulty:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the  provisions of this Act, as amended by the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1991,</p>
                  <p>the Central Government may, by order, do anything not inconsistent  with such provisions for the purpose of removing the difficulty:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry Of two  years from the 1st day of October, 1991.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every order made under sub- section (2) shall be laid before  each House of Parliament.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
