<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1873/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1873/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Government Savings Banks Act, 1873"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1873/5/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1873/5/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1873/5/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1873/5/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Government Savings Banks Act, 1873</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Government Savings Banks Act, 1873.</p>
            <p>Local extent.—</p>
            <p>It extends1 to</p>
            <p>the whole of India.</p>
            <p>***.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply to deposits in Anchal Savings Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall not apply to any deposits made in the Anchal Savings Bank of the State of Travancore-Cochin, and, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, any law in force in the said State immediately before the commencement of the Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951 (3 of 1951), relating to such deposits, shall continue to apply thereto as if that law had not been repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation-clause.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act—</p>
            <p>“depositor” means a person by whom, or on whose behalf money has been heretofore, or shall be hereafter, deposited in a Government Savings Bank, and “deposit” means money so deposited:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>“Government Savings Bank” means—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a Post Office Savings Bank; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a banking company, or any other company or institution, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, for the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>“Secretary” means— tc " “Secretary” means—"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the case of a Post Office Savings Bank, the Postmaster-General appointed for the area in which the Post Office Savings Bank is situated, or any officer of the Government as the Central Government may, by general or special order, specify in this behalf; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the case of a banking company or other company or institution, an officer of that banking company or other company or institution, as the case may be, or any officer of the Government or any other person as the Central Government may, by general or special order, specify in this behalf;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“minor” means a person who is not deemed to have attained his majority under the Indian Majority Act, 1875 (9 of 1875):</p>
            <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Nomination by depositor.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, or in any disposition, whether testamentary or otherwise, by a depositor in respect of his deposit, where any nomination made in the prescribed manner purports to confer on any person the right to receive the deposit on the death of the depositor, the nominee shall, on the death of the depositor become entitled, to the exclusion of all other persons, to be paid the deposit, unless the nomination is varied or cancelled in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any nomination referred to in sub-section (1) shall become void if the nominee predeceases, or where there are two or more nominees, all the nominees predecease, the depositor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the nominee is a minor it shall be lawful for the depositor to appoint in the prescribed manner any person to receive the deposit in the event of his death during the minority of the nominee. ]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Payment on death of depositor.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a depositor dies and there is in force at the time of the death of the depositor a nomination in favour of any person, the deposit shall be paid to the nominee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the nominee is a minor, the deposit shall be paid—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any case where a person has been appointed to receive it under sub-section (3) of section 4, to that person; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where there is no such person, to the guardian of the minor for the use of the minor.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a deposit is payable to two or more nominees and either or any of them is dead, the deposit shall be paid to the surviving nominee or nominees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a depositor dies and there is no nomination in force at the time of his death and probate of his will or letters of administration of his estate or a succession certificate granted under the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), is not within three months of the death of the depositor produced to the Secretary of the Government Savings Bank in which the deposit is, then—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the deposit does not exceed</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4A.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>such limit as may be prescribed the Secretary may pay the same to any person appearing to him to be entitled to receive it or to administer the estate of the deceased; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>within the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>limit prescribed under clause (a), any officer employed in the management of a Government Savings Bank who is empowered in this behalf by a general or special order of the Central Government may, to the extent to which he is empowered by such order and subject to any general or special orders of the Secretary in this behalf, pay the deposit to any person appearing to him to be entitled to receive it or to administer the estate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to require any person to accept payment of a deposit, which is a time deposit, before it has become due.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Payment to be a discharge.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any payment made in accordance with the foregoing provisions of this Act shall be a full discharge from all further liability in respect of the money so paid:</p>
            <p>Saving of right of executor.—</p>
            <p>But nothing herein contained precludes any executor or administrator, or other representative of the deceased, from recovering from the person receiving the same the amount remaining in his hands after deducting the amount of all debts or other demands lawfully paid or discharged by him in due course of administration.</p>
            <p>Saving of right of creditor.—</p>
            <p>And any creditor or claimant against the estate of the deceased may recover his debt or claim out of the money paid under this Act,*** to any person, and remaining in his hands unadministered, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the latter had obtained letters of administration of the estate of the deceased.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Security for due administration.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Secretary of any such Bank</p>
            <p>or any officer empowered</p>
            <p>under sub-section (4) of section 4A may take such security as he thinks necessary from any person</p>
            <p>to whom he pays any money under sub-section (4) of section 4A for the due administration of the money so paid,</p>
            <p>and he may assign the said security to any person interested in such administration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to administer oath.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of ascertaining the right of the person claiming to be entitled as aforesaid, the Secretary of any such Bank</p>
            <p>or any officer empowered</p>
            <p>under sub-section (4) of section 4A may take evidence on oath or affirmation according to the law3 for the time being relating to oaths and affirmations.</p>
            <p>Penalty for false statements.—</p>
            <p>Any person who, upon such oath or affirmation, makes any statement which is false, and which he either knows or believes to be false or does not believe to be true, shall be deemed guilty of an offence under section 193 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Deposit when excluded in computing court fees.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the amount of the deposit belonging to the estate of a deceased depositor does not exceed</p>
            <p>three thousand rupees, such amount shall be excluded in computing the fee chargeable, under the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), on the probate, or letters of administration, or certificate (if any), granted in respect of his property:</p>
            <p>Provided that the person claiming such probate or letters or certificate shall exhibit to the Court authorized to grant the same a certificate of the amount of the deposit in any Government Savings Bank belonging to the estate of the deceased. Such certificate shall be signed by the Secretary of such Bank, and the Court shall receive it as evidence of the said amount.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply to deposits belonging to estates of European soldiers or deserters.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Government Savings Banks (Amendment) Act, 1959 (45 of 1959), sec. 7 (w.e.f. 18-9-1959).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Payment of deposits to minor or guardian.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any deposit made by, or on behalf of, any minor, may be paid to him personally, if he made the deposit, or to his guardian for his use if the deposit was made by any person other than the minor, together with the interest accrued thereon.</p>
            <p>The receipt of any minor or guardian, for money paid to him under this section, shall be a sufficient discharge therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Legalization of like payments heretofore made.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Government Savings Banks (Amendment) Act, 1959 (45 of 1959), sec.7 (w.e.f. 18-9-1959).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Payment of deposits belonging to lunatics.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any depositor becomes insane or otherwise incapable of managing his affairs,</p>
            <p>and if such insanity or incapacity is proved to the satisfaction of the Secretary of the Bank in which his deposit may be,</p>
            <p>such Secretary may, from time to time, make payments out of the deposit to any proper person,</p>
            <p>and the receipt of such person, for money paid under this section, shall be a sufficient discharge therefor.</p>
            <p>Where a committee or manager of the depositor’s estate has been duly appointed, nothing in this section authorizes payments to any person other than such committee or manager.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Payment of married women’s deposits.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any deposit made by or on behalf of a married woman, or by or on behalf of a woman who afterwards marries, may be paid to her, whether or not</p>
            <p>section 20 of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), applies to her marriage; and her receipt for money paid to her under this section shall be a sufficient discharge therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Secretary or any other officer of the Government in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the persons by whom and the terms and conditions subject to which deposits may be made in a Government Savings Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the maximum limits of deposits and the conditions as to interest or discount relating to deposits generally, or any class of deposits in particular;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the non-accrual of interest on deposits when the maximum limits are exceeded and the recovery of any interest paid in excess in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue or in any other manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the persons to whom and the manner in which deposits may be paid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the form of nominations, the manner in which, the persons in whose favour and the conditions and restrictions subject to which, nominations may be made and the registration of nominations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the variation or cancellation of nominations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the fees that may be levied for registration of nominations and for variation or cancellation thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which any person may be appointed for the purpose of sub-section (3) of section 4; tc " (h) the manner in which any person may be appointed for the purpose of sub-section (3) of section 4;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the limit under clause (a) of sub-section (4) of section 4A.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or</p>
            <p>in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the sucessive sessions aforesaid both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under this rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
