<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Mangrol And Manavadar (Administration Of Property) Act, 1949"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1949-02-14" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Mangrol And Manavadar (Administration Of Property) Act, 1949</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 2 OF 1949</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 14th February, 1949.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the vesting of certain properties belonging to  the States of Mangrol and Manavadar in Kathiawar in the Managers  of the said States.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS the administration of the States of Mangrol and Manavadar  has been taken over by the Central Government;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the vesting of certain  properties belonging to the said States in the Managers thereof  appointed by or on behalf of the Central Government and for certain  matters incidental thereto;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted an follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the mangrol and Manavadar</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Administration of Property) Act, 1949.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act," Manager" means the Manager for the  time being of the State of Mangrol or the State of Manavadar, as the  case may be, appointed by, or on behalf of, the Central Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of property in Manager. Notwithstanding anything  contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any  instrument or other document whatsoever, the properties described in  the Schedule, which stand in the name of the Sheikh of Mangrol or in  the name of the Khan of Manavadar, whether in his personal capacity or  as the legal representative of any deceased person or in any other  capacity, or the Begum Sahiban Fatma, or of any karbhari or other  officer of Mangrol or Manavadar in his official capacity, or in the  names of more than one of them, shall be deemed to have vested and  always to have been vested on and from the 1st day of November, 1947,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>as follows, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the properties are included in Part I of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theninthemanagerofthestateofmangrol">
      <doc name="theninthemanagerofthestateofmangrol">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", then in the manager of the State of Mangrol,"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theninthemanagerofthestateofmangrol">
            <heading>and</heading>
            <paragraph id="theninthemanagerofthestateofmangrol.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="theninthemanagerofthestateofmangrol.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="theninthemanagerofthestateofmangrol.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>if the properties are included in Part II of the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-theninthemanagerofthestateof">
      <doc name="theninthemanagerofthestateof">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/theninthemanagerofthestateof"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", then in the Manager of the State of"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14/theninthemanagerofthestateof"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14/theninthemanagerofthestateof"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/2/eng@1949-02-14"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theninthemanagerofthestateof">
            <heading>Manavadar.</heading>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Powers of Manager. The manager shall have and exercise, in  relation to properties vested in him under section 3, all the rights,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>powers and authority which a full owner has or exercises in relation  to his own property:</p>
                  <p>Provided that where any of the said properties was, immediately  before the first day of November, 1947, subject to nay trust lawfully  created, the Manager shall, in the exercise of his powers in relation  to such property be bound by the terms of that trust.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Payment to Manger to be a discharge of obligations. Any  payment made to the Manager in the discharge of any of the obligations  in relation to any of the properties described in the Schedule shall  be a full discharge to the person or authority making the payment from  all liability in respect of such payment.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Issue of duplicate securities.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where for any reason any of  the Government securities described in the Schedule is not in the  custody of the Manager in whom it has vested under the provisions of  this Act, the Manager may make an application to the Reserve Bank of</p>
                  <p>India for the issue of a duplicate security in lieu thereof.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When an application under sub- section (1) has been made,</p>
                  <p>then, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time  being in force, the Reserve Bank of India shall issue a duplicate  security to the Manager as if the original security had been lost.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any duplicate security issued under the provisions of this  section shall have the same effect as if it had been issued under  section 11 of the Public Debt (Central Government) Act, 1944 (18 of</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1944">
              <num>1944.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1944.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Transfers otherwise than by Manager void. Any transfer or  other disposition of any property described in the Schedule made on or  after the 1st day of November, 1947, by any person other than the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Manager or without his consent shall be, and shall always be deemed to  have been, void and of no effect.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Power to call for information.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Central</p>
                  <p>Government is of opinion that any person is in possession of any  property which belongs to the State of Mangrol or the State of</p>
                  <p>Manavadar, it may, by notice in writing, require such person to  furnish such information as it may consider necessary for the purpose  of determining whether the property is</p>
                  <p>property belonging to the State of Mangrol or the State of Manavadar,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any person to whom a notice is sent under sub- section (1)</p>
                  <p>fails to comply therewith he shall be punishable with imprisonment  which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to one  thousand rupees or with both.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of Court.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No Court shall have  jurisdiction to entertain any civil or criminal proceeding in relation  to any of the properties described in the Schedule or to enforce any  liability in respect thereof save at the instance of the Manager.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to prohibit the  submission to the Central Government by any person other than the  manager of any claim in relation to any such property and the decision  of the Central Government on such claim shall be final and shall not  be called in question in any Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Power of the Central Government to add to the Schedule.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-10.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette, amend or alter the Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, the Central Government may, by notification as  aforesaid, add to the items of property included in Parts I and II of  the Schedule any other item which in its opinion represents property  belonging to the State of Mangrol or the State of Manavadar, as the  case may be, and on the issue of such notification any property  specified in the notification shall be deemed to be and always to have  been included in Part I or Part II of the Schedule, as the case may  be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit, prosecution or other legal  proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the Reserve Bank  of India, any bank or company mentioned in the Schedule, or the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Manager or any other person for anything which is in good faith done  or intended to be done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this</p>
                  <p>Act.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Repeal.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Mangrol and Manavadar (Administration of</p>
                  <p>Property) Ordinance, 1948 (22 of 1948), is hereby repealed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken in exercise of any power conferred by or under the said</p>
                  <p>Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken in exercise of  the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act had come  into force on the 16th day of August, 1948.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
