<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Customs Tariff Act, 1975"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1975-08-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Customs Tariff Act, 1975</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 51 OF 1975</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th August, 1975.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to customs duties.</p>
        <p>BE, it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of  the</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Customs Tariff Act, 1975.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date' as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Duties specified in the Schedule to be levied. The rates at  which duties of customs shall be levied under the Customs Act,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1962">
        <num>1962.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1962.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, (52 of 1962) are specified in the First and Second Schedules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Levy of additional duty equal to excise duty.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any article  which is imported into India shall, in addition, be liable to a duty</p>
            <p>(hereafter in this section referred to as the additional duty) equal  to the excise duty for the time being leviable on a like article if  produced or manufactured in India and if such excise duty on a like  article is leviable at any percentage of its value, the additional  duty to which the imported article shall be so liable shall be  calculated at that percentage, of the value of the imported article.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- In this section, the expression" the excise duty for  the time being leviable on a like article if produced or manufactured  in India" means the excise duty for the time being in force which  would be leviable on a like article if produced or manufactured in</p>
            <p>India or, if a like article is not so produced or manufactured, which  would be leviable on the class or description of articles to which  the imported article belongs, and where such duty is leviable at  different rates, the highest duty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of calculating- under this section the  additional duty on any imported article, where such duty is leviable  at any percentage of its value, the value of the imported article  shall, notwithstanding anything contained in section 14 of the Customs</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act, 1962, (52 of 1962) be the aggregate of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the value of the imported article determined under sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>section (1) of the said section 14 or the tariff value of  such article fixed under sub- section (2) of that section, as  the case may be; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any duty of customs chargeable on that article under  section 12 of the Customs Act, 1962, (52 of 1962) and any sum  chargeable on that article under any law for the time being  in force as an addition to, and in the same manner as, a duty  of customs, but not including the duty referred to in sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary  in the public interest to levy on any imported article whether on  such article duty is leviable under sub- section (1) or not such  additional duty as would counter- balance the excise duty leviable on  any raw materials, components and ingredients of the same nature as,</p>
            <p>or similar to those, used in the production or manufacture of such  article, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that  such imported article shall, in addition, be liable to an additional  duty representing such portion of the excise duty leviable on such raw  materials, components</p>
            <p>and ingredients as, in either case, may be determined by rules made by  the Central Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rules for the purposes of sub- section (3), the</p>
            <p>Central Government shall have regard to the average quantum of the  excise duty payable on the raw materials, components or ingredients  used in the production or manufacture of such like article.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The duty chargeable under this section shall be in addition  to any other duty imposed under this Act or under any other law for  the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Customs Act, 1962, (52 of 1962) and  the rules and regulations thereunder, including those relating to  drawbacks, refunds and exemption duties, shall,' so far as' may' be,</p>
            <p>apply to the duty chargeable under this section as they apply in  relation to the duties leviable under that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Levy of duty where standard rate and preferential rate are  specified.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in respect of any Article a preferential rate of  revenue' duty is specified in the First Schedule, or is admissible by  virtue of a notification under section 25 of the Customs Act, 1962,</p>
            <p>(52 of 1962) the duty to be levied and collected shall be at the  standard rate, unless the owner of the article claims at the time of  importation that it is chargeable with a preferential rate of duty,</p>
            <p>being  the produce or manufacture of such preferential area] as is  notified under subsection' (3) and the article is determined, in  accordance with the rules made under sub- section (2), to be such  produce or manufacture.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, make rules for determining if any article is  the produce or  manufacture of any preferential area].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this section and the First Schedule,</p>
            <p>preferential area'] means any country or territory which the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by Notification from in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>declare to be such area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained ins sub- section (1), where  the Central Government is satisfied that, that in the interests of  trade including promotion of exports, it is necessary to take  immediate action for discontinuing the preferential rate, or  increasing the preferential rate to a rate not exceeding the standard  rate, or decreasing the preferential rate, in respect of an article  specified in the First Schedule, the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct an amendment of the said</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51"/>
              <FRBRalias value="be made so as to provide for, such discontinuance of, or  increase or decrease, as the case may be, in, the preferential rate."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <subsection id="scheduleto.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every notification issued under sub- section (3) or sub-</p>
                <p>section (4) shall,' as soon as may be after it is issued, be' laid  before each House of Parliament.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Levy of a lower rate of duty under a trade agreement.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where  under a trade agreement between the Government of India and the</p>
                  <p>Government of a foreign country or territory, duty at a rate lower  than that specified in the First Schedule is to be charged on articles  which are the produce or manufacture of such foreign country or  territory, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, make rules for determining if any article is the produce or  manufacture of such foreign country or territory and for requiring the  owner to make a claim at the time of importation, supported by such  evidence as may be prescribed in the said rules, for assessment at the  appropriate lower rate under such Agreement.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any question arises whether any trade agreement applies  to any country or territory, or whether it has ceased to apply to</p>
                  <p>India or any foreign country or territory, it shall be referred to the</p>
                  <p>Central Government for decision and the decision of the Central</p>
                  <p>Government shall be final and shall not be liable to be questioned in  any court of law.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Power of Central Government to levy protective duties in  certain cases.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Central Government, upon a recommendation</p>
                  <p>' made to it in this behalf by the Tariff Commission established under  the Tariff Commission Act, 1951, (50 of 1951) is satisfied that  circumstances exist which render it necessary to take immediate action  to provide for the protection of the interests of any industry</p>
                  <p>established in India, the Central Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, impose on any goods imported into India in  respect of which the said recommendation is made, a duty of customs of  such amount, not exceeding the amount proposed in the said  recommendation, as it thinks fit.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every duty imposed on any goods under sub- section (1) shall,</p>
                  <p>for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to have been specified in the</p>
                  <p>First Schedule as the duty leviable in respect of such goods.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where a notification has been issued under sub- section (1),</p>
                  <p>the Central Government shall, unless the notification is in the  meantime rescinded, have a Bill introduced in Parliament, as soon as  may be, but in any case during the next session of Parliament  following the date of the issue of the notification to give effect to  the proposals in regard to the continuance of a protective duty of  customs on the goods to which the notification relates, and the  notification shall cease to have effect when such Bill becomes law,</p>
                  <p>whether with or without modifications, but without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done thereunder:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the notification under sub- section (1) is issued  when Parliament is in session, such a Bill shall be introduced in</p>
                  <p>Parliament during that session:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that where for any reason a Bill as aforesaid  does not become law within six months from the date of its  introduction in Parliament, the notification shall cease to have  effect on the expiration of the said period of six months, but without  prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Duration of protective duties and power of Central Government  to alter them.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the duty specified in respect of any article  in the First Schedule is characterised as protective in  column (5)]</p>
                  <p>of that Schedule, that duty shall have effect only up to and inclusive  of the date, if any, specified in that Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where in respect of any such article the Central Government  is satisfied after such inquiry as it thinks necessary that such duty  has become ineffective or excessive for the purpose of securing the  protection intended to be afforded by it' to be a similar article  manufactured in India and that circumstances exist which render it  necessary to take immediate action, it may, by notification in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette, increase of reduce such duty to such extent as it  thinks necessary.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification under sub- section (2), in so far as it  relates to increase of such duty, shall be laid before each House  of Parliament if it is sitting as soon as may be after the issue of  the notification, and if it is not sitting within seven days of its  re- assembly, and the Central Government shall seek the approval of</p>
                  <p>Parliament to the notification by a resolution moved within a period  of fifteen days beginning with the day on which the notification is so  laid before the House of the People and if Parliament make' s any  modification in the notification or directs that the notification  should cease to have effect, the notification shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done  thereunder.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any  notification issued under sub- section (2), including any such  notification approved or modified under sub- section (3), may be  rescinded by the Central Government at any time by notification in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Emergency power of Central Government to increase or levy  export duties.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where, in respect of any article, whether included  in the Second Schedule or not, the Central Government is satisfied  that the export duty leviable thereon should be increased or that an  export duty should be levied, and that circumstances exist which  render it necessary to take immediate action, the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct and amendment of  the Second Schedule to be made so as to provide for an increase the  export duty leviable or, as the case may be, for the levy of an export  duty, on that article.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of sub- section (3) and (4) of section 7 shall  apply to any notification issued under sub- section (1) as they apply  in relation to any notification increasing duty issued under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (2) of section 7.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8A">
              <num>8A.</num>
              <heading>Emergency power of Central Government to increase import  duties</heading>
              <subsection id="section-8A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where in respect of any article included in the First</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary">
      <doc name="thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", the Central Government is satisfied that the import duty  leviable thereon under section 12 of the Customs Act, 1962 should be  increased and that circumstances exist which render it necessary to  take immediate action, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette  direct an amendment of that Schedule to be made so as to provide for  an increase in the import duty leviable on such article to such extent  as it thinks necessary:"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18/thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18/thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/51/eng@1975-08-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary">
            <heading>Provided that the Central Government shall not issue any  notification under this sub- section for substituting. the rate of,</heading>
            <paragraph id="thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>import duty in respect of any article as specified by an earlier  notification issued under this sub- section be that Government before  such earlier notification has been approved with. or with. out  modifications under sub- section (2).</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="thecentralgovernmentissatisfiedthattheimportdutyleviablethereonundersection12ofthecustomsact1962shouldbeincreasedandthatcircumstancesexistwhichrenderitnecessarytotakeimmediateactionitmaybynotificationintheofficialgazettedirectanamendmentofthatscheduletobemadesoastoprovideforanincreaseintheimportdutyleviableonsucharticletosuchextentasitthinksnecessary.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4) of section 7  shall apply to any notification issued under sub- section (1) as they  apply in relation to any notification increasing duty issued under  sub- section (2) of section 7."]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Additional import duty on bountyfed articles.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Where any  country or territory pays, or bestows, directly or indirectly, any  bounty or Subsidy upon the manufacture or production therein or the  exportation therefrom of any article, then, upon the importation of  any such article into India, whether the same is imported directly  from the country of manufacture, production or otherwise, and whether  it is imported in the same condition as when exported from the country  of manufacture or production or has been changed in condition by  manufacture, production or otherwise, the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, impose,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>if the article is not otherwise chargeable with' duty  under the provisions of this Act, a duty or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>if the article is otherwise so chargeable, an  additional duty, not exceeding the amount of such bounty or  subsidy:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the Central Government may, pending the  determination in accordance with the provisions of this section and  the rules made thereunder of the amount of such bounty or grant,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>impose a duty or additional duty under this sub- section not exceeding  the amount of such bounty or subsidy as provisionally estimated by it  and if such duty or additional duty exceeds such bounty or subsidy as  so determined,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list4.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the Central Government shall, having regard to such  determination and as soon as may be after such determination,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>reduce such duty or additional duty; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list6.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>refund shall be made of so much of such duty or  additional duty which has been collected as is in excess of  the duty or additional duty as so reduced.];</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount of any such bounty or subsidy 1 as aforesaid  shall, from time to time, be ascertained, determined, and declared by  the Central Government, after such inquiry as it may consider  necessary and the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette, make rules for the identification of such articles  and for the assessment and collection of any  duty or additional  duty, as the case may be,] imposed upon the importation thereof under  sub- section (1).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification issued under sub- section (1) shall, as  soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before each House of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9A">
              <num>9A.</num>
              <heading>Antidumping duty.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any article is exported from  any country or territory (hereafter in this section referred to as the   exporting country or territory) to India at less than its normal  value, then, upon the importation of such article into India, the</p>
                  <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>impose,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>if the article is not otherwise chargeable with duty  under the provisions of this Act, a duty; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>if the article is otherwise so chargeable, an additional  duty, not exceeding the margin of dumping in relation to such  article:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>not exceeding the margin of dumping in relation to such  article:</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sub- section (1) and (2) of section 9 shall stand amended as  follows when section 2 of Act No. 52 of 1982 comes into force:--</p>
                  <p>" (1) Where any country or territory pays, or bestows, directly  or indirectly, any bounty or subsidy upon the manufacture or  production therein or the exportation therefrom of any article, then,</p>
                  <p>upon the importation of any such article into India, whether the same  is imported directly from the country of manufacture, production or  otherwise, and whether it is imported in the same condition as when  exported from the country of manufacture, production or has been  changed in condition by manufacture, production or otherwise, the</p>
                  <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>impose,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list5.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>if the article is not otherwise chargeable with duty  under the provisions of this Act, a duty; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list5.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>if the article is otherwise so chargeable, an additional  duty, not exceeding the amount of such bounty or subsidy;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the Central Government may, pending the  determination in accordance with the provisions of this section and  the rules made thereunder of the amount of such bounty or grant,</p>
                  <p>impose a duty or additional duty under this sub- section not exceeding  the amount of such bounty or subsidy as provisionally estimated by it  and if such duty or additional duty exceeds such bounty or subsidy as  so determined,--</p>
                  <p>athe Central Government shall, having regard to such  determination and as soon as may be after such determination,</p>
                  <p>reduce such duty or additional duty; and</p>
                  <p>brefund shall be made of so much of such duty or  additional duty which has been collected as is in excess of  the duty of the duty or additional duty as so reduced.";</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list12">
                    <listIntroduction>bin sub- section (2),--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list12.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>for the words" not amount of any such bounty or  grant", the words" amount of any such bounty or subsidy"</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list14">
                    <listIntroduction>shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list14.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>for the words" additional duty", the words" duty  or additional duty, as the case may be," shall be  substituted.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the, Central Government may, pending the  determination in accordance with the provisions of this section and  the rules made thereunder of the normal value and the margin of  dumping in relation to any article, impose on the importation of such  article into India a duty or additional duty under this sub- section on  the basis of a provisional estimate of such value and margin and if  such duty or additional duty exceeds the margin as so determined,-</p>
                  <p>athe Central Government shall, having regard to such  determination and as soon as may be after such determination,</p>
                  <p>reduce such duty or additional duty; and</p>
                  <p>brefund shall be made of so much of such duty or  additional duty which has been collected as is in excess of  such duty or additional duty as so reduced.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</p>
                  <p>a" margin of dumping", in relation to an article, means  the difference between the price at which such article is  exported and its normal value;</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list22">
                    <listIntroduction>b" normal value", in relation to an article, means-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list22.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the comparable price in the ordinary course of  trade for the said article or like article when meant  for consumption in the exporting country or territory-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9A.1.list24">
                    <listIntroduction>as determined under sub- section (2); or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9A.1.list24.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>where such comparable price cannot be ascertained  because of the particular market situation or for any  other reason, such value shall be either-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Athe highest comparable price for the said  article or like article from the exporting country  or territory to any third country in the ordinary  course of trade as determined under subsection (2);</p>
                  <p>or</p>
                  <p>Bthe cost of production of the said article or  like article in the country of origin along with  reasonable addition for selling and any other cost,</p>
                  <p>and for profits, as determined under susection (2).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to any rules made under sub- section (3), the Central</p>
                  <p>Government shall, after making due allowance in each case for  differences in conditions and terms of sale, for differences in  taxation and for other differences affecting price comparability, and,</p>
                  <p>after such inquiry as it may consider necessary, determine, for the  purposes of sub- section (1), the export price and the normal value of,</p>
                  <p>and the margin of dumping in relation to, any article.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, make rules for the purposes of this section, and without  prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, such rules may provide  for the manner in which articles liable for any duty or additional  duty under sub- section (1) may be identified, and for the manner in  which the export price and the normal value of, and the margin of  dumping in relation to, such articles may be determined and for the  assessment and collection of such duty or additional duty.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9A.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification issued under sub- section (1) shall, as  soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before each House of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9B">
              <num>9B.</num>
              <heading>No levy under section 9 or section 9A in certain cases in  the absence of injury to industry in India.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in section 9 or section 9A, the Central Government  shall not levy any duty or additional duty under either of those  sections on the import into India of any article from any country or  territory to which this section applies unless that Government, after  making investigation in accordance with the rules made under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (3), declares, by notification in the Official Gazette, that  the import of such article into India causes or threatens material  injury to any industry established in India or materially retards the  establishment of any industry in India,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>This section applies to every country or territory which is  specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette to be a country, or territory which, by reason of its being a  party to the General Agreement on Tariff and Trade or by reason of any  agreement between it and India for giving the most- favoured nation  treatment or for any other reason, levies duty or additional duty of  the nature referred to in section 9 or section 9A on articles imported  from India only when such import causes or threatens any material  injury to any industry established in such country or territory or  material retards the establishment of such industry in such country or  territory.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9B.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, make rules for the purposes of this section, and without</p>
                  <p>Prejudice, to the generality of the foregoing, such rules may provide  for the manner in which any investigation may be made for the purposes  of sub- section (1), the factors to which regard shall be had in any  such investigation and for all matters connected with such  investigation.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9B.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification issued under, sub- section, (1) or sub-</p>
                  <p>section (2) shall, as soon as may be after it is issued, be laid  before each House of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," industry", in  relation to any article, includes the manufacture or production of  like articles, any activity connected therewith find the persons  engaged in such production, manufacture or activity</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Rules to be laid before Parliament. Every rule made under this</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
                  <p>House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule,</p>
                  <p>or both House agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall,</p>
                  <p>thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Power of Central Government to alter duties under certain  circumstances.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Central Government is satisfied that it  is necessary so to do for the purpose of giving effect to any  agreement entered into before the commencement of this Act with a  foreign Government, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                  <p>increase or reduce the duties referred to in section 2 to such extent  as each case may require:</p>
                  <p>Provided that not notification under this sub- section increasing  or reducing the duties as aforesaid shall be issued by the Central</p>
                  <p>Government after the expiration of a period of one year from the  commencement of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification issued under sub- section (1) shall, as  soon as may be after it is issued, be laid before each House of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Indian Triff Act, 1934, (32 of</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1934">
              <num>1934.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1934.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>) and the Indian Tariff (Amendment) Act, 1949, (1 of 1949) are  hereby repealed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-1934.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding the repeal of any of the Acts mentioned in  sub- section (1), anything done or any action taken (including any  notification published and any rules and orders made or deemed to have  been made under the provisions of those Acts and in force immediately   before the commencement of this Act) shall, in so far as such thing or  action is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed  to have been done or taken under the provisions of this Act and shall  continue in force accordingly until superseded by anything done or  any action taken under this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Consequential amendment of Act 52 of 1962. In the Customs Act,</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1962">
              <num>1962.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1962.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, in sub- section 1 of section 12 and in sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-1962.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of  section 14, for the words and figures" Indian Tariff Act, 1934", (32   of 1934) the words and figures" Customs Tariff Act, 1975" shall be  substituted.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
