<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/39/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/39"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Illegal Migrants (Determination By Tribunals) Act, 1983"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/39/eng@1983-12-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/39/eng@1983-12-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1983-12-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/39/eng@1983-12-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/39/eng@1983-12-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Illegal Migrants (Determination By Tribunals) Act, 1983</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 39 OF 1983</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 25th December, 1983.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- fourth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of Tribunals for the  determination, in a fair manner, of the question whether a person is  an illegal migrant to enable the Central Government to expel illegal  migrants from India and for matters connected therewith or incidental  thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS a good number of the foreigners who migrated into India  across the borders of the eastern and north- eastern regions of the  country on and after the 25th day of March, 1971, have, by taking  advantage of the circumstances of such migration and their ethnic  similarities and other connections with the people of India and  without having in their possession any lawful authority so to do,</p>
        <p>illegally remained in India;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the continuance of such foreigners in India is  detrimental to the interests of the public of India;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS on account of the number of such foreigners and the  manner in which such foreigners have clandestinely been trying to pass  off as citizens of India and all other relevant circumstances, it is  necessary for the protection of the citizens of India to make special  provisions for the detection of such foreigners in Assam and also in  any other part of India in which such foreigners may be found to have  remained illegally;</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Illegal Migrants (Determination by Tribunals) Act, 1983.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force in the State of</p>
              <p>Assam on the 15th day of October, 1983 and in any other State on such  date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different</p>
              <p>States and references in this Act to the commencement of this Act  shall be</p>
              <p>construed in relation to any State as references to the date of  commencement of this Act in such State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Application. Nothing in this Act shall apply to or in relation  to--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any person who was in any State and who had been  expelled from that State or India before the commencement of this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act in that State or in relation to whose expulsion from such</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>State or India any order made before such commencement under any  other law is in force;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any person detected as a foreigner at the time of his  entry across any border of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any foreigner who, having entered into India under a  valid passport or travel document, continued to remain therein  after the expiry of the period for which he was authorised to  remain in India under such passport or travel document.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions and construetion of references.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In this Act,</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>unless the context otherwise requires,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Appellate Tribunal" means an Appellate Tribunal  established by the Central Government under sub- section (1) of  section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" foreigner" has the same meaning as in the Foreigners</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Act, 1946; (31 of 1946.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.1.list4.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" illegal migrant" means a person in respect of whom each  of the following conditions is satisfied, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list4.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>he has entered into India on or after the 25th day  of March, 1971,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list4.c.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>he is a foreigner,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list4.c.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>he has entered into India without being in  possession of a valid passport or other travel document or  any other lawful authority in that behalf;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Tribunal" means a Tribunal established by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government under sub- section (1) of section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in  any area shall, in relation to that area, be construed as a reference  to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Overriding effect of the Act.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act  or of any rule or order made thereunder shall have effect  notwithstanding anything contained in the Passport (Entry into India)</p>
              <p>Act, 1920 (34 of 1920.) or the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946.) or  the Immigrants (Expulsion from Assam) Act, 1950 (10 of 1950.) or the</p>
              <p>Passports Act, 1967 (15 of 1967.) or any rule or order made under any  of the said Acts and in force for the time being.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  provisions of sub- section (1), nothing in the proviso to section 2 of  the Immigrants (Expulsion from Assam) Act, 1950 (10 of 1950.) shall  apply to or in relation to an illegal migrant as defined in clause (c)</p>
              <p>of sub- section (1) of section 3.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF TRIBUNALS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF TRIBUNALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of Illegal Migrants (Determination) Tribunals.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification, establish, for the  purposes of this Act, as many Illegal Migrants (Determination)</p>
              <p>Tribunals as it may deem necessary and specify the principal place of  sitting of, and the territorial limits within which, each such</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall exercise its jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be appointed as a member of any such Tribunal  unless he is or has been a District Judge or an Additional District</p>
              <p>Judge in any State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each Tribunal shall consist of two members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the establishment of a Tribunal, the Central Government  shall appoint one of the members thereof as the Chairman of such</p>
              <p>Tribunal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Each Tribunal shall sit in its principal place of sitting and  in such other place or places as its Chairman may, from time to time,</p>
              <p>appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Filling of vacancies. If, for any reason, any vacancy occurs  in the office of the Chairman or the member of a Tribunal, the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may fill the vacancy by appointing any person who fulfils  the qualifications specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, as the</p>
              <p>Chairman, or, as the case may be, member of such Tribunal.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Staff of the Tribunals. The Central Government shall make  available to every Tribunal such staff as may be necessary for the  discharge of its functions under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>References or applications to Tribunals.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question  arises as to whether any person is or is not an illegal migrant, the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, whether such question has arisen on a  representation made by such person against any order under the</p>
              <p>Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946.) requiring him not to remain in</p>
              <p>India or to any other effect or has arisen in any other manner  whatsoever, refer such question to a Tribunal for decision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person may make an application to the Tribunal, for its  decision, as to whether the person whose name and other particulars  are given in the application, is or is not an illegal migrant:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Proveded that no such application shall be entertained by the</p>
              <p>Tribunal unless the person in relation to whom the application is made  is found, or resides, within the jurisdiction of the same police  station wherein the applicant has his place of residence.";</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 2.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by s. 3, ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Omitted and rules. by s. 4, ibid.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application made under sub- section (2) shall be made in  such form and in such manner as may be prescribed and shall be  accompanied by affidavits sworn by not less than two persons residing  within the jurisdiction of the same police station in which the person  refferred to in the application is found, or residin, corroborating  the averments made in the application, and shall also be accompanied  by such fee, being not less than ten and not more than one hundred,</p>
              <p>rupees, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every reference under sub- section (1) shall be made to  the Tribunal within the territorial limits of whose jurisdiction the  place of residence of the person named in such reference is, at the  time of making such reference, situated:</p>
              <p>Provided that where such person has no place of residence, the  reference shall be made to the Tribunal within the territorial limit  of whose jurisdiction such person is, at the time of making such  reference, found.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application under sub- section (2) shall be made to the</p>
              <p>Tribunal within the territorial limis off whose jurisdiction the  person named in such application is found or, as the case may be, has  his place of residence, at the time of making such application."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8A">
          <num>8A.</num>
          <heading>Application to the Central Government for reference.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person may make an application to the Cenral Government, for  decision by a Tribunal, as to whether the person whose name and other  particulars are given in the application, is or is not an illegal  migrant, and where any such application is received by the Central</p>
              <p>Government, it may, on the basis of any information in its possesion  or after making such inquiry as it deems fit, reject the application  on the ground that the application is frivolous orr vexatious or it  does not comply with the requirements of this section or refer such  application to a Tribunal for decision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application made under sub- section (1) shall be made in  such form and in such manner as may be prescribed and shall be  accompanied by a declaration by another person residing within the  jurisdiction of the same revenue sub- division in which the aspplicant  resides in such form as may be prescribed to the effect that the  particculars mentioned in the application are true to his knowledge,</p>
              <p>information and belief:</p>
              <p>Provided that no person shall make more than ten such appli-</p>
              <p>cations or more than ten such declarations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8A.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every reference under sub- section (1) shall be made to the</p>
              <p>Tribunal within the territorial limits of whose jurisdiction the place  of residence of the person named in such reference is, at the time of  making such reference, situated:</p>
              <p>Provided that where such person has no cplace cof cresidence, the  reference shall be made to the Tribunal within the territorial limits  of whose jurisdiction such person is, at the time of making such  reference, found."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Powers of the Tribunal. Every Tribunal shall have the same  powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908.) while trying a suit, in respect of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses and  examining them on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>discovery and production of any document;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>requisitioning of public records from any court or  office;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>issuing of any commission for the examination of  witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Procedure with respect to references under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of  section 8. On receipt of a reference under sub- section (1) of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>or sub- section (1) of section 8A the Tribunal shall serve on the  person named in such reference, a notice, accompanied by a copy of  such reference, calling upon him to make, within a period of thirty  days from the date of receipt of such notice, such representation with  regard to the averments made in the reference, and to produce such  evidence as he may think fit in support of his defence:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that if the Tribunal is satisfied that the person  aforesaid was prevented by sufficient cause from making his  representation and from producing evidence in support of his defence  within the said period of thirty days, it may permit him to make his  representation and to produce evidence in support of his defence,</p>
              <p>within such further period, not exceeding thirty days, as it may, by  order, specify.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Procedure with respect to applications under sub- section (2)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>of section 8.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of an application under sub- section (2)</p>
              <p>of section 8, the Tribunal shall issue a notice, accompanied by a copy  of the application, to the prescribed authority calling upon it to  furnish, after making such inquiry as that authority may deem fit, a  report to the Tribunal with regard to the averments made in the  application.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 4.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Ins. by s. 5, ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Subs. b s. 6, ibid.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If, on a consideration of the report made by the prescribed  authority, the Tribunal is satisfied that--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the person named in the application is not an illegal  migrant or that the application is frivolous or vexatious, or has  not been made in good faith, the Tribunal shall, after giving the  applicant an opportunity to be heard, reject the application;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person  named in the application is an illegal migrant, the Tribunal  shall issue a notice accompanied by a copy of the application, to  the person named in the application, calling upon him to make,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>within thirty days from the date of receipt of the notice, such  representation with regard to the averments made in the  application and to produce such evidence as he may think fit in  support of his defence:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the Tribunal is satisfied that the person  aforesaid was prevented by sufficient cause from making his  representation and from producing evidence in support of his  defence within the said period of thirty days, it may permit him  to make his representation and to produce evidence in support of  his defence, within such further period, not exceeding thirty  days, as it may, by order, specify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Determination of the question as to whether a person is an  illegal migrant.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Tribunal to which a reference has been made  under" section 8, or section 8A, or to which an application has been  made under section 8" shall after taking such evidence as may be  adduced before it may think fit and after hearing such persons as it  may deem appropriate, by order, decide the question as to whether the  person named in such reference or application, as the case may be, is  or is not an illegal migrant:</p>
              <p>Provided that where for the determination of such question in any  case the decision on any issue renders any decision on any other issue  or issues unnecessary, the Tribunal may not decide such other issue or  issues.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the members of the Tribunal differ in their opinion  on any point, the Chairman of the Tribunal shall state the point or  points on which they differ and make a reference to the President of  the Appellate Tribunal which exercises jurisdiction in relation to  the Trubunal who shall refer the case for hearing on such point or  points by a member of another Trubunal under its jurisdiction and  such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion of  that member and such decision shall be deemed to be the decision of  the Tribunal.."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Tribunal shall send a copy of every order passed by it to  the prescribed authority or authorities and to the parties to the  reference, or the appliction, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order passed under sub- section (1) shall, subject to  the decision of the Appellate Tribunal, be final and shall not be  called in question in any court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Reference and application to be disposed of within six  months. Every reference made to a Tribunal under" section 8A or</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Application made to Tribunal under section 8" shall be inquired  into as expeditiously as possible and every endeavour shall be made to  conclude such inquiry within a period of six months from the date of  the service, on the person concerned, of a copy of such reference or  application.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Subs. and ins. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 7.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by s. 8, ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Appeal. The Central Government, or any person, named in a  reference or an application under section 8, or any applicant under  sub- section (2) of that section" or any person named in a reference  under section 8" may, if or he is not satisfied with any order made  by a Tribunal under section 12, prefer an appeal to the Appellate</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Tribunal against such order.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by  notification, establish for each State in which this Act is in force  an Appellate Tribunal to be known as the Illegal Migrants</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.Determination">
                  <num>(Determination)</num>
                  <p>Appellate Tribunal for deciding appeals preferred  under section 14 against orders made by Tribunals in the State and  specify the principal place of sitting of such Appellate Tribunal.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be appointed as a member of an Appellate</p>
              <p>Tribunal unless he is or has been a Judge of a High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An Appellate Tribunal shall consist of as many members, not  being less than two and more than six, as the Central Government may  think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall appoint one of the members of an</p>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal to be the President thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An Appellate Tribunal shall sit in its principal place of  sitting or any such other place or places as the President thereof  may, from time to time, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The powers and functions of an Appellate Tribunal may be  exercised and discharged by benches constituted by the President  thereof from amongst the members thereof" which may either be single  member benches or benches consisting of not less than tow members".</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall make available to every</p>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal such staff as may be necessary for the discharge of  its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every memorandum of appeal to an Appellate Tribunal shall be  made in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, and, in the  case of an appeal preferred by an applicant under sub- section (2) of  section 8, shall also be accompanied by such fee, not being less than  twenty- five and more than one hundred rupees, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every appeal shall be preferred within thirty days from the  date on which the order sought to be appealed against was communicated  to the appellant:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that  the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the  appeal within the said period, admit an appeal after the expiry of the  aforesaid period of thirty days.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Appellate Tribunal shall have the same powers as  are vested in an appellate court under the Code of Civil Procedure,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1908">
          <num>1908.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1908.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, while hearing an appeal."].</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Ins. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 9.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by s. 10, ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Order of the Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Appellate Tribunal  may, after giving the parties to the appeal a reasonable opportunity  of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it may think fit,</p>
              <p>confirming, modifying or annulling the order appealed against or may  remand the case to the Tribunal which had passed such order with such  directions to that Tribunal as the Appellate Tribunal may think fit,</p>
              <p>for fresh determination after taking additional evidence, if  necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an appeal had been heard by the Appellate Tribunal and  the members thereof differ in their opinion on any point, the decision  on such point shall, where there is a majority, be according to the  opinion of such majority, and where there is no majority and the  members are equally divided in their opinion, they shall draw up a  statement of the facts of the case and the point or points on which  they differ in their opinion and make a reference of the point or  points or of the appeal, as the case may be, to the President of such</p>
              <p>Tribunal, and on receipt of such reference, the President of the</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall arrange for the hearing of such point or points, or the  appeal, by one or more of the members of the Appellate Tribunal, and  such point or points, or the appeal, as the case may be, shall be  decided according to the opinion of the majority of the members of the</p>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal, who have heard the appeal, including those who had  first heard it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order  passed by it under sub- section (1) to the parties to the appeal,</p>
              <p>to the Tribunal concerned and to the prescribed authority or  authorities."].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order passed under sub- section (1), other than an order  remanding the case, shall be final and no order passed under that  sub- section shall be called in question in any court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Power of superintendence by Appellate Tribunals.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Appellate Tribunal shall have superintendence overr all the</p>
              <p>Tribunals in the State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provi-</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>sions, the Appellate Tribunal may--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>call for returns from any Tribunal;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>make general rules and specify forms for regulating the  practice and proceedings of Tribunals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>specify the forms in which books, entries and accounts  shall be kept by the officers of Tribunals."]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Subs. and Omitted by Act 24 of 1988, s. 11.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by s. 12, ibid.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO ALL TRIBUNALS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO ALL TRIBUNALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Procedure. Subject to the provisions of this Act and the  rules made thereunder, every Tribunal and every Appellate Tribunal  shall have the power to regulate its own procedure in all matters  arising out of the exercise of its powers or for the discharge of its  functions.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Proceeding before every Tribunal to be judicial proceeding  for certain purposes. Every proceeding before a Tribunal or the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within  the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-196">
          <num>196.</num>
          <heading>of the Indian Penal Code; (45 of 1860.) and every such Tribunal or</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-196.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal, as the case may be, shall be deemed to be a civil  court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of</p>
              <p>Criminal Procedure, 1973. (2 of 1974.)</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ENFORCEMENT OF THE ORDERS MADE BY THE TRIBUNALS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ENFORCEMENT OF THE ORDERS MADE BY THE TRIBUNALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Expulsion of illegal migrant.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>] Where a person has been  determined by a Tribunal, or, as the case may be, by the Appellate</p>
              <p>Tribunal, to be an illegal migrant, the Central Government shall, by  order served on such person, direct such person to remove himself from</p>
              <p>India within such time and by such route as may be specified in the  order and may give such further directions in regard to his removal  from India as it may consider necessary or expedient.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any police officer not below the rank of a Superintendent  of Police shall have such powers as may be necessary, including the  power to obtain a bond from any person for the due compliance of an  order under sub- section (1) and to arrest such person in the event of  his failure to furnish such bond to the satisfaction of such police  officer."].</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by  notification, direct that the powers and duties conferred or imposed  on it by this Act, other than the powers conferred by section 28, and  the powers conferred by this section, may, subject to such conditions  as may be specified in the notification, be exercised or discharged  also by--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any officer subordinate to the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any State Government or any officer subordinate to that</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21A">
          <num>21A.</num>
          <heading>Power to bind certain persons against whom complaint is  made under the Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in any other  law for the time being in force, it shall be lawful for a police, if  he is satisfied that the ccircumstances so require and for reasons to  be recorded in writing, to direct any person against whom a reference  or an application has been made under this Act to enter into a bond  with or without sureties for making himself available for the inquiry  and observance of such restrictions or conditions as may be specified  by such police officer:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that if such person person fails to enter into such bond  he may be arrested and detained in such manner as may be prescribed."]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Power to give effect to the orders, etc. Any authority  empowered by or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act to exercise  any power, may, in addition to any other action expressly provided for  in this Act, take, or cause to be taken, such steps, and use, or cause  to be used, such force, as may in its opinion be reasonably necessary  for the effective exercise of such power.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Renumbered and ins. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 13.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Ins, by s. 14, ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of civil courts. Where a Tribunal or</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal has been established for any area for the purpose  of determining whether a person is or is not an illegal migrant, no  civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any question relating  to that matter in that area and no injunction or any other order in  respect of any action taken by, or before, the Tribunal or Appellate</p>
              <p>Tribunal in respect of that matter shall be granted or made by any  civil court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Transitory provision. Where in any suit or other legal  proceeding pending, whether in a civil court or in any Tribunal  established under any other law for the time being in force,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>immediately before the commencement of this Act, a question arises as  to whether a person is or is not an illegal migrant, such court or</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall, without deciding such question, make an order  transferring such suit or other legal proceeding to the Tribunal under  this Act within the territorial limits of whose jurisdiction such  court or other Tribunal is situate and on such transfer such question  shall be dealt with by such Tribunal in accordance with the provisions  of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Any person who,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>contravenes or attempts to contravene, or abets the  contravention of, any order made under section 20; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fails to comply with any direction given by any such  order; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>harbours any person who has contravened any order made  under section 20 or has failed to comply with any direction given  by any such order,  shall be punishable with imprisonment for  a term which shall not be less than one year but which may extend  to three years and with fine which shall not be less than two  thousand rupees:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the court may, for adequate and special reasons to  be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a  term of less than one year or a fine of less than two thousand  rupees."].</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall he against any person for  anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order to be published in the Official Gazette, make such  provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as  appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be  after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Subs. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 15.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the form and the manner in which an application may be  made and the fee which shall accompany such application, as  required by sub- section (3) of section 8;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.aa">
                      <num>(aa)</num>
                      <p>the form and the manner in which an application,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and the form in which a declaration, may be made under sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 8A;"]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the authority or authorities to be prescribed under  section 11, 12 and 16;"].</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the form and the manner in which an appeal to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Appellate Tribunal may be preferred and the fee which shall  accompany such appeal, as required by sub- section (8) of section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.ca">
                  <num>(ca)</num>
                  <p>the manner of arrest and detention under the  proviso to section 21A;"]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Illegal Migrants (Determination by</p>
              <p>Tribunals) Ordinance, 1983, (8 of 1983.) is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Ins. and Subs. by Act 24 of 1988, s. 16.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
