<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/20"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Coal Bearing Areas (Acquisition Anddevelopment) Act, 1957"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/20/eng@1957-06-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/20/eng@1957-06-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1957-06-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/20/eng@1957-06-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/20/eng@1957-06-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Coal Bearing Areas (Acquisition Anddevelopment) Act, 1957</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 20 OF 1957</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 8th June, 1957.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eight Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to establish in the economic interest of India greater  public control over the coal mining industry and its development by  providing for the acquisition by the State of unworked land containing  or likely to contain coal deposits or of rights in or over such land,</p>
        <p>for the extinguishment or modification of such rights accruing by  virtue of any agreement, lease, licence or otherwise, and for matters  connected therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
        <p>Short title, extent and commencement.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called  the Coal Bearing Areas (Acquisition and Development) Act, 1957.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India, except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            <p>Definitions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" competent authority" means any person appointed  to be a competent authority under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Government company" means a Government company as  defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956, in  which any land or rights in or over land shall have  vested under section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Mineral Concession Rules" means the rules for the  time being in force made under the Mines and Minerals</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>(Regulation and Development) Act, 1948;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.CC">
                <num>(CC)</num>
                <p>" mining lease" includes a mining sub- lease, and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>" lessee' shall be construed accordingly;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the expression" person interested" includes all  persons claiming an interest in compensation to be made  on account of the acquisition of land, or of the  acquisition, extinguishment or modification of any  rights in or over land, under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under  this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Tribunal" means the Tribunal constituted under  section 14.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Appointment of competent authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of competent authority. The Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint any person to be  the competent authority for the purposes of this Act; and different  persons may be appointed as competent authorities for different  provisions of this Act and for different areas.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Preliminary notification respecting intention to prospect for coal inany area  and of Powers of competent authorities thereupon.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Preliminary notification respectng intention to prospect for  coal in any area and Powers of competent authorities thereupon.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever it appears to the Central Government that coal is likely to  be obtained from land in any locality, it may, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, give notice of its intention to prospect for coal  therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification under sub- section (1) shall give a brief  description of the land and state its approximate area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the issue of a notification under sub- section (1), it  shall be lawful for the competent authority and for his servants and  workmen-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter upon and survey any land in such  locality;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to dig or bore into the sub- soil;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to do all other acts necessary to prospect for  coal in the land;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to set out the boundaries of the land in which  prospecting is proposed to be done and the intended line  of the work, if any, proposed to be made thereon;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to mark such boundaries and line by placing marks;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and where otherwise the survey cannot be completed and  the boundaries and line marked, to cut down and clear  away any part of any standing crop, fence or jungle:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall enter into any building or upon any  enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling house (unless with the   consent of the occupier thereof) without previously giving such  occupier at least seven days notice in writing of his intention to do  so.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In issuing a notification under this section the Central</p>
            <p>Government shall exclude therefrom that portion of any land in which</p>
            <p>coal mining operations are actually being carried on in conformity  with the provisions of any enactment, rule or order for the time being  in force or any premises on which any process ancillary to the  getting, dressing or preparation for sale of coal obtained as a result  of such operations is being carried on are situate.</p>
            <p>Effect of notification on prospecting licences and mining leases.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Effect of notification on prospecting licences and mining  leases. On the issue of a notification under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of  section 4 in respect of any land-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any prospecting licence  which authorises any  person] to prospect for coal or any other mineral in the  land shall cease to have effect; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any mining lease  shall, in so far as it  authorises the lessee or any person claiming through him  to undertake any operation in the land, cease to have  effect for so long as the notification under that sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>section is in force.</p>
            <p>Compensation for any necessary damage done under section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Compensation for any necessary damage done under section 4.</p>
            <p>Whenever any action of the nature described in sub- section (3) of  section 4 is to be taken, the competent authority shall, before or at  the time such action is taken, pay or tender payment for all necessary  damage which is likely to be caused, and in case of dispute as to the  sufficiency of the amount so paid or tendered or as to the person to  whom it should be paid or tendered he shall at once refer the dispute  to the decision of the Central Government, and the decision of the</p>
            <p>Central Government shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fact that there exists any such dispute as is referred  to in this section shall not be a bar to action under sub- section (3)</p>
            <p>of section 4.</p>
            <p>Power to acquire land or rights in or over land notified under section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Power to acquire land or rights in or over land notified  under section 4. If the Central Government is satisfied that coal is  obtainable in the whole or any part of the land notified under sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) of Section 4, it may, within a period of two years from  the date of the said notification or within such further period not  exceeding one year in the aggregate as the Central Government may  specify in this behalf, by notification in the Official Gazette, give  notice of its intention to acquire the whole or any part of the land  or of any rights in or over such land, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If no notice to acquire the land or any rights in or over  such land is given under sub- section (1) within the period allowed  thereunder, the notification issued under sub- section (1) of section 4  shall cease to have effect on the expiration of three years from the  date thereof.</p>
            <p>Objections to acquisitions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Objections to acquisitions. Any person interested in any  land in respect of which a notification under section 7 has been  issued may, within thirty days of the issue of the notification,</p>
            <p>object to the acquisition of the whole or any part of the land or of  any rights in or over such land.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- It shall not be an objection within the meaning of  this section for any person to say that he himself desires to under-</p>
            <p>take mining operations in the land for the production of coal and that  such operations should not be undertaken by the Central Government or  by any other person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every objection under sub- section (1) shall be made to the  competent authority in writing, and the competent authority shall give  the objector an opportunity of being heard either in person or by a  legal practitioner and shall, after hearing all such objections and  after making such further inquiry, if any, as he thinks necessary,</p>
            <p>' either make a report in respect of the land which has been notified  under subsection (1) of section 7 or of rights in or over such land,</p>
            <p>or make different reports in respect of different parcels of such land  or of rights in or over such land, to the Central Government,</p>
            <p>containing his recommendations on the objections, together with the  record of the proceedings held by him, for the decision of that</p>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this section, a person shall be deemed to  be interested in land who would be entitled to claim an interest in  compensation if the land or any rights in or over such land were  acquired under this Act.</p>
            <p>Declaration of acquisition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Declaration of acquisition. When the Central Government is  satisfied, after considering the report, if any, made under section 8  that any land or any rights in or over such land should be acquired, a  declaration shall be made by it to that effect , and different  declarations may be made from time to time in respect of different  parcels of any land, or of rights in or over such land, covered by the  same notification under sub- section (1) of section 7, irrespective of  whether one report or different reports has or have been made</p>
            <p>(wherever required) under sub- section (2) of section 8]:</p>
            <p>Provided that no declaration in respect of any particular land,</p>
            <p>or rights in or over such land, covered by a notification under sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) of section 7, issued after the commencement of the Coal</p>
            <p>Bearing Areas (Acquisition and Development) Amendment and Vali-</p>
            <p>dation Act, 1971, shall be made after the expiry of three years from  the date of the said notification.</p>
            <p>Provided further that, where a declaration] relates to any land  or to anyrights in or over land belonging to a State Government which  has orhave not been leased out, no such declaration shall be made  exceptafter previous consultation with the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every declaration] shall be published in the Official</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Gazette  and-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any case where land is to be acquired, shall  state the district or other territorial division in  which the land is situate and its approximate area;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and, where a plan shall have been made of the land, the  place where such plan may be inspected;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any case where rights in or over such land are  to be acquired, shall state the nature and extent of the  rights in addition to the matters relating to the land  specified' in clause (a); and a copy of every such declaration shall be sent to the State Government  concerned.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9A">
        <num>9A.</num>
        <heading>Special powers in cases of urgency. If the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government is satisfied that it is necessary to acquire immediately  the whole or any part of the land notified under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of  section 4 or any rights in or over such land, the Central Government  may direct that the provisions of section 8 shall not apply, and if it  does so direct, a declaration may be made under section 9 in respect  thereof at any time after the issue of the notification under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>]</p>
            <p>Vesting of land or rights in Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of land or rights in Central Government.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the  publication in the Official Gazette of the declaration under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, the land or the rights in or over the land, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>shall vest absolutely in the Central Government  free from all  encumbrances].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the rights under any mining lease  granted or deemed  to have been granted by a State Government] to any person are acquired  under this Act, the Central Government shall, on and from the date of  such vesting, be deemed to have become the lessee of the State</p>
            <p>Government as if a mining lease under the Mineral Concession Rules had  been granted by the State Government to the Central Government, the  period thereof being the entire period for which such a lease could  have been granted by the State Government under those rules.</p>
            <p>Power of Central Government to direct vesting of land or rights in  aGovernment company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to direct vesting of land or  rights in a Government company.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained  in section 10, the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that a</p>
            <p>Government company is willing to comply, or has complied, with such  terms and conditions as the Central Government may think fit to  impose, direct, by order in writing, that the land or the rights in or  over the land, as the case may be, shall, instead of vesting in the</p>
            <p>Central Government under section 10 or continuing to so vest, vest in  the Government company either on the date of publication of the  declaration or on such other date as may be specified in the  direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the rights under any mining lease acquired under this</p>
            <p>Act vest in a Government company under sub- section (1), the Government  company shall, on and from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have  become the lessee of the State Government as if a mining lease under  the Mineral Concession Rules had been granted by the State Government  to the Government company, the period thereof being the entire period  for which such a lease could have been granted by the State Government  under those rules; and all the rights and liabilities of the Central</p>
            <p>Government in relation to the lease or the land covered by it shall,</p>
            <p>on and from the date of such vesting, be</p>
            <p>deemed to have become the rights and liabilities of the Government  company.</p>
            <p>Power to take possession of land acquired.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to take possession of land acquired. The competent  authority may, by notice in writing, require any person in possession  of any land acquired under this Act to surrender or deliver possession  of the land within such period as may be specified in the notice, and  if a person refuses or fails to comply with any such notice, the  competent authority may enter upon and take possession of the land,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and for that purpose may use or cause to be used such force as may be  necessary.</p>
            <p>Compensation for prospecting licences ceasing to have effect, rightsunder  mining leases being acquired, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Compensation for prospecting licences ceasing to have  effect, rights under mining leases being acquired, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a  prospecting licence ceases to have effect under section 5, there shall  be paid to the person interested compensation, the amount of which  shall be a sum made up of all items of reasonable and bona- fide  expenditure actually incurred in respect of the land, that is to say,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the expenditure incurred in obtaining the licence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the expenditure, if any, incurred in respect of  the preparation of maps, charts and other documents  relating to the land, the collection from the land of  cores or other mineral samples and the due analysis  thereof and the preparation of any other relevant  records or material;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the expenditure, if any, incurred in respect of  the construction of roads or other essential works on  the land, if such roads or works are in existence and in  a usable condition;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the expenditure, if any, incurred in respect of  any other operation necessary for prospecting carried  out in the land.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the rights under a mining lease are acquired under  this Act, there shall be paid to the person interested compensation,</p>
            <p>the amount of which shall be a sum made up of the following items,</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>namely,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if the lease was granted after prospecting  operations had been carried out in respect of the land  under a prospecting licence, the sum of all items of  reasonable and bonafide expenditure actually incurred  with respect to the matters specified in clauses (i),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>, (iii) and (iv) of subsection (1) before the date  of the lease:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where two or more leases had been granted  in relation to any land covered previously by one  prospecting licence, only so much of the expenditure  aforesaid as bears to the total expenditure the same</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>proportion as the area under the mining lease in respect  of which the rights have been acquired bears to the  total area covered by the mining leases shall be payable  under this clause;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any reasonable and bona fide expenditure of the  nature referred to in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) of  sub,- section (1) actually incurred in relation to the  lease, together with the salami if any, paid for  obtaining the lease;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list6.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the expenditure, if any, incurred by way of  payment of dead- rent or minimum royalty during any year  or years when there was no production of coal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list6.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>interest on any such expenditure referred to in  clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) as has actually been incurred    up to] the year in which the rights under the lease  are acquired, interest being calculated in the following  manner, that is to say,-- interest at the rate- of five  per centum per annum in respect of the expenditure  incurred during each calendar year for the first five  years commencing from the year in which such expenditure  was incurred plus interest at the rate of four per  centum per annum in respect of each subsequent year  after the expiration of the first five years and ending  with the year in which the rights under the lease are  acquired:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the total sum payable under this clause shall not  exceed one- half of the total amount referred to in  clauses (i), (ii)</p>
            <p>and (iii)].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the rights under a mining lease acquired under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>relate only to a part of the land covered by the mining lease, the  amount of compensation payable shall be such as bears to the total  compensation which would have been payable if the rights of the mining  lessee in respect of the entire land had been acquired, the same  proportion which the area of the land in respect of which the rights  are acquired bears to the total area of the land covered by the mining  lease.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a mining lease ceases to have effect for any period  under clause (b) of section 5, there shall be paid by way of  compensation for the period during which the lease so ceased to have  effect, a sum equivalent to five per centum of any such expenditure as  is</p>
            <p>referred to in clauses (i) and (iii) of sub- section (2) for each year  during which the lease remains suspended.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where any land is acquired under section 9, there shall be  paid compensation to the person interested the amount of which shall  be determined after taking into consideration-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the market value of the land at the date of the  publication of the notification under sub- section (1) of  section 4;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.5.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- The value of any minerals lying in the land  shall not be taken into consideration in determining the  market value of any land;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.5.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the damage sustained by the person interested, by  reason of the taking of any standing crops or trees  which may be on the land at the time of the taking  possession thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.5.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the damage, if any, sustained by the person  interested, at the time of taking possession of the  land, by reason of severing such land from other land;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.5.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the damage, if any, sustained by the person  interested, at the time of taking possession of the  land, by reason of the acquisition injuriously affecting  his other immovable property in any other manner, or his  earnings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.5.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>if, in consequence of the acquisition of the  land, the person interested is compelled to change his  residence or place of business, the reasonable expenses,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.5.list5">
              <listIntroduction>if any, incidental to such change; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.5.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the damage, if any, bona fide resulting from  diminution of the profits of the land between the time  of the publication of the notification under sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 4 and the time of the publication of the  declaration under sub- section (2) of section 9.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5A">
          <num>(5A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In determining the amount of compensation for any land  acquired under section 9, any increase to the value of the other land  of the person interested, likely to accrue from the use to which the  land acquired will be put shall not be taken into consideration.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any operation carried on by or on behalf of the</p>
            <p>Central Government in the exercise of any powers conferred by this Act  causes or is likely to cause damage to the surface of any land or any  works thereon and in respect thereof no provision for compensation is  made elsewhere in this Act, the competent authority shall pay or  tender payment for all such damage, and, in case of dispute as to the  sufficiency of the amount so paid or tendered or as to the</p>
            <p>personto whom it is to be paid or tendered, he shall refer the  dispute to the decision of the Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No compensation under this section in relation to maps,</p>
            <p>charts and other documents shall be paid unless the person to whom it  is payable has delivered to the prescribed authority all the maps,</p>
            <p>charts and other documents.</p>
            <p>Method of determining compensation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Method of determining compensation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the amount of any  compensation payable under this Act can be fixed by agreement, it  shall be paid in accordance with such agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where no such agreement can be reached, the Central Govern-</p>
            <p>ment shall constitute a Tribunal consisting of a person who is or has  been or is qualified to be a judge of a High Court for the purpose of  determining the amount.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may in any particular case nominate a  person having expert knowledge in mining to assist the Tribunal, and  where such nomination is made, the person or persons interested may  also nominate any other person for the same purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At the commencement of the proceedings before the Tribunal  the Central Government and the person interested shall state what in  their respective opinions is a fair amount of compensation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall, after hearing the dispute, make an award  determining the amount of compensation which appears to it to be just,</p>
            <p>and specify the person or persons to whom the compensation shall be  paid; and in making the award the Tribunal shall have regard to the  circumstances of each case and to the foregoing provisions of this Act  with respect to the manner in which the amount of compensation shall  be determined in so far as the said provisions or any of them may be  applicable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there Is a dispute as to the person or persons  entitled to compensation and the Tribunal finds that more persons than  one are entitled to compensation, It shall apportion the amount  thereof among such persons and in such manner as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in the Arbitration Act, 1940, (10 of 1940) shall  apply to any proceedings under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.8.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Tribunal, in the proceedings before it, shall have all  the powers which a civil court has while trying a suit under the Code  of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908), in respect of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.8.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any  person and examining him on oath</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.8.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any  document</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.8.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.8.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record from any court or  office; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.8.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for examination of witnesses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Costs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Costs. Every award made by the Tribunal shall also state the  amount of costs incurred in the proceedings before it and by what  persons and in what proportions they are to be paid.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Interest on awards.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Interest on awards. If the sum which in the opinion of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Tribunal ought to have been awarded as compensation is in excess of  the sum which the Central Government has stated to be a fair amount of  compensation, the award of the Tribunal may direct that the Central</p>
            <p>Government shall pay interest on such excess at the rate of five per  centum per annum from the date on which it became payable to the date  of payment of such excess.</p>
            <p>Payment of compensation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Payment of compensation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any compensation payable under  this Act may be tendered or paid to the persons interested entitled  thereto, and the Central Government shall pay it to them unless  prevented by some one or more of the contingencies mentioned in sub-</p>
            <p>section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the persons interested entitled thereto shall not consent  to receive it or if there be any dispute as to the sufficiency of the  amount of compensation or the title to receive it or the apportionment  thereof, the Central Government shall deposit the amount of  compensation with the Tribunal:</p>
            <p>Provided that any person admitted to be interested may receive  such payment under protest as to the sufficiency of the amount:</p>
            <p>Provided further that every person who claims to be an  interested person (whether such person has been admitted to be   interested or not) including the person referred to in the preceding  proviso shall be entitled to prefer a claim for compensation before  the Tribunal:</p>
            <p>Provided also that no person who has received the amount  otherwise than under protest shall be entitled to prefer any such  claim before the Tribunal.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the amount of compensation is not paid or deposited as  required by this section, the Central Government shall be liable to  pay interest thereon at the rate of five per centum per annum from the  time the compensation became due until it shall have been so paid or  deposited.</p>
            <p>Prospecting and mining to be done by Central Government in conformitywith the</p>
            <p>Mineral Concession Rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Prospecting and mining to be done by Central Government in  conformity with the Mineral Concession Rules. Where prospecting is  done under this Act by or on behalf of the Central Government in any  land situate within the jurisdiction of a State Government or where  the Central Government or a Government company has become the lessee  of a State Government in respect of any land under this Act, the terms  and conditions under which the prospecting can be done or rights under  the lease exercised shall, as far as may be, be the same as the terms  and conditions applicable to prospecting licences and mining leases  under the Mineral Concession Rules; and in case of doubt or dispute,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>shall be settled by arbitration or in such other manner as the Central</p>
            <p>Government and the State Government may decide.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18A">
        <num>18A.</num>
        <heading>Payment to State Governments in lieu of royalty.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, where any land or any  rights in or over land belonging to a State Government (other than the  rights under a mining lease granted or deemed to have been granted by   the State Government to any person) vest in the Central Government  under section 10 or in a Government Company under section 11, the</p>
            <p>Central Government or the Company, as the case may be, may pay to the</p>
            <p>State Government such sum of money as would have been payable as  royalty by a lessee had such land or rights been under a mining lease  granted by the State Government.]</p>
            <p>Power to delegate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, direct that all or any of the powers or  duties which may be exercised or discharged by it under this Act  shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may  be specified in the notification, be exercised or discharged also by  any person specified in this behalf in the notification; and any such  person may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, by  order in writing direct that any power or duty which has been directed  to be exercised or discharged by him shall, in such circumstances and  under such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the direction,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>be exercised or discharged by any such person subordinate to him as  may be specified therein.</p>
            <p>Appeals.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Appeals. Any person aggrieved by any award of the Tribunal  under section 14 may, within thirty days from the date of such award,</p>
            <p>prefer an appeal to the High Court within whose jurisdiction the land  or some portion of the land which has been acquired or the land or  some portion of the land covered by a prospecting licence</p>
            <p>or by a mining lease in respect of which mining rights have been  acquired is situate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order made by a competent  authority or by any other person in virtue of any powers</p>
            <p>exercisable by him under this Act may, within twenty- one days from the  date of the order, prefer an appeal to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an appeal under sub- section (2), the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, after calling for a report from the competent  authority or person concerned, and giving an opportunity to the  parties to be heard, and after- making such further inquiry as may be  necessary, pass such orders as it thinks fit, and the order of the</p>
            <p>Central Government shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an appeal is preferred under sub- section (2), the</p>
            <p>Central Government may stay the enforcement of the order of the  competent authority or person concerned for such period and on such  conditions as it thinks fit.</p>
            <p>Power to obtain information.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Power to obtain information. The Central Government or any  person authorised in writing by it in this behalf may, by order in  writing, require any person to furnish to such authority as may be  specified in the order such information in his possession as may be  required relating to any property in respect of which action is  proposed to be taken under this Act.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Power to enter and inspect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter and inspect. The competent authority, or any  person authorised in writing by it in this behalf, by general or  special order, may enter and inspect any property for the purpose of  determining whether and, if so, in what manner an order under this Act  should be made in relation to any property or with a view to securing  compliance with any order made under this Act.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Penalties.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Penalties. Whoever wilfully obstructs any person in doing any  of the acts authorised by subsection (3) of section 4 or wilfully  fills up, destroys, damages or displaces any mark made under section</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, or wilfully obstructs the lawful exercise of any other power  conferred by or under this Act, or fails to comply with any order made  or direction given under this Act, shall be punishable with imprison-</p>
            <p>ment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to  one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            <p>Service of notices and orders.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Service of notices and orders. Subject to any rules that may  be made under this Act, every notice or order issued or made under  this Act shall-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of a notice or order of a general nature  or affecting a number of persons, be notified in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Official Gazette and also published in the locality in  such manner as may be prescribed; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in the case of a notice or order directed to an  individual,  be served on such individual]-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>wherever it is practicable to do so by delivering  or tendering it to that individual; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>if it cannot be so delivered or tendered, by  affixing it on the door or some other conspicuous part  of the residence in which that individual lives, and a  written report thereof shall be prepared and witnessed  by two persons living in the neighbourhood; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>failing service by these means, by post.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Protection of action taken in good faith.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</p>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
            <p>Government or any person for anything which is in good faith done or  intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made  thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the</p>
            <p>Central Government or the competent authority or any other person for  any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good  faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule  or order made thereunder.</p>
            <p>Jurisdiction of Civil Courts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Civil Courts. Save as otherwise expressly  provided in this Act, no Civil Court shall have jurisdiction in  respect of any matter which the Central Government or the competent  authority or any other person is empowered by or under this Act to  determine.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Power to make Rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification In the Official Gazette, make rules 2 for carrying out  the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in making any inquiry  under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the Tribunal in  proceedings under section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which appeals to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government may be made under this Act; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall be laid for not less  than thirty days before each House of Parliament as soon as may</p>
            <p>be after they are made and shall be subject to such modifications as</p>
            <p>Parliament may make during the session in which they are so laid or  the session immediately following.</p>
            <p>Notifications under Act 1 of 1894 in which proceedings are pending tobe  treated as notifications under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Notifications under Act 1 of 1894 in which proceedings are  pending to be treated as notifications under this Act.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every  notification issued before the commencement of this Act, whether by  the Central Government or by a State Government, under section 4 of  the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894.) (hereinafter referred to   as the said Act), in which lands were stated to be needed for the  prospecting of coal seams for the development of collieries to be  worked by the Union of India shall be deemed to have been issued by  the Central Government under section 4 of this Act as if this Act had  been in force on the date of the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued before the commencement of this</p>
            <p>Act, whether by the Central Government or by a State Government, under  section 6 of the said Act in which lands were stated to be needed for  the development of coal shall be deemed to have been issued under  section 9 of this Act as if this Act had been in force on the date of  the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any objection preferred under section 5A of the said Act in  respect of any land covered by any notification issued under section 4  of the said Act shall be deemed to be an objection preferred under  section 8 of this Act to the relevant competent authority and may be    disposed of by him as if the objection had been made in relation to  a notification issued under section 7 of this Act  in respect of such  land or of any rights in or over such land; and the Central</p>
            <p>Government may at any time make a declaration under section 9 of this</p>
            <p>Act in respect of the land or any part thereof or any rights in or  over such land or part]].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.3A">
          <num>(3A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in respect of any land covered by any notification  issued under section 4 of the said Act, no objection has been  preferred under section 5A thereof within the period specified in that  section, then it shall be deemed that a notification had been issued  under section 7 of this Act in respect of such land or of any rights  in or over such land and that no objection to the acquisition of the  land or any rights in or over the land had been preferred under  section 8 of this Act, and accordingly the Central Government may at  any time make a declaration under section 9 of this Act in respect of  the land or any part thereof or any rights in or over such land or  part.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions contained in this section, the  provisions of this Act (including provisions relating to compensation)</p>
            <p>shall apply in relation to any such notification as is referred to in  sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) as they apply in relation to any  notification issued under section 4 or section 9, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
