<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mdp/act/1952/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mdp/act/1952/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Madhya Bharat Whipping Act, 1952"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mdp/act/1952/2/eng@1951-12-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mdp/act/1952/2/eng@1951-12-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-12-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mdp/act/1952/2/eng@1951-12-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mdp/act/1952/2/eng@1951-12-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Madhya Bharat Whipping Act, 1952</p>
      <p>Act No. 02 of 1952</p>
      <p>PREAMBLE,</p>
      <p>AN ACT to provide for the law relating to the punishment of whipping in Madhya Bharat.</p>
      <p>Be it enacted a follows,-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called "The Madhya Bharat Whipping Act, Samvat 2008".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of Madhya Bharat.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force after 15 days from its publication in the Government Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Whipping added to punishments described in section 53 of the Code.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the punishments described in section 53 of the Indian Penal Code, as adopted in Madhya Bharat, offenders are also liable to the punishment of whipping.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Offences punishable with whipping in lieu of other punishment.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever commits any of the following offences, namely,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>theft, as defined in section 378 of the Indian Penal Code, as adopted in Madhya Bharat, other than theft by a clerk or servant of property in possession of his master;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>theft in a building, tent or vessel, as defined in section 380 of the said Code;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>theft after preparation for causing death or hurt, as defined in section 382 of the said Code;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>lurking house-trespass, or housebreaking, as defined in sections 443 and 445 of the said Code, in order to the committing of any offence punishable with whipping under this section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>lurking house-trespass by night, or housebreaking by night, as defined in sections 444 and 446 of the said Code, in order to the committing of any offence punishable with whipping under this section;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may be punished with whipping in lieu of any punishment to which he may for such offence be liable under the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Offences punishable with whipping in lieu of or in addition to other punishment.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>abets, commits or attempts to commit rape, as defined in section 375 of the Indian Penal Code as adopted in Madhya Bharat;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>compels, or induces any person by fear of bodily injury, to submit to an unnatural offence as defined in section 377 of the said Code;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>voluntarily causes hurt in committing or attempting, to commit robbery, as denned in section 390 of the said Code;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may be punished with whipping in lieu of or in addition to any other punishment to which he may for such offence, abetment or attempt be liable under the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Juvenile offenders when punishable with whipping.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any juvenile offender who abets, commits or attempts to commit,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any offence punishable under the Indian Penal Code, as adopted in Madhya Bharat, except offences specified in Chapter VI and in sections 153A and 505 of that Code and offences punishable with death; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any offence punishable under any other, law with imprisonment which the Government may, by notification in the Government Gazette, specify in this behalf;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may be punished with whipping in lieu of any other punishment to which he may for such offence, abetment or attempt be liable.</p>
            <p>Explanation: In this section the expression "Juvenile offender" means an offender whom the Court, after making such enquiry (if any) as may be deemed necessary, shall find to be under sixteen years of age, the finding of the Court in all cases being final and conclusive.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Special provision as to punishment with whipping in forest districts.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever the Government has, by notification in the government Gazette, declared the provisions of this section to be in force in any wild tract of country within the jurisdiction of the Government, any person who in such district or tract of country after such notification as aforesaid, commits any offence punishable under the Indian Penal Code as adopted in Madhya Bharat, with imprisonment for three years or upwards, may be punished with whipping in lieu of any other punishment to which he may be liable under the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
