<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Agricultural Produce (Grading And Marking) Act, 1937"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1937-02-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Agricultural Produce (Grading And Marking) Act, 1937</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 1 OF 1937</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th February, 1937.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the grading and marking of agricultural  and  other] produce.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Agricultural Produce (Grading and Marking) Act, 1937.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Explanations. In this Act, unless the contrary appears from  the subject or context,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" agricultural produce" includes all produce of  agriculture or horticulture and all articles of food or  drink wholly or partly manufactured from any such  produce, and fleeces and the skins of animals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" counterfeit" has the meaning assigned to that word by  section 28 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" covering" includes any vessel box, crate, wrapper, tray  or other container;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" grade designation" means a designation prescribed as  indicative of the quality of any scheduled article;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" grade designation mark" means a mark prescribed as  representing a particular grade designation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" quality", in relation to any article, includes the  state and condition of the article;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" scheduled article" means an article included in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-">
      <doc name="">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value=";"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="">
            <paragraph id=".paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id=".paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>an article is said to be marked with a grade designation  mark, if the article itself is marked with a grade  designation mark or any covering containing or label  attached to such article is so marked.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.j">
                    <num>(j)</num>
                    <p>an article is said to be misgraded if,--</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the article is not of the quality prescribed  for the grade designation with which it is marked;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the composition of the article offered for  grading is altered in any way after a sample has been  drawn for analysis and determination of the grade  designation of the article in accordance with the rules  made under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>the article is tampered with in any manner;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id=".paragraph-0.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>any false claim is made for the quality  prescribed for its grade designation, upon the label or  through advertisement or in any other manner.]</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Prescription of grade designations.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-3.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>] The Central</p>
                  <p>Government may, after previous publication by notification in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette,  make rules to carry out the provisions of this</p>
                  <p>Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-3.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--]</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>fixing grade designations to indicate the quality of any  scheduled article;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>defining the quality indicated by every grade  designation;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>specifying grade designation marks to represent  particular grade designations;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>authorising a person or a body of persons, subject to  any prescribed conditions, to mark with a grade  designation mark any article in respect of which such  mark has been prescribed or any covering containing or  label attached to any such article;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>specifying the conditions referred to in clause (d)</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>including in respect of any article conditions as to  the manner of marking, the manner in which the article  shall be packed, the type of covering to be used, and  the quantity by weight, number or otherwise to be  included in each covering;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list3.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>providing for the payment of any expenses incurred in  connection with the manufacture or use of any implement  necessary for the reproduction of a grade designation  mark or with the manufacture or use of any covering or  label marked with a grade designation mark  or with  measures for the control of the quality of articles  marked with grade designation marks including testing  of samples and inspection of such articles or with any  publicity work carried out to promote the sale of any  class of such articles];</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list3.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>providing for the confiscation and disposal of produce  marked otherwise than in accordance with the prescribed  conditions with a grade designation mark.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.2.list3.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>prescribed.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-3.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this</p>
                  <p>Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
                  <p>House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3A">
              <num>3A.</num>
              <heading>Powers of entry, inspection and search.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-3A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any officer  of the Central Government or a State Government or any authority,</p>
                  <p>being an officer of a gazetted rank or of equivalent rank,</p>
                  <p>authorised by the Central Government may, if he has reason to believe  that any provision of this Act or the rules made thereunder has been,</p>
                  <p>or is being, contravened, enter any premises at any reasonable  time and make necessary inspection of, and search for, the  agricultural produce in relation to which such contravention has been,</p>
                  <p>or is being, made.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-3A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every authorisation made under sub- section (1) shall be  deemed to be a warrant referred to in section 93 of the Code of</p>
                  <p>Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3B">
              <num>3B.</num>
              <heading>Powers of the authorised officer to seize agricultural  produce.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-3B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An officer authorised under sub- section (1) of section 3A</p>
                  <p>may seize and detain any agricultural produce in relation to which an  offence under this Act or the rules made thereunder is being, or  appears to have been, committed, or which is intended or likely to be  used in the commission of such offence:</p>
                  <p>Provided that where any agricultural produce seized under this  sub- section is subject to speedy or natural decay, the officer so  authorised may dispose of such produce in such manner as may be  prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-3B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of section 102 of the Code of Criminal</p>
                  <p>Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974.) shall apply to every seizure made under  this section.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Penalty for unauthorised working with grade designation mark.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Whoever marks any scheduled article with a grade designation mark, not  being authorised to do so by rule made under section 3, shall be  punishable  with imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months  and fine not exceeding five thousand rupees].</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Penalty for counterfeiting grade designation mark. Whoever  counterfeits any grade designation mark or has in his possession any  die, plate or other instrument for the purpose of counterfeiting a  grade designation mark shall be punishable  with imprisonment for a  term not exceeding three years and fine not exceeding five thousand  rupees].</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5A">
              <num>5A.</num>
              <heading>Penalty for selling misgraded articles. Whoever sells any  scheduled article which is misgraded shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months and fine not  exceeding five thousand rupees.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5B">
              <num>5B.</num>
              <heading>Power to prescribe compulsory grade designations in respect  of certain articles.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Central Government is of opinion  that it is necessary in the public interest or for the protection of  consumers that any scheduled article or class of articles shall not be  sold or distributed except after such article or class of articles is  marked with the grade designation mark, it may, by notification in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette, make a declaration to that effect.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any notification issued under sub- section (1) shall specify  the area or areas in relation to which the notification shall have  effect.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5B.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where a notification under sub- section (1) is issued in  respect of any area or areas, no person shall sell or offer to sell or  distribute or offer to distribute any scheduled article or class  thereof in the area or areas except in accordance with the provisions  of this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5B.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of this section shall be  punishable with imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months and  fine not exceeding five thousand rupees.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5C">
              <num>5C.</num>
              <heading>Institution of prosecution. No court shall take cognizance of  an offence punishable under this Act except upon a complaint in  writing made by--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-5C.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the Central Government or the State Government or any  officer authorised by it in writing; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the person aggrieved; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5C.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>a recognised consumer association, whether the person  aggrieved is a member of that association or not.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," recognised  consumer association" means a voluntary consumer association  registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956.) or any other law  for the time being in force.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Extension of application of Act. The Central Government, after  such consultation as it thinks fit of the interests likely to be  affected, may by notification in the Official Gazette declare that the  provisions of this Act shall apply to an article of agricultural  produce not included in the Schedule  or to an article other than an  article of agricultural produce], and on the publication of such  notification such article shall be deemed to be included in the</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1937/1/eng@1937-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule"/>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
