<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1967/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Orissa Grama Rakshi Act, 1967"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Orissa Grama Rakshi Act, 1967</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the regulation of Grama Rakshis in the State of Orissa</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Orissa in the Eighteenth Year of the Republic of India, as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Orissa Grama Rakshi Act, 1967.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall extend to the whole of the State of Orissa.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act unless the context otherwise requires -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government of Orissa;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Grama Panchayat" and "Village" shall have the same meaning as have been respectively assigned to them in the Orissa Grama Panchayat Act, 1964 (Orissa Act 1 of 1965);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"President" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all other words and expressions used in this Act but not defined herein shall have the same meanings as have been respectively assigned to them in the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861);</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Grama Rakshi Force</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, for the villages within the state their shall be a Grama Rakshi Force which shall be constituted in such manner as may be prescribed and shall consist of such number of Grama Rakhis as Government shall determine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Administration and control of Grama Rakshis</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The administration of the Grama Rakshis within a district shall, subject to the control and direction of the Revenue Divisional Commissioner, vest in the Magistrate of the district.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Grama Rakshis</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Magistrate of the district may appoint within his jurisdiction persons having the prescribed qualifications to be Grama Rakshis.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The manner of appointment, pay, allowances and other conditions of service of the Grama Rakshis shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Magistrate of the district may, with the approval of the Revenue Divisional Commissioner, delegate his powers under Sub­sec. (1) to the Superintendent of Police of the district or to any Sub­Divisional Officer within the district to be exercised within their respective jurisdictions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of Grama Rakshis</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, (5 of 1898), every Grama Rakshi shall exercise and discharge the following powers and duties, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to give immediate information to the officer¬in­charge of the police station within whose local limits, the village, of which he is the Grama Rakshi, is situated, of every unnatural, suspicious or sudden death which may occur and of every offence specified in the Schedule which is committed in such village;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to keep the police informed of all disputes, which are likely to lead to a riot or serious affray;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to the best of his ability, to prevent and interpose for the purpose of preventing the commission of any offence specified in the Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to assist private persons in making such arrests as they may lawfully make and to report such arrests without delay to the officer¬in­charge of the aforesaid police station;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to observe and from time to time, to report to the officer ¬in charge of the aforesaid police station the movements of all bad characters and also of the arrival of any suspicious characters within his jurisdiction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to report the births and deaths, which have occurred within his jurisdiction to the officer¬in­charge of the aforesaid police station at an interval of fifteen days;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to supply any local information which the Magistrate of the district, sub­divisional officer or any Police officer may require;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to assist the Grama Panchayat and the Revenue Officers within whose local limits he is appointed, in making collection of taxes levied by the Grama Panchayat and of dues payable to Government and to assist the Grama Panchayat in serving the notices issued by it and calling persons to attend at all meetings convened by it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to assist the Police­officers in investigation of offences and in identification of witnesses, persons summoned by a Court, and persons against whom warrants of arrest have been issued by a Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>to report immediately to the officer¬in­charge of the aforesaid police­station any damage to any protected monument or public property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>to regulate and control the traffic in the streets, and to prevent obstructions therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>to take care of Government land, orchards trees and other Government property entrusted to him; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>to exercise and perform such other powers and duties as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Punishment of Grama Rakshis for neglect of duties, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the rules made in that behalf, the appointing authority shall have the power to suspend, dismiss or fine up to an amount of ten rupees, any Grama Rakshi under his control, if the Grama Rakshi without reasonable cause neglects or refuses to exercise the powers or discharges the duties conferred or imposed on him by or under this Act or to obey any lawful order or direction given to him for exercising and performing his powers and duties or is guilty of any breach of discipline or misconduct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the appointing authority passes an order suspending, fining or dismissing any Grama Rakshi under Sub­sec. (1) he shall record such order with the reasons therefor and note of the enquiry in writing and no such order shall be passed unless the Grama Rakshi concerned has been given an opportunity of being heard in his defence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Grama Rakshi aggrieved by an order made under Sub­sec. (1) may prefer an appeal against such order before the prescribed authority within thirty days of the date of communication of such order and the said authority, after hearing the appellant, may pass such order as he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Revenue Divisional Commissioner may at any time call for and examine any record for the purpose of satisfying himself as to the legality or propriety of any order passed under Sub­sec. (1) or under Sub­sec. (3) and pass such order as he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order passed under Sub­sec. (1) shall, subject to orders, if any, passed under Sub­sec. (3) or under Sub­sec. (4), be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any fine imposed under this section may be recovered in the manner provided by the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) as if such fine were imposed by a Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Grama Rakshis to be public servants</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Grama Rakshis acting under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>manner of constitution of Grama Rakshi force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>qualifications, manner of appointment, pay, allowances, conditions of service, jurisdiction, powers and duties of the Grama Rakshis;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the authority before whom appeals under Sub­sec. (3) of Section 7 shall lie; and.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any matter which has to be or may be prescribed under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>AH rules made under this section shall, as soon as may be after they are made, be laid before the State Legislature for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one or more sessions and if during the said period the State Legislature makes modifications, if any, there in the rules, shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form, so however that such modification shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under the rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Orissa Grama Rakshi (No. 2) Ordinance, "1967 (Orissa Ordinance No. 9 of 1967) is hereby repeated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal anything done, any action taken, any rules or appointments made or any notifications issued in exercise Ordinance, 1967 (Orissa Ordinance No. 1 of 1967) or the Orissa Grama Rakshi (No. 2) Ordinance, 1967 (Orissa Ordinance No. 9 of 1967) shall be deemed to have been done, taken, made or issued in exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this Act was in force on the day on which such thing was done, such action was taken, such rules or appointments were made or such notification was issued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1967/17"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1967/17/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Offences for which a Grama Rakshi may give information</p>
                <p>[See Section 6]</p>
                <p>Murder, culpable homicide, rape (when the offender is not the husband of the woman raped), dacoity, robbery, theft, mischief by fire, house breaking, counterfeiting coins, voluntarily causing grievous hurt, riot, administering stupefying drugs, kidnapping and all attempts and preparations to commit and abetment of the said offences</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
