<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Marine Insurance Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/11/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/11/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/11/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/11/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Marine Insurance Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Marine Insurance Act, 1963.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“contract of marine insurance” means a contract of marine insurance as defined by section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“freight” includes the profit derivable by a ship-owner from the employment of his ship to carry his own goods or other movables, as well as freight payable by a third party, but does not include passage money;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“insurable property” means any ship, goods or other movables which are exposed to maritime perils;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“marine adventure” includes any adventure where—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any insurable property is exposed to maritime perils;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the earnings or acquisition of any freight, passage money, commission, profit or other pecuniary benefit, or the security for any advances, loans, or disbursements is endangered by the exposure of insurable property to maritime perils;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any liability to a third party may be incurred by the owner of or other person interested in or responsible for, insurable property by reason of maritime perils;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“maritime perils” means the perils consequent on, or incidental to, the navigation of the sea, that is to say, perils of the sea, fire, war perils, pirates, rovers, thieves, captures, seizures, restraints and detainments of princes and peoples, jettisons, barratry and any other perils which are either of the like kind or may be designated by the policy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“movables” means any movable tangible property, other than the ship, and includes money, valuable securities and other documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“policy” means a marine policy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“ship” includes every description of vessel used in navigation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“suit” includes counter-claim and set-off.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Marine insurance defined.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A contract of marine insurance is an agreement whereby the insurer undertakes to indemnify the assured, in the manner and to the extent thereby agreed, against marine losses, that is to say, the losses incidental to marine adventure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Mixed Sea and Land Risks.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A contract of marine insurance may, by its express terms, or by usage of trade, be extended so as to protect the assured against losses on inland waters or on any land risk which may be incidental to any sea voyage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a ship in course of building or the launch of a ship, or any adventure analogous to a marine adventure, is covered by a policy in the form of a marine policy, the provisions of this Act, in so far as applicable, shall apply thereto, but, except as by this section provided, nothing in this Act shall alter or affect any rule of law applicable to any contract of insurance other than a contract of marine insurance as by this Act defined.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>An adventure analogous to a marine adventure’ includes an adventure where any ship, goods or other movables are exposed to perils incidental to local or inland transit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Lawful marine adventure.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, every lawful marine adventure may be the subject of a contract of marine insurance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Avoidance of wagering contracts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every contract of marine insurance by way of wagering is void.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A contract of marine insurance is deemed to be a wagering contract—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the assured has not an insurable interest as defined by this Act, and the contract is entered into with no expectation of acquiring such an interest; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the policy is made “interest or no interest”, or “without further proof of interest than the policy itself”, or “without benefit of salvage to the insurer”, or subject to any other like term:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, where there is no possibility of salvage, a policy may be effected without benefit of salvage to the insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Insurable interest defined.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, every person has an insurable interest who is interested in a marine adventure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular a person is interested in a marine adventure where he stands in any legal or equitable relation to the adventure or to any insurable property at risk therein, in consequence of which he may benefit by the safety or due arrival of insurable property, or may be prejudiced by its loss, or by damage thereto, or by the detention thereof, or may incur liability in respect thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>When interest must attach.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The assured must be interested in the subject-matter insured at the time of the loss, though he need not be interested when the insurance is effected:</p>
            <p>Provided that, where the subject-matter is insured “lost or not lost”, the assured may recover although he may not have acquired his interest until after the loss, unless at the time of effecting the contract of insurance the assured was aware of the loss, and the insurer was not.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured has no interest at the time of the loss, he cannot acquire interest by any act or election after he is aware of the loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Defeasible or contingent interest.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A defeasible interest is insurable, as also is a contingent interest.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular, where the buyer of goods has insured them, he has an insurable interest, notwithstanding that he might, at his election, have rejected the goods, or have treated them as at the seller’s risk, by reason of the latter’s delay in making delivery or otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Partial interest.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A partial interest of any nature is insurable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Reinsurance.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The insurer under a contract of marine insurance has an insurable interest in his risk, and may reinsure in respect of it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, the original assured has no right or interest in respect of such reinsurance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Bottomry.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The lender of money on bottomry or respondentia has an insurable interest in respect of the loan.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Master’s and Seamen’s Wages.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The master or any member of the crew of a ship has an insurable interest in respect of his wages.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Advance freight.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the case of advance freight, the person advancing the freight has an insurable interest, in so far as such freight is not repayable in case of loss.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Charges of insurance.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The assured has an insurable interest in the charges of any insurance which he may effect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Quantum of interest.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter insured is mortgaged, the mortgagor has an insurable interest in the full value thereof, and the mortgagee has an insurable interest in respect of any sum due or to become due under the mortgage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A mortgagee, consignee, or other person having an interest in the subject-matter insured may insure on behalf and for the benefit of other persons interested as well as for his own benefit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner of insurable property has an insurable interest in respect of the full value thereof, notwithstanding that some third person may have agreed, or be liable to indemnify him in case of loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Assignment of interest.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured assigns or otherwise parts with his interest in the subject-matter insured, he does not thereby transfer to the assignee his rights under the contract of insurance, unless there be an express or implied agreement with the assignee to that effect.</p>
            <p>But the provisions of this section do not affect transmission of interest by operation of law.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Measure of insurable value.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision or valuation in the policy, the insurable value of the subject-matter insured must be ascertained as follows:—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In insurance on ship, the insurable value is the value, at the commencement of the risk, of the ship, including here outfit provisions, and stores for the officers and crew, money advanced for seamen’s wages, and other disbursements if any incurred to make the ship fit for the voyage or adventure contemplated by the policy, plus the charges of insurance upon the whole; tc " (1) In insurance on ship, the insurable value is the value, at the commencement of the risk, of the ship, including here outfit provisions, and stores for the officers and crew, money advanced for seamen’s wages, and other disbursements if any incurred to make the ship fit for the voyage or adventure contemplated by the policy, plus the charges of insurance upon the whole;"</p>
            <p>The insurable value, in the case of a steamship, includes also the machinery, boilers, and coals and engine stores if owned by the assured; in the case of a ship driven by power other than steam includes also the machinery and fuels and engine stores, if owned by the assured; and in the case of a ship engaged in a special trade, includes also the ordinary fittings requisite for that trade; tc " The insurable value, in the case of a steamship, includes also the machinery, boilers, and coals and engine stores if owned by the assured; in the case of a ship driven by power other than steam includes also the machinery and fuels and engine stores, if owned by the assured; and in the case of a ship engaged in a special trade, includes also the ordinary fittings requisite for that trade;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In insurance on freight, whether paid in advance or otherwise, the insurable value is the gross amount of the freight at the risk of the assured, plus the charges of insurance; tc " (2) In insurance on freight, whether paid in advance or otherwise, the insurable value is the gross amount of the freight at the risk of the assured, plus the charges of insurance;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In insurance on goods or merchandise, the insurable value is the prime cost of the property insured, plus, the expenses of and incidental to shipping and the charges of insurance upon the whole; tc " (3) In insurance on goods or merchandise, the insurable value is the prime cost of the property insured, plus, the expenses of and incidental to shipping and the charges of insurance upon the whole;"</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In insurance on any other subject-matter, the insurable value is the amount at the risk of the assured when the policy attaches, plus the charges of insurance. tc " (4) In insurance on any other subject-matter, the insurable value is the amount at the risk of the assured when the policy attaches, plus the charges of insurance."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Insurance is uberrimae fidei.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A contract of marine insurance is a contract based upon the utmost good faith, and if the utmost good faith be not observed by either party, the contract may be avoided by the other party.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Disclosure by assured.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this section, the assured must disclose to the insurer, before the contract is concluded, every material circumstance which, is known to the assured, and the assured is deemed to know every circumstance which, in the ordinary course of business, ought to be known to him. If the assured fails to make such disclosure, the insurer may avoid the contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every circumstance is material which would influence the judgment of a prudent insurer in fixing the premium, or determining whether he will take the risk.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the absence of inquiry the following circumstances need not be disclosed, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any circumstance which diminishes the risk.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any circumstance which is known or presumed to be known to the insurer. The insurer is presumed to know matters of common notoriety or knowledge, and matters which an insurer in the ordinary course of his business as such ought to know;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any circumstance as to which information is waived by the insurer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any circumstance which it is superfluous to disclose by reason of any express or implied warranty.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whether any particular circumstance, which is not disclosed, be material or not is, in each case, a question of fact.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term “circumstance” includes any communication made to, or information received by, the assured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Disclosure by agent effecting insurance.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of the preceding section as to circumstances which need not be disclosed, where an insurance is effected for the assured by an agent, the agent must disclose to the insurer—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>every material circumstance which is known to himself, and an agent to insure is deemed to know every circumstance which in the ordinary course of business ought to be known by, or to have been communicated to him; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every material circumstance which the assured is bound to disclose, unless it comes to his knowledge too late to communicate it to the agent.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Representations pending negotiation of contract.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every material representation made by the assured or his agent to the insurer during the negotiations for the contract, and before the contract is concluded, must be true. If it be untrue the insurer may avoid the contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A representation is material which would influence the judgment of a prudent insurer in fixing the premium, or determining whether he will take the risk.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A representation may be either as to a matter of fact, or as to a matter of expectation or belief.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A representation as to matter of fact is true, if it be substantially correct, that is to say, if the difference between what is represented and what is actually correct would not be considered material by a prudent insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A representation as to matter of expectation or belief is true if it be made in good faith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A representation may be withdrawn or corrected before the contract is concluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whether a particular representation be material or not, is, in each case, a question of fact.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>When contract is deemed to be concluded.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A contract of marine insurance is deemed to be concluded when the proposal of the assured is accepted by the insurer, whether the policy be then issued or not; and for the purpose of showing when the proposal was accepted, reference may be made to the slip, covering note or other customary memorandum of the contract, although it be unstamped.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Contract must be embodied in policy.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A contract of marine insurance shall not be admitted in evidence unless it is embodied in a marine policy in accordance with this Act. The policy may be executed and issued either at the time when the contract is concluded, or afterwards.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>What policy must specify.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A marine policy must specify—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the name of the assured, or of some person who effects the insurance on his behalf;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the subject-matter insured and the risk insured against;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the voyage, or period of time, or both, as the case may be, covered by the insurance;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the sum or sums insured;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the name or names of the insurer or insurers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Signature of insurer.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A marine policy must be signed by or on behalf of the insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a policy is subscribed by or on behalf of two or more insurers, each subscription, unless the contrary be expressed, constitute a distinct contract with the assured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Voyage and time policies.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the contract is to insure the subject-matter at and from, or from one place to another or others, the policy is called a “voyage policy”, and where the contract is to insure the subject-matter for a definite period of time, the policy is called a “time policy”. A contract for both voyage and time may be included in the same policy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A time policy which is made for any time exceeding twelve months is invalid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Designation and subject-matter.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The subject-matter insured must be designated in a marine policy with reasonable certainty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The nature and extent of the interest of the assured in the subject-matter insured need not be specified in the policy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the policy designates the subject-matter insured in general terms, it shall be construed to apply to the interest intended by the assured to be covered.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the application of this section regard shall be had to any usage regulating the designation of the subject-matter insured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Valued policy.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A policy may be either valued or unvalued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A valued policy is a policy which specifies the agreed value of the subject-matter insured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, and in the absence of fraud, the value fixed by the policy is, as between the insurer and assured, conclusive of the insurable value of the subject intended to be insured, whether the loss be total or partial.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, the value fixed by the policy is not conclusive for the purpose of determining whether there has been a constructive total loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Unvalued policy.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An unvalued policy is a policy which does not specify the value of the subject-matter insured, but subject to the limit of the sum insured, leaves the insurable value to be subsequently ascertained, in the manner hereinbefore explained.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Floating policy by ship or ships.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A floating policy is a policy which describes the insurance in general terms, and leaves the name or names of the ship or ships and other particulars to be defined by subsequent declaration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The subsequent declaration or declarations may be made by endorsement on the policy, or in other customary manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, the declarations must be made in the order of dispatch or shipment. They must, in the case of goods, comprise all consignments within the terms of the policy, and the value of the goods or other property must be honestly stated, but an omission or erroneous declaration may be rectified even after loss or arrival, provided the omission or declaration was made in good faith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, where a declaration of value is not made until after notice of loss or arrival, the policy must be treated as an unvalued policy as regards the subject-matter of that declaration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Construction of terms in policy.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A policy may be in the form in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, and unless the context of the policy otherwise requires, the terms and expressions mentioned in the Schedule shall be construed as having the scope and meaning assigned to them in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Premium to be arranged.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an insurance is effected at a premium to be arranged, and no arrangement is made, a reasonable premium is payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an insurance is effected on the terms that an additional premium is to be arranged in a given event, and that event happens but no arrangement is made, then a reasonable additional premium is payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Double insurance.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where two or more policies are effected by or on behalf of the assured on the same adventure and interest or any part thereof, and the sums insured exceed the indemnity allowed by this Act, the assured is said to be over-insured by double insurance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-34.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the assured is over-insured by double insurance—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the assured, unless the policy otherwise provides, may claim payment from the insurers in such order as he may think fit, provided that he is not entitled to receive any sum in excess of the indemnity allowed by this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the policy under which the assured claims is a valued policy, the assured must give credit as against the valuation, for any sum received by him under any other policy, without regard to the actual value of the subject-matter insured;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the policy under which the assured claims is an unvalued policy he must give credit, as against the full insurable value, for any sum received by him under any other policy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>where the assured receives any sum in excess of the indemnity allowed by this Act, he is deemed to hold such sum in trust for the insurers, according to their right of contribution among themselves.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Nature of warranty.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A warranty, in the following sections relating to warranties, means a promissory warranty, that is to say a warranty by which the assured undertakes that some particular thing shall or shall not be done, or that some condition shall be fulfilled, or whereby he affirms or negatives the existence of a particular state of facts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A warranty may be express or implied.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A warranty, as above defined, is a condition which must be exactly complied with, whether it be material to the risk or not. If it be not so complied with, then, subject to any express provision in the policy the insurer is discharged from liability as from the date of the branch of warranty but without prejudice to any liability incurred by him before that date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>When breach of warranty excused.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-36.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Non-compliance with a warranty is excused when, by reason of a change of circumstances, the warranty ceases to be applicable to the circumstances of the contract, or when compliance with the warranty is rendered unlawful by any subsequent law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a warranty is broken, the assured cannot avail himself of the defence that the breach has been remedied, and the warranty complied with before loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A breach of warranty may be waved by the insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Express warranties.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An express warranty may be in any form of words from which the intention to warrant is to be inferred.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An express warranty must be included in, or written upon, the policy, or must be contained in some document incorporated by reference into the policy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An express warranty does not exclude implied warranty, unless it be inconsistent therewith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Warranty of neutrality.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-38.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where insurable property, whether ship or goods, is expressly warranted neutral, there is an implied condition that the property shall have a neutral character at the commencement of the risk, and that, so far as the assured can control the matter, its neutral character shall be preserved during the risk.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a ship is expressly warranted “neutral”, there is also an implied condition that, so far as the assured can control the matter, she shall be properly documented, that is to say, that she shall carry the necessary papers to establish her neutrality, and that she shall not falsify or suppress her papers, or use simulated papers. If any loss occurs through breach of this condition, the insurer may avoid the contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>No implied warranty of nationality.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There is no implied warranty as to the nationality of a ship, or that her nationality shall not be changed during the risk.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Warranty of good safety.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter insured is warranted “well” or “in good safety” on a particular day, it is sufficient if it be safe at any time during that day.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Warranty of seaworthiness of ship.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-41.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a voyage policy there is an implied warranty that at the commencement of the voyage the ship shall be seaworthy for the purpose of the particular adventure insured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the policy attaches while the ship is in port, there is also an implied warranty that she shall, at the commencement of the risk, be reasonably fit to encounter the ordinary perils of the port.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the policy relates to a voyage which is performed in different stages, during which the ship requires different kinds of or further preparation or equipment, there is an implied warranty that at the commencement of each stage the ship is seaworthy in respect of such preparation or equipment for the purposes of that stage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A ship deemed to be seaworthy when she is reasonably fit in all respects to encounter the ordinary perils of the sea of the adventure insured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a time policy there is no implied warranty that the ship shall be seaworthy at any stage of the adventure, but where, with the privity of the assured, the ship is sent to sea in an unseaworthy state, the insurer is not liable for any loss attributable to unseaworthiness.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>No implied warranty that goods are seaworthy.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-42.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a policy on goods or other movable there is no implied warranty that the goods or movables are seaworthy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a voyage policy on goods or other movables there is an implied warranty that at the commencement of the voyage the ship is not only seaworthy as a ship, but also that she is reasonably fit to carry the goods or other movables to the destination contemplated by the policy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Warranty of legality.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There is an implied warranty that the adventure insured is a lawful one, and that, so far as the assured can control the matter, the adventure shall be carried out in a lawful manner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Implied conditions as to commencement of risk.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-44.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter is insured by a voyage policy “at and from” or “from” a particular place, it is not necessary that the ship should be at that place when the contract is concluded, but there is an implied condition that the adventure shall be commenced within a reasonable time, and that if the adventure be not so commenced the insurer may avoid the contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-44.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The implied condition may be negatived by showing that the delay was caused by circumstances known to the insurer before the contract was concluded, or showing that he waived the condition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Alteration of port of departure.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the place of departure is specified by the policy, and the ship instead of sailing from that place sails from any other place, the risk does not attach.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-46">
        <num>46.</num>
        <heading>Sailing for different destination.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the destination is specified in the policy, and the ship, instead of sailing for that destination, sails for any other destination, the risk does not attach.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47">
        <num>47.</num>
        <heading>Change of voyage.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-47.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, after the commencement of the risk, the destination of the ship is voluntarily changed from the destination contemplated by the policy, there is said to be a change of voyage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, where there is a change of voyage, the insurer is discharged from liability as from the time of change, that is to say, as from the time when the determination to change it is manifested, and it is immaterial that the ship may not in fact have left the course of voyage contemplated by the policy when the loss occurs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Deviation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-48.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a ship, without lawful excuse, deviates from the voyage contemplated by the policy, the insured is discharged from liability as from the time of deviation, and it is immaterial that the ship may have regained her route before any loss occurs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-48.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There is a deviation from the voyage contemplated by the policy—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-48.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the course of the voyage is specifically designated by the policy, and that course is departed from; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-48.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the course of the voyage is not specifically designated by the policy, but the usual and customary course is departed from.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The intention to deviate is immaterial; there must be a deviation in fact to discharge the insurer from his liability under the contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Several ports of discharge.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-49.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where several ports of discharge are specified by the policy, the ship may proceed to all or any of them, but, in the absence of any usage or sufficient cause to the contrary, she must proceed to them, or such of them as she goes to, in the order designated by the policy. If she does not there is a deviation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-49.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the policy is to “ports of discharge”, within a given area, which are not named, the ship must, in the absence of any usage or sufficient cause to the contrary, proceed to them, or such of them as she goes to, in their geographical order. If she does not there is a deviation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Delay in voyage.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the case of a voyage policy, the adventure insured must be prosecuted throughout its course with reasonable despatch, and, if without lawful excuse it is not so prosecuted, the insurer is discharged from liability as from the time when the delay became unreasonable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-51">
        <num>51.</num>
        <heading>Excuse for deviation or delay.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-51.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-51.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Deviation or delay in prosecuting the voyage contemplated by the policy is excused—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where authorised by any special term in the policy; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where caused by circumstances beyond the control of the master and his employer; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where reasonably necessary in order to comply with an express or implied warranty; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>where reasonably necessary for the safety of the ship or subject-matter insured; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for the purpose of saving human life or aiding a ship in distress where human life may be in danger; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>where reasonably necessary for the purpose of obtaining medical or surgical aid for any person on board the ship; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>where caused by the barratrous conduct of the master or crew, if barratry be one of the perils insured against.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-51.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the cause excusing the deviation or delay ceases to operate, the ship must resume her course, and prosecute her voyage, with reasonable dispatch.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>When and how policy is assignable.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-52.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A marine policy may be transferred by assignment unless it contains terms expressly prohibiting assignment. It may be assigned either before or after loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-52.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a marine policy has been assigned so as to pass the beneficial interest in such policy, the assignee of the policy is entitled to sue thereon in his own name; and the defendant is entitled to make any defence arising out of the contract which he would have been entitled to make if the suit had been brought in the name of the person by or on behalf of whom the policy was effected.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-52.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A marine policy may be assigned by endorsement thereon or in other customary manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-53">
        <num>53.</num>
        <heading>Assured who has no interest cannot assign.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured has parted with or lost his interest in the subject-matter insured, and has not, before or at the time of so doing expressly or impliedly agreed to assign the policy, any subsequent assignment of the policy is inoperative:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section affects the assignment of a policy after loss.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-54">
        <num>54.</num>
        <heading>When premium payable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Unless otherwise agreed, the duty of the assured or his agent to pay the premium, and the duty to the insurer to issue the policy to the assured or his agent, are concurrent conditions, and the insurer is not bound to issue the policy until payment or tender of premium.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-55">
        <num>55.</num>
        <heading>Included and excluded loses.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-55.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, and unless the policy otherwise provides, the insurer is liable for any loss proximately caused by a peril insured against, but, subject as aforesaid, he is not liable for any loss which is not proximately caused by a peril insured against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-55.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-55.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-55.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the insurer is not liable for any loss attributable to the wilful misconduct of the assured, but, unless the policy otherwise provides, he is liable for any loss proximately caused by a peril insured against, even though the loss would not have happened but for the misconduct or negligence of the master or crew;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-55.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>unless the policy otherwise provides, the insurer on ship or goods is not liable for any loss proximately caused by delay, although the delay be caused by a peril insured against;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-55.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>unless the policy otherwise provides, the insurer is not liable for ordinary wear and tear, ordinary leakage and breakage, inherent vice or nature of the subject-matter insured, or for any loss proximately caused by maritime perils.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-56">
        <num>56.</num>
        <heading>Partial and total loss.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-56.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A loss may be either total or partial. Any loss other than a total loss, as hereinafter defined, is a partial loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-56.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A total loss may be either an actual total loss, or a constructive total loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-56.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless a different intention appears from the terms of the policy, an insurance against total loss includes a constructive, as well as an actual, total loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-56.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured brings a suit for a total loss and the evidence proves only a partial loss, he may, unless the policy otherwise provides, recover for a partial loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-56.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where goods reach their destination in specie, but by reason of obliteration of marks, or otherwise, they are incapable of identification, the loss, if any is partial and not total.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-57">
        <num>57.</num>
        <heading>Actual total loss.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-57.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter insured is destroyed, or so damaged as to cease to be a thing of the kind insured, or where the assured is irretrievably deprived thereof, there is an actual total loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-57.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of an actual total loss no notice of abandonment need be given.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-58">
        <num>58.</num>
        <heading>Missing ship.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the ship concerned in the adventure is missing, and after the lapse of a reasonable time no news of her has been received, an actual total loss may be presumed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-59">
        <num>59.</num>
        <heading>Effect of transhipment, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where, by a peril insured against, the voyage is interrupted at intermediate port or place, under such circumstances as, a part from any special stipulation in the contract of affreightment to justify the master in landing and reshipping the goods or other movables, or in transhipping them, and sending them on to their destination, the liability of the insurer continues, notwithstanding the landing or transhipment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-60">
        <num>60.</num>
        <heading>Constructive total loss defined.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-60.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision in the policy, there is a constructive total loss where the subject-matter insured is reasonably abandoned on account of its actual total loss appearing to be unavoidable, or because it could not be preserved from actual total loss without an expenditure which would exceed its value when the expenditure had been incurred.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-60.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-60.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, there is a constructive total loss—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-60.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>where the assured is deprived of the possession of his ship or goods by a peril insured against, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-60.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>it is unlikely that he can recover the ship or goods, as the case may be, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-60.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the cost of recovering the ship or goods, as the case may be, would exceed their value when recovered; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-60.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the case of damage to a ship, where she is so damaged by a peril insured against that the cost of repairing the damage would exceed the value of the ship when repaired.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-60.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>In estimating the cost of repairs, no deduction is to be made is respect of general average contributions to those repairs payable by other interests, but account is to be taken of the expense of future salvage operations and of any future general average contributions to which the ship would be liable if required; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-60.2.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>in the case of damage to goods, where the cost of repairing the damage and forwarding the goods to their destination would exceed their value on arrival.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-61">
        <num>61.</num>
        <heading>Effect of constructive total loss.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a constructive total loss the assured may either treat the loss as a partial loss, or abandon the subject-matter insured to the insurer and treat the loss as if it where an actual total loss.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-62">
        <num>62.</num>
        <heading>Notice of abandonment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-62.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this section, where the assured elects to abandon the subject-matter insured to the insurer, he must give notice of abandonment. If he fails to do so the loss can only be treated as a partial loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of abandonment may be given in writing, or by word of mouth, or partly in writing and partly by word of mouth, and may be given in any terms which indicate the intention of the assured to abandon his insured interest in the subject-matter insured unconditionally to the insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of abandonment must be given with reasonable diligence after the receipt of reliable information of the loss, but where the information is of a doubtful character the assured is entitled to a reasonable time to make inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where notice of abandonment is properly given, the rights of the assured are not prejudiced by the fact that the insurer refuses to accept the abandonment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The acceptance of an abandonment may be either express or implied from the conduct of the insurer. The mere silence of the insurer after notice is not an acceptance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where notice of abandonment is accepted the abandonment is irrevocable. The acceptance of the notice conclusively admits liability for the loss and the sufficiency of the notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of abandonment is unnecessary where at the time when the assured receives information of the loss, there would be no possibility of benefit of the insurer if notice were given to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of abandonment may be waived by the insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When an insurer has reinsured his risk, no notice of abandonment need be given by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-63">
        <num>63.</num>
        <heading>Effect of abandonment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-63.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a valid abandonment the insurer is entitled to take over the interest of the assured in whatever may remain of the subject-matter, insured, and all proprietary rights incidental thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-63.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon the abandonment of a ship, the insurer thereof is entitled to any freight in course of being earned, and which is earned by her subsequent to the casualty causing the loss, less the expenses of earning it incurred after the casualty; and, where the ship is carrying the owner’s goods, the insurer is entitled to a reasonable remuneration for the carriage of them subsequent to the casualty causing the loss.</p>
            <p>Partial Losses (Including salvage and General Average and Particular Charges)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-64">
        <num>64.</num>
        <heading>Particular average loss.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-64.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A particular average loss is a partial loss of the subject-matter insured, caused by a peril insured against, and which is not a general average loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-64.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Expenses incurred by or on behalf of the assured for the safety or preservation of the subject-matter insured, other than general average and salvage charges, are called particular charges. Particularly charges are not included in particular average.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-65">
        <num>65.</num>
        <heading>Salvage charges.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-65.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision in the policy, salvage charges incurred in preventing a loss by perils insured against may be recovered as a loss by those perils.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-65.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Salvage charges” means the charges recoverable under maritime law by a salvor independently of contract. They do not include the expenses of services in the nature of salvage rendered by the assured or his agents, or any person employed for hire by them, for the purpose of averting a peril insured against. Such expenses, where properly incurred, may be recovered as particular charges or as a general average loss, according to the circumstances under which they were incurred.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-66">
        <num>66.</num>
        <heading>General average loss.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-66.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A general average loss is a loss caused by or directly consequential on a general average act. It includes a general average expenditure as well as a general average sacrifice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There is a general average act where any extraordinary sacrifice or expenditure is voluntarily and reasonably made or incurred in time of peril for the purpose of preserving the property imperilled in the common adventure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a general average loss, the party on whom it falls is entitled, subject to the conditions imposed by maritime law, to a ratable contribution from the other parties interested, and such contribution is called a general average contribution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision in the policy, where the assured has incurred a general average of expenditure, he may recover from the insurer in respect of the proportion of the loss which falls upon him; and in the case of a general average sacrifice, he may recover from the insurer in respect of the whole loss without having enforced his right of contribution from the other parties liable to contribute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision in the policy, where the assured has paid, or is liable to pay, a general average contribution in respect of the interest insured, he may recover therefor from the insurer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the absence of express stipulation, the insurer is not liable for any general average loss or contribution where the loss was not incurred for the purpose of avoiding, or in connection with the avoidance of a peril insured against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where ship, freight, and cargo, or any two of those interests, are owned by the same assured, the liability of the insurer in respect of general average losses or contributions is to be determined as if those interests were owned by different persons.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-67">
        <num>67.</num>
        <heading>Extent of liability of insurer for loss.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-67.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The sum which the assured can recover in respect of a loss on a policy by which he is insured, in the case of an unvalued policy to the full extent of the insurable value or in the case of a valued policy to the full extent of the value fixed by the policy, is called the measure of indemnity.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-67.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a loss recoverable under the policy, the insurer or each insurer if there be more than one, is liable for such proportion of the measure of indemnity as the amount of his subscription bears to the value fixed by the policy in the case of a valued policy, or to the insurable value in the case of an unvalued policy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-68">
        <num>68.</num>
        <heading>Total loss.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-68.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, and to any express provision in the policy, where there is a total loss of the subject-matter insured—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-68.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>if the policy be a valued policy, the measure of indemnity is the sum fixed by the policy;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-68.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>if the policy be an unvalued policy the measure of indemnity is the insurable value of the subject-matter insured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-69">
        <num>69.</num>
        <heading>Partial loss of ship.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-69.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a ship is damaged, but is not totally lost, the measure of indemnity subject to any express provision in the policy, is as follows:—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-69.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where the ship has been repaired, the assured is entitled to the reasonable cost of the repairs, less the customary deductions, but not exceeding the sum insured in respect of any one casualty;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-69.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where the ship has been only practically repaired, the assured is entitled to the reasonable cost of such repairs, computed as above, and also to be indemnified for the reasonable depreciation, if any, arising from the unprepaired damage, provided that the aggregate amount shall not exceed the cost of repairing the whole damage, computed as above;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-69.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where the ship has not been repaired, and has not been sold in her damaged state during the risk, the assured is entitled to be indemnified for the reasonable depreciation arising from the unrepaired damage, but not exceeding the reasonable cost of repairing such damage, computed as above;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-69.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where the ship has not been repaired, and has been sold in her damaged state during the risk, the assured is entitled to be indemnified for the reasonable cost of repairing the damage, computed as above, but not exceeding the depreciation in value as ascertained by the sale.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-70">
        <num>70.</num>
        <heading>Partial loss of freight.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision in the policy, where there is a partial loss of freight, the measure of indemnity is such proportion of the sum fixed by the policy in the case of a valued policy or of the insurable value in the case of an unvalued policy, as the proportion of freight lost by the assured bears to the whole freight at the risk of the assured under the policy.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-71">
        <num>71.</num>
        <heading>Partial loss of goods, merchandise, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-71.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a partial loss of goods, merchandise, or other movable, the measure of indemnity, subject to any express provision in the policy, is as follows:—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-71.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where part of the goods, merchandise or other movable insured by a valued policy is totally lost, the measure of indemnity is such proportion of the sum fixed by the policy as the insurable value of the part lost bears to the insurable value of the whole, ascertained as in the case of an unvalued policy;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-71.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where part of the goods, merchandise or other movable insured by an unvalued policy is totally lost, the measure of indemnity is the insurable value of the part lost, ascertained as in case of total loss;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-71.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>where the whole or any part of the goods or merchandise insured has been delivered damaged at its destination, the measure of indemnity is such proportion of the sum fixed by the policy in the case of a valued policy, or of the insurable value in the case of an unvalued policy, as the difference between the gross sound and damaged values at the place of arrival bears to the gross sound value;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-71.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Gross value” means the wholesale price, or, if there be no such price, the estimated value, with, in either case, freight, landing charges, and duty paid beforehand; provided that, in the case of goods or merchandise customarily sold in bond, the bonded price is deemed to be the gross value. “Gross proceeds” means the actual price obtained at a sale where all charges on sale are paid by the sellers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-72">
        <num>72.</num>
        <heading>Apportionment of valuation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-72.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where different species of property are insured under a single valuation, the valuation must be apportioned over the different species in proportion to their respective insurable values, as in the case of an unvalued policy. The insured value of any part of species is such proportion of the total insured value of the same as the insurable value of the part bears to the insurable value of the whole, ascertained in both cases as provided by this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-72.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a valuation has to be apportioned, and particulars of the prime cost of each separate species, quality, or description of goods cannot be ascertained, the division of the valuation may be made over the net arrived sound values of the different species, qualities, or descriptions of goods.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-73">
        <num>73.</num>
        <heading>General average contributions and salvage charges.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-73.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any express provision in the policy, where the assured has paid, or is liable for, any general average contribution, the measure of indemnity is the full amount of such contribution if the subject-matter liable to contribution is insured for its full contributory value; but, if such subject-matter be not insured for its full contributory value, or if only part of it be insured, the indemnity payable by the insurer must be reduced in proportion to the under-insurance, and where there has been a particular average loss which constitutes a deduction from the contributory value, and for which the insurer is liable, that amount must be deducted from the insured value in order to ascertain what the insurer is liable to contribute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-73.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the insurer is liable for salvage charges the extent of his liabilities must be determined on the like principle.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-74">
        <num>74.</num>
        <heading>Liabilities to third parties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured has effected an insurance in express terms against any liability to a third party, the measure of indemnity, subject to any express provision in the policy, is the amount paid or payable by him to such third party in respect of such liability.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-75">
        <num>75.</num>
        <heading>General provisions as to measure of indemnity.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-75.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there has been a loss in respect of any subject-matter not expressly provided for in the foregoing provisions of this Act, the measure of indemnity shall be ascertained as nearly as may be, in accordance with those provisions, in so far as applicable to the particular case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-75.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in the provisions of this Act relating to the measure of indemnity shall affect the rules relating to double insurance, or prohibit the insurer from disproving interest wholly or in part, or from showing that at the time of the loss the whole or any part of the subject-matter insured was not at risk under the policy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-76">
        <num>76.</num>
        <heading>Particular average warranties.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-76.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter insured is warranted free from particular average, the assured cannot recover for a loss of part, other than a loss incurred by a general average sacrifice, unless the contract contained in the policy be apportionable; but, if the contract be apportionable, the assured may recover for a total loss of any apportionable part.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-76.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter insured is warranted free from particular average, either wholly or under a certain percentage, the insurer is nevertheless liable for salvage charges, and for particular charges and other expenses properly incurred pursuant to the provisions of the suing and labouring clause in order to avert a loss insured against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-76.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, where the subject-matter insured is warranted free from particular average under a specified percentage, a general average loss cannot be added to a particular average loss to make up the specified percentage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-76.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of ascertaining whether the specified percentage has been reached, regard shall be had only to the actual loss suffered by the subject-matter insured. Particular charges and the expenses of and incidental to ascertaining and proving the loss must be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-77">
        <num>77.</num>
        <heading>Successive losses.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-77.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless the policy otherwise provides, and subject to the provisions of this Act, the insurer is liable for successive losses, even though the total amount of such losses may exceed the sum insured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-77.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, under the same policy, a partial loss, which has not been repaired or otherwise made good, is followed by a total loss, the assured can only recover in respect of the total loss:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall affect the liability of the insurer under the suing and labouring clause.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-78">
        <num>78.</num>
        <heading>Suing and labouring clause.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-78.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the policy contains a suing and labouring clause, the engagement thereby entered into is deemed to be supplementary to the contract of insurance, and the assured may recover from the insurer any expenses properly incurred pursuant to the clause, notwithstanding that the insurer may have paid for a total loss, or that the subject-matter may have been warranted free from particular average, either wholly or under a certain percentage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-78.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>General average losses and contributions and salvage charges, as defined by this Act, are not recoverable under the suing and labouring clause.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-78.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Expenses incurred for the purpose of averting or diminishing any loss not covered by the policy are not recoverable under the suing and labouring clause.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-78.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is the duty of the assured and his agents, in all cases, to take such measures as may be reasonable or the purpose of averting or minimising a loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-79">
        <num>79.</num>
        <heading>Right of subrogation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-79.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the insurer pays for a total loss, either of the whole, or in the case of goods of any apportionable part, of the subject-matter insured, he thereupon becomes entitled to take over the interest of the assured in whatever may remain of the subject-matter so paid for and he is thereby subrogated to all rights and remedies of the assured in and in respect of that subject-matter as from the time of the casualty causing the loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-79.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the foregoing provisions, where the insurer pays for a partial loss, he acquires no title to the subject-matter insured, or such part of it as may remain, but he is thereupon subrogated to all rights and remedies of the assured in and in respect of the subject-matter insured as from the time of the casualty causing the loss, in so far as the assured has been indemnified, according to this Act, by such payment for the loss.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-80">
        <num>80.</num>
        <heading>Right of contribution.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-80.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured is over-insured by double insurance, each insurer is bound, as between himself and the other insurers, to contribute ratably to the loss in proportion to the amount for which he is liable under his contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-80.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any insurer pays more than his proportion of the loss, he is entitled to maintain a suit for contribution against the other insurers, and is entitled to the like remedies as a surety who has paid more than his proportion of the debt.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-81">
        <num>81.</num>
        <heading>Effect of under insurance.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-81.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the assured is insured for an amount less than the insurable value, or, in the case of valued policy, for an amount less than the policy valuation, he is deemed to be his own insurer in respect of the uninsured balance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-82">
        <num>82.</num>
        <heading>Enforcement of return.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-82.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-82.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the premium, or proportionate part thereof, is, by this Act, declared to be returnable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-82.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if already paid, it may be recovered by the assured from the insurer, and,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-82.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if unpaid, it may be retained by the assured or his agent.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-83">
        <num>83.</num>
        <heading>Return by agreement.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-83.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the policy contains a stipulation for the return of the premium, or a proportionate part thereof, on the happening of a certain event, and that event happens, the premium, or, as the case may be, the proportionate part thereof, is thereupon returnable to the assured.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-84">
        <num>84.</num>
        <heading>Return for failure of consideration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-84.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the consideration for the payment of the premium totally fails, and there has been no fraud or illegality on the part of the assured or his agents, the premium is thereupon returnable to the assured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-84.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the consideration for the payment of the premium is apportionable and there is a total failure of any apportionable part of the consideration, a proportionate part of the premium is, under the like conditions, thereupon returnable to the assured.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-84.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-84.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-84.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the policy is void, or is avoided by the insurer as from the commencement of the risk, the premium is returnable, provided there has been no fraud or illegality on the part of the assured; but if the risk is not apportionable, and has not once attached, the premium is not returnable;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-84.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the subject-matter insured, or part thereof, has never been imperilled the premium, or, as the case may be, a proportionate part thereof, is returnable:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-84.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where the subject-matter has been insured “lost or not lost”, and has arrived in safety at the time when the contract is concluded, the premium is not returnable unless, at such time, the insurer knew of the safe arrival;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-84.3.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the assured has no insurable interest throughout, the currency of the risk the premium is returnable, provided that the rule does not apply to a policy effected by way of wagering;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-84.3.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>where the assured has a defeasible interest which is terminated during the currency of the risk, the premium is not returnable;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-84.3.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>where the assured has over-insured under an unvalued policy, a proportionate part of the premium is returnable;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-84.3.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>subject to the foregoing provisions, where the assured has over-insured by double insurance, a proportionate part of the several premiums is returnable:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, if the policies are effected at different times, and any earlier policy has at any time borne the entire risk, or if a claim has been paid on the policy in respect of the full sum insured thereby, no premium is returnable in respect of that policy, and when the double insurance is effected knowingly by the assured no premium is returnable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-85">
        <num>85.</num>
        <heading>Ratification by assured.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-85.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a contract of marine insurance is in good faith effected by one person on behalf of another, the person on whose behalf it is effected may ratify the contract even after he is aware of a loss.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-86">
        <num>86.</num>
        <heading>Implied obligation varied by agreement or usage.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-86.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any right, duty, or liability would arise under a contract of marine insurance by implication of law, it may be negatived or varied by express agreement, or by usage, if the usage be such as to bind both parties to the contract.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-86.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this section extend to any right, duty, or liability declared by this Act which may be lawfully modified by agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-87">
        <num>87.</num>
        <heading>Reasonable time, etc., a question of fact.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-87.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where by this Act any reference is made to reasonable time, reasonable premium, or reasonable diligence, the question what is reasonable is a question of fact.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-88">
        <num>88.</num>
        <heading>Covering note as evidence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-88.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a duly stamped policy, reference may be made, as heretofore, to the slip or covering note, in any legal proceeding.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-89">
        <num>89.</num>
        <heading>Power to apply Act with modifications etc., in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-89.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the provisions of this Act shall, in their application to contracts of marine insurance relating to any class of ships exclusively used in inland navigation, be subject to such conditions, exceptions and modifications as it may specify in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-90">
        <num>90.</num>
        <heading>Certain provisions to override Transfer of Property Act, 1882.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-90.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in clause (e) of section 6 of the Transfer of Property Act, 1882, shall affect the provisions of sections 17, 52, 53 and 79.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-91">
        <num>91.</num>
        <heading>Savings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-91.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The rules of law, including the law merchant, which applied to contracts of marine insurance immediately before the commencement of this Act, save in so far as they are inconsistent with the express provisions of this Act, shall continue to apply to contracts of marine insurance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-92">
        <num>92.</num>
        <heading>Repeals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-92.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1974 (56 of 1974), sec. 2 and Sch. 1 (20-12-1974).</p>
            <p>The Marine Insurance Act, 1963</p>
            <p>The Schedule</p>
            <p>FORM OF POLICY</p>
            <p>(See section 24)</p>
            <p>Be it known that ......................... as well in ..................................................own name as for and in the name and names of all and every other person or persons to whom the same doth, may, or shall appertain, in part or in all doth make assurance and cause ......................... and them, and every of them, to be insured lost or not lost, at and from upon any kind of goods and merchandises, and also upon the body, tackle, apparel, ordnance, munitions, artillery, boat and other furniture, of and in the good ship or vessel called the .........................whereof is master for this present voyage .........................or whosoever else shall go for master in the said ship or by whatsoever other name or names the said ship, or the master thereof, is or shall be named or called; beginning the adventure upon the said goods and merchandises from the loading thereof aboard the said ship, .........................upon the said ship, etc. .........................and so shall continue and endure, during her abode there, upon the said ship etc.</p>
            <p>And further, until the said ship with all her ordnance, tackle, apparel, etc., and goods and merchandises whatsoever shall be arrived at .........................upon the said ship, etc., until she hath moored at anchor twenty four hours in good safety; and upon the goods and merchandises, until the same be there discharged and safely landed. And it shall be lawful for the said ship, etc., in this voyage to proceed and sail to and touch and stay at any ports or places whatsoever without prejudice to this insurance. The said ship, etc., goods and merchandises, etc., for so much as concerned the assured by agreement between the assured and assurers in this policy are and shall be .........................</p>
            <p>Valued at.........................</p>
            <p>Touching the adventures and perils which we the assurers are contended to bear and do take upon us in this voyage; they are of the seas, men of war, fire, enemies, privates, rovers, thieves, jettisons, letter of mart and counterpart, surprisals, takings at sea, arrests, restraints, and detainments of all kings, princes, and people, of what nation, condition, or quality soever, barratry of the master and mariners, and of all other perils losses, and misfortunes that have or shall come to the hurt, detriment, or damage of the said goods and merchandises, and ship, etc., or any part thereof.</p>
            <p>And in a case of any loss or misfortune it shall be lawful to the assured, their factors, servants and assigns to sue, labour, and travel for, in and about the defence, safeguards and recovery of the said goods and merchandises and ship etc., or any part thereof, without prejudice to this insurance; to the charges whereof we, the assurers, will contribute each one according to the rate and quantity of his sum herein assured.</p>
            <p>And it is especially declared and agreed that no acts of the insurer or insured in recovering, saving, or preserving the property insured shall be considered as a waiver, or acceptance of abandonment. And so we, the assurers, are contended, and do hereby promise and bind ourselves, each one for his own part, our heirs, executors, and goods to the assured, their executors, administrators, and assigns, for the true performance of the premises, confessing ourselves paid the consideration due into us for this assurance by the assured, at and after the rate of</p>
            <p>In witness whereof, we, the assurers, have subscribed our names and sums   assured in</p>
            <p>Memorandum N.B.—</p>
            <p>Corn, fish, salt, fruit, flour, and seed are warranted free from average, unless general or the ship be stranded,—</p>
            <p>sugar, tobacco, hemp, flax, hides and skins are warranted free from average, under five per cent., and all other goods also the ship and freight, are warranted free from average, under three per cent, unless general or the sip be stranded.</p>
            <p>Rules for Construction of Policy</p>
            <p>The following are the rules referred to by this Act for the construction of a policy in the above or other like form, where the context does not otherwise require:—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Lost and not lost.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter is insured “lost or not lost” and the loss has occurred before the contract is concluded, the risk attaches unless, at such time the assured was aware of the loss, and the insurer was not.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>From.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the subject-matter is insured “from” a particular place, the risk does not attach until the ship starts on the voyage insured.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>At and from.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Where a ship is insured “at and from” a particular place, and she is at that place in good safety when the contract is concluded, the risk attaches immediately.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>If she be not at that place when the contract is concluded, the risk attaches as soon as she arrives there in good safety, and unless the policy otherwise provides, it is immaterial that she is covered by another policy for a specified time after arrival.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Where chartered freight is insured “at and from”, a particular place, and the ship is at that place in good safety when the contract is concluded, the risk attaches immediately. If she be not there when the contract is concluded, the risk attaches as soon as she arrives there in good safety.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Where freight, other than chartered freight, is payable without special conditions and is insured “at and from” a particular place, the risk attaches pro rata as the goods or merchandise are shipped; provided that if there be cargo in readiness which belongs to the ship-owner, or which some other person has contracted with him to ship, the risk attaches as soon as the ship is ready to receive such cargo.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>From the loading thereof.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where goods or other movables are insured “from the loading thereof”, the risk does not attach until such goods or movables are actually on board, and the insurer is not liable for them while in transit from the shore to the ship.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Safety landed.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the risk on goods or other movables continues until they are “safely landed”, they must be landed in the customary manner and within a reasonable time after arrival at the port of discharge, and if they are not so landed the risk ceases.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Touch and stay.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the absence of any further license or usage, the liberty to touch and stay “at any port or place whatsoever”, does not authorise the ship to depart from the course of her voyage from the port of departure to the post of destination.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Perils of the Seas.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “perils of the seas” refers only to fortuitous accidents or casualties of the seas. It does not include the ordinary action of the winds and waves.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Pirates.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “pirates” includes passengers who mutiny and rioters who attack the ship from the shore.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Thieves.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “thieves” does not cover clandestine theft or a theft committed by any one of the ship’s company, whether crew or passengers.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Restraint of Princes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “arrests, etc., of kings, princes, and people” refers to political or executive acts, and does not include a loss caused by riot or by ordinary judicial process.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Barratry.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “barratry” includes every wrongful act wllfully committed by the master or crew to the prejudice of the owner or, as the case may be, the chaterer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>All other perils.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “all other perils” includes only perils similar in kind to the perils specifically mentioned in the policy.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Average unless General.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “average unless general” means a partial loss of the subject-matter insured other than a general average loss, and does not include “particular charges”.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Stranded.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the ship has stranded, the insurer is liable for the excepted loses although the loss is not attributable to the stranding, provided that when the standing takes place the risk has attached and, if the policy be on goods, that the damaged goods are on board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Ship.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “ship” includes the hull, material and outfit, stores and provisions for the officers and crew, and, in the case of vessels engaged in a special trade, the ordinary fittings requisite for the trade and also in the case of a steamship, the machinery, boilers, and coals and engine stores, if owned by the assured and also in the case of a ship driven by power other than steam, the machinery and fuels and engine stores, if owned by the assured.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Freight.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “freight” includes the profit derivable by a ship owner from the employment of his ship to carry his own goods or movables as well as freight payable by a third party, but does not include passage money.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Goods.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term “goods” means goods in the nature of merchandise, and does not include personal effects or provisions and stores for use on board.</p>
            <p>In the absence of any usage to the contrary, deck cargo and living animals must be insured specially, and not under the general denomination of goods.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
