<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1958/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1958/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Animal Preservation Act, 1958"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1958/10/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1958/10/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1958/10/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1958/10/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Animal Preservation Act, 1958</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[07th May, 1958]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 10 of 1958]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the preservation of certain animals by regulating the slaughter thereof.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for the preservation of certain animals by regulating the slaughter thereof;</p>
        <p>Be it enacted in the Ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Animal Preservation Act, 1958.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" animal” means a bull, bullock, cow, calf, he­buffalo or she­buffalo or buffalo calf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" competent authority” means the person or authority appointed under section 3 to perform the functions of a competent authority under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Executive Authority " means an Executive Authority as defined in clause (8) of section 3 of the Tamil Nadu Public Health Act, 1939 (Tamil Nadu Act III of 1939), or in clause (10) of section 2 of the Travancore­Cochin Public Health Act, 1955 (Travancore­Cochin Act XVI of 1955);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Government” means the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of competent authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, appoint the Executive Authority or any other authority or person to perform all or any of the functions of a competent authority under this Act for such area as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of slaughter of animals without certificate</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Not withstanding anything in any law for the time being in force or any usage to the contrary, no person shall slaughter or cause to be slaughtered any animal unless on an application made in this behalf he has obtained a certificate in the prescribed from the competent authority for the area in which the animal is to be slaughtered that the animal is fit for slaughter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application for a certificate under subsection (1) shall be in such form and shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No certificate shall be granted under subsection (1) unless the competent authority, for reasons to be recorded in writing, is of opinion that –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the animal is over ten years of age and is unfit for work and breeding; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the animal has become permanently incapacitated for work or breeding due to injury, deformity or any incurable disease:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the operation of any of the provisions of the Madras City Municipal Act, 1919 (Tamil Nadu Act IV of 1919), the Tamil Nadu District Municipalities Act, 1920 (Tamil Nadu Act V of 1920), the Tamil Nadu District Boards Act, 1920 (Tamil Nadu Act XIV of 1920), the Tamil Nadu Village Panchayats Act, 1950 (Tamil Nadu Act X of 1950), the Travancore District Municipalities Act, 1116 (Travancore Act XXIII of 1116), or the Travancore­Cochin Panchayats Act, 1950 (Travancore­Cochin Act II of 1950), or any other law for the time being in force or any rule, regulation or by-law made thereunder relating to the slaughter of animals, except in so far as the provisions or the rules made thereunder are inconsistent with subsection (3).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Appeals and revisions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by the refusal of a competent authority to grant a certificate under section 4, may, within fifteen days from the date of communication to him of such refusal, appeal to the Government against the order of refusal and the Government may pass such order thereon as they think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, at any time, for the purpose of satisfying themselves as to the legality or propriety of any action taken by the competent authority under section 4 call for and examine the record of any case and may pass such order thereon, as they think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this section any action taken by the competent authority under section 4 shall be final and shall not be liable to be questioned in any Court of Law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of slaughter of animals in places not provided for by a local authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No animal shall be slaughtered</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in case any place has been provided for use as a slaughter house by or under any law relating to local authorities in force in the area, except in such place, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in case no such place has been provided, except in such place as may be provided for the purpose by the prescribed authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter and inspect premises</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of enforcing the provisions of this Act, the competent authority or any person authorized in this behalf by the Government or by the competent authority (hereinafter referred to as the authorized person) shall have power to enter and inspect any premises where the competent authority or the authorized person has reason to believe that an offence under this Act has been or is likely to be committed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person in occupation of any such premises shall allow the competent authority or the authorized person such excess to the premises as may be necessary for the aforesaid purpose and shall answer to the best of his knowledge and belief any question put to him by the competent authority or by the authorized person:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall be compelled under this subsection to answer any question or give evidence tending to incriminate himself.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever poisons, maims or renders useless any animal with intent to make, or knowing that he is likely to make, such animal fit for slaughter under the provisions of this Act, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes any other provision of this Act or of any rule made thereunder shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Abetments and attempts</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever abets any offence punishable under this Act or attempts to commit any such offence shall be punished with the punishment provided in this Act for such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Certain persons to be public servants</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The competent authority and every authorized person while exercising any power or performing any duty under this Act, shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by general or special order and subject to such restrictions and conditions as they may think fit to impose in such order, direct that the provisions of this Act shall not apply to the slaughter of any animal for any religious, medicinal, research or teaching purposes or to relieve it of its suffering caused by injury or disease, provided the exemption granted shall be subject to the provisions of the Tamil Nadu Animals and Birds Sacrifices Prohibition Act, 1950 (Tamil Nadu Act XXXII of 1950).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, direct that the powers exercisable by them by or under this Act shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions if any, as may be specified in the notification, be exercisable also by any officer subordinate to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the competent authority in the exercise of its functions under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the form of the application under section 4 and the particulars which that form, shall contain;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form of, and the fees payable for, the certificate to be granted under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the places in which animals may be slaughtered in pursuance of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made and all notifications published under this Act, shall, as soon as possible after they are made or published, be placed on the table of the Legislative Assembly and shall be subject to such modifications by way of amendment or repeal as the Legislative Assembly may make within fourteen days on which the House actually sits either in the same session or in more than one session.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
