<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/29"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/29/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/29/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/29/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/29/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Force” means the Railway Protection Force constituted under section 3 of the Railway Protection Force Act, 1957 (23 of 1957);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“member of the Force” means a person appointed to the Force, other than a superior officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“officer of the Force” means an officer of and above the rank of Assistant Sub-Inspector appointed to the Force and includes a superior officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“railway property” includes any goods, money or valuable security or animal, belonging to, or in the charge or possession of, a railway administration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“superior officer” means any of the officers appointed under Section 4 of the Railway Protection Force Act, 1957 (23 of 1957), and includes any other officer appointed by the Central Government as a superior officer of the force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>words and expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in the Indian Railway Act, 1890 (9 of 1890), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them under that Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for unlawful possession of railway property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever is found, or is proved to have been, in possession of any railway property reasonably suspected of having been stolen or unlawful obtained shall, unless he proves that the railway property came into his possession lawfully, be punishable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, or with fine, or with both and in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be mentioned in the judgment of the Court, such imprisonment shall not be less than one year and such fine shall not be less than one thousand rupees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the second or a subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and also with fine and in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be mentioned in the judgment of the Court, such imprisonment shall not be less than two years and such fine shall not be less than two thousand rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for connivance at offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any owner or occupier of land or building, or any agent of such owner or occupier incharge of the management of that land or building, who wilfully connives at an offence against the provisions of this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Offences under the Act not to be cognizable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) an offence under this Act shall not be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any superior officer or member of the Force may, without an order from a Magistrate and without a warrant, arrest any person who has been concerned in an offence punishable uner this Act or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists of his having been so concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of persons arrested.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every person arrested for an offence punishable under this Act shall, if the arrest was made by a person other than an officer of the Force, be forwarded without delay to the nearest officer of the Force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Inquiry how to be made against arrested persons.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any person is arrested by an officer of the Force for an offence punishable under this Act or is forwarded to him under Section 7, he shall proceed to inquire into the charge against such person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For this purpose the officer of the Force may exercise the same powers and shall be subject to the same provisions as the officer incharge of a police station may exercise and is subject to under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), when investigating a cognizable case:</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the officer of the Force is of opinion that there is sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion against the accused person, he shall either admit him to bail to appear before a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the case, or forward him in custody to such Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if it appears to the officer of the Force that there is no sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion against the accused person, he shall release the accused person, on his executing a bond, with or without sureties as the officer of the Force may direct, to appear, if and when so required before the Magistrate having jurisdiction, and shall make a full report of all the particulars of the case to his official superior.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to summon persons to give evidence and produce documents.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An officer of the Force shall have power to summon any person whose attendance he considers necessary either to give evidence or to produce a document, or any other thing in any inquiry which such officer in making for any of the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A summons to produce documents or other things may be for the production of certain specified documents or things or for the production of all documents or things of a certain description in the possession or under the control of the person summoned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All persons, so summoned, shall be bound to attend either in person or by an authorized agent as such officer may direct; and all persons so summoned shall be bound to state the truth upon any subject respecting which they are examined or make statements and to produce such documents and other things as may be required:</p>
            <p>Provided that the exemptions under sections 132 and 133 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), shall be applicable to requisitions for attendance under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such inquiry as aforesaid shall be deemed to be a “judicial proceeding” within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Issue of search warrant.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If an officer of the Force has reason to believe that any place is used for the deposit or sale of railway property which has been stolen or unlawfully obtained, he shall make an application to the Magistrate, having jurisdiction over the area in which that place is situate, for issue of a search warrant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Magistrate to whom an application is made under sub-section (1), may, after such inquiry as he thinks necessary, by his warrant authorise any officer of the Force—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter with such assistance as may be required, such place;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to search the same in the manner specified in the warrant;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to take possession of any railway property therein found which he reasonably suspects to be stolen or unlawfully obtained; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to convey such railway property before a Magistrate, or to guard the same on the spot until the offender is taken before a Magistrate, or otherwise to dispose thereof in some place of safety.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Searches and arrests how to be made.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All searches and arrests made under this Act shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), relating respectively to searches and arrests made under that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Officers required to assist.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All officers of Government and all village officers are hereby empowered and required to assist the superior officers and members of the force in the enforcement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power of courts to order forfeiture of vehicles, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any court trying an offence punishable under this Act may order the forfeiture to Government of any property in respect of which the court is satisfied that an offence under this Act has been committed and may also order the forfeiture of any receptacles, packages or coverings in which such property is contained and the animals, vehicles, or other conveyances used in carrying the property.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Railway Stores (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1955 (51 of 1955) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to offences punishable under the Act hereby repealed and such offences may be investigated and tried as if this Act had not been passed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The mention of particular matters in sub-section (2) shall not be held to prejudice or affect the general application of section 6 of the General Act, 1857 (10 of 1897), with regard to the effect of repeals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
