<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/82/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/82"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/82/eng@1971-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/82/eng@1971-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1971-12-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/82/eng@1971-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/82/eng@1971-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 82 OF 1971</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 30th December, 1971.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the proper management of the Sikh Gurdwaras and</p>
        <p>Gurdwara property in Delhi and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras Act, 1971.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the date on which this Act shall come into  force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Board" means the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board constituted under  section 3 of the Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras (Management) Act, 1971;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Committee" means the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Management Committee  established under section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Delhi" means the Union territory of Delhi;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Director Gurdwara Elections" means the Director Gurdwara</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Elections appointed by the Central Government under section 13;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Gurdwaras" means the Sikh Gurdwaras situated in Delhi as were,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>immediately before the appointed day, being managed by or affiliated  to the Board and includes such other local Gurdwaras as may, after the  appointed day, be affiliated to or managed by the Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" Gurdwara property" means,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>all movable and immovable property which, immediately before the  appointed day, vested or was kept in deposit in the name of the Board;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>all property which stands in the name of the Gurdwaras or in the  name of the Board or the present or old managers of the historic</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Gurdwaras;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>all offerings in cash or kind made in various Gurdwaras or  institution, managed or controlled by the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>all property in cash or kind, movable as well as immovable that  may be acquired by purchase, exchange or otherwise by the Gurdwaras,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>or the Committee, from time to time;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>all grants, donations or contributions made, from time to time, by  any person or authority to the Gurdwaras or the Committee,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>and includes any actionable claim with respect to such Gurdwara  property;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" local Gurdwara" means a Gurdwara in Delhi, other than a Gurdwara  under the control or management of the Board immediately before the  appointed day;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>a person shall not be deemed to be" ordinarily resident" in a ward  on the ground only that he owns or is in possession of a dwelling-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
                <listIntroduction>house therein and a person absenting himself temporarily from his  place of ordinary residence shall not by reason thereof cease to be  ordinarily resident therein;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.j.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" patit" means a Sikh who trims or shaves his beard or hair</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.j.list0.keshas">
                      <num>(keshas)</num>
                      <p>or who after taking Amrit commits any one or more of the four</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14">
                <listIntroduction>Kurahitis;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" registered Singh Sabha" means a Singh Sabha registered as a  society under the Societies Registration Act, 1860, (21 of 1860.)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16">
                <listIntroduction>which is managing or controlling a local Gurdwara in Delhi;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" regulation" means a regulation made under this Act by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18">
                <listIntroduction>Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>" rule" means a rule made under this Act by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>" Sikh" means a person who professes the Sikh religion, believes  and follows the teachings of Sri Guru Granth Sahib and the ten Gurus  only and keeps unshorn hair (Keshas). For the purposes of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>if any question arises as to whether any living person is or is not a</p>
              <p>Sikh, he shall be deemed respectively to be or not to be a Sikh  according as he makes or refuses to make in the manner prescribed by  rules the following declaration:-</p>
              <p>" I solemnly affirm that I am a Keshadhari Sikh, that I believe in and  follow the teachings of Sri Guru Granth Sahib and the ten Gurus only,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list23">
                <listIntroduction>and that I have no other religion.";</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list23.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>" Amritdhari Sikh" means and includes every Sikh who has taken</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Khande ka Amrit or Khanda Pahul, prepared and administered according  to the tenets of Sikh religion and rites at the hands of five Pyaras  or" beloved ones".</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>THE COMMITTEE</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE COMMITTEE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Incorporation of the Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date  as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, appoint, there shall be established a Committee to be called  the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Management Committee for the proper management  and control of the Gurdwaras and Gurdwara property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall be a body corporate with the name  aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal and shall by  such name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall have its head office in Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Composition of the Committee. The Committee shall consist of-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>forty- six members to be elected from various wards into which</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Delhi shall be divided in accordance with the provisions of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>nine members to be co- opted by the elected members of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Committee referred to in clause (a) in the manner hereinafter ap-</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>pearing,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>two members to represent the registered Singh Sabhas of Delhi who  shall be chosen by drawing of lots out of the Presidents of those  registered Singh Sabhas;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>four members, each being the head priest of the (1) Sri Akal</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Takhat Sahib, Amritsar, (2) Sri Takhat Kesgarh Sahib, Anandpur, (3)</p>
              <p>Sri Takhat Patna Sahib, Patna, and (4) Sri Takhat Hazur Sahib, Nanded:</p>
              <p>Provided that the head priest shall have no right to vote for  the purpose of election of office- bearers and other members of the</p>
              <p>Executive Board under sub- section (1) and sub- section (2) of section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>one member, being the nominee of the Shromani Gurdwara</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Parbandhak Committee, Amritsar;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>two members to represent the Sikh community of Delhi, other than  those referred to in sub- clause (i), sub- clause (ii) and sub- clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>, to be chosen in accordance with the system of proportional  representation by means, of a single transferable vote.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Term of office.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this  section, Vie term of office or a member of the Committee shall be four  years and shall commence from the date on which the first meeting of  the Committee is held under section 15, and no longer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a vacancy occurs in the Committee owing to death,</p>
              <p>resignation, removal or otherwise of a member, a new member shall be  elected or co- opted, as the case may be, in the manner in which the  member whose seat is to be filled was elected or co- opted and every  such member shall continue to hold office so long only as the member  in whose place he is elected or co- opted would have been entitled to  hold office, if the vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall continue in office until the  notification of election or co- option of his successor is published  under section 12,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Delimitation of wards.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of election of  members of the Committee, Delhi shall be divided into single member  wards.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Director Gurdwara Elections shall by order determine-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the number of wards; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the extent of each ward.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director Gurdwara Elections may, from time to time, in  consultation with the Committee, alter or amend any order made under  subsection (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Electoral roll.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An electoral roll shall be prepared in  such manner as may be prescribed by rules for every ward notified  under section 6 on which shall be entered the names of all persons  entitled to be registered as voters in that ward.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral  roll for any ward more than once.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral  roll for more than one ward.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Qualifications of elector. Every person who-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>has been ordinarily resident in a ward for not less than one  hundred and eighty days during the qualifying period,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is a Sikh of not less than twenty- one years of age on  qualifying date,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall, be entitled to be registered in the electoral roll for that  ward:</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no person shall be registered as an elector who-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>trims or shaves his beard or keshas;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>smokes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>takes alcoholic drinks.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section, the" qualifying  date" and the" qualifying period"-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in the case of electoral rolls first prepared under this Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be the 1st day of January, 1972, and the period beginning on the</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1st">
          <num>1st.</num>
          <heading>day of January, 1971 and ending on the 31st day of December, 1971,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1st.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1st.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>respectively; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1st.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in the case of every electoral roll subsequently prepared under  this Act, shall be the 1st day of January of the year in which it is  prepared and the year immediately preceding that year respectively.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Right to vote. Every person registered on the electoral roll  for the time being in force for any ward for the election of a member  of the Committee, shall be entitled while so registered to vote at an  election of a member for that ward, provided that no person shall be  entitled to vote at an election in more than one ward.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Qualifications of member.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall not be qualified  to be chosen or co- opted as a member of the Committee if such person-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>has not attained the age of twenty- five years;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is not a citizen of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of an elected member, if he is not registered as an  elector in the electoral roll for any ward;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>is not an Amritdhari Sikh;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>being an Amritdhari Sikh, trims or shaves his beard or keshas;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>takes alcoholic drinks;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>smokes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>is a patit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>has been convicted of an offence involving moral turpitude or has  been dismissed from service by Government, Board, Committee or any  local authority, on account of moral turpitude;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>is a paid servant of any Gurdwara or a local Gurdwara;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>not being a blind person cannot  read and write] Gurmukhi.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- A person shall be deemed to-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>be able to read Gurmukhi if he is able to recite Sri Guru Granth</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Sahib, in Gurmukhi, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list5.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>write Gurmukhi if he fills his nomination paper for election to  the Committee in Gurmukhi in his own handwriting.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>If any question arises whether a candidate is or is not able to  read an write Gurmukhi, the question shall be decided in such manner  as may be  prescribed by rules].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a person sits or votes as a member of the Committee when  he knows that he is not qualified for such membership, he shall be  liable in respect of each day on which he so sits or votes to a  penalty of three hundred rupees which shall be recoverable as an  arrear of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Elections. Election of members under clause (a) of section 4  whether for the purpose of initial constitution of the Committee under  section 3, or for filling vacancies arising by efflux of time or a  casual vacancy, shall be conducted by the Director Gurdwara Elections  in accordance with the rules made in this behalf:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that no election shall be held to fill a casual vacancy  occurring within four months prior to the holding of a general  election under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Director Gurdwara Elections.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may,</p>
              <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a suitable person to  be the Director Gurdwara. Election in whom shall vest the  superintendence, direction and control of the preparation of electoral  rolls for, and the conduct of, elections of members of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as Director</p>
              <p>Gurdwara Elections unless he is a citizen of India and possesses  judicial or administrative experience for a period of not less than  ten years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of section 37, the term of office,</p>
              <p>and the terms and conditions of service of the Director Gurdwara</p>
              <p>Elections shall be such as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>First meeting of the elected members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The persons to be  co- opted as members of the Committee under clause (b) of section 4  shall be chosen at the first meeting of the elected members which  shall be convened by the Director Gurdwara Elections as early as  possible and not later than fifteen days after publication of the  results of the election under sub- section (1) of section 12.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director Gurdwara Elections may adjourn the first meeting  of the elected members to any other date or dates, being not later  than fifteen days from the date of the first meeting aforesaid, if the  elected members are unable to choose all persons to be co- opted at  that first meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>First meeting of the Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director Gurdwara</p>
              <p>Elections shall summon the first meeting of the Committee to meet on  such date, not being later than tee, fifteen days after the  publication of the names of the members co- opted Under sub- section (2)</p>
              <p>of section 12, as he thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The first meeting shall be held at such time and place as the</p>
              <p>Director Gurdwara Elections may appoint and shall be presided by him:</p>
              <p>Provided that while so presiding at the meeting of the Committee,</p>
              <p>the Director Gurdwara Elections shall have no right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every member of the Committee shall, before taking his seat  make and subscribe before the Director Gurdwara Elections an oath  according to the form set out for the purpose in the Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The members of the Committee shall proceed thereafter to  elect from amongst themselves a pro tempore Chairman in such manner as  may be prescribed by rules, who shall preside at the meeting until the</p>
              <p>Committee elects the President.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Election of office- bearers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall, at its  first meeting after the election of the pro tempore Chairman under  sub- section (4) of section 15, elect from amongst its members a</p>
              <p>President, who shall conduct the election if other office- bearers and  members of the Executive Board under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall also at its first meeting elect from  amongst its members a Senior Vice- President, Junior Vice- President,</p>
              <p>General Secretary and a Joint Secretary (hereinafter referred to as   office- bearers of the Committee), and shall also at the same meeting  in like manner elect ten of its members to be members of the Executive</p>
              <p>Board of the Committee, and the office- bearers and members so elected  shall be the Executive Board of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be eligible for election as the President or  other office- bearer unless he is at least a matriculate or has passed</p>
              <p>Higher Secondary Examination of any recognised University or Board or  is a Giani or possesses any other equivalent educational  qualification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No member of the Committee shall, at the same time, bold any  of the offices referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) in  more than one capacity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President and other members of the Executive Board  elected under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall hold office for  a term of one year but shall be eligible for re- election for one more  term only:</p>
              <p>Provided that an outgoing office- bearer or member shall continue  it office until election of his successor is held.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election of the President and other office- bearers and  members of the Executive Board under sub- section (1) or sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or any subsequent annual election to any of those offices shall be  held in such manner as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 5 shall apply  so far as may be to the filling of a casual vacancy in the  office of  the President, any other office- bearer or member of the Executive</p>
              <p>Board]</p>
              <p>as they apply in relation to casual vacancies in the membership of the</p>
              <p>Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16A">
          <num>16A.</num>
          <heading>Power to convene another meeting for election of  office- bearers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Committee at its first meeting is unable to  elect a pro tempore Chairman or a President or any other office- bearer  or member of the Executive Board under sub- section (4) of section 15  or sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) of section 16, the Director</p>
              <p>Gurdwara Elections shall summon another meeting of the Committee,</p>
              <p>being not later than fifteen days from the date of the first meeting,</p>
              <p>for the election of the pro tempore Chairman, the President or the  remaining office- bearers or members of the Executive Board, as the  case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 15 and 16 shall, so far as may  be, apply to the conduct of election under sub- section (1).]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Vacation, resignation and removal of members and office-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>bearers.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member of the Committee may resign his office by  writing under his hand addressed to the President.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>An office- bearer or any other member of the Executive Board  shall vacate his office if he ceases to be a member of the Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>may at any time by writing under his hand addressed to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Committee resign his office; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>may be removed from his office by a resolution of the Com-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>mittee passed by a three- fourth majority of the total members thereof:</p>
              <p>Provided that no resolution for the purpose of clause (c) shall  be moved unless it is supported by not less than seventeen members of  the Committee and fourteen days' notice has been given of their  intention to move the resolution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The resignation of office under sub- section (1) or clause (b)</p>
              <p>of sub- section (2) shall be effective from the date from which it is  accepted by the Executive Board or the Committee, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Fees and allowances of members. Any office- bearer or other  member of the Executive Board or any other member of the Committee  may, if he so desires, draw such fees and allowances for attending the  meetings of the Executive Board or the Committee and for attending to  any other work of the Executive Board or the Committee, as the case  may be, as may be prescribed by regulations.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Committee and the Executive Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  annual general meeting of the Committee shall be held in every year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Executive Board shall meet at least once in every  fortnight or at such intervals as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President, or in his absence the Senior Vice- President an  in the absence of both, the Junior Vice- President, and in the absence  of all the three, any other member elected from amongst themselves  shall preside at any meeting of the Committee or of the Executive</p>
              <p>Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee or the Executive Board shall observe such rules  of procedure in regard to transaction of the business at its meetings  a may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided, all questions which come up  before any meeting of the Committee or the Executive Board shall be  decide by a majority of votes of the members present and voting and in  the event of equality of votes, the person presiding shall have a  second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All proceedings of the meetings of the Committee or the</p>
              <p>Executive Board shall be recorded in Punjabi in Gurmukhi script.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Sub- committees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Executive Board may constitute such  number of subcommittees from amongst the members of the Committee as  it thinks fit and for such purpose as it may decide.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A sub- committee constituted under sub- section (1) shall meet  at such time and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in  regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be  prescribed by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member of a sub- committee may, if he so desires, draw such  fees and allowances for attending its meetings and for attending to  any other work of the sub- committee, as may be prescribed by  regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Validity of acts of Committee, Executive Board or sub-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>committees not to be questioned by reason of vacancy, etc. No act or  proceeding of the Committee or the Executive Board or any sub-</p>
              <p>committee shall be invalidated by reason only of the existence of any  vacancy amongst its members or any defect in the constitution thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Officers and other employees of the Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Committee may appoint such number of officers and other employees as  it considers necessary for the efficient performance of its functions,</p>
              <p>and may, from time to time, determine the number, designations, grades  and scales of pay or other remuneration of the officers and other  employees, and may at any time reduce, suspend, remove or dismiss or  impose any other penalty on any officer or other employee for  carelessness, unfitness, neglect of duty or other misconduct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The officers and other employees appointed under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be  prescribed by regulations or as may, from time to time, be delegated  by the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the officers and other  employees shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMITTEE</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMITTEE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of the Committee. Subject to the  provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, the control,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>direction and general superintendence over all the Gurdwaras and</p>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Gurdwara property in Delhi shall vest in the Committee, and it shall  be the duty of the Committee-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to arrange for the proper performance of the religious rites and  ceremonies in the Gurdwaras,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to provide facilities for worship by the devotees at the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Gurdwaras,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>to ensure safe custody of its funds, movable and immovable  properties, deposits, offerings in cash or kind,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>to do all such things as may be incidental and conducive to the  efficient management of the affairs of Gurdwaras, educational and  other institutions under the Committee and their properties or to the  convenience of devotees,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>to provide suitable accommodation and facilities for pilgrims,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>to maintain free langars,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>to manage the historic and other Gurdwaras, educational and  other institutions and their properties in such a way as to make them  inspiring centres of the Sikh tradition, culture and religion,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>to ensure maintenance of order, discipline and proper hygienic  conditions in Gurdwaras, educational and other institutions under its  management,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>to open free dispensaries,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>to spread education, especially the knowledge of Punjabi, in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Gurmukhi script,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>to establish educational institutions, research centres and  libraries.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>to render financial assistance to religious and educational  institutions, societies and needy persons,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.xiii">
                  <num>(xiii)</num>
                  <p>to give stipends to needy and deserving students,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.xiv">
                  <num>(xiv)</num>
                  <p>to render help in the case of the uplift of the Sikh community  and propagation of Sikh religion,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.xv">
                  <num>(xv)</num>
                  <p>to perform such other functions and to do such religious or  charitable acts, as may be prescribed by regulations for carrying out  the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>GURDWARA FUND, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>GURDWARA FUND, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition regarding making of contributions for political  purposes. Nothing contained in this Act shall, or shall be deemed to,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>authorise the Committee to contribute any amount or amounts-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to any political party, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for the benefit of any political party, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for any political purpose to any individual or body.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Budget.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In respect of every financial year, budget</p>
              <p>(annual financial statement) of the estimated receipts and expenditure  of the Committee for the year shall be placed before the Committee and  duly passed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No moneys out of the Gurdwara Fund shall be appropriated ex-</p>
              <p>cept as passed and approved by the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of accounts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall maintain  proper accounts showing receipts on account of and expenditure out of</p>
              <p>Gurdwara Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At the end of each calendar month, a statement of income and  expenditure relating to that month shall be prepared and placed before  the Committee and it shall be pasted at prominent places outside all</p>
              <p>Gurdwaras; and a consolidated annual statement, showing income and  expenditure relating to a financial year shall likewise be prepared  and placed before the Committee and outside the Gurdwaras at the end  of each financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Audit of Accounts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Committee  including those of the Gurdwaras, and Gurdwara property including  educational and other charitable institutions administered by the</p>
              <p>Committee, shall be audited by one or more auditors duly qualified to  act as auditor under subsection (1) of section 226 of the Companies</p>
              <p>Act, 1956 (hereinafter referred to as the auditor) who shall be  appointed by the Committee within sixty days of the</p>
              <p>close of every financial year and shall receive such remuneration as  the Committee may fix:</p>
              <p>Provided that the first appointment of auditors shall be made by  the Committee within sixty days from the date of its first meeting  held under section 15.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of any such audit and examination of accounts  the auditors may, by a demand in writing, require from the Committee  or any office- bearer or member or employee of the Committee or any</p>
              <p>Gurdwara, educational or other institution of the Committee, the pro-</p>
              <p>duction before him of all books, deeds, vouchers and all other docu-</p>
              <p>ments and papers which he deems necessary, and may require any person  holding or accountable for any such books, deeds, vouchers, documents  and papers to appear before him at any audit and examination, to  answer all questions which may be put to him with respect to the same  or to prepare and submit any further statement which such auditor may  consider necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Within thirty days after the audit and examination have been  completed, the auditor shall submit a report to the Committee upon  each account audited and examined.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The audit report shall be published in, at least two daily  papers of Delhi (one in English and one in Punjabi) as well as in</p>
              <p>Gurdwara Journal, if any, within thirty days of its receipt.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The report of the auditor shall, among other matters, specify  all items of expenditure which in his opinion are illegal, irregular  or improper, all cases of failure of recoveries of money or property  due to the Committee, all instances of loss or wasteful expenditure of  money or property due to negligence or misconduct and all instances in  which any money or property has been devoted to any purpose not  authorised by this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Consideration of the auditor' s report by the Committee. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Committee, in meeting next following the date of receipt of the  auditor' s report, shall consider such report and satisfy itself that  no expenditure shown therein has been incurred otherwise than in  accordance with the provisions of this Act and shall pass such orders  as are, in its opinion, necessary and proper to rectify the illegal,</p>
              <p>unauthorised or improper expenditure and may also pass such further  orders upon the report, as it may deem proper:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the next meeting falls on a day earlier than two  months after the receipt of the report it may be considered in the  meeting next following which shall be convened before the expiry of a  period of three months from the date of receipt of the said report.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>SETTLEMENT OF ELECTIONS AND OTHER DISPUTES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SETTLEMENT OF ELECTIONS AND OTHER DISPUTES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Election disputes, electoral offences, etc. The provisions of  sections 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 22, 23, 24, 25, 27, 28, 29 and 30 of  the Delhi Municipal Corporation Act, 1957 (66 of 1957.), shall mutatis  mutandis apply, subject to such modifications as the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may by order direct, in relation to settlement of disputes  regarding elections, corrupt practices and electoral offences in  respect of election or co- option of members of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of District Court in other matters. The Court of  the District Judge in Delhi shall also have jurisdiction in respect  of the following matters, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Petitions regarding complaints, irregularities, breach of  trust, mismanagement in any Gurdwara, educational or other institu-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>tions against any member, office- bearer or officer or other employee  of the Committee.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>Petitions arising out of any type of disputes between the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Committee and its employees including past employees.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>Applications regarding failure of publication of, or non-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>implementation or non- clearance of the objections raised in, any  annual report of the auditors of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Appeals.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person aggrieved by an order passed by the</p>
              <p>District Judge may, within sixty days of the order, prefer an appeal  to the High Court at Delhi and the orders of the High Court on such  appeal shall be final and conclusive.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 5 and 12 of the Limitation Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1963">
          <num>1963.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, shall, so far as may be, apply to appeals under this section.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for affiliation of local Gurdwaras.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A registered</p>
              <p>Singh Sabha may, in relation to any local Gurdwara under its control,</p>
              <p>decide by a resolution adopted by three- fourth majority of its total  membership for affiliating that local Gurdwara to the Committee and if  the Committee consents thereto, the said local Gurdwara shall be  deemed to be affiliated to the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All assets and liabilities of the local Gurdwara so  affiliated and of the registered Singh Sabha shall thereafter vest in  the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Act not to affect rites and practices of Sikh religion.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in  force shall-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act or the rules or  regulations made thereunder, affect any honour, emolument or  perquisite to which any person is entitled by custom or otherwise in  any Gurdwara;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>authorise any interference with the religious or spiritual func-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>tions performed in any Gurdwara.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Salary, etc., of the Director Gurdwara Elections to be  defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India in the first instance.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances payable to the Director Gurdwara</p>
              <p>Elections or to the officers and other employees engaged for the  conduct of elections to the Committee, shall be defrayed out of the</p>
              <p>Consolidated Fund of India in the first instance, but shall be  recoverable from the Committee by debit to the Gurdwara Fund after the  close of each financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any sum due to the Central Government under sub- section (1) shall,</p>
              <p>if not paid within three months after the demand has been made, be  recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken. No suit, prosecution or other  legal proceedings shall lie against any member of the Committee, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Executive Board or any sub- committee, the Director Gurdwara Elections  or any other officer or employee of the Committee for anything which  is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any  rule or regulation made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for or regulate all or any of  the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-39.2.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the manner in which a declaration for the purpose of clause (n) of  section 2 shall be made;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list1.a.list0.aa">
                      <num>(aa)</num>
                      <p>the manner and the criterion for deciding whether a candidate  for election as a member of the Committee is able to read and write</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Gurmukhi;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the particulars to be entered in the electoral rolls;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the preliminary publication of electoral rolls;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which and the time within which claims and  objections as to entries in electoral rolls may be preferred;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which notices of claims or objections shall be  published;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the place date and time at which claims or objections shall be  heard and the manner in which claims or objections shall be heard and  disposed of;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the final publication of electoral rolls;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the revision and correction of electoral rolls and inclusion of  names therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of returning officers, assistant returning</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Officers, Presiding officers and polling officers for the conduct of  elections;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list5.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the nomination of candidates, form of nomination papers,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>objections to nominations and scrutiny of nominations;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list7.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the deposits to be made by candidates, time and manner of making  such deposits and the circumstances under which such deposits may be  refunded to candidates or forfeited to the Committee</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list7.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the withdrawal of candidatures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list7.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of agents of candidates;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list7.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>the procedure in contested and uncontested elections,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list7.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the date, time and place for poll and other matters relating  to the conduct of elections including-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of polling stations for each ward,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the hours during which the polling station shall be kept open for  the casting of votes,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>the printing and issue of ballot papers,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>the checking of voters by reference to the electoral roll,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>the marking with indelible ink of the left forefinger or any other  finger or limb of the voter and prohibition of the delivery of any  ballot paper to any person if at the time such person applies for such  paper he has already such mark so as to prevent personation of voters,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.vi">
                      <num>(vi)</num>
                      <p>the manner in which votes are to be given and in particular in  the case of illiterate voters or of voters under physical or other  disability,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.vii">
                      <num>(vii)</num>
                      <p>the procedure to be followed in respect of challenging votes and  tendered votes,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.viii">
                      <num>(viii)</num>
                      <p>the scrutiny of votes, counting of votes, the declaration of  the results and the procedure in case of equality of votes or in the  event of a member being elected to represent more than one ward,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.ix">
                      <num>(ix)</num>
                      <p>the custody and disposal of papers relating to elections,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.2.list7.o.list0.x">
                      <num>(x)</num>
                      <p>the suspension of polls in case of any interruption by riot,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list9">
                <listIntroduction>violence or any other sufficient cause and the holding of a fresh  poll,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list9.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>the holding of a fresh poll in the case of destruction of, or  tampering with, ballot boxes before the count,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list9.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>the countermanding of the poll in the case of the death of a  candidate before the poll;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list9.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>the fee to be paid on an election petition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list9.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of service of the Director Gurdwara</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list11">
                <listIntroduction>Elections;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list11.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>the procedure for the election of pro tempore Chairman under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>section (4) of section 15, and of the President and other office-</p>
              <blockList id="section-39.2.list14">
                <listIntroduction>bearers and members of the Executive Board under section 16;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.2.list14.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>any other matter in respect of which the Central Government deems  it necessary to make rules under this section or in respect of which  this Act makes no provision or makes insufficient provision and  provision is, in the opinion of the Central Government, necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.2.list14.t">
                  <num>(t)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which results of election or co- option of members of  the Committee shall be published, or the orders made under the rules  shall be widely made known by affixing copies thereof in conspicuous  public places, by publishing the same by beat of drum or by  advertisement in local newspapers.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making any rule under this section the Central Government  may provide that any contravention thereof shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or  with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rules made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be, after they are made, before each House of Parliament while it  is in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be  comprised in one session or in  two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid,] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rules or both Houses agree that the rules should  not be made, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
              <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under those rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Power of Committee to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee may  make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or  the rules made thereunder for carrying out its functions under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-40.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing powers, such regulations; may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely.-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>date for election</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fees and allowances to which office- bearers and other members of  the Executive Board or other members of the Committee or of a sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-40.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>committee shall be entitled for attending meetings or any other work  of the Executive Board, Committee or sub- committee respectively;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the periods of interval at which meetings of the Executive Board  shall be hold, the manner in which meetings of the Committee or the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Executive Board or any sub- committee shall be convened, the quorum for  the transaction of business thereat and the rules of procedure to be  followed for transaction of business at meetings of the Committee, the</p>
              <blockList id="section-40.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Executive Board or any sub- committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which a majority decision of the Executive Board  shall be obtained by circulation to its, office- bearers and members of  any matter requiring decision;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the matters in respect of which powers may be exercised or duties  performed by the President or other office- bearers of the Executive</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-40.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Board or by any officer or other employee of the Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.2.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of service of officers and other em-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-40.2.list10">
                <listIntroduction>ployees of the Committee including recruitment, transfer, fixation of  seniority, promotion of, and disciplinary action or punishment  against, such officers and other employees;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.2.list10.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>any other functions or religious or charitable acts which, in  addition to those specified in section 24, may be performed or done by  the Committee, and the conditions and restrictions subject to which  those functions or acts shall be performed or done;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which cash or other moneys of the Gurdwara Fund  shall be deposited or invested;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the form in which the budget of the Committee shall be presented;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list10.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the form in which the accounts of the Committee shall be  maintained and the publication of such accounts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list10.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which any regulations or orders made thereunder  shall be published or widely made known by affixing copies thereof in  conspicuous public places, by publishing the same by beat of drum or  by advertisement in local newspapers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.2.list10.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and Saving.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the date of the establishment  of the Committee, the Delhi Sikh Gurdwaras (Management) Act, 1971 (24   of 1971.) shall stand repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding such repeal,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any appointment, notification, order or rule made or issued under  the said Act shall, in so far as it is not inconsistent with the  provisions of this Act, continue in force and be deemed to have been  made or issued under the provisions of this Act unless and until it is  superseded by any appointment, notification, order or rule made or  issued under the said provisions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all budget estimates made, all obligations and liabilities in-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>curred, all contracts entered into and all matters and things engaged  to be done by, with or for the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board shall be  deemed to have been made, incurred, entered into or' engaged to be  done by, with or for the Committee under the provisions of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all Gurdwara property, movable and immovable and all interests of  whatsoever nature and kind therein vested in, belonging or due to, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board, immediately before such establishment,</p>
              <p>shall, with all rights, powers and privileges of whatsoever  description, used, enjoyed or possessed by the Board vest in the</p>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list7.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all sums of money including rents due to the Board immediately  before such establishment shall be deemed to be due to the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or which might  have been instituted by or against the Delhi Sikh Gurdwara Board may  be continued or instituted by or against the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any will deed or other instrument which contains any bequest,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>gifts or trusts in favour of the Board shall as from such  establishment, be construed as if the Committee were therein named  instead of the said Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
