<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1914/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1914/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Destructive Insects And Pests Act, 1914"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1914/2/eng@1914-02-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1914/2/eng@1914-02-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1914-02-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1914/2/eng@1914-02-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1914/2/eng@1914-02-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Destructive Insects And Pests Act, 1914</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 2 OF 1914</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 3rd February, 1914.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to prevent the introduction into  India]  and the  transport from one province to another ]  of any insect, fungus or  other pest, which is or may be destructive to crops.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>] This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Destructive Insects and Pests Act, 1914.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" crops" includes all agricultural or horticultural crops    and all trees, bushes or plants];</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" import" means the bringing or taking by sea,  land  or air]  across any customs frontier as defined by  the Central Government];</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" infection" means infection by any insect, fungus or  other pest injurious to a crop;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to regulate or prohibit the import  of articles likely to infect.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, prohibit or regulate, subject to  such restrictions and conditions as it may impose, the import into</p>
            <p>India] or any part thereof, or any specified place therein, of any  article or class of articles likely to cause infection to any crop    or of insects generally or any class of insects].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A notification under this section may specify any article or  class of articles  or any insect or class of insects] either  generally or in any particular manner, whether with reference to the  country of origin or the route by which imported or otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification under this  section, also levy and collect such fees at such rates and in such  manner as may be specified therein for making an application for a  permit to import, or for making inspection, fumigation, disinfection,</p>
            <p>disinfestation or supervision of, any article or class of articles or  any insect or class of insects under this section.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Operation notification under section 3. A notification under  section 3 shall operate as if it had been issued under section 19 of  the Sea Customs Act, 1878, (8 of 1878.) and the officers of Customs at  every port shall have the same powers in respect of any article with  regard to the importation of which such a notification has been issued  as they have for the time being in respect of any article the  importation of which is regulated, restricted or prohibited by the law  relating to Sea Customs, and the law for the time being in force  relating to Sea Customs or any such article shall apply accordingly.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to regulate or prohibit  transport from State to State of insects or articles likely to  infect. The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Gazette, prohibit or regulate, subject to such conditions as the</p>
            <p>Central Government may impose, the export from a State or the  transport from one State to another State  of any article or class  of articles likely to cause infection to any crop or of insects  generally or any class of insects.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4B">
        <num>4B.</num>
        <heading>Refusal to carry article of which transport is prohibited.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a notification has been issued under section 4A, then,</p>
            <p>notwithstanding any other law for the time being in force, the person</p>
            <blockList id="section-4B.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>responsible for the booking of goods or parcels at any railway station  or inland steam vessel station,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4B.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the notification prohibits export or transport,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4B.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>shall refuse to receive for carriage at, or to forward  or knowingly allow to be carried on, the railway or  inland steam vessel from that station anything, of  which import or transport is prohibited, consigned to  any place in a State other than the State in which such  station is situate; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4B.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the notification imposes conditions upon export or  transport, shall so refuse, unless the consignor  produces, or the thing consigned is accompanied by, a  document or documents of the prescribed nature showing  that those conditions are satisfied.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4C">
        <num>4C.</num>
        <heading>Application of section 4B to articles exported to the State  of Jammu and Kashmir. Rep. by the Jammu and Kashmir (Extension of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Laws) Act, 1956 (62 of 1956), s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 11- 1956).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4D">
        <num>4D.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>] The</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make  rules prescribing the nature of the documents which shall accompany  any article or insect the export or transport whereof is subject to  conditions imposed under section 4A, or which shall be held by the  consignor or consignee thereof, the authorities which may issue such  documents and the manner in which the documents shall be employed:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this  section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State</p>
            <p>Government may,  by notification in the Official gazette,]  make  rules for the detention, inspection, disinfection or destruction  of  any insect or class of insects or] of any article or class of articles  in respect of which a notification has been issued under section 3    or under section 4A] or of any article which may have been in  contact or proximity thereto, and for regulating the powers and duties  of the officers whom it may appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rule under this section the State Government  may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine, which  may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this  section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the</p>
            <p>State Legislature.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Penalties. Any person who knowingly exports any article or  insect from a State or transports any article or insect from one State  to another  in contravention of a notification issued under  section 4A, or attempts so to export or transport any article or  insect  and any person responsible for the booking of goods or  parcels at a railway or inland steam vessel station who knowingly  contravenes the provisions of section 4B shall be punishable with fine  which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees and, upon any  subsequent conviction, with fine which may extend to two thousand  rupees.]</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Protection to persons acting under Act. No suit, prosecution  or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything in  good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
