<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Government Of Union Territories Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1963-05-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Government Of Union Territories Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 20 OF 1963</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 10th May, 1963.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for Legislative Assemblies and Councils of Ministers  for certain Union territories and for certain other matters.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Government of Union Territories Act, 1963.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:</p>
              <p>Provided that it shall come into force in the Union territory  of Mizoram on such date, being a date not earlier than the date of  commencement of the Government of Union Territories (Amendment) Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1971">
          <num>1971.</num>
          <heading>(83 of 1971), as the Central Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, appoint:]</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1971.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1971.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Provided further that it shall come into force in the Union  territory of Arunachal Pradesh on such date, being a date not earlier  than the date of commencement of the Government of Union Territories</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1971.paragraph-0.list1.Amendment">
                  <num>(Amendment)</num>
                  <p>Act, 1975 (29 of 1975), as the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided also that, subject to the preceding provisos,]</p>
              <p>different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act  and for different Union territories and any reference in any such  provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a  reference to the coming into force of that provision.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions and interpretation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the  context otherwise requires,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Administrator" means the administrator of  the Union  territory] appointed by the President under artcle 239;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" article" means an article of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" assembly constituency" means a constituency provided  under this Act for the purpose of elections to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  appointed by the President under article 324;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Judicial Commissioner" includes an Additional Judicial</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Commissioner;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" scheduled castes" in relation to  the Union  territory] mean such castes, races or tribes or parts  of or groups within such castes, races or tribes as are  deemed under article 341 to be scheduled castes in  relation to that Union territory;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" scheduled tribes" in relation to  the Union  territory] mean such tribes or tribal communities or  parts of or groups within such tribes or tribal  communities as are deemed under article 342 to be  scheduled tribes in relation to that Union territory;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Union territory" means the Union territory of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Pondicherry.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any reference in this Act to laws made by Parliament shall be  construed as including a reference to Ordinances promulgated by the</p>
              <p>President under article 123 and a reference to Regulations made by the</p>
              <p>President under article 240.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLIES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Legislative Assemblies for Union territories and their  composition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be a Legislative Assembly for each Union  territory.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of    the Union territory] to be filled by persons chosen by direct  election shall be thirty.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may nominate not more than three  persons, not being persons in the service of Government, to be members  of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes in the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The number of seats reserved for the scheduled castes or the  scheduled tribes in the Legislative Assembly  of  the Union  territory]] under sub- section (4) shall bear, as nearly as may be, the  same proportion to the total number of seats in the Assembly as the  popu-</p>
              <p>lation of the scheduled castes in the Union territory or of the  scheduled tribes in the Union territory, as the case may be, in  respect of which seats are so reserved, bears to the total population  of the Union territory.</p>
              <p>' Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression</p>
              <p>" population" means the population as ascertained at the last preceding  census of which the relevant figures have been published.</p>
              <p>Provided that the reference in this Explanation to the last  preceding census of which the relevant figures have been published  shall, until the relevant figures for the first census taken after the  year 2000 have been published, be construed as a reference to the 1971  census.']</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything in sub- section (4), the  reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes in the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of the Union territory shall cease to have effect on the same  date on which the reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes in the</p>
              <p>House of the People shall cease to have effect under article 334:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall affect any  representation in the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory  until the dissolution of the then existing Assembly.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Qualification for membership of Legislative Assembly. A person  shall not be qualified to be chosen to fill a seat in the Legislative</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly of  the Union territory] unless he--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is a citizen of India and makes and subscribes before  some person authorised in that behalf by the Election</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Commission an oath or affirmation according to the form  set out for the purpose in the First Schedule;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is not less than twenty- five years of age; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>possesses such other qualifications as may be prescribed  in that behalf by or under any law.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Duration of Legislative Assemblies. The Legislative Assembly  of  the Union territory], unless sooner dissolved, shall continue  for five years from the date appointed for its first meeting and no  longer, and the expiration of the said period of five years shall  operate as a dissolution of the Assembly:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the said period may, while a Proclamation of</p>
              <p>Emergency issued under clause (1) of article 352 is in operation, be  extended by the President by order for a period not exceeding one year  at a time and not extending in any case beyond a period of six months  after the Proclamation has ceased to operate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Sessions of Legislative Assembly, prorogation and dissolution.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator shall, from time to time, summon the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit, but six  months shall not intervene between its last sitting in one session and  the date appointed for its first sitting in the next session.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Administrator may, from time to time,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>prorogue the Assembly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>dissolve the Assembly.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Speaker and Deputy Speaker of Legislative Assembly.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly shall, as soon as may be, choose two members of  the Assembly to be respectively Speaker and Deputy Speaker thereof  and, so often as the office of Speaker or Deputy Speaker becomes  vacant, the Assembly shall choose another member to be Speaker or</p>
              <p>Deputy Speaker, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member holding office as Speaker or Deputy Speaker of an</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall vacate his office if he ceases to be a member of  the Assembly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>may at any time by writing under his hand addressed, if  such member is the Speaker, to the Deputy Speaker, and  if such member is the Deputy Speaker, to the Speaker,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>resign his office;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>may be removed from his office by a resolution of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Assembly passed by a majority of all the then members  of the Assembly:</p>
              <p>Provided that no resolution for the purpose of clause (c) shall  be moved unless at least fourteen days' notice has been given of the  intention to move the resolution:</p>
              <p>Provided further that whenever the Assembly is dissolved, the</p>
              <p>Speaker shall not vacate his office until immediately before the first  meeting of the Assembly after the dissolution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>While the office of Speaker is vacant, the duties of the  office shall be performed by the Deputy Speaker or, if the office of</p>
              <p>Deputy Speaker is also vacant, by such member of the Assembly as may  be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During the absence of the Speaker from any sitting of the</p>
              <p>Assembly, the Deputy Speaker, or, if he is also absent, such person as  may be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly, or, if no  such person is present, such other person as may be determined by the</p>
              <p>Assembly, shall act as Speaker.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be paid to the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of  the Legislative Assembly such salaries and allowances as may be  respectively fixed by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory  by law and, until provision in that behalf is so made, such salaries</p>
              <p>and allowances as the Administrator may, with the approval of the</p>
              <p>President, by order determine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Speaker or Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution  for his removal from office is under consideration.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any sitting  of the Legislative Assembly, while any resolution for the removal of  the Speaker from his office is under consideration, the Speaker, or  while any resolution for the removal of the Deputy Speaker from his  office is under consideration, the Deputy Speaker, shall not, though  he is present, preside and the provisions of sub- section (4) of  section 7 shall apply in relation to every such sitting as they apply  in relation to a sitting from which the Speaker or, as the case may  be, the Deputy Speaker is absent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Speaker shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise  to take part in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly while any  resolution for his removal from office is under consideration in the</p>
              <p>Assembly and shall, notwithstanding anything in section 12, be  entitled to vote only in the first instance on such resolution or on  any other matter during such proceedings but not in the case of an  equality of votes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Right of Administrator to address and send messages to</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator may address the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly and may for that purpose require the attendance  of members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator may also send messages to the Assembly  whether with respect to a Bill then pending in the Assembly or  otherwise, and when a message is so sent, the Assembly shall with all  convenient dispatch consider any matter required by the message to be  taken into consideration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Rights of Ministers as respects Legislative Assembly. Every</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Minister shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise to take part  in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly of the Union  territory, and to speak in, and otherwise to take part in the  proceedings of, any committee of the Legislative Assembly of which he  may be named a member, but shall not by virtue of this section be  entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Oath or affirmation by members. Every member of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] shall, before taking  his seat, make and subscribe before the Administrator, or some person  appointed in that behalf by him, an oath or affirmation according to  the form set out for the purpose in the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Voting in Assembly, power of Assembly to act notwithstanding  vacancies and quorum.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all  questions at any sitting of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] shall</p>
              <p>be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting  other than the Speaker or person acting as such.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Speaker or person acting as such shall not vote in the  first instance but shall have and exercise a casting vote in the case  of an equality of votes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] shall  have power to act notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership  thereof, and any proceedings in the Legislative Assembly of a  the</p>
              <p>Union territory] shall be valid notwithstanding that it is discovered  subsequently that some person who was not entitled so to do, sat or  voted or otherwise took part in the proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The quorum to constitute a meeting of the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of  the Union territory] shall be one- third of the total  number of members of the Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at any time during a meeting of the Legislative Assembly  of  the Union territory] there is no quorum, it shall be the duty of  the Speaker, or person acting as such, either to adjourn the Assembly  or to suspend the meeting until there is a quorum.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Vacation of seats.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be a member both of</p>
              <p>Parliament and of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory]</p>
              <p>and if a person is chosen a member both of Parliament and of such</p>
              <p>Assembly, then, at the expiration of such period as may be specified  in the rules made by the President, that person' s seat in Parliament  shall become vacant, unless he has previously resigned his seat in the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If a member of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory]--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes subject to any disqualification mentioned in    section 14 or section 14A] for membership of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>resigns his seat by writing under his hand addressed to  the Speaker,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>his seat shall thereupon become vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If for a period of sixty days a member of the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of  the union territory] is without permission of the</p>
              <p>Assembly absent from all meetings thereof, the Assembly may declare  his seat vacant:</p>
              <p>Provided that in computing the said period of sixty days, no  account shall be taken of any period during which the Assembly is  prorogued or is adjourned for more than four consecutive days.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications for membership.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall be  disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory]--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he holds any office of profit under the Government of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>India or the Government of any State or the Government  of  the Union territory] other than an office  declared by law made by Parliament or by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory not to  disqualify its holder; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he is for the time being disqualified for being  chosen as, and for being, a member of either House of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Parliament under the provisions of sub- clause (b), sub-</p>
              <p>clause (c) or sub- clause (d) of clause (1) of article</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-102">
          <num>102.</num>
          <heading>or of any law made in pursuance of that article.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-102.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this section, a person shall not be  deemed to hold an office of profit under the Government of India or  the Government of any State or the Government of  the Union  territory] by reason only that he is a Minister either for the Union  or for such State or Union territory.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-102.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises as to whether a member of the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] has become  disqualified for being such a member under the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1), the question shall be referred for the decision of the</p>
              <p>President and his decision shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-102.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before giving any decision on any such question, the</p>
              <p>President shall obtain the opinion of the Election Commission and  shall act according to such opinion.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14A">
          <num>14A.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification on ground of defection for being a  member. The provisions of the Tenth Schedule to the Constitution  shall, subject to the necessary modifications (including modifications  for construing references therein to the Legislative Assembly of a</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State, article 188, article 194 and article 212 as references,</p>
              <p>respectively, to the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory],</p>
              <p>section 11, section 16 and section 37 of this Act), apply to and in  relation to the members of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] as they apply to and in relation to the members of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-14A.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly of a State, and accordingly,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14A.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the said Tenth Schedule as so modified shall be deemed  to form part of this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14A.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a person shall be disqualified for being a member of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] if he is so  disqualified under the said Tenth Schedule as so modified.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for sitting and voting before making oath or  affirmation or when not qualified or when disqualified. If a person  sits or votes as a member of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] before he has complied with the requirements of section 11  or when he knows that he is not qualified or that he is disqualified  for membership thereof, he shall be liable in respect of each day on  which he so sits or votes to a penalty of five hundred rupees to be  recovered as a debt due to the Union.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Powers, privileges, etc., of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act and to the rules and standing orders regulating  the procedure of the Legislative Assembly, there shall be freedom of  speech in the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No member of the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] shall be liable to any proceedings in any court in respect  of anything said or any vote given by him in the Assembly or any  committee thereof, and no person shall be so liable in respect of the  publication</p>
              <p>by or under the authority of such Assembly of any report, paper, votes  or proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In other respects, the powers, privileges and immunities of  the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] and of the members  and the committees thereof shall be such as are for the time being  enjoyed by the House of the People and its members and committees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall apply  in relation to persons who by virtue of this Act have the right to  speak in, and otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] or any committee  thereof as they apply in relation to members of that Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Salaries and allowances of members. Members of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] shall be entitled to  receive such salaries and allowances as may from time to time be  determined by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory by law  and, until provision in that behalf is so made, such salaries and  allowances as the Administrator may, with the approval of the</p>
              <p>President, by order determine.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Extent of legislative power.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of  this Act, the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] may make  laws for the whole or any part of the Union territory with respect to  any of the matters enumerated in the State List or the Concurrent List  in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution in so far as any such  matter is applicable in relation to Union territories.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall derogate from the powers  conferred on Parliament by the Constitution to make laws with respect  to any matter for  the Union territory] or any part thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Exemption of property of the Union from taxation. The  property of the Union shall, save in so far as Parliament may by law  otherwise provide, be exempted from all taxes imposed by or under any  law made by the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] or by  or under any other law in force in  the Union territory]:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall, until Parliament by  law otherwise provides, prevent any authority within  the Union  territory] from levying any tax on any property of the Union to which  such property was immediately before the commencement of the</p>
              <p>Constitution liable or treated as liable, so long as that tax  continues to be levied in that Union territory.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Restrictions on laws passed by Legislative Assembly with  respect to certain matters.  1] The provisions of article 286,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>article 287 and article 288 shall apply in relation to any law passed  by the Legislative Assembly of</p>
              <p>the Union territory] with respect to any of the matters referred to  in those articles as they apply in relation to any law passed by the</p>
              <p>Legislature of a State with respect to those matters.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of article 304 shall, with the necessary  modifications, apply in relation to any law passed by the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of  the Union territory] with respect to any of the matters  referred to in that article as they apply in relation to any law  passed by the Legislature of a State with respect to those matters.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Inconsistency between laws made by Parliament and laws  made by Legislative Assembly. If any provision of a law made by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] with respect to any  matter enumerated in the State List in the Seventh Schedule to the</p>
              <p>Constitution is repugnant to any provision of a law made by Parliament  with respect to that matter, whether passed before or after the law  made by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory, or, if any  provision of a law made by the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] with respect to any matter enumerated in the Concurrent</p>
              <p>List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution is repugnant to any  provision of any earlier law, other than a law made by the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of the Union territory, with respect to that matter, then, in  either case, the law made by Parliament, or, as the case may be, such  earlier law shall prevail and the law made by the Legislative Assembly  of the Union territory shall, to the extent of the repugnancy, be  void:</p>
              <p>Provided that if such law made by the Legislative Assembly of the</p>
              <p>Union territory has been reserved for the consideration of the</p>
              <p>President and has received his assent, such law shall prevail in that</p>
              <p>Union territory:</p>
              <p>Provided further that nothing in this section shall prevent</p>
              <p>Parliament from enacting at any time any law with respect to the same  matter including a law adding to, amending, varying or repealing the  law so made by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Sanction of the administrator required for certain  legislative proposals. No Bill or amendment shall be introduced into,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or moved in, the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory]</p>
              <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>without the previous sanction of the Administrator, if such Bill or  amendment makes provision with respect to any of the following  matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>constitution and organisation of the court of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Judicial Commissioner;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>jurisdiction and powers of the court of the Judicial</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Commissioner with respect to any of the matters in the</p>
              <p>State List or the Concurrent list in the Seventh</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Constitution."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Special provisions as to financial Bills.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-23.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill or  amendment shall not be introduced into, or moved in, the Legislative</p>
                  <blockList id="section-23.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Assembly of  the Union territory] except on the recommendation of  the Administrator, if such Bill or amendment makes provision for any  of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-23.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the imposition, abolition, remission, alteration or  regulation of any tax;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.1.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the amendment of the law with respect to any financial  obligations undertaken or to be undertaken by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-23.1.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Government of the Union territory;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-23.1.list4.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund  of the Union territory;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.1.list4.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the declaring of any expenditure to be expenditure  charged on the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory  or the increasing of the amount of any such  expenditure;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.1.list4.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund  of the Union territory or the custody or issue of such  money:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that no recommendation shall be required under this sub-</p>
                  <p>section for the moving of an amendment making provision for the  reduction or abolition of any tax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill or amendment shall not be deemed to make provision for  any of the matters aforesaid by reason only that it provides for the  imposition of fines or other pecuniary penalties, or for the demand or  payment of fees for licences or fees for services rendered, or by  reason that it provides for the imposition, abolition, remission,</p>
                  <p>alteration or regulation of any tax by any local authority or body for  local purposes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill which, if enacted and brought into operation, would  involve expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of  the Union  territory] shall not be passed by the Legislative Assembly of the</p>
                  <p>Union territory unless the Administrator has recommended to that</p>
                  <p>Assembly the consideration of the Bill.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Procedure as to lapsing of Bills.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-24.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill pending in the</p>
                  <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] shall not lapse by  reason of the prorogation of the Assembly.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Bill which is pending in the Legislative Assembly of  the</p>
                  <p>Union territory] shall lapse on a dissolution of the Assembly.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Assent to Bills.-- When a Bill has been passed by the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory], it shall be presented  to the Administrator and the Administrator shall declare either that  he assents to the Bill or that he withholds assent therefrom or that  he reserves the Bill for the consideration of the President:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Administrator may, as soon as possible after  the presentation of the Bill to him for assent, return the Bill if it  is not a Money Bill together with a message requesting that the</p>
                  <p>Assembly will reconsider the Bill or any specified provisions thereof,</p>
                  <p>and, in particular, will consider the desirability of introducing any  such amendments as he may recommend in his message and, when a Bill is  so returned, the Assembly will reconsider the Bill accordingly, and if  the Bill is passed again with or without amendment and presented to  the Administrator for assent, the Administrator shall declare either  that he assents to the Bill or that he reserves the Bill for the  consideration of the President:</p>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided further that the Administrator shall not assent to, but  shall reserve for the consideration of the President, any Bill which,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>in the opinion of the Administrator would, if it became  law, so derogate from the powers of the High Court as  to endanger the position which that Court is, by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>Constitution, designed to fill; or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list7.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>relates to any of the matters specified in clause (1) of  article 31A; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list7.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the President may, by order, direct to be reserved for  his consideration; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list7.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>relates to matters referred to in sub- section (5) or  section 7 or section 17 or section 34 or sub- section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-25.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of section 45 or in entry 1 or entry 2 of the State</p>
                  <p>List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution:</p>
                  <p>Provided also that without prejudice to the provisions of the  second proviso, the Administrator shall not assent to, but shall  reserve for the consideration of the President, any Bill which has  been passed by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of</p>
                  <p>Mizoram and which relates to any area comprised in any autonomous  district in that Union territory under the Sixth Schedule to the</p>
                  <p>Constitution.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 25A, a</p>
                  <p>Bill shall be deemed to be a Money Bill if it contains only provisions  dealing with all or any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) of  section 23 or any matter incidental to any of those matters and, in  either case, there is endorsed thereon the certificate of the Speaker  of the Legislative Assembly signed by him that it is a Money Bill.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25A">
              <num>25A.</num>
              <heading>Bills reserved for consideration.-- When a Bill is reserved  by an Administrator for the consideration of the President, the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>President shall declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he  withholds assent therefrom:</p>
                  <p>Provided that where the Bill is not a Money Bill, the President  may direct the Administrator to return the Bill to the Legislative</p>
                  <p>Assembly together with such a message as is mentioned in the first  proviso to section 25 and, when a Bill is so returned, the Assembly  shall reconsider it accordingly within a period of six months from the  date of receipt of such message and, if it is again passed by the</p>
                  <p>Assembly with or without amendment, it shall be presented again to the</p>
                  <p>President for his consideration.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Requirements as to sanction and recommendations to be  regarded as matters of procedure only.-- No Act of the Legislative</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Assembly of  the Union territory] no provision in any such Act,</p>
                  <p>shall be invalid by reason only that some previous sanction or  recommendation required by this Act was not given, if assent to that</p>
                  <p>Act was given  by the Administrator, or, on being reserved by the</p>
                  <p>Administrator for the consideration of the President, by the</p>
                  <p>President].</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Annual financial statement.--</heading>
              <subsection id="section-27.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Administrator of each</p>
                  <p>Union territory shall in respect of every financial year cause to be  laid before the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory, with the  previous approval of the President, a statement of the estimated  receipts and expenditure of the Union territory for that year, in this</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <part id="part-referred">
              <num>referred</num>
              <heading>to as the" annual financial statement".</heading>
              <subsection id="part-referred.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="part-referred.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The estimates of expenditure embodied in the annual financial  statement shall show separately--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-referred.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the sums required to meet expenditure described by this</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="part-referred.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Act as expenditure charged upon the Consolidated Fund  of the Union territory, and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-referred.2.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the sums required to meet other expenditure proposed to  be made from the Consolidated Fund of the Union  territory;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>and shall distinguish expenditure on revenue account from other  expenditure.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-referred.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The following expenditure shall be expenditure charged on the</p>
                  <blockList id="part-referred.3.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Consolidated Fund of each Union territory:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the emoluments and allowances of the Administrator and  other expenditure relating to his office as determined  by the President by general or special order;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the charges payable in respect of loans advanced to the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="part-referred.3.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Union territory from the Consolidated Fund of India  including interest, sinking fund charges and redemption  charges, and other expenditure connected therewith;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list4.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the salaries and allowances of the Speaker and the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="part-referred.3.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list6.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>expenditure in respect of the salaries and allowances of  a Judicial Commissioner;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list6.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>any sums required to satisfy any judgment, decree or  award of any court or arbitral tribunal;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list6.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>expenditure incurred by the Administrator in the  discharge of his special responsibility;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-referred.3.list6.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>any other expenditure declared by the Constitution or by  law made by Parliament or by the Legislative Assembly  of the Union territory to be so charged.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Procedure in Legislative Assembly with respect to  estimates.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-28.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>So much of the estimates as relates to expenditure  charged upon the Consolidated Fund of  the Union territory] shall  not be submitted to the vote of the Legislative Assembly of  the</p>
                    <p>Union territory], but nothing in this sub- section shall be construed  as preventing the discussion in the Legislative Assembly of any of  those estimates.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>So much of the said estimates as relates to other expenditure  shall be submitted in the form of demands for grants to the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly, and the Legislative Assembly shall have power to  assent, or to refuse to assent, to any demand, or to assent to any  demand subject to a reduction of the amount specified therein.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No demand for a grant shall be made except on the  recommendation of the Administrator.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Appropriation Bills.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-29.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As soon as may be after the grants  under section 28 have been made by the Assembly, there shall be  introduced a Bill to provide for the appropriation out of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-29.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Consolidated Fund of the Union territory of all moneys required to  meet--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-29.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the grants so made by the Assembly, and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-29.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Union territory but not exceeding in any case the  amount shown in the statement previously laid before  the Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-29.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No amendment shall be proposed to any such Bill in the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly which will have the effect of varying the amount  or altering the destination of any grant so made or of varying the  amount of any expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory and the decision of the person presiding as to whether  an amendment is inadmissible under this sub- section shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-29.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, no money shall  be withdrawn from the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory except  under appropriation made by law passed in accordance with the  provisions of this section.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Supplementary, additional or excess grants.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-30.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The</p>
                    <blockList id="section-30.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Administrator shall--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-30.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if the amount authorised by any law made in accordance  with the provisions of section 29 to be expended for a  particular service for the current financial year is  found to be insufficient for the purposes of that year  or when a need has arisen during the current financial  year for supplementary or additional expenditure upon  some new service not contemplated in the annual  financial statement for that year, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-30.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if any money has been spent on any service during a  financial year in excess of the amount granted for that  service and for that year,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>cause to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the Union  territory, with the previous approval of the President, another  statement showing the estimated amount of that expenditure or cause to  be presented to the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory with  such previous approval a demand for such excess, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-30.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sections 27, 28 and 29 shall have effect in  relation to any such statement and expenditure or demand and also to  any law to be made authorising the appropriation of moneys out of the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of the Union territory to meet such expenditure or  the grant in respect of such demand as they have effect in relation to  the annual financial statement and the expenditure mentioned therein  or to a demand for a grant and the law to be made for the  authorisation of appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund  of the Union territory to meet such expenditure or grant.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Votes on account.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-31.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything in the  foregoing provisions of this Part, the Legislative Assembly of  the</p>
                    <p>Union territory] shall have power to make any grant in advance in  respect of the estimated expenditure</p>
                    <p>for a part of any financial year pending the completion of the  procedure prescribed in section 28 for the voting of such grant and  the passing of the law in accordance with the provisions of section 29  in relation to that expenditure and the Legislative Assembly shall  have power to authorise by law the withdrawal of moneys from the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of the Union territory for the purposes for which  the said grant is made.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-31.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sections 28 and 29 shall have effect in  relation to the making of any grant under sub- section (1) or to any  law to be made under that sub- section as they have effect in relation  to the making of a grant with regard to any expenditure mentioned in  the annual financial statement and the law to be made for the  authorisation of appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund  of the Union territory to meet such expenditure.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly.-- Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing  provisions of this Part, the Administrator may authorise such  expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory as he  deems necessary for a period of not more than six months beginning  with the date of the constitution of the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory, pending the sanction of such expenditure by the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Rules of procedure.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-33.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Legislative Assembly of  the  union territory] may make rules for regulating, subject to the  provisions of this Act, its procedure and the conduct of its business:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Administrator shall, after consultation with  the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly and with the approval of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-33.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>President, make rules--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>for securing the timely completion of financial  business;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>for regulating the procedure of, and the conduct of  business in, the Legislative Assembly in relation to  any financial matter or to any Bill for the  appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of  the Union territory;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>for prohibiting the discussion of, or the asking of  questions on, any matter which affects the discharge of  the functions of the Administrator in so far as he is  required by this Act to act in his discretion.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-33.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Until rules are made under sub- section (1), the rules of  procedure and standing orders with respect to the Legislative Assembly</p>
                    <p>of the State of Uttar Pradesh in force immediately before the  commencement of this Act in  the Union territory] shall have effect  in relation to the Legislative Assembly of that Union territory  subject to such modifications and adaptations as may be made therein  by the Administrator.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Official language or languages of Union territory and  language or languages to be used in Legislative Assembly thereof.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-34.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] may by law adopt  any one or more of the languages in use in the Union territory or</p>
                    <p>Hindi as the official language or languages to be used for all or any  of the official purposes of the Union territory:</p>
                    <p>Provided that so long as the Legislative Assembly of the Union  territory of Pondicherry does not decide otherwise, the French  language shall continue to be used as an official language of that</p>
                    <p>Union territory for the same official purposes for which it was being  used in that territory immediately before the commencement of this</p>
                    <p>Act:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-34.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided further that the President may be order direct--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list6.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>that the official language of the Union shall be adopted  for such of the official purposes of the Union  territory as may be specified in the order;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list6.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>that any other language shall also be adopted  throughout the Union territory or such part thereof for  such of the official purposes of the Union territory as  may be specified in the order, if the President is  satisfied that a substantial proportion of the  population of the Union territory desires the use of  that other language for all or any of such purposes.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The business in the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] shall be transacted in the official language or languages  of the Union territory or in Hindi or in English:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly or person  acting as such, as the case may be, may permit any member who</p>
                    <p>cannot adequately express himself in any of the languages aforesaid to  address the Assembly in his mother- tongue.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Language to be used for Acts, Bills, etc.-- Notwithstanding  anything contained in section 34, until Parliament by law otherwise  provides, the authoritative texts--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>of all Bills to be introduced or amendments thereto to  be moved in the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory],</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>of all Acts passed by the Legislative Assembly of  the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Union territory], and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>of all orders, rules, regulations and bye- laws issued  under any law made by the Legislative Assembly of    the Union territory],</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be in the English language:</p>
                    <p>Provided that where the Legislative Assembly of  the Union  territory] has prescribed any language other than the English language  for use in Bills introduced in, or Acts passed by, the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly of the Union territory or in any order, rule, regulation or  bye- law issued under any law made by the Legislative Assembly of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory, a translation of the same in the English language  published under the authority of the Administrator in the Official</p>
                    <p>Gazette shall be deemed to be the authoritative text thereof in the</p>
                    <p>English language.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Restriction on discussion in the Legislative Assembly.-- No  discussion shall take place in the Legislative Assembly of  the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Union territory] with respect to the conduct of any Judicial</p>
                    <p>Commissioner or of any judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court  in the discharge of his duties.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Courts not to inquire into proceedings of Legislative</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Assembly.--</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-37.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The validity of any proceedings in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly of  the Union territory] shall not be called in question on  the ground of any alleged irregularity of procedure.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No officer or member of the Legislative  the Union  territory] in whom powers are vested by or under this Act for  regulating procedure or the conduct of business, or for maintaining  order in the Legislative Assembly shall be subject to the jurisdiction  of any court in respect of the exercise by him of those powers.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Definitions.-- In this Part, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-38.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-38.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" associate member" means a member associated with the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Delimitation Commission under section 42  or with the</p>
                    <p>Election Commission  under section 43A or section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43C">
                <num>43C.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-43C.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>]];</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>" Delimitation Commission" means the Delimitation</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Commission constituted under section 3 of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Delimitation Commission Act, 1962 (61 of 1962);</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.paragraph-0.list4.bb">
                        <num>(bb)</num>
                        <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  appointed by the President under article 324;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43C.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>" latest census figures" mean the census figures in    the Union territory] ascertained at the latest  census of which the finally published figures are  available;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43C.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>" parliamentary constituency" means a constituency  provided by law for the purpose of elections to the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>House of the People from  the Union territory]</p>
                    <p>including the Union territory of Delhi.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-39">
                <num>39.</num>
                <heading>Assembly constituencies.-- For the purpose of elections to  the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory], the Union  territory shall be divided into single- member assembly constituencies  in accordance with the provisions of this Part in such manner that the  population of each of the constituencies shall, so far as practicable,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>be the same throughout the Union territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-40">
                <num>40.</num>
                <heading>Representation of Pondicherry in the House of the People.--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be allotted one seat to the Union territory of Pondicherry  in the House of the People and that Union territory shall form one  parliamentary constituency.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-41">
                <num>41.</num>
                <heading>Duties of Delimitation Commission.--</heading>
                <subsection id="section-41.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-41.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>It shall be the duty  of the Delimitation Commission--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-41.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>to delimit the assembly constituencies in each Union  territory, and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-41.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>to determine, on the basis of the latest census figures,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>the number of seats to be reserved for the scheduled  castes and for the scheduled tribes in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly of  the Union territory] other than the</p>
                    <p>Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu, and the  constituencies in which these seats shall be so  reserved.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-41.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>It shall also be the duty of the Delimitation Commission--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-41.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>to readjust, on the basis of the latest census figures,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>the division of each of the Union territories of Delhi,</p>
                    <p>Himachal Pradesh, Manipur and Tripura into  parliamentary constituencies,  the number being 7, 4,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-2">
                <num>2.</num>
                <heading>and 2];</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>to determine the constituency in which the seat shall be  reserved for the scheduled castes or for the scheduled  tribes, as the case may be; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>to divide the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu into  two single- member parliamentary constituencies.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-42">
                <num>42.</num>
                <heading>Associate members.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-42.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the purpose of assisting the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-42.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Delimitation Commission in its duties, the Delimitation Commission  shall associate with itself,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in respect of the Union territory of Delhi, all the  members of the House of the People representing that</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-42.1.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Union territory;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.1.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in respect of each of the Union territories of Himachal</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Pradesh, Manipur and Tripura, all the members of the</p>
                    <p>House of the People representing that Union territory  and three members of the Legislative Assembly of that</p>
                    <p>Union territory to be nominated by the Speaker of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-42.1.list9">
                      <listIntroduction>Assembly from among the members thereof;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.1.list9.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>in respect of the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-42.1.list11">
                      <listIntroduction>the two members of the House of the People representing  that Union territory;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.1.list11.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>in respect of the Union territory of Pondicherry, three  members of the Legislative Assembly of that Union  territory to be nominated by the Speaker of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Assembly from among the members thereof.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The nomination of members of the several Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assemblies under sub- section (1) shall be made by the respective</p>
                    <p>Speakers thereof as soon as practicable and shall be communicated to  the Delimitation Commission.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If owing to death or resignation the office of an associate  member falls vacant, it shall be filled as soon as practicable under  and in accordance with the foregoing provisions of this section.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-42.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>None of the associate members shall have the right to vote or  to sign any decision of the Delimitation Commission.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43">
                <num>43.</num>
                <heading>Procedure as to delimitation.-- The provisions of sections 7,</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-9">
                <num>9.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, 10 and 11 of the Delimitation Commission Act, 1962 (61 of 1962),</p>
                    <p>shall apply, as far as may be, in relation to the delimitation of  parliamentary and assembly constituencies under this Part as they  apply in relation to the delimitation of parliamentary and assembly  constituencies under that Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43A">
                <num>43A.</num>
                <heading>Special provision for delimitation of constituencies of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-43A.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Mizoram Legislative Assembly.--</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-43A.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sections 39 to</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43">
                <num>43.</num>
                <heading>(both inclusive) shall not apply to the delimitation of  constituencies for the purpose of elections to the Legislative</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Assembly of the Union territory of Mizoram.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-43.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Election Commission shall, in the manner herein provided,</p>
                    <p>distribute the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of the Union  territory of Mizoram under sub- section (2) of section 3 to single  member assembly constituencies and delimit them on the basis of the  latest census figures having regard to the provisions of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-43.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Constitution and to the following provisions:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43.2.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be  geographically compact areas;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43.2.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in delimiting the constituencies, regard shall be had to  physical features, existing boundaries of  administrative units, facilities of communication and  public convenience.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>For the purpose of assisting in the performance of its  functions under sub- section (2), the Election Commission shall  associate with itself as associate members--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all the persons who, having been elected to the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the State of Assam from the</p>
                    <p>Lungleh, Aijal East and Aijal West territorial  constituencies, are members of that Assembly  immediately before the day appointed under clause (b)</p>
                    <blockList id="section-43.3.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>of section 2 of the North- Eastern Areas</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43.3.list5.Reorganisation">
                        <num>(Reorganisation)</num>
                        <p>Act, 1971 (81 of 1971); and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43.3.list5.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>such three elected members of the District Council of  the Mizo District as the Chairman thereof may nominate:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to  vote or sign any decision of the Election Commission.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If, owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate  member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance  with the provisions of sub- section (3).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43.5.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43.5.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>publish its proposals for the delimitation of  constituencies, together with the dissenting proposals,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>if any, of any associate member who desires publication  thereof in the Official Gazette and in such other  manner as the Commission</p>
                    <blockList id="section-43.5.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>may consider fit, together with a notice inviting  objections and suggestions in relation to the proposals  and specifying a date on or after which the proposals  will be further considered by it;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43.5.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have  been received by it before the date so specified;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43.5.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>after consideration of objections and suggestions which  may have been received by it before the date so  specified, determine by one or more orders the  delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or  orders to be published in the Official Gazette; and  upon such publication, the order or orders shall have  the full force of law and shall not be called in  question in any court.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43.6.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43.6.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>correct any printing mistake in any order made under  sub- section (5) or any error arising therein from  inadvertent slip or omission;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43.6.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division  mentioned in any such order or orders are or is  altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be  necessary or expedient for bringing such order up- to-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>date.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.7">
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under sub- section (5) and every notification  issued under sub- section (6) shall be laid as soon as may be after it  is made or issued before the Legislative Assembly of the Union  territory of Mizoram.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.8">
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement  of this Act in the Union territory of Mizoram with a view to  delimiting the territorial constituencies of that Union territory for  purposes of elections to the Legislative Assembly of that Union  territory shall, in so far as they are in conformity with the  foregoing provisions of this section, be deemed to have been done or  taken under those provisions as if those provisions were in force at  the time such things were done or such steps were taken.]</p>
                    <p>Representation of Arunachal Pradesh in the House of the people.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43B">
                <num>43B.</num>
                <heading>Representation of Arunachal Pradesh in the House of the  people. In the House of the People to be constituted after the general  election to that House to be held after the commencement of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-43B.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government of Union Territories (Amendment) Act, 1975 (29 of 1975)</p>
                    <p>and thereafter, there shall be allotted two seats to the Union  territory of Arunachal Pradesh and the First Schedule to the</p>
                    <p>Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950) shall be deemed  to have been amended accordingly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43C">
                <num>43C.</num>
                <heading>Special provisions for delimitation of parliamentary  constituencies in Arunachal Pradesh and constituencies of Arunachal</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-43C.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Pradesh Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-43C.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sections 39 to 43</p>
                    <p>(both inclusive) shall not apply to the delimitation of parliamentary  constituencies in the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh or to the  delimitation of constituencies for the purpose of elections to the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of that Union territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Election Commission shall divide the Union territory of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh into two single- member parliamentary constituencies  on the basis of the latest census figures.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall also, in the manner herein  provided, distribute the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh under sub- section (2) of  section 3 to single- member assembly constituencies and delimit them on  the basis of the latest census figures having regard to the following  provisions:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be  geographically compact areas;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43C.3.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>every assembly constituency shall be so delimited as to  fall only within one parliamentary constituency;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43C.3.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>in delimiting the constituencies, regard shall be had to  physical features, existing boundaries of  administrative units facilities of communication and  public convenience.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>For the purpose of assisting in the performance of its  functions under sub- sections (2) and (3), the Election Commission  shall associate with itself as associate members--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the member of the House of the People representing the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.4.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.4.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>such five members of the Legislative Assembly of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh as the Speaker of</p>
                    <p>that Assembly shall, having regard to the composition  of the Legislative Assembly, nominate:</p>
                    <p>Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to  vote or sign any decision of the Election Commission.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate  member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance  with the provisions of sub- section (4).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.6.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.6.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>publish its proposals for the delimitation of  constituencies together with the dissenting proposals,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.6.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>if any, of any associate member who desires publication  thereof in the Official Gazette and in such other  manner as the Commission may consider fit, together  with a notice inviting objections and suggestions in  relation to the proposals and specifying a date on or  after which the proposals will be further considered by  it;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.6.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have  been received by it before the date so specified;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43C.6.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>after consideration of objections and suggestions which  may have been received by it before the date so  specified, determine by one or more orders the  delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or  orders to be published in the Official Gazette; and  upon such publication, the order or orders shall have  the full force of law and shall not be called in  question in any court.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.7">
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43C.7.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43C.7.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>correct any printing mistake in any order made under  sub- section (6) or any error arising therein from  inadvertent slip or omission;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-43C.7.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division  mentioned in any such order or orders are or is  altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be  necessary or expedient for bringing such order up- to-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>date.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.8">
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under sub- section (6) and every notification  issued under sub- section (7) shall be laid as soon as may be after</p>
                    <p>it is made or issued before the House of the People and the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43C.9">
                  <num>(9)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement  of this Act in the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh with a view to  delimiting the territorial constituencies of that Union territory for  purposes of elections to the Legislative Assembly of that Union  territory shall, in so far as they are in conformity with the  foregoing provisions of this section, be deemed to have been done or  taken under those provisions as if these provisions were in force at  the time such things were done or such steps were taken.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43D">
                <num>43D.</num>
                <heading>Special provision for determination of constituencies in  the Legislative Assembly of Goa, Daman and Diu for Scheduled Castes  and Scheduled Tribes.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-43D.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43D.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall determine on  the basis of the latest census figures--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43D.1.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the number of seats to be reserved for the Scheduled</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Castes and for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly of the Union territory of Goa, Daman and</p>
                    <p>Diu (hereafter in this section referred to as the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-43D.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly) having regard to the provisions  of sub- section (5) of section 3; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43D.1.list6.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the constituencies in which those seats shall be so  reserved having regard to the provisions of clause (c),</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>or, as the case may be, clause (d), of sub- section (1)</p>
                    <p>of section 9 of the Delimitation Act and without  altering the extent of any constituency as delimited by  the Delimitation Commission.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43D.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-43D.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-43D.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>publish its proposals for the determination of the  constituencies in which seats shall be reserved for the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/scheduled"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Castes or for the Scheduled Tribes, as the  case may be, in the Gazette of India and in the"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10/scheduled"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10/scheduled"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/20/eng@1963-05-10"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <heading>Official Gazette of the Union territory of Goa, Daman  and Diu and also in such other manner as the Election</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduled.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Commission may consider fit, together with a notice  inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the  proposals and specifying a date on or after which the  proposals will be further considered by it;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have  been received by it before the date so specified;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>after consideration of objections and suggestions which  may have been received by it before the date so  specified, determine by one or more orders the number  of seats to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes or for  the Scheduled Tribes, as the case may be, in the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Legislative Assembly and the constituencies in which  those seats shall be so reserved and cause such order  or orders to be published in the Gazette of India and  in the Official Gazette of the Union territory of Goa,</p>
                <p>Daman and Diu; and upon such publication in the Gazette  of India, the order or orders shall have the full force  of law and shall not be called in question in any court  and the Second Schedule to the Representation of the</p>
                <p>People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950) and the order made by  the Delimitation Commission under section 9 of the</p>
                <p>Delimitation Act in relation to the Legislative</p>
                <p>Assembly shall be deemed to have been amended  accordingly.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="scheduled.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (4), the re-</p>
                <p>adjustment of representation of any territorial constituencies in the</p>
                <p>Legislative Assembly necessitated by any order made by the Election</p>
                <p>Commission under this section, shall apply in relation to every  election to the Legislative Assembly held after the publication in the</p>
                <p>Gazette of India, under sub- section (2), of such order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduled.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing contained in the foregoing sub- sections shall affect  the representation in the Legislative Assembly existing on the date of  publication in the Gazette of India, under sub- section (2), of any  order made by the Election Commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduled.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.5.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  notification in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazette of  the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.5.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>correct any printing mistake in any order made under  sub- section (2) or any error arising therein from  inadvertent slip or omission;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.5.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division  mentioned in any such order are, or is, altered, make  such amendments as appear to it to be necessary or  expedient for bringing such order up- to- date.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduled.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every order made under sub- section (2) and every notification  issued under sub- section (5) shall be laid, as soon as may be, after  it is made or issued before the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                <blockList id="scheduled.6.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- In this section,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.6.list2.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>" Delimitation Act" means the Delimitation Act, 1972 (76   of 1972);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.6.list2.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>" Delimitation Commission" means the Delimitation</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Commission constituted under section 3 of the</p>
                <p>Delimitation Act.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-43E">
              <num>43E.</num>
              <heading>Special provisions as to readjustment of territorial  constituencies. Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 38 to</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43D">
              <num>43D.</num>
              <heading>(both inclusive), until the relevant figures for the first census  taken after the year 2000 have been published, it shall not be  necessary to readjust the division of each Union territory into  territorial constituencies and any reference to the" latest census  figures" in this Part shall be construed as a reference to the 1971  census figures.]</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-43D.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>COUNCIL OF MINISTERS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <part id="part-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>COUNCIL OF MINISTERS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-44">
                <num>44.</num>
                <heading>Council of Ministers.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-44.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be a Council of</p>
                    <p>Ministers in each Union territory with the Chief Minister at the head  to aid and advise the Administrator in the exercise of his functions  in relation to matters with respect to which the Legislative Assembly  of the Union territory has power to make laws except in so far as he  is required by or under this Act to act in his discretion or by or  under any law to exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial functions:</p>
                    <p>Provided that, in case of difference of opinion between the</p>
                    <p>Administrator and his Ministers on any matter, the Administrator shall  refer it to the President for decision and act according to the  decision given thereon by the President, and pending such decision it  shall be competent for the Administrator in any case where the matter  is in his opinion so urgent that it is necessary for him to take  immediate action, to take such action or to give such direction in the  matter as he deems necessary:</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If and in so far as any special responsibility of the</p>
                    <p>Administrator is involved under this Act, he shall, in the exercise of  his functions, act in his discretion.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not  a matter as respects which the Administrator is by or under this Act  required to act in his discretion, the decision of the Administrator  thereon shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not  a matter as respects which the Administrator is required by any law to  exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial functions, the decision of the</p>
                    <p>Administrator thereon shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The question whether any, and if so what, advice was tendered  by Ministers to the Administrator shall not be inquired into in any  court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-45">
                <num>45.</num>
                <heading>Other provisions as to Ministers.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-45.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Chief Minister  shall be appointed by the President and the other Ministers shall be  appointed by the President on the advice of the Chief Ministers.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the</p>
                    <p>President.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Council of Ministers shall be collectively responsible to  the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Before a Minister enters upon his office, the Administrator  shall administer to him the oaths of office and of secrecy according  to the forms set out for the purpose in the First Schedule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Minister who for any period of six consecutive months is  not a member of the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory shall  at the expiration of that period cease to be a Minister.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-45.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The salaries and allowances of Ministers shall be such as the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory may from time to time by  law determine, and until the Legislative Assembly so determines, shall  be determined by the Administrator with the approval of the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-46">
                <num>46.</num>
                <heading>Conduct of business.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-46.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-46.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The President shall make rules--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-46.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>for the allocation of business to the Ministers; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-46.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>for the more convenient transaction of business with the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Ministers including the procedure to be adopted in the  case of a difference of opinion between the</p>
                    <p>Administrator and the Council of Ministers or a</p>
                    <p>Minister.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all executive action  of the Administrator, whether taken on the advice of his Ministers or  otherwise, shall be expressed to be taken in the name of the</p>
                    <p>Administrator.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Orders and other instruments made and executed in the name of  the Administrator, shall be authenticated in such manner as may be  specified in rules to be made by the Administrator, and the validity  of an order or instrument which is so authenticated shall not be  called in question on the ground that it is not an order or instrument  made or executed by the Administrator.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-47">
                <num>47.</num>
                <heading>Consolidated Fund of the Union territory.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-47.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As from such  date  as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                    <p>Gazette, appoint in this behalf, all revenues received in  the Union  territory] by the Government of India or the Administrator of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory in relation to any matter with respect to which the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory has power to make laws,</p>
                    <p>and all grants made and all loans advanced to the Union territory  from the Consolidated Fund of India and all moneys received by the</p>
                    <p>Union territory in repayment of loans shall form one Consolidated Fund  to be entitled" the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory".</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of  the Union  territory] shall be appropriated except in accordance with, and for  the purposes and in the manner provided in, this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The custody of the Consolidated Fund of  the Union  territory], the payment of moneys into such Fund, the withdrawal of  moneys therefrom and all other matters connected with or ancillary to  those matters shall be regulated by rules made by the Administrator  with the approval of the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>Contingency Fund of the Union territory.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-48.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be  established a Contingency Fund in the nature of an imprest to be  entitled" the Contingency Fund of the Union territory" into which  shall be paid from and out of the Consolidated Fund of the Union  territory such sums as may, from time to time, be determined by law  made by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory; and the said</p>
                    <p>Fund shall be held by the Administrator to enable advances to be made  by him out of such Fund.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-48.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No advances shall be made out of the Contingency Fund of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory except for the purposes of meeting unforeseen  expenditure pending authorisation of such expenditure by the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory under appropriations made  by law.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-48.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Administrator may make rules regulating all matters  connected with or ancillary to the custody of, the payment of moneys  into, and the withdrawal of moneys from, the Contingency Fund of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-49">
                <num>49.</num>
                <heading>Audit reports. The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>General of India relating to the accounts of  the Union territory]</p>
                    <p>for any period subsequent to the date referred to in sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-49.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>of section 47 shall be submitted to the Administrator who shall cause  them to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the Union  territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-50">
                <num>50.</num>
                <heading>Relation of Administrator and his Ministers to President.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything in this Act, the Administrator and his</p>
                    <p>Council of Ministers shall be under the general control of, and comply  with such particular directions, if any, as may from time to time be  given by, the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Provision in case of failure of constitutional machinery. If  the President, on receipt of a report from the Administrator of  the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Union territory] or otherwise, is satisfied,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>that a situation has arisen in which the administration  of the Union territory cannot be carried on in  accordance with the provisions of this Act, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>that for the proper administration of the Union  territory it is necessary or expedient so to do,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>the President may, by order, suspend the operation of all or any of  the provisions of this Act for such period as he thinks fit and make  such incidental and consequential provisions as may appear to him to  be necessary or expedient for administering the Union territory in  accordance with the provisions of article 239.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading>Authorisation of expenditure by President. Where the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of  the Union territory] is dissolved, or its  functioning as such Assembly remains suspended, on account of an order  under section 51, it shall be competent for the President to authorise  when the House of the People is not in session expenditure from the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of that Union territory pending the sanction of such  expenditure by Parliament.]</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-53">
                <num>53.</num>
                <heading>Provisions for election to Parliament from Goa, Daman and</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Diu, and Pondicherry.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-53.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-53.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>As soon as practicable after the  commencement of this Act, elections shall be held in accordance with  law--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-53.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>to fill the seats in the House of the People allotted to  the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-53.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>to fill the seat in the House of the People and the seat  in the Council of States allotted to the Union  territory of Pondicherry.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-53.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the  time being in force, the members nominated to represent the Union  territory of Goa, Daman and Diu in the House of the People shall  continue to be such until the election of the members to fill the two  seats in that House allotted to that Union territory:</p>
                    <p>Provided that where the dates of election of the members are  different, the members so nominated shall cease to be members of that</p>
                    <p>House on the earlier of those two dates.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression" date of  election" has the same meaning as in section 67A of the Representation  of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-54">
                <num>54.</num>
                <heading>Transitional provisions for administration of justice in  certain areas in the Union territory of Mizoram. On and from the  commencement of this Act in the Union territory of Mizoram and until  other provisions in this behalf are made by a competent Legislature or  other competent authority, the administration of justice in those  areas of that Union territory which are not comprised in any  autonomous district under the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution shall  be carried on, so far as may be, in accordance with the provisions of  paragraphs 4 and 5 of that Schedule, as if those areas were comprised  in an autonomous district under that Schedule and the provisions of  the said paragraphs were in force in those areas and for this  purpose,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-54.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>all powers and functions of a District Council under the  provisions of the said paragraph 4 shall be exercised  and discharged by the Administrator or any officer  appointed by him in this behalf;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the said paragraph 5 shall have effect as if references  to the District Council, the Regional Council and the  courts constituted by the District Council, by whatever  form of words, had been omitted therefrom; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>references to Governor in the said paragraphs 4 and 5  shall be construed as references to the Administrator.]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-54A">
                <num>54A.</num>
                <heading>Provision as to provisional Legislative Assembly of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-54A.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-54A.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act</p>
                    <p>(including provisions relating to the strength of the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh), until the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh has  been duly constituted and summoned to meet for the first session under  and in accordance with the provisions of this Act, there shall be a  provisional Legislative Assembly which shall consist of members, being  those persons referred to in clauses (b), (c) and (d) of section 3 of  the North- East Frontier Agency (Administration) Supplementary</p>
                    <p>Regulation, 1971 (4 of 1971) and who are functioning, immediately  before the commencement of this Act in the Union territory of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh, as members of the Pradesh Council constituted under  the said section 3.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-54A.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The term of office of the members of the provisional</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly shall expire immediately before the first meeting  of the Legislative Assembly duly constituted after the first general  election to that Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-54A.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisional Legislative Assembly constituted under this  section shall, for so long as it is in existence, be deemed to be the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly duly constituted under this Act and accordingly  the other provisions of this Act, so far as may be, apply in relation  to the provisional Legislative Assembly as they apply in relation to  the Legislative Assembly.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-55">
                <num>55.</num>
                <heading>Contracts and suits. For the removal of doubts it is hereby  declared that--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-55.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-55.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all contracts in connection with the administration of    the Union territory] are contracts made in the  exercise of the executive power of the Union;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-55.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>all suits and proceedings in connection with the  administration of  the Union territory] shall be  instituted by or against the Government of India.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-56">
                <num>56.</num>
                <heading>Power of President to remove difficulties. If any difficulty  arises in relation to the transition from the provisions of any of the  laws repealed by this Act or in giving effect to the provisions of  this Act and, in particular, in relation to the constitution of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly for  the Union territory], the President may by  order do anything not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act  which appear to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of  removing the difficulty.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-57">
                <num>57.</num>
                <heading>Amendment to certain- enactments.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-57.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-57.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The enactments specified  in the Second Schedule--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-57.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>shall, together with all rules, notifications and orders  made or issued thereunder, extend to and come into  force in the Union territories of Goa, Daman and Diu,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-57.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>and Pondicherry; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-57.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>shall be subject to the amendments mentioned in the  fourth column of the said Schedule.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-57.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement  of this Act in connection with the preparation or revision of  electoral rolls for the purpose of elections to the House of the</p>
                    <p>People from the Union territories of Goa, Daman and Diu, and</p>
                    <p>Pondicherry, and to the Legislative Assemblies of those Union  territories shall, in so far as they are in conformity with the  provisions of the Represen-</p>
                    <p>tation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950), as amended by this Act,</p>
                    <p>be deemed to have been done in accordance with law.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-58">
                <num>58.</num>
                <heading>Repeal and savings.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-58.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-58.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The following laws are hereby  repealed:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-58.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the Territorial Councils Act, 1956 (103 of 1956);</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-58.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the Decree No. 46- 2381, dated the 25th October, 1946, as  subsequently amended, relating to the Representative</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-58.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Assembly of the State of Pondicherry;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-58.1.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the Decree No. 47- 1490, dated the 12th August, 1947, as  subsequently amended, relating to the setting up of a</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-58.1.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Council of Government in the State of Pondicherry;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-58.1.list5.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the State of Pondicherry (Representation of the People)</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Order, 1955, in so far as it relates to the</p>
                    <p>Representative Assembly of Pondicherry.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-58.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Territorial Councils Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1956">
                <num>1956.</num>
                <heading>(103 of 1956),--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>every officer and other employee of the Territorial</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Council of  the Union territory] serving under the</p>
                    <p>Council immediately before such repeal shall become an  officer or other employee of Government and shall be  employed in connection with the administration of the</p>
                    <p>Union territory with such designation as the</p>
                    <p>Administrator may determine and shall hold office by  the same tenure and at the same remuneration and on the  same terms and conditions of service as he would have  but for such repeal held the same and shall continue to  do so unless and until such tenure, remuneration and  terms and conditions are duly altered by the</p>
                    <p>Administrator:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the tenure, remuneration and terms and  conditions of service of any such officer or other  employee shall not be altered to his disadvantage  without the previous sanction of the Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list9">
                      <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list9.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>any service rendered by any such officer  or other employee before such repeal shall be  deemed to be service rendered in connection with  the administration of the Union territory;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list9.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>the Administrator may employ any such  officer or other employee in the discharge of such  functions as the Administrator may think proper  and every such officer or other employee shall  discharge those functions accordingly;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list9.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>anything done or any action taken (including any  notification, order, scheme, rule, form, notice or bye-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>law made or issued, any licence or permission granted)</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list12">
                      <listIntroduction>under the repealed Act shall in so far as it is not  inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, continue  in force unless and until it is superseded by anything  done or any action taken in accordance with law;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list12.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all  contracts entered into and all matters and things  engaged to be done by, with or for the Territorial</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list14">
                      <listIntroduction>Council before such repeal shall be deemed to have been  incurred, entered into or engaged to be done in  exercise of the executive power of the Union for the  purposes of the administration of the Union territory;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list14.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>all assessments, valuations, measurements or divisions  made by the Territorial Council shall, in so far as  they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list16">
                      <listIntroduction>Act, continue in force unless and until they are  superseded by any assessment, valuation, measurement or  division made by the Administrator in accordance with  law;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list16.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>all properties, movable and immovable, and all interests  of whatsoever nature and kind, vested in the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Territorial Council immediately before such repeal  shall, with all rights of whatsoever description, used,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list19">
                      <listIntroduction>enjoyed or possessed by that Council, vest in the Union  for the purposes of the administration of the Union  territory;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list19.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>all rates, taxes, cesses, fees, rents, fares and other  charges which immediately before such repeal were being  lawfully levied by the Territorial Council shall  continue to be levied at the same rate at which they  were being levied by the Council immediately before  such repeal until provision to the contrary is made by  law;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list19.g">
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <p>all rates, taxes, cesses, fees, rents, fares and other  charges due to the Territorial Council immediately  before such repeal shall be deemed to be due to the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Union in connection with the administration of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list22">
                      <listIntroduction>Union territory;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list22.h">
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <p>all suits, prosecutions and other legal proceedings  instituted or which might have been instituted by or  against the Territorial Council may be continued or  instituted by or against the Government of India.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
