<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1914/9/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1914/9"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Local Authorities Loans Act, 1914"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1914/9/eng@1914-02-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1914/9/eng@1914-02-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1914-02-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1914/9/eng@1914-02-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1914/9/eng@1914-02-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Local Authorities Loans Act, 1914</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 9 OF 1914  PREAMBLE.</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 28th February, 1914.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the grant of loans  to Local Authorities.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating  to the borrowing powers of local authorities; It is hereby enacted as  follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Local</p>
            <p>Authorities Loans Act, 1914.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States.]</heading>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.- In this Act," local authority" means any person  legally entitled to the control or management of any local or  municipal fund, or legally entitled to impose any cess, rate, duty or  tax within any local area;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>" funds", used with reference to any local authority, includes any  local or municipal fund to the control or management of which such  authority is legally entitled, and any cess, rate, duty or tax which  such authority is legally entitled to impose, and any property vested  in such authority;</p>
              <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act; and</p>
              <p>" work" includes a survey, whether incidental to any other work or  not.</p>
              <p>The Government" or" the appropriate Government" means, in  relation to cantonment authorities and in relation to port authorities  in major ports, the Central Government, and in relation to other local  authorities, the State Government.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing powers of local authorities.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A local authority  may, subject to the prescribed conditions, borrow on the security of  its funds or any portion thereof for any of the following purposes,</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the carrying out of any works which it is legally  authorized to carry out.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the giving of relief and the establishment and  maintenance of relief works in times of famine or  scarcity,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the prevention of the outbreak or spread of any  dangerous epidemic disease.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>any measures which may be connected with or ancillary  to any purposes specified in clauses (ii) and (iii),</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the repayment of money previously borrowed in accordance  with law:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that nothing in clause (v) shall be deemed to empower a  local authority to fix a period for the repayment of any money  borrowed thereunder which, when the period fixed for the repayment of  the money previously borrowed is taken into account, will exceed the  maximum period fixed for the repayment of a loan by or under any  enactment for the time being in force:</p>
              <p>Provided further that, in the case of loans other than loans  made by the  appropriate Government], no amount exceeding twenty-</p>
              <p>five lakhs of rupees shall be borrowed unless the terms, including the  date of flotation, of such loan have been approved by the    appropriate Government].]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorize any  local authority--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to borrow or spend money for any purpose for which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>under the law for the time being in force, it is not  authorized to apply its funds, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to borrow money by means of the issue of bills or  promissory notes payable within any period not  exceeding twelve months.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to Government to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  appropriate</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Government] may make  rules consistent with this Act as to--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the nature of the funds on the security of which money  may be borrowed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the works for which money may be borrowed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the manner of making applications for permission to  borrow money;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the inquiries to be made in relation to such loans, and  the manner of conducting such inquiries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the cases and the forms in which particulars of  applications and proceedings, and orders thereon, shall  be published;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the cases in which the  appropriate Government] may  make loans ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the cases in which local authorities may take loans  from persons other than the  appropriate</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government];]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the manner of recording and enforcing the conditions  on which money is to be borrowed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>the manner and time of making or raising loans;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>the inspection of any works carried out by means of  loans;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>the instalments, if any, by which loans shall be  repaid, the interest to be charged on loans, and the  manner and time of repaying loans and of paying the  interest thereon;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>the sum to be charged against the funds which are to  form the security for the loan, as costs in  effecting the loan;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.xiii">
                  <num>(xiii)</num>
                  <p>the attachment of such funds, and the manner of  disposing of or collecting them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.xiv">
                  <num>(xiv)</num>
                  <p>the accounts to be kept in respect of loans;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list4.xv">
                  <num>(xv)</num>
                  <p>the utilization of unexpended balances of loans either  in the reduction in any way of the debt of the local  authority, or in carrying out any works which that  authority is legally authorized to carry out; and the  sanction necessary to such utilization;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and as to all other matters incidental to carrying this Act into  effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published  in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette; and on such publication, shall have effect as if  enacted in this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Remedy by attachment if loan not repaid.- If any money borrowed  in accordance with the provisions of this Act, or any interest or  costs due in respect thereof, is or are not repaid according to the  conditions of the loan, the  appropriate Government], if itself the  lender, may, and, if the  appropriate</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government] is not the lender, shall, on the application of the  lender, attach the funds on the security of which the loan was made.</p>
              <p>After such attachment, no person, except an officer appointed in this  behalf by the  appropriate Government], shall in any way deal with  the attached funds; but such officer may do all acts in respect  thereof which the borrowers might have done if such attachment had not  taken place, and may apply the proceeds in satisfaction of the loan  and of all interests and costs due in respect thereof and of all  expenses caused by the attachment and subsequent proceedings:</p>
              <p>Attachment not to defeat prior charges legally made.-- Provided that  no such attachment shall defeat or prejudice any debt for which the  funds attached were previously pledged in accordance with law; but all  such prior charges shall be paid out of the proceeds of the funds  before any part of the proceeds is applied to the satisfaction of the  liability in respect of which such attachment is made.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Issue of short term bills.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of  section 26 of the Indian Paper Currency Act, 1910 , the local  authorities mentioned in Schedule I and any other local authority to  which the  appropriate Government] may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, extend the provisions of this section, may, with the  previous sanction of the  appropriate Government], borrow money by  means of the issue of bills or promissory notes payable within any  period, not exceeding twelve months, for any purpose for which such  local authority may lawfully borrow money under any law for the time  being in force:</p>
              <p>Provided that the amount of the bills or promissory notes which  may be so issued, shall not exceed, when the amount of the other  moneys for the time being borrowed by such local authority is taken  into account, the total amount which such local authority is empowered  by law to borrow.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  appropriate Government] may, by general or special  order, regulate the conditions on which money may be borrowed or  repaid under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Loans not to be effected except under this Act.- Except as  provided by or under this Act, no local authority shall, for any  purpose, borrow money upon, or otherwise charge, its funds; and any  contract otherwise made for that purpose after the passing of this Act  shall be void:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing herein contained shall be deemed--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to preclude any local authority from exercising the  borrowing powers conferred on it by any special  enactment now or hereafter in force; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to affect the power conferred on any local authority by  any such enactment to charge its funds, by guaranteeing  the payment of interest on money to be applied to any  purpose to which the funds of the local authority can  legally be applied.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Application of Act to loans existing previous to the fifth  of September, 1871.- The remedy mentioned in section 5 shall be  available for the recovery of any money lent by the Secretary of State  in Council to any local authority before the fifth day of September,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>eighteen hundred and seventy- one, and the interest due on such money.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Repeals.- Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), s. 2  and Sch.</heading>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
