<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Rent Control Act, 1999"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Rent Control Act, 1999</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[27th November, 2001]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 34 of 2001</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the regulation of rent and eviction of buildings, in certain areas of the State of Karnataka, and for the matters connected their with or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the fiftieth year of the Republic of India, as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Rent Act, 1999.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Karnataka.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force from such date as the State Government may, bynotification, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different areas or for different provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Application of the Act.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Chapters-I to III and Chapter-V to VIII of this Act shall apply to areas specified in the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Chapters I, and IV shall apply only to areas specified in the Second Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.3.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>to any premises belonging to,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.3.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the State Government or the Central Government or a local authority;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.3.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>a Muzarai or religious or charitable institution;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.3.list1.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>a Wakf.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- If any doubt arises whether any institution referred to in sub-clause (ii) and (iii) above is a muzarai or religious or charitable institution or a wakf, the decision of the Divisional Commissioner shall be final.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to any building belonging to a Co-operative Society registered or deemed to be registered under the Karnataka Co-operative Societies Act, 1959 (Karnataka Act 11 of 1959) or the Multi state Co-operative Societies Act, 1984 (Central Act 51 of 1984);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to any building belonging to a Market Committee established under the Karnataka Agricultural Produce Marketing Regulation Act, 1966 (Karnataka Act 29 of 1966);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to any tenancy or other like relationship created by a grant from the State Government or the Central Government in respect of any premises taken on lease or requisitioned by the State Government or the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.3.list3.e.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>to any premises, deemed rent on the date of commencement of this Act or the standard rent of which exceeds,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.3.list3.e.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>three thousand five hundred rupees per month in any area referred to in part A of the first schedule; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.3.list3.e.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>two thousand rupees per month in any other area.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- "Deemed rent on the date of commencement of this Act" shall be the rent calculated in the manner provided in section 7, together with revision, if any, as provided in section 9 and decreased in the case of premises constructed after the commencement of this Act at the same rate as the rate of enhancement stipulated in the third Schedule to reflect the position on the date of commencement of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>to any premises constructed or substantially renovated, either before or after the commencement of this Act for a period of fifteen years from the date of completion of such construction or substantial renovation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation-I.- A premises may be said to be substantially renovated if not less than seventy-five percent of the premises is built new in accordance with the criteria prescribed for determining the extent of renovation;</p>
              <p>Explanation-II.- ‘Date of completion of construction’ shall be the date of completion as intimated to the concerned authority or of assessment of property tax,whichever is earlier, and where the premises have been constructed in stages the</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list9">
                <listIntroduction>date on which the initial building was completed and an intimation thereof was sent to the concerned authority or was assessed to property tax, whichever is earlier.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list9.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>to any premises used for non-residential purpose but excludingpremises having a plinth area of not exceeding fourteen square meters used forcommercial purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list9.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>to any building or group of buildings or premises which the State Government may by notification exempt in public interest from all or any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may by notification apply all or any of the provisions of this Act to such other areas or class of buildings within any area from such date ordates as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may at any time by notification, direct that all or any of the provisions of the Act shall cease to be applicable to any area whether or not specified in Schedules I or II, from such date as may be specified in the notification, or to any class of buildings within any area; and from that date the said provisions shall cease to be applicable to such area or class of buildings:</p>
              <p>Provided that section 6 of the Karnataka General Clause Act, 1899 shall apply when any provision of this Act ceases to be applicable to any area or class of buildings in any area as if it had been repealed by a Karnataka Act:</p>
              <p>Provided further that the issue of a notification under sub-section (5) shall not preclude the issue of a notification under sub-section (4) applying all or any of the provisions of the said chapter to such area or class of buildings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>"building" means any building or hut or part of a building or hut other than a farm house, let or to be let separately and includes,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the garden, grounds and out-houses, if any appurtenant to such building, hut or part of such building or hut and let or to be let along with such building or hut or part of building or hut;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>any furniture or equipment supplied by the landlord for the use in such building or hut or part of a building or hut;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>any fittings affixed to such building or part of a building for the more beneficial enjoyment thereof, but does not include a room or other accommodation in a hotel or a lodging house;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Controller" means a Controller appointed under section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>"Court" means,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>in respect of the area comprised within the limits of the City of Bangalore, the Court of Small Causes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in such other area as the State Government, may, in consultation with the High Court, by notification specify, the Court of Civil Judge (Senior Division)having territorial jurisdiction over such area; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>in respect of areas other than those referred to in sub-clauses (i) and (ii), the Court of Civil judge (Junior Division) having territorial jurisdiction over such area;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"Family" in relation to a person means the wife or husband of such person and his or her dependent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"landlord" means a person who for the time being is receiving or is entitled to receive, the rent of any premises, whether on his own account or on account of or on behalf of or for the benefit of any other person or as a trustee, guardian or receiver for any other person or who would so receive the rent or to be entitled to receive the rent, if the premises were let to a tenant;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"lawful increase" means an increase in rent permitted under the provisions of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"local area in relation to the premises let" means the area of jurisdiction and surrounding area as specified in the First Schedule, of the local authority within which the premises let is situate;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>"local authority" means,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a City Municipal Corporation constituted under the Karnataka Municipal Corporations Act, 1976 (Karnataka Act 14 of 1977);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>a Municipal Council or Town Panchayat constituted under the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964 (Karnataka Act 22 of 1964) including a Contonment Board constituted under the Contonment Act, 1924 (Central Act 2 of 1924);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>an Urban Development Authority constituted under the KarnatakaUrban Development Authority Act, 1987 (Karnataka Act 14 of 1987);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>a Grama Panchayat, a Taluk Panchayat or a Zilla Panchayat constituted under the Karnataka Panchayat Raj Act, 1993 (Karnataka Act 14 of 1993);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>an Improvement Board constituted under the Karnataka Improvement Boards Act, 1976 (Karnataka Act 11 of 1976);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.vi">
                      <num>(vi)</num>
                      <p>The Bangalore Development Authority constituted under the Bangalore Development Authority Act, 1976 (Karnataka Act 12 of 1976); or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h.list2.vii">
                      <num>(vii)</num>
                      <p>any other authority, as the State Government may by notification, declare to be a local authority;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>"premises" means,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a building as defined in clause (a);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>any land not used for agricultural purpose;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>"public institution" includes any educational institution maintained out of State Funds or aid received out of State Funds or free hostel attached to such educational institution, library, a Government Hospital, charitable dispensary, orphanage, disabled home and destitute home;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>"residential purpose", "residential user" or "purpose of residence" include letting out for running a public institution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>"Schedule" means a Schedule appended to this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>"standard rent" in relation to any premises means the standard rent referred to in section 7 or where the standard rent has been increased under section 9, such increased rent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.n.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>"tenant" means any person by whom or on whose account or behalf the rent of any premises, is or but for a special contract would be, payable, and includes,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.n.list4.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a sub-tenant;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.n.list4.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>any person continuing in possession after the termination of his tenancy, but does not include any person to whom a licence as defined in section 52 of the Indian Easements Act, 1882 (Central Act 5 of 1882) has been granted;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.n.list4.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>A deserted wife of a tenant who has been or is entitled to be in occupation of the matrimonial home or tenanted premises of husband; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.n.list4.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>a divorced wife of a tenant who has a decree of divorce in which the right of residence in the matrimonial home or tenanted premises has been incorporated as one of the conditions of the decree of divorce.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>"urban area" means the areas specified in the First or Second Schedule</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Regulation of rent</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Registration of tenancy agreement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 107 of the Transfer of Property Act, 1882 (Central Act 4 of 1882), no person shall, after the commencement of this Act, let or take on rent any premises except by an agreement in writing.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every agreement referred to in sub-section (1) or required to be registered under sub-section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be registered under the Registration Act, 1908 (Central Act 16 of 1908), within such period as may be prescribed and for this purpose the agreement shall be deemed to be a document for which registration is compulsory under section 17 of the said Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where, in relation to a tenancy created before the commencement of this Act,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an agreement in writing was entered into and was not registered under the Registration Act, 1908 (Central Act 16 of 1908) the landlord and the tenant shall, jointly present a copy thereof for registration before the registering officer under the said Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>no agreement in writing was entered into, the landlord and the tenant shall enter into an agreement in writing with regard to that tenancy and present the same for registration before the registering officer under the said Act:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that where the landlord and the tenant fail to present jointly a copy of tenancy agreement under clause (a) or fail to reach an agreement under clause (b)such landlord and the tenant shall separately file the particulars about such tenancywith the prescribed authority in such form and in such manner and within such periodas may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Inheritability of tenancy.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In the event of death of a tenant, the right of tenancy shall devolve for a period of ten years from the date of his death to his successors in the following order, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>spouse;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>son or daughter or where there are both son and daughter both of them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>parents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>daughter-in-law, being the widow of his pre-deceased son:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the successor has ordinarily been living or carrying on busines in the premises with the deceased tenant as a member of his family up to the date of his death and was dependent on the deceased tenant:</p>
              <p>Provided further that a right to tenancy shall not devolve upon a successor in case such successor or his spouse or any of his dependent son or daughter isowning or occupying a premises in the local area in relation to the premises let.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a person, being a successor mentioned in sub-section (1), was ordinarily living in or carrying on business in the premises with the deceased tenant but was not dependent on him on the date of his death, or he or his spouse or any of his dependent son or daughter is owning or occupying a premises in the local area in relation to the premises let to which this Act applies such successor shall acquire a right to continue in possession as a tenant for a limited period of one year from the date of death of the tenant; and, on the expiry of that period, or on his death,</p>
              <p>whichever is earlier, the right of such successor to continue in possession of the premises shall become extinguished.</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where, by reason of sub-section (2), the right of any successor to continue in possession of the premises becomes extinguished, such extinguishment shall not affect the right of any other successor of the same category to continue in possession of the premises but if there is no other successor of the same category,the right to continue in possession of the premises shall not, on such extinguishment,pass on to any other successor specified in any lower category or categories,as the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the right of every successor, referred to in sub-section (1) to continue in possession of the premises shall be personal to him and shall not, on the death of such successor, devolve on any of his heirs.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Rent payable.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The rent payable in relation to a premises shall be,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the rent agreed to between the landlord and the tenant as enhanced in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>the manner provided in the Third Schedule; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the standard rent specified under section 7, as revised under section 9.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a tenancy entered into before the commencement of this Act, the landlord may, by notice in writing to the tenant within three months from the date of such commencement, enhance the rent as specified under section 7, and the rent so enhanced, shall be payable from the date of such commencement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Standard rent.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Standard rent in relation to any premises, shall be the rent calculated on the basis of ten per cent per annum of the aggregate amount ofthe cost of construction and the market price of the land comprised in the premises on the date of commencement of the construction:</p>
              <p>Provided that the standard rent calculated as aforesaid shall be enhanced in the manner provided in the Third Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>cost of construction shall include cost of electrical fittings, water pumps, overhead tanks, storage tank and other water, sewerage and other fixtures and fittings affixed in the premises;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in case any fixture and fittings referred to in clause (a) are in common use by more than one occupant in a building, such proportion of cost of the fixtures equipment and fittings shall be included in the cost of construction of the premises as bears proportion to the plinth area of such premises to the plinth area of that building;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the cost of construction shall be the actual amount spent on construction, and in a case where such amount cannot be ascertained, such cost shall be determined as per the scheduled rates of the State Public Works Department for cost of construction for similar construction for the year in which the premises was constructed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the market price of the land shall be the price for which the land was bought as determined from the deed of sale registered under the Registration Act, 1908 (Central Act 16 of 1908), if construction commenced in the year of registration or the land rates notified by the State Government or a local authority for the year in which construction was commenced, whichever is higher;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the land comprised in the premises shall be the plinth area of the building and such of the vacant land up to fifty per cent, of the plinth area as is appurtenant thereto;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>in a case where a premises forms part of a building having more than one premises, such proportion of price of land forming part of such building shall be taken to be the market price of the land comprised in the premises as is equal to the proportion of the plinth area of such premises to the plinth area of that building;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>notwithstanding anything contained in clauses (c) and (d), the cost of construction and the market price of the land comprised in the premises purchased from or allotted by the Government or a local authority shall be the aggregate amount payable to such Government or he local authority for the premises:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the Controller may, for the purpose of arriving at, the cost of construction and the market price of the land comprised in the premises, allow in addition, subject to a maximum of thirty per cent of amount payable to the Government or the local authority, to the amount so payable for any expenditure incurred by the landlord or by the first or any subsequent purchaser or allottee for any improvement, addition or structural alteration in the premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Other charges payable.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A tenant shall be liable to pay to the landlord, besides the rent, the following charges, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>charges, not exceeding fifteen per cent of the rent for the amenities as specified in the Fourth Schedule or as agreed to between the landlord and the tenant;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>maintenance charges at the rate of ten per cent of the rent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>without prejudice to the liability of landlord to pay the property tax to the local authority, the prorata property tax in relation to the premises.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of calculating the monthly charges payable by the tenant to the landlord towards the property tax, the amount paid or payable as property tax for the immediately preceding year or the estimated tax payable shall form the basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The landlord shall be entitled to recover from the tenant the amount paid by him towards charges for electricity or water consumed or other charges levied by alocal or other authority which is ordinarily payable by the tenant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Revision of rent in certain cases.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a landlord has at any time, before the commencement of this Act with or without the approval of the tenant or after the commencement of this Act with the written approval of the tenant incurred expenditure for any improvement, addition or structural alteration in the premises, not being expenditure on decoration or tenantable repairs necessary or usual for such premises, and the cost of that improvement, addition or alteration has not been taken into account in determining the rent of the premises, the landlord may lawfully increase the rent per year by an amount not exceeding ten percent of such cost.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, after the rent of a premises has been fixed under this Act, or agreed upon, as the case may be, there has been a decrease, diminution or deterioration of accommodation in such premises, the tenant may claim a reduction in the rent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Notice of revision of rent.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a landlord wishes to revise the rent of any premises under sub-section (1) of section 9, he shall give the tenant a notice of his intention to make the revision and, in so far as such revision is lawful under this Act, it shall be due and recoverable from the date of improvement, addition or structural alteration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notice under sub-section (1) shall be in writing signed by or on behalf of the landlord and given in the manner provided in section 106 of the Transfer of Property Act, 1882 (Central Act 4 of 1882).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Unlawful charges not to be claimed.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall not be lawful for the tenant or any other person acting or purporting to act on behalf of the tenant or a sub-tenant to claim or receive any payment in consideration of the relinquishment,transfer or assignment of his tenancy or sub-tenancy, as the case may be of anypremises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this section shall apply,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to any payment made in pursuance of an agreement entered into before the commencement of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to any payment made under an agreement by any person to a landlord for the purpose of financing the construction of the whole or part of any premises on the land belonging to, or taken on lease by, the landlord if one of the conditions of the agreement is that the landlord should let to that person the whole or part of the premises when completed for the use of that person or any member of his family but not exceeding the amount of agreed rent for a period of five years, for the whole or part of the premises to be let to such person.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of clause (b) of this sub-section, a member of the family of a person means, in the case of an un-divided Hindu family, any member of the joint family of that person and in the case of any other family, the husband, wife, son, daughter, father, mother, brother, sister or any other relative dependent on that person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Controller to fix standard rent, etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Controller shall, on an application made to him in this behalf, in the prescribed manner, fix in respect of any premises,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the deemed rent for the purpose of clause (e) of sub-section (3) of section 2;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the enhancement in rent in the manner provided in Third Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the standard rent as per the provisions of section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the other charges payable as per the provisions of section 8; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the revision in rent as per the provisions of section 9:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that it shall not be permissible for the land lord to apply for the fixation of standard rent as per the provisions of section 7 in the case of a tenancy entered into after the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In working out the cost of construction of any premises or the market price ofland comprised in such premises for the purposes of section 7 or the expenditure incurred for any improvement, addition or structural alteration or the decrease, diminution or deterioration of accommodation in a premises for the purpose of section 9, the Controller may take the assistance of a prescribed valuer who shall carry out the assessment in the manner prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In fixing the standard rent of any premises or the lawful increase or decrease of the rent or determining the other charges payable, the Controller shall fix or determine an amount which appears to him to be reasonable having regard to the provisions of section 7 or section 8 or section 9 and other circumstances of the case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In fixing the standard rent of any premises part of which has been lawfully sub-let, the Controller may also fix the standard rent of such part sub-let.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where for any reason it is not possible to determine the standard rent of any premises on the principles set forth in section 7, the Controller may fix such rent as would be reasonable having regard to the situation, locality and condition of the premises and the amenities provided therein, and where there are similar or nearly similar premises in the locality, having regard also to the rent payable in respect of such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The standard rent shall in all cases be fixed for a tenancy of twelve months:</p>
              <p>Provided that where any premises are let or re-let for a period of less than twelve months, the standard rent for such tenancy shall bear the same proportion to the annual rent as the period of tenancy bears of twelve months.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In fixing the standard rent of any premises under this section, the Controller shall fix the standard rent thereof in an unfurnished state and may also determine an additional charge to be payable on account of any fittings or furniture supplied by the landlord and it shall be lawful for the landlord to recover such additional charge from the tenant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In fixing the standard rent or lawful increase or decrease of rent or determining the other charges payable in respect of any premises under this section, the Controller shall specify a date from which the amount, so fixed shall be deemed to have effect:</p>
              <p>Provided that, in no case the date so specified shall be earlier than the date of filing of the application for the increase or decrease of the standard rent:</p>
              <p>Provided further that if the increase is because of improvement, addition orstructural alteration, it shall come into effect from the date of completion of suchimprovement, addition or alteration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Controller may, while fixing standard rent or lawful increase or decrease in rent or other charges payable, order for payment of the arrears of amount due by the tenant to the landlord in such number of instalments as he deems proper.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Fixation of interim rent.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When an application for fixing the standard rent or for determining the lawful increase or decrease of such rent and other charges payable is made under section 12, the Controller shall, as expeditiously as possible, make an order specifying the amount of the rent and other charges payable or the lawful increase to be paid by the tenant to the landlord pending final decision on the application and shall specify the date from which the rent and other charges payable or lawful increase so specified shall be deemed to have effect.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Limitation for application for fixation of standard rent etc.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any landlord or tenant may file an application to the Controller for fixing the standard rent and other charges of the premises or for determining the lawful increase or decrease of such rent and other charges:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of any premises which were let, or in which the cause of action for lawful increase or decrease of rent and other charges arose, before thecommencement of this Act, within two years from such commencement.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of any premises in which the cause of action for lawful increase or decrease of rent and other charges arises after the commencement of this Act,within two years from the date on which the cause of action arises.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of any premises constructed on or after the commencement of this Act and for which the provisions of the Act are made applicable by virtue of subsection(4) of section 2, within two years from the date of such application:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the Controller may entertain the application after the expiry of thesaid period of two years, if he is satisfied that the applicant was prevented bysufficient cause from filing the application in time.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Refund of rent, premium, etc.,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where any sum or other consideration has been paid, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, by or onbehalf a tenant to a landlord, in contravention of any of the provisions of this Act the Controller may, on an application made to him within a period of one year from thedate of such payment, order the landlord to refund such sum or the value of suchconsideration to the tenant or order adjustment of such sum or the value of such consideration against the rent payable by the tenant.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Receipt to be given for rent and other charges paid.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every tenant shall pay rent and other charges payable within the time fixed by contract or in theabsence of such stipulation, by the fifteenth day of the month next following the month for which it is payable and where any default occurs in the payment of rent orother charges, the tenant shall be liable to pay simple interest at the rate of twelveper cent per annum from the date on which it becomes payable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every tenant who makes payment of rent or other charges payable or advance towards such rent or other charges to his landlord shall be entitled, to obtainforthwith from the landlord or his authorised agent a written receipt for the amountpaid to him, signed by the landlord or his authorised agent:</p>
              <p>Provided that it shall be open to the tenant to remit the rent or other charges to his landlord by postal money order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the landlord or his authorised agent refuses or neglects to pass to thetenant the receipt referred to in sub-section (2), the Controller may, on an applicationmade to him in this behalf by the tenant within two months from the date of paymentand after hearing the landlord or his authorised agent, by order direct the landlordor his authorised agent to pay to the tenant, by way of damages, such sum notexceeding double the amount of rent or other charges paid by the tenant and thecosts of the application and shall also grant a certificate to the tenant in respect of therent or other charges paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the landlord or his authorised agent refuses to accept or evades acceptance of receipt of rent or other charges payable to him, the tenant may, bynotice in writing, ask the landlord to furnish him the particulars of his bank account ina bank in the place where the premises is situate into which the tenant may depositthe rent and other charges payable to the credit of the landlord.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the landlord furnishes the particulars of his bank account, the tenant shalldeposit the rent and other charges payable in such bank account from time to time</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the landlord does not furnish the particulars of the bank account under sub-section (4), the tenant shall remit the rent and the other charges payable to thelandlord from time to time through postal money order after deducting the postalcharges.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Deposit of rent</heading>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Deposit of rent and other charges by the tenant.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord does not accept any rent and other charges tendered by the tenant within the timeand the manner referred to in section 16 or refuses or neglects to deliver a receipt referred to therein, or where there is a bonafide doubt as to the person or persons to whom the rent and other charges are payable, the tenant may deposit such rent andother charges with the Controller in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The deposit shall be accompanied by an application by the tenant containing the following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the premises for which the rent and other charges deposited with adescription sufficient for identifying the premises;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the period for which the rent and other charges are deposited;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the name and address of the landlord or the person or persons claiming to be entitled to such rent and other charges;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the reasons and circumstance for which the application for depositingthe rent is made;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>such other particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On deposit of the rent and other charges being made, the Controller shallsend, in the prescribed manner, a copy of the application to the landlord or personsclaiming to be entitled to the rent and other charges with an endorsement of the dateof the deposit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If an application is made for the withdrawal of any deposit of rent and othercharges, the Controller shall, if satisfied that the applicant is the person entitled toreceive the rent and other charges deposited, order the amount of the rent and othercharges to be paid to him in the manner prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that no order for payment of any deposit of rent and other charges shall be made by the Controller under this sub-section without giving all persons named bythe tenant in his application under sub-section (2) as claiming to be entitled topayment of such rent and other charges an opportunity of being heard and suchorder shall be without prejudice to the rights of such persons to receive such rent andother charges being decided by a court of competent jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, at the time of filing the application under sub-section (4), but not after the expiry of thirty days from receiving the notice of deposit, the landlord or the person orpersons claiming to be entitled to the rent and other charges complains or complainto the Controller that the statements in the tenant’s application of the reasons andcircumstances which led him to deposit the rent and other charges are untrue, theController, after giving the tenant an opportunity of being heard, may levy on thetenant a fine which may extend to an amount equal to two months rent and othercharges, if the Controller is satisfied that the said statements were materially untrueand may order that the fine realised or any part thereof be paid to the landlord as compensation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Controller may, on the complaint of the tenant and after giving an opportunity of being heard, to the land lord levy on the landlord a penalty which mayextend to an amount equal to two months rent, if the Controller is satisfied that thelandlord, without any reasonable cause, refused to accept rent though tendered tohim within the time referred to in sub-section (1) of section 16 and may further orderthat the penalty realised or any part thereof be paid to the tenant as compensation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Time limit for making deposit and consequence of incorrect particularsin application for deposit.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No rent and other charges deposited under section 17 shall be considered to have been validly deposited under that section, unless thedeposit is made within twenty-one days of the time referred to in section 16 forpayment of the rent and other charges.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No such deposit shall be considered to be validly made, if the tenant wilfully makes any false statement in his application for depositing the rent and othercharges, unless the landlord has withdrawn the amount deposited before the date offiling an application for the recovery of possession of the premises from the tenant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the rent and other charges is deposited within the time mentioned in subsection(1) and does not cease to be a valid deposit for the reason mentioned in subsection(2), the deposit shall constitute payment of rent and other charges to thelandlord, as if the amount deposited had been validly tendered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Saving as to acceptance of rent and other charges and forfeiture of rent in deposit.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The withdrawal of rent and other charges deposited undersection 17 in the manner provided therein shall not operate as an admission againstthe person with-drawing of the correctness of the rate of rent and other charges, theperiod of default, the amount due, or of any other facts stated in the tenant’sapplication for depositing the rent and other charges under the said section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any rent and other charges in deposit which is not withdrawn by the landlord or by the person or persons entitled to receive such rent shall except in cases wherethere is bonafide dispute of title be forfeited to Government by an order made by theController, if it is not withdrawn before the expiration of five years from the date ofposting of the notice of deposit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before passing an order of forfeiture, the controller shall give notice to thelandlord or the person or persons entitled to receive the rent and other charges indeposit by registered post at the last known address of such landlord or person orpersons and shall also publish the notice in his office and in any local newspaper.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Registration of middlemen or estate agents</heading>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Registration of Middlemen or Estate Agents.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Middleman or Estate Agent by whatever name called who is engaged in brokerage of houses shallregister his name with the Controller of the area in which he is so engaged in suchmanner and within such period and on payment of such fee, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A middleman or Estate Agent shall be entitled for commission at such rate as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Middleman or Estate Agent shall renew his registration within suchtime and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Middlemen or Estate Agents to file information and returns.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every middleman or Estate Agent carrying on business in any area from prior to the date ofapplication of this chapter to that area, shall within thirty days from the date of application of this part submit to the Controller, a statement in the prescribed formshowing his name, place of business and area of activity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Middleman or Estate Agent shall within ten days from the last day of each quarter of every calendar year file return in such form and in such manner asmay be prescribed, to the Controller giving details of every transaction handled byhim during the quarter, and the brokerage or commission received by him in eachcase.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Limitation of liability of middleman.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No Middleman or Estate Agent shall be liable to pay to his principal in respect of any premises any sum by way of rentalcharges which exceeds the amount which he is entitled to receive under this Act,from the tenant or tenants of the premises.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Controllers, their powers and procedure</heading>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Controllers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint as many Controllers as it thinks fit, and define the local limits within which, each Controller shall exercise the powersconferred or perform the duties imposed on Controllers by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Controller,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in any area referred to in Part A of the First Schedule unless he has for at least five years held office as Assistant Commissioner;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in any area referred to in Part B of the First Schedule unless he has for atleast five years held office as a Senior Tahsildar; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>in any other area unless he has for atleast three years held office as a Tahsildar, in the Revenue Service of the State.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Controller.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-24.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Controller shall have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Central Act 5 of1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>proof of facts by affidavit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>discovery and production of documents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>issuing commission for local inspection and for the examination of witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-24.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purposes of holding an enquiry or discharging any duty under this Act, the Controller may,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>after giving not less than twenty-four hours, notice in writing enter and inspect or authorise any officer subordinate to him to enter and inspect any premisesat any time between sunrise and sunset; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by written order, require any person to produce for his inspection all such accounts books or other documents relevant to the inquiry at such time and atsuch place as may be specified in the order.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Controller may, if he thinks fit, appoint one or more persons havingspecial knowledge of the matter under consideration as an assessor to advise him inthe proceeding before him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Procedure to be followed by Controller and time limit for deciding cases generally.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order which prejudicially affects any person shall be made by the Controller under this Act without giving such person a reasonable opportunityof showing cause against the order proposed to be made, and until his objection, ifany, and any evidence that may be adduced in support of the same have been consideredby the Controller.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Controller shall, while holding enquiry in any proceeding before him, follow such procedure as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All proceedings before the Controller shall ordinarily conclude within six months from the date of first appearance of the Respondent in response to thesummons issued for his appearance in the case, or from the date on which therespondent is set experte:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Controller may extend the hearing of the case beyond six months for reasons to be recorded by him on each day of hearing.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of an application under section 49, the controller shall commence the hearing of the application within seven days of the filing thereof andshall dispose off the same as per may be possible within thirty days of start of suchhearing, unless for reasons to be recorded the controller adjourns the case beyondsuch time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Appeal.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person aggrieved by an order passed by the Controller under the provisions of chapters II, III or IV may within thirty days from the date thereof,appeal,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to the Deputy Commissioner when the officer passing the order is an officer not below the rank of an Assistant Commissioner; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to the Assistant Commissioner in any other case, and the appellate authority may pass such order in appeal as it deems fit.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Regulation of eviction</heading>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Protection of tenants against eviction.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law or contract, no order or decree for therecovery of possession of any premises shall be made by the Court, District Judge orHigh Court in favour of the landlord against a tenant, save as provided in sub-section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Court may, on an application made to it in the prescribed manner, make an order for the recovery of possession of the premises on one or more of thefollowing grounds only, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant has neither paid nor tendered the whole of the arrears ofthe rent and other charges legally recoverable from him within two months from thedate on which a notice of demand for payment of has been served on him by thelandlord in the manner provided in section 106 of the Transfer of Property Act, 1882(Central Act 4 of 1882):</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that a tenant shall not be entitled to the benefit of service of notice by the landlord under this clause where, having obtained such benefit once in respect ofany premises, he again makes a default in the payment of rent and other chargespayable in respect of those premises:</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Provided further that where in a proceeding for eviction of a tenant on the groundspecified in this clause, the tenant is to be evicted, the Court shall make an orderdirecting the tenant to vacate the premises unless he pays to the landlord or depositsinto Court within one month of the date of order, an amount calculated at the rate atwhich it was last paid, for the period for which the arrears of rent and other chargeswere legally recoverable from him, including the period subsequent thereto up to theend of the month previous to that in which payment or deposit is made;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-27.2.list4.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>that the tenant has,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list4.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>on or after the date of application of Part V of the Karnataka Rent Control Act, 1961 (Karnataka Act 32 of 1961) to the local area inrelation to the premises, but before the date of application of thisChapter to such local area; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list4.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>after the commencement of this Act without the consent in writing ofthe landlord,sub-let, assigned or otherwise parted with the possession of the whole or any part of the premises;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant has used the premises for a purpose other than that forwhich they were let, without obtaining the consent in writing of the landlord:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no application for recovery of possession of any premises shall lieon this ground unless the landlord has given to the tenant a notice by registered postserved personally on him requiring him to stop the misuse of the premises and thetenant has refused or failed to comply with such requirement within one month of thedate of service of the notice and no order for eviction against the tenant shall bemade in such a case, unless the Court is satisfied that the misuse of the premises isof such a nature that it is a public nuisance or that it causes damage to the interest ofthe landlord;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-27.2.list6.d.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>that the premises were let and,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list6.d.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the tenant or any member of his family has been in occupation thereof for a period of six months;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list6.d.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the tenant has not been occupation thereof, without a reasonablecause for a period of two years,immediately before the date of the filing of the application for the recovery of possession thereof:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the landlord may, on request in writing of the tenant, permitoccupancy of the premises by a person other than the tenant or his family notexceeding the period of tenancy.</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause and clause (r), "family" means parents, spouse, dependent sons and daughters or such other relatives as areordinarily living with the tenant and are dependent upon him;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list9.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>that the premises or any part thereof have become unsafe or unfit for human habitation and are required by the landlord for carrying out repairs or reconstructionwhich cannot be carried out without the premises being vacated:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no order for the recovery of possession under this clause, or clauses (g), (h) or (i) shall be made unless the Court is satisfied that the plans andestimates of such repairs or re-construction, as the case may be, have been properlyprepared and that the landlord has the necessary means to carry out the said repairsor re-construction:</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list12">
                <listIntroduction>Provided further that if the landlord proposes to change the use of the premises after re-construction, then, he shall so specify in his application for recovery ofpossession and, after such re-construction, the landlord shall, if it is otherwisepermissible under law, utilize the built up area equal to the previous area for theoriginal use to the extent required for the purpose of sub-section (1) of section 35 andthe rest for any other use;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list12.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>that the premises or any part thereof are required by the landlord for the purpose of immediate demolition ordered by the Government or any local authority orthe premises are required by the landlord to carry out any building work at theinstance of the Government or a local authority in pursuance of any improvementscheme or development scheme and that such building work cannot be carried outwithout the premises being vacated;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list12.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>that the premises or any part thereof are required by the landlord for carrying out any repairs which cannot be carried out without the premises beingvacated;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list12.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>that the premises are required by the landlord for the purpose of buildingor re-building or make thereto any substantial addition or alteration includingconstruction on the terrace of the premises or on the appurtenant land and that suchbuilding or re-building or addition or alteration cannot be carried out without thepremises being vacated;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list12.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>that the premises consist of not more than two floors and the same are required by the landlord for the purpose of immediate demolition with a view to rebuildthe same:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list14">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that where the building of which such premises or premises possession in respect of which has been recovered under clause (e), clause (f), clause (g) orclause (h) forms a part has been re-built to an extent of less than seventy-five percent, a tenant so dispossessed shall have a right to re-entry at the new terms oftenancy in the premises in the re-built building equivalent in area to the originalpremises for which he was a tenant;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list14.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant, his spouse or a dependent son or daughter ordinarily living with him has whether before or after the commencement of this Act, built oracquired vacant possession of or been allotted a residence or as the case may be acommercial premises :</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list16">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the Court may in appropriate cases allow the tenant to vacate the premises within such period as he may permit but not exceeding one year from thedate of passing of the order of eviction;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list16.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>that the premises were let to the tenant for use as a residence by reason of his being in the service or employment of the landlord, and that the tenant hasceased, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, to be in such serviceor employment:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list18">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no order for the recovery of possession of any premises shall bemade on this ground if the Court is of the opinion that there is any bonafide disputeas to whether the tenant has ceased to be in the service or employment of thelandlord;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list18.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant has, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, caused or permitted to be caused substantial damage to, or such alteration of,the premises as has the effect of changing its identity or diminishing its value.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, "substantial damage" shall mean such damage as shall involve an expenditure equivalent to six months rent or moreof the premises or such less expenditure as the Court is satisfied keeping in view, thespecial nature of damage, justifies the same to be treated as substantial damage forcarrying out the repairs for such damage:</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list21">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no order for the recovery of possession of any premises shall be made on the ground specified in this clause, if the tenant, within such time as may bespecified in this behalf by the Court, carries out repairs to the damage caused to thesatisfaction of the Court or pays to the landlord such amount by way of compensationas the Court may direct;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list21.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant or any person residing or carrying on business with the tenant has been convicted of causing nuisance or annoyance to a person living in theneighbourhood of the premises or has been convicted of using or allowing the use ofthe premises for an immoral or illegal purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list21.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant has, notwithstanding previous notice, used or dealt with the premises in a manner contrary to any condition imposed on the landlord bythe Government or the Local Authority while giving him a lease of the land on whichthe premises are situate:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list23">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no order for the recovery of possession of any premises shall bemade on this ground if the tenant, within such time as may be specified in this behalfby the Court, complies with the condition imposed on the landlord by any of theauthorities referred to in this clause or pays to the authority imposing such conditionsthe amount by way of compensation as the Court may direct;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list23.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant in his reply having denied the ownership of landlord, has failed to prove it or that such denial was not made in a bonafide manner;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list23.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>that the person in occupation of the premises has failed to prove that he is a bonafide tenant;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list23.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant after having agreed with or having informed the landlordin writing the date to vacate the premises does not do so on or after the date soagreed or informed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list23.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>that the premises let are required, whether in the same form or after reconstruction or re-building, by the landlord for occupation for himself or for anymember of his family if he is the owner thereof, or for any person for whose benefitthe premises are held and that the landlord or such person has no other reasonablysuitable accommodation:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that where the landlord has acquired the premises by transfer, no application for the recovery of possession of such premises shall lie under this clauseunless a period of one year has elapsed from the date of the acquisition:</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list26">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation-I.- For the purposes of this clause and sections 28 to 31,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list26.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>where the landlord in his application supported by an affidavit submits that the premises are required by him for occupation for himself or for any member ofhis family dependent on him, the Court shall presume that the premises are sorequired;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list26.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>premises let for a particular use may be required by the landlord for a different use if such use is permissible under law.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation-II.- For the purposes of this clause and sections 28 to 31 anoccupation by the landlord of any part of a building of which any premises let out byhim forms a part shall not disentile him to recover the possession of such premises.</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list29">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation-III.- For the purposes of this clause, and sections 28 to 31 “owner of the premises” includes a person who has been allotted such premises by theBangalore Development Authority or any other local authority by way of anagreement of hire-purchase, lease or sub-lease, even before the full ownership rightsaccrue to such hire-purchaser, lessee or sub-lessee, as the case may be;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list29.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>that where the landlord is a trustee of any Public Charitable trust, the premises are required for occupation for the purpose of the trust;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any proceeding for eviction under clause (e), (f), (g), (h) or (r) of subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or sections 28 to 31 the Court may allow eviction from only a part of the premises if the landlord is agreeable to the same:</p>
              <p>Provided that, in case of such part-eviction, the rent and other charges payableby the tenant shall be decreased in proportion to the part vacated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order for the recovery of possession in any proceeding under subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be binding on any sub-tenant referred to in section 33 who has givennotice of his sub-tenancy to the landlord under the provision of that section, unlessthe sub-tenant is made a party to the proceeding and the order for eviction is madebinding on him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Right to recover immediate possession of premises to accrue to certain persons.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a landlord who being a person in occupation of any premises allotted to him by the Government or any local authority is required, by, orin pursuance of, any general or special order made by that Government or authority,to vacate such premises or in default, to incur certain obligations, on the ground thathe owns, in the local area, where he normally resides or carrying on business, anaccommodation either in his own name or in the name of his wife or dependent child,there shall accrue, on and from the date of such order, to such landlord, notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act or in any other law for thetime being in force or in any contract (whether express or implied), custom orusage to the contrary, a right to recover immediate possession of any premises letout by him :</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be construed as conferring a right on a landlord owning, in the local area where he normally resides two or more premises,whether in his own name or in the name of his wife or dependent child, to recover thepossession of more than one premises and it shall be lawful for such landlord toindicate the premises, possession of which he intends to recover.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section and sections 29, 30 and 31 ‘immediate possession’ shall mean possession recoverable on the expiry of sixtydays from the date of order of eviction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord exercises the right of recovery conferred on him by subsection</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, or sections 27, 29, 30 or 31 and he had received,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any rent in advance from the tenant, he shall, within a period of ninety days from the date of recovery of possession of the premises by him, refund to thetenant such amount as represents the rent payable for the unexpired portion of thelease ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any other payment, he shall, within the period aforesaid, refund to the tenant a sum which shall bear the same proportion to the total amount so received,as the unexpired portion of the contract or agreement, lease bears to the total periodof contract or agreement or lease:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, if any default is made in making any refund as aforesaid, the landlord shall be liable to pay simple interest at the rate of twelve per cent, perannum on the amount which he has omitted or failed to refund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Right to recover immediate possession of premises to accrue to members of the armed forces, etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where the landlord,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is a released or retired person from any armed forces and the premises let out by him his spouse or his dependent son or daughter are requiredfor his own use; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is a dependent of a member of any armed forces who had been killed in action and the premises let out by such member are required for the use of the family of such member, such person his spouse or his dependent son or daughter, as the case may be, may,within one year from the date of his release or retirement from such armed forces or,as the case may be, the date of death of such member, or within a period of one yearfrom the date of commencement of this Act, whichever is later, apply to the Courtfor recovering the immediate possession of such premises.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord is a member of any of the armed forces and has a period of less than one year preceding the date of his retirement and the premises let out byhim his spouse or his dependent son or daughter are required for his own use afterhis retirement, he may, at any time, within a period of one year before the date of hisretirement, apply to the Court for recovering immediate possession of such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord referred to in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) has let out more than one premises, it shall be open to him his spouse or his dependent sonor daughter to make an application under that sub-section in respect of only one ofthe premises chosen by him.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, "armed forces" means an armedforce of the Union constituted under an Act of Parliament and includes a member ofthe police force constituted under the Karnataka Police Act, 1963.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Right to recover immediate possession of premises to accrue to employee of State or Central Government.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord is a retired employee of the State or Central Government, and the premises let out by him, hisspouse or his dependent son or daughter are required for his own use, suchemployee may, within one year from the date of his retirement or within a period of one year from the date of commencement of this Act, whichever is later, apply to the Court for recovering immediate possession of such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord is an employee of the State or Central Government andhas a period of less than one year preceding the date of his retirement and thepremises let out by him, his spouse or his dependent son or daughter are required byhim for his own use after his retirement, he may, at any time within a period of oneyear before the date of his retirement, apply to the Court for recovering immediatepossession of such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord, his spouse or his dependent son or daughter referred to in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) has let out more than one premises, it shall beopen to him his spouse or his dependent son or daughter, as the case may be tomake an application under that sub-section in respect of only one of the premiseschosen by him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Right to recover immediate possession of premises to accrue to a widow.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where the landlord is,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a widow and the premises let out by her, or by her husband;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a handicapped person and the premises let out by him;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a person who is of the age of sixty-five years or more and the premises let out by him,is required for use by her or him or for her or his family or for any one for ordinarilyliving with her or him for use, she or he may apply to the Court for recovery ofimmediate possession of such premises.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord referred to in sub-section (1) has let out more than onepremises, it shall be open to him to make an application under that sub-section inrespect of any one residential and one non-residential premises each chosen by him.</p>
              <p>Explanation-I.- For the purposes this section, “handicapped person” shall meana person who is as if being an assessee entitled for the time being to the benefits ofdeduction under section 80U of the Income Tax Act, 1961 (Central Act 48 of 1961).</p>
              <p>Explanation-II.- The right to recover possession under this section shall beexercisable only once in respect of each for residential and for non-residential use.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Restriction on sub-letting.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, at any time before the date of application of Part V of the Karnataka Rent Control Act, 1961 (Karnataka Act 32 of1961) to the local area in relation to the premises, a tenant has sub-let the whole orany part of the premises and the sub-tenant is, at the commencement of this Act, inoccupation of such premises, then, notwithstanding that the consent of the land lord was not obtained for such sub-letting the premises shall be deemed to have been lawfully sub-let.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>After the commencement of this Act, no tenant shall, without the previousconsent in writing of the landlord,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>sub-let the whole or any part of the premises held by him as a tenant; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>transfer or assign his rights in the tenancy or in any part thereof.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No landlord shall claim or receive the payment of any sum as premium orpugree or claim or receive any consideration whatsoever in cash or in kind for givinghis consent to the sub-letting of the whole or any part of the premises held by thetenant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Notice of creation and termination of sub-tenancy.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where after the commencement of this Act, any premises are sub-let either in whole or in part by thetenant with the previous consent in writing of the landlord, the tenant or the subtenantto whom the premises are sub-let may, in the prescribed manner, give noticeto the landlord of the creation of the sub-tenancy within one month of the date ofsuch sub-letting and notify the termination of such sub-tenancy within one month ofsuch termination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, before the commencement of this Act, any premises have been lawfully sub-let either in whole or in part by the tenant, the tenant or the sub-tenant towhom the premises have been sub-let may, in the prescribed manner, give notice tothe landlord of the creation of the sub-tenancy within six months of thecommencement of this Act, and notify the termination of such sub-tenancy within onemonth of such termination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Sub-tenant to be tenant in certain cases.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where an order for eviction in respect of any premises is made under section 27 against a tenant but not against a sub-tenant referred to in section 32 and a notice of the sub-tenancy has been givento the land-lord, the sub-tenant shall, with effect from the date of the order, be deemed to become a tenant holding directly under the landlord in respect of the premises in his occupation on the same terms and conditions on which the tenantwould have held from the landlord, if the tenancy had continued.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of possession for occupation and re-entry.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where a land-lordrecovers possession of any premises from the tenant in pursuance of an order madeunder clause (f) of sub-section (2) of section 27, or under sections 28, 29, 30, 31 or 37 the land lord shall not, except with the permission of the Court obtained in theprescribed manner, re-let the whole or any part of the premises within three yearsfrom the date of obtaining such possession, and in granting such permission, theCourt may direct the landlord or unless the tenant waives the right put such evictedtenant in possession of the premises:</p>
              <p>Provided that where a landlord recovers possession of any premises from the tenant in pursuance of an order made under clause (r) of sub-section (2) of section27 for occupation after re-construction or re-building, the period of three years shallbe reckoned from the date of completion of re-construction or re-building, as the casemay be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a landlord recovers possession of any premises as aforesaid and the premises are not occupied by the landlord or by the person for whose benefit thepremises are held, within two months of obtaining such possession, or the premiseshaving been so occupied are, at any time within three years from the date of obtaining possession, re-let to any person other than the evicted tenant withoutobtaining the permission of the Court under sub-section (1) or the possession of suchpremises is transferred to another person for reasons which do not appear to theCourt to be bonafide, the Court may, on an application made to him in this behalf bysuch evicted tenant within such time as may be prescribed, direct the landlord to put the tenant in possession of the premises or to pay him such compensation as theCourt thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of possession for repairs and re-building and re-entry.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making any order on the grounds specified in clauses (h) or (i) of sub-section (2) of section 27 or of sections 28, 29,30,31 or 37 the Court shall unless the landlord has obtained permission for conversion of user of the premises after re-building andrepair, for a commercial purpose ascertain from the tenant whether he elects to beplaced in occupation of the premises or part thereof from which he is to be evictedand if the tenant so elects, shall record the fact of these election in the order andspecify therein the date on or before which he shall deliver possession so as toenable the landlord to commence the work of repairs or building or re-building, as thecase may be, and the date before which the landlord shall deliver the possession ofthe said premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the tenant delivers possession on or before the date specified in the order, the landlord shall, on the completion of the work of repairs or building or re-building,place the tenant in occupation of the premises or part thereof before the datespecified in sub-section (1) or such extended date as may be specified by the Courtby an order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, after the tenant has delivered possession on or before the date specified in the order, the landlord fails to commence the work or repairs or re-building withinone month of the specified date or fails to complete the work in a reasonable time orhaving completed the work, fails to place the tenant in occupation of the premises inaccordance with sub-section (2), the Court may, on an application made to him in thisbehalf by the tenant within such time as may be prescribed, order the landlord toplace the tenant in occupation of the premises or part thereof or to pay to the tenantsuch compensation being an amount not less than three times of the standard rent ofthat premises as the Court thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of possession in case of tenancies for limited period.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a landlord does not require the whole or any part of any premises for a particular period, and the landlord, after obtaining the permission of the Court in theprescribed manner, let the whole of the premises or part thereof for such period asmay be agreed to in writing between the landlord and the tenant and the tenant doesnot, on the expiry of the said period, vacate such premises, then, notwithstandinganything contained in section 27 or in any other law, the Court may, on an applicationmade to him in this behalf by the landlord within such time as may be prescribed,place the landlord in vacant possession of the premises or part thereof by evictingthe tenant and every other person who may be in occupation of such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Court shall not,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-37.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>grant permission under sub-section (1) in relation to a premises consecutively more than two times except for good and sufficient reasons to berecorded in writing.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-37.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- A permission granted under sub-section (1) shall not be construed to be consecutive, if a period of five years or more has elapsed after the expiry of thelast limited period tenancy;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-37.2.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>entertain any application from the tenant calling in question thebonafides of the landlord in letting the premises under this section.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All applications made before the Court and revision made before the DistrictJudge or the High Court by the tenant shall abate on the expiry of the period forwhich permission has been granted under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>While making an order under sub-section (1), the Court may award to thelandlord damages for the use or occupation of the premises at double the last rentpaid by the tenant together with interest at the rate of fifteen per cent per annum forthe period from the date of such order till the date of actual vacation by the tenant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Special provision for recovery of possession in certain cases.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-38.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where the landlord in respect of any premises is any company or other body corporate or any public institution then, notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 or in anyother law, the Court may, on an application made to it in this behalf by such landlord,place the landlord in vacant possession of such premises by evicting the tenant andevery other person who may be in occupation thereof, if the Court is satisfied:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-38.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant to whom such premises were let for use as a residence at a time when he was in the service or employment of the land lord, has ceased to be insuch service or employment; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the tenant has acted in contravention of the terms, express or implied, under which he was authorised to occupy such premises; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that any other person is in unauthorised occupation of such premises; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>that the premises are required bonafide by the public institution for the furtherence of its activities.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section "Public institutions" does not include any such institutions set up by a Private Trust.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Permission to construct additional structures.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where the landlord proposes to make any improvement, in or construct any additional structure on, anybuilding, which has been let to a tenant and the tenant refuses to allow the landlordto make such improvement or construct such additional structure and the Court, onan application made to it in this behalf by the landlord, is satisfied that the landlord isready and willing to commence the work and that such work will not cause any unduehardship to the tenant, the Court may permit the landlord to do such work and maymake such other order as it thinks fit in the circumstances of the case.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Special provision regarding vacant building sites.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-40.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 where any premises let comprise of vacant landupon which it is permissible under the building regulations or municipal bye-laws, for the time being in force, to erect any building, whether for use as a residence or forany other purpose and the landlord proposing to erect such building is unable toobtain possession of the land from the tenant by agreement with him and the Court,on an application made to it in this behalf by the landlord, is satisfied that the landlordis ready and willing to commence the work and that the severance of the vacant landfrom the rest of the premises will not cause undue hardship to the tenant, the Courtmay,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>direct such severance;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>place the landlord in possession of the vacant land;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>refer the case to the Controller to determine the rent payable by the tenant in respect of the rest of the premises; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>make such other order as it thinks fit in the circumstances of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Vacant possession to landlord.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, where the interest of a tenant in any premises is determined for anyreason whatever and an order is made by the Court under this Act for the recoveryof possession of such premises, the order shall subject to the provisions of section34, be binding on all persons who may be in occupation of the premises and vacantpossession thereof shall be given to the landlord by evicting all such persons therefrom:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any person who has an independent title to such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Procedure to be followed by the Court.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order which prejudicially affects any person shall be made by the Court under this Act without giving him areasonable opportunity of showing cause against the order proposed to be made anduntil his objections, if any, and any evidence he may produce in support of the samehave been considered by the Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any rules that may be made under this Act and the other provisions of this Act, the Court shall, while holding an inquiry in any proceedingbefore it, follow as far as may be the practice and procedure of a Court of SmallCauses, including recording of evidence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Court shall not ordinarily allow more than three adjournments at the request of a party throughout the proceedings and in case it decides otherwise itshall record its reasons therefor and order to pay the other party reasonable cost ofadjournment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Court shall, in addition to, and simultaneously with the issue of summons for personal service on the opposite party, also direct the summons tobe served by registered post acknowledgement due, addressed to the oppositeparty or his agent empowered to accept the service at the place where the oppositeparty or his agent actually and voluntarily resides or carries on business or personallyworks for gain and may, if the circumstances of the case so require, also direct thepublication of the summons in a newspaper circulating in the locality in which theopposite party is last known to have resided or carried on business or personally worked for gain.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When an acknowledgement purporting to be signed by the opposite party or his agent is received by the Court or the registered article containing the summons isreceived back with an endorsement purporting to have been made by a postalemployee that the addressee had refused to take delivery of the registered article,the Court may declare that there has been a valid service of summons.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-42.6.list0">
                <item id="section-42.6.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>every application by a landlord for the recovery of possession of any premises on the ground specified in clauses (f), (h) or (n) of sub-section (2) of section27, or under sections 30,31 or 37 shall be dealt with in accordance with theprocedure specified in this sub-section.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.6.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the tenant on whom the summons is duly served whether in the ordinary way or by registered post in the prescribed form shall not contest the prayerfor eviction from the premises unless he files an affidavit stating the grounds onwhich he seeks to contest the application for eviction and obtains leave of the Courtas hereinafter provided and in default of his appearance in pursuance of the summons or of obtaining such leave, the statement made by the landlord in hisapplication for eviction shall be deemed to be admitted by the tenant and the applicant shall be entitled to an order for eviction on the ground aforesaid.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.6.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Court shall give to the tenant leave to contest the application if the affidavit filed by the tenant discloses such facts as would disentitle the landlord fromobtaining an order for the recovery of possession of the premises.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.6.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>where leave is granted to the tenant to contest the application, the Court shall ordinarily commence the hearing of the application within seven days of thegrant of such leave and shall provide day-to-day hearing and dispose off theapplication within thirty days of commencement of such hearing. Failing suchcommencement of hearing or disposal of application within such time, the Court shallmake a record of its reasons therefor.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.6.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>where the leave to contest under clause (c) is denied to the tenant, he may file an application for review before the Court within ten days of such denial andthe Court shall endeavour to dispose of such application within seven days of itsfiling.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application made to the Court shall be heard as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made to conclude the hearing and to dispose off theapplication within six months of it being filed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Dispute of relationship of landlord and tenant.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>where in any proceeding before the Court, a contention is raised denying the existence of relationship of landlord and tenant as between the parties it shall be lawful for the Court to accept the document of lease or where there is no document of lease, a receipt of acknowledgement of payment of rent purported to be signed by thelandlord as prima-facie evidence of relationship and proceed to hear the case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-43.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-43.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the lease pleaded is oral and either party denies relationship, and noreceipt or acknowledgement of payment of rent as referred to in subsection (1) above is produced, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-43.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the opinion of the Court there is reason to suspects the genuineexistence of the document of lease or the receipt or acknowledgement ofpayment of rent. The Court shall at once stop all further proceedings before it and direct the parties toapproach a competent Court of civil jurisdiction for declaration of their rights.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Court to promote negotiated settlement of disputes.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-44.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Court shall, in all cases where the respondent enters or is permitted to enter defence against theapplication, at any time before the evidence is recorded in the case, endeavour to bring about a negotiated settlement of the dispute between the parties, in appropriate cases, by referring them to the appropriate Authority under the Legal ServicesAuthorities Act, 1987 (Central Act 39 of 1987)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1) and subject to suchrules as may be prescribed, the Court shall follow such procedure as it deemsproper to promote a compromise expeditiously</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where there has been a settlement of the case by compromise, the courtshall record the terms of the compromise and pass final order in those terms.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Deposit and payment of rent during the pendency of proceedings for eviction.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No tenant against whom an application for eviction has been made by a landlord under section 27, shall be entitled to contest the application before theCourt under that section or to prefer or prosecute a revision petition under section 46against an order made by the Court on application under section 27 unless he haspaid or pays to the landlord or deposits with the Court or the District Judge or theHigh Court, as the case may be, all arrears of rent and other charges due in respectof the premises upto the date of payment or deposits and continues to pay or todeposit any rent which may subsequently become due in respect of the premises atthe rate at which it was last paid or agreed to be paid, until the termination of theproceedings before the Court or the District Judge or the High Court, as the casemay be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The deposit of the rent and other charges under sub-section (1) shall bemade within the time and in the manner prescribed and shall be accompanied bysuch fee as may be prescribed for the service of the notice referred to in sub-section(5).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where there is any dispute as to the amount of rent and other charges to bepaid or deposited under sub-section (1), the Court shall, on application made to iteither by the tenant or the landlord and after making such enquiry as it deemsnecessary determine summarily the rent to be so paid or deposited.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any tenant fails to pay or deposit the rent as aforesaid, the Court, theDistrict Judge or the High Court as the case may be, shall unless the tenant hasshown sufficient cause to the contrary, stop all further proceedings and make anorder directing the tenant to put the landlord in possession of the premises ordismiss the appeal or revision petition, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any deposit is made under sub-section (1) the Court, the DistrictJudge or the High Court, as the case may be, shall cause notice of the deposit to beserved on the landlord in the prescribed manner and the amount deposited may,subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, be withdrawn by the landlord onapplication made by him to the Court in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Revision.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court may, at any time call for and examine anyorder passed or proceeding taken by the Court of Small Causes or the Court of CivilJudge Senior Division referred to in items (i) and (ii) of clause (c) of section 3 for thepurpose satisfying itself as to the legality or correctness of such order or proceedingand may pass such order in reference thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The District Judge may at any time call for and examine any order passed orproceeding taken by the Court of Civil Judge Junior Division referred to in item (iii) ofclause (c) of section 3 for the purpose of such order or proceeding and may passsuch order in reference thereto as he thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The costs incidental to all proceedings before the High Court or the District Judge shall be in the discretion of the High Court or the District Judge as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Special obligations of landlords and tenants</heading>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Landlord’s duty to keep the premises in good repair.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to anycontract in writing to the contrary every landlord shall be bound to keep the premisesin good and tenantable repairs in relation to matters falling under Part A ofSchedule V.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- Good and tenantable repairs under this section and under section49 shall mean such repairs as shall keep the premises in the same condition in whichit was let out, except for the normal wear and tear.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any repairs in relation to a matter falling under Part A of Schedule Vwithout which the premises are not habitable or useable except with undueinconvenience are to be made and the landlord neglects or fails to make them withina period of three months after notice in writing, the tenant may apply to the Controllerfor permission to make such repairs himself and may submit to the Controller anestimate of the cost of such repairs, and, the Controller, may, after giving the landlordan opportunity of being heard and after considering such estimate of the cost andmaking such inquiries as he may consider necessary, by an order in writing, permitthe tenant to make repairs at such cost as may be specified in the order and it shallthereafter be lawful for the tenant to make such repairs himself and to deduct thecost thereof, from the rent or otherwise recover it from the landlord:</p>
              <p>Provided that the amount so deducted or recoverable from rent in any yearshall not exceed one-half of the rent payable by the tenant for that year and anyamount remaining not recovered in that year shall be deducted or recovered from therent in the subsequent years at the rate of not more than twenty-five percent of therent for a month:</p>
              <p>Provided further that where there are more than one premises owned by alandlord in a building, the tenants thereof may jointly carry out the repairs and sharethe expenses proportionately.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in sub-section (2) shall apply to premises,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>which at the time of letting out was not habitable or useable except withundue inconvenience and the tenant had agreed to take the same in that condition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>which was after being let out, caused to be not habitable or useableexcept with undue inconvenience, by the tenant.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Duties of tenant.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-48.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every tenant shall be bound to keep the premises ingood and tenantable repairs in relation to matters falling under Part B of Schedule V.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any repairs, in relation to a matter falling under Part B of Schedule V, without which the premises are not habitable or useable except with undueinconvenience are to be made and the tenant neglects or fails to make them within aperiod of two months after notice in writing, the landlord may apply to the Controllerfor permission to make such repairs himself and may submit to the Controller anestimate of the cost of such repairs, and, thereupon the Controller may, after givingthe tenant an opportunity of being heard and after considering such estimate of thecost and making such enquiries as he may consider necessary, by an order inwriting, permit the landlord to make such repairs at such cost as may be specified inthe order, and it shall thereafter be lawful for the landlord to make such repairshimself and to recover the cost of such repairs, which shall in no case exceed theamount so specified, from the tenant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The landlord or a person authorised by him shall have the right to enter andinspect the premises after notice to the tenant in the manner prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tenant shall make good all damages caused to the premises by hisnegligence within three months of being informed in writing to do so by the landlordfalling which the landlord may apply to the Controller for permission to make good thesaid damages and the Controller shall decide the matter in the manner provided insub-section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tenant shall hand over possession of the premises on determination oftenancy in the same condition, except for the normal wear and tear, as it was in whenit was handed over to him at the beginning of such tenancy and in a case wherecertain damages have been caused, not being damages caused by force major, thetenant shall make good the damages caused to the premises failing which landlordmay apply to the Controller for permission to make good the said damages and theController shall decide the matter in the manner provided in sub-section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The tenant shall not, whether during the subsistence of tenancy orthereafter, demolish any improvement or alteration carried out by him in thepremises or remove any material used in such improvement or alteration, other thanany fixture of a removable nature, without the permission of the landlord failing whichsuch demolition or alteration shall be deemed to be a damage caused by such tenantunder sub-section (4) and shall be dealt with accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Cutting off or withholding essential supply or service.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No landlordeither himself or through any person purporting to act on his behalf shall without justand sufficient cause cut off or withhold any essential supply or service enjoyed by thetenant in respect of the premises let to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a landlord contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1), the tenant may make an application to the Controller complaining of such contravention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Controller is satisfied that the essential supply or service was cut off or withheld by the landlord with a view to compel the tenant to vacate the premises or to pay an enhanced rent, the Controller may pass an order directing the landlord to restore the amenities immediately, pending enquiry referred to in sub-section (4).</p>
              <p>Explanation.- An interim Order may be passed under this sub-section without giving notice to the landlord.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Controller on inquiry finds that the essential supply or service enjoyedby the tenant in respect of the premises was cut off or withheld by the landlord without just and sufficient cause, he shall make an order directing the landlord to restore such supply or service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-49.5.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Controller may in his discretion direct that compensation not exceeding fifty rupees,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-49.5.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be paid to the landlord by the tenant, if the application under sub-section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-49.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>was made frivolously or vexatiously;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-49.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>be paid to the tenant by the landlord, if the landlord had cut off or withheld the supply or service without just and sufficient cause.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation I.- In this section, "essential supply or service" includes supply of water, electricity, lights in passage and on staircases, conservancy and sanitary services.</p>
              <p>Explanation II.- For the purposes of this section, withholding any essential supply or service shall include acts or omissions attributable to the landlord on account of which the essential supply or service is cut off by the local authority or any other competent authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of Civil Courts barred in respect of certain matters.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-50.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no Civil Court shall entertain any suit or proceeding in so far as it relates to the fixation of standard rent in relation to any premises to which this Act applies or to any other matter which the Controller isempowered by or under this Act to decide, and no injunction in respect of any action taken or to be taken by the Controller under this Act shall be granted by any CivilCourt or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall be construed as preventing a Civil Court from entertaining any suit or proceeding to decide any question of title to any premises to which this Act applies or any question as to the person or persons who are entitled to receive the rent of such premises.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings by or against legal representatives.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any application made, appeal preferred, or proceeding taken under this Act by or against any person,may, in the event of his death be continued by or against his legal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any application, appeal or other proceeding would have been made, preferred or taken under this Act by or against any person such application, appeal or other proceeding may, in the event of his death, be made, preferred or taken by or against his legal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Landlord and tenant to furnish particulars.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every landlord and every tenant of a building shall be bound to furnish to the Controller or any person authorised by him in that behalf, such particulars in respect of the building as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offences and Power to prosecute.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-53.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No Court inferior to that of a Judicial Magistrate of the First Class shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-53.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All offences under the Act shall be bailable and non-congnizable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-53.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Controller or any other officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf may prosecute any person for contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Offences and penalties.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejedice to any other action that may be taken to enforce the regulation or this Act,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>If any landlord or tenant fails to present copy of the lease agreement forregistration as required under clauses (a) or (b) of sub-section (3) of section 4 or failsto file the particulars as required under the proviso thereto, he shall on conviction bepunishable with fine upto two thousand rupees or with simple imprisonment for aterm upto one month or with both and shall also be liable to fine of rupees fivehundred for each day of continuing default till the agreement is presented or as thecase may be particulars furnished ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>If any person contravenes the provisions of section 11, he shall on conviction be punishable with fine which may extend to a sum which exceeds the unlawful charges claimed or received by two thousand five hundred rupees or withsimple imprisonment for a term upto one month or with both ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>Every middleman or Estate agent who.-</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>fails to register his name in contravention or sub-section (1) of section 20 shall on conviction be punishable with fine upto two thousand rupees or with simple imprisonment for a term upto one month or with both, and shall also be liable to fine of rupees two thousand for each day of continuing default till he complies with the law;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fails to submit statements as required under sub-section (1) of section 21 shall on conviction be punishable with fine upto one thousand rupees or with simple imprisonment for a term upto one month or both and shall also be liable to fine of rupees two hundred for each day of continuing default till the statement is filed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>fails to file returns as required under sub-section (2) of section 21 shall on conviction be punishable with a fine upto two thousand rupees or with simple imprisonment for a term upto on minimum with both, and shall also be liable to fine of two hundred rupees for each day of continuing default till the returns are filed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>If any tenant sub-lets, assigns or otherwise parts with the possession of, the whole or part of any premises in contravention of the provisions of clause (b) of subsection(2) of section 27 he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or double the rent received by the tenant for subletting for everymonth till such time the cause of complaint ceases, whichever is more or withimprisonment for a term upto one month, or with both;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>If any landlord makes a false statement in his affidavit under item (i) of explanation I to clause (r) of sub-section (2) of section 27, he shall on conviction bepunishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or double the rentreceivable for a period of three months in case it has been relet, whichever is more,or with imprisonment for a term upto one month or with both;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>If any landlord claims or receives the payment of any sum as premium or pugree or other consideration in contravention of sub-section (2) of section 32, heshall on conviction be punishable with fine upto three thousnd rupees or with simpleimprisonment for a term upto one month or with both;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>If any landlord relets the whole or any part of any premises in contraventionof sub-section (1) of section 35, he shall on conviction be punishable with fine whichmay extend to five thousand rupees, or double the rent the landlord receives after relettingwhichever is more, or imprisonment which may extend upto one month or withboth.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-54.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this clause and clause (iv) in cases where it is difficult to prove the rent which the landlord or the tenant as the case may be, isreceiving after re-letting or sub-letting, the fine may extend to five thousand rupees;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list3.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>If any tenant without reasonable excuse, fails to make re-entry under subsection (2) of section 36 within three months from the date of the completion ofrepairs or building or re-building, as the case may be, intimated in writing by thelandlord without reasonable excuse, he shall forfeit his right to re-entry and shall onconviction be punishable with fine equivalent to three month’s rent of the premises;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list3.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>If any landlord or tenant contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 49, he shall on conviction be punishable with fine equivalent in amount to therent for three months or with upto one month’s imprisonment, or with both, and shallalso be liable to fine of one hundred rupees for each day of continuing default,commencing on the date of cutting off or withholding essential supply or service tillthe date the essential supply or service is restored.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list3.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>if any landlord or tenant fails to furnish particulars as required under section 52 he shall on conviction be punishable with fine upto one thousand rupees or withimprisonment for a term upto one month or with both.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-55.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act is committed by a company, the company, as well as every person in charge of, andresponsible to, the company for the conduct of its business at the time of thecommission of the offence shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall beliable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly :</p>
              <p>Provided that, nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without hisknowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of suchoffence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-55.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or thatcommission of the offence is attributable to any neglect on the part of any director,manager secretary or other officer such Director, Manager, Secretary or other officershall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceededagainst and punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-55.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-55.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"Company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-55.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Controllers to be public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All Controllers appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the PenalCode, 1860 (Central Act 45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-57.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any Controller any officer or servant of the StateGovernment or any person acting under his direction or assisting him in respect ofanything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or rule or orders made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-57.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the State Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or of order madethereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Controller to recover fines as arrears of land revenue.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any fine imposed by a Controller under this Act shall be paid by the person fined within such time asmay be allowed by the Controller and the Controller may, for good and sufficientreason extend the time, and in default of such payment, the amount shall berecoverable as arrears of land revenue under the Karnataka Land Revnue Act, 1964.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Procedure in Appeals.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-59.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In computing the period specified in this Act for filing appeals, the time taken to obtain certified copies of the order appealed againtshall be excluded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of section 5 of the Limitation Act, 1963, shall be applicable to appeals under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On an appeal being preferred under this Act, the Deputy Commissioner orthe Assistant Commissioner, as the case may be, may order stay of furtherproceeding in the matter pending decision on the appeal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Deputy Commissioner or the Assistant Commissioner as the case may be, shall send for the records of the case from the controller and after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard and if necessary after making such furtherenquiry as he thinks fit either himself through the Controller, shall decide the appeal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>All proceedings before the Controller to be judicial proceedings.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All proceedings before the Court or the Controller shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings for the purposes of section 193 and 228 of the Penal Code, 1860(Central Act 45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Decisions which have become final not to be reopened.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Court or the Controller shall summarily reject any application under this Act which raisesbetween the same parties or between parties under whom they or any of them claim,substantially the same issues as have been finally decided in a former proceedingunder this Act or under any of the enactments repealed by section 70.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Orders to be pronounced in open Court.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every order passed by a Court or the Controller under this Act, shall be pronounced in open Court on the day onwhich the case is finally heard, or on some future day of which due notice is given tothe parties.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Finality of Orders.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, every order made by the Court or controller and every order passed in appeal or revisionthere against under this Act shall be final and shall not be called in question in anysuit, application or execution proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Orders.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Clerical or arithmetical mistakes in any order passed by a Court, Controller or the revisional or appellate authority under the Act orerror arising therein from any accidental slip or omission may, at any time, becorrected by such Court, Controller or the appellate or revisional authority on anapplication received in this behalf from any of the parties or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Costs.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be prescribed, the cost of, and incidental to all proceedings before the Court or theController shall be in the discretion of the Court or the Controller which or who shallhave full power to determine by whom or out of what property and to what extentsuch costs, are to be paid.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-66.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after previous publication in the official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-66.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-66.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-66.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner of approval of valuers and the procedure to be followed bysuch valuers under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 12;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>manner of determining the extent of renovation of a building;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which and the period within which an application may be made to the Controller;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which an application for deposit of rent may be</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-66.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>made the particulars which it may contain;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which a Controller may hold enquiry under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the powers of the Civil Court which may be vested in the Controller;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the form or manner in which an application for appeal may be madeunder the Act ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the Court has refer dispute for negotiatedsettlement and procedure for disposal of cases so referred;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>for appointing the Authority for registration and renewal of registration of middleman or estate agents and prescribing his qualifications and terms ofappointment;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>brokerage or commission chargeable by the middleman or estate agents for residential user and the term and manner in which they shall file returns;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the manner of service notice under the Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-66.2.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be provided by rules for in giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Rules and Notifications to be laid before the State Legislature.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act and notification issued under section 2 or under section 68, shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may becomprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry ofthe session in which it is also laid or the session immediately following, both Housesagree in making any modification in the rule or notification or both Houses agree thatthe rule or notification should not be made, the rule of notification shall thereafterhave effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; sohowever that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to thevalidity of anything previously done under that rule or notification.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Removal of difficulties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-68.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any doubt or difficulty arise in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may by notification, make suchprovision as appears to it, to be necessary or expedient for removing the doubts or difficulties:</p>
              <p>Provided that no order shall be made under this section after expiry of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-68.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions made by any notification under sub-section (1) shall, subject to the provisions of sections 67 have effect as if enacted in this Act, and any suchnotification may be made so as to be retrospective to any date not earlier than thedate of commencement of this Act-</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of pending cases.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-69.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>On the commencement of this Act,-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-69.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>all cases pertaining to matters in respect of which the Controller shall have jurisdiction under this Act and pending in the Court under the Karnataka Rent ControlAct, 1961 shall stand transferred to the Controller and the Controller may proceed tohear such cases either de-novo or from the stage it was at the time of such transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>all cases pertaining to matters in respect of which the Court shall have jurisdiction under this Act and pending before the Controller under the KarnatakaRent Control Act, 1961 shall stand transferred to the Court and the Court mayproceed to hear such cases either de-novo or from the stage, it was at the time ofsuch transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-70">
          <num>70.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and Savings.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-70.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Karnataka Rent Control Act, 1961 (Karnataka Act 32 of 1961) is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-70.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding such repeal and subject to the provisions of section 69,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-70.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all proceedings in execution of any decree or order passed under the repealed Act, and pending at the commencement of this Act, in any Court shall becontinued and disposed off by such Court as if the said enactment had not beenrepealed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all cases and proceedings other than those referred to in clause (a) pending at the commencement of this Act before the Controller, DeputyCommissioner, Divisional Commissioner, Court, District Judge or the High Court orother authority, as the case may be in respect of the premises to which this Actapplies shall be continued and disposed off by such Controller, DeputyCommissioner, Divisional Commissioner, Court, District Judge or the High Court orother authority in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all other cases and proceedings pending in respect of premises to which this Act does not apply shall as from the date of commencement of the Act standabated.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise provided in section 69 and in sub-section (2) of this section, provisions of section 6 of the Karnataka General Clauses Act, 1899(Karnataka Act III of 1899), shall so far as may be applicable in respect of repeal ofthe said enactment, and sections 8 and 24 of the said Act shall be applicable as if thesaid enactment had been repealed and re-enacted by this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-firstschedule">
      <doc name="firstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="firstschedule">
            <heading>[See section 2 (1)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="firstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Areas to which Chapters I to III and V to VIII apply.</p>
                <p>Part-A</p>
                <p>Areas within the limits of Cities constituted under the Karnataka MunicipalCorporation Act 1976 and within a radius of three kilometres from the limit of the saidcities.</p>
                <p>Part-B</p>
                <p>Areas within the limits of the City Municipal Councils constituted under KarnatakaMunicipalities Act 1964.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-secondschedule">
      <doc name="secondschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/secondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SECOND SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/secondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/secondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="secondschedule">
            <heading>[See section 2 (2)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="secondschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Areas to which Chapters I and IV apply.</p>
                <p>Areas within the limits of Cities constituted under the Karnataka MunicipalCorporations Act, 1976 and within a radius of three kilometres from the limits of thesaid cities.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thirdschedule">
      <doc name="thirdschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/thirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THIRD SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/thirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/thirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thirdschedule">
            <heading>[(See sections 6 and 7)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>The rent enhanceable under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 6 or subsection (1) of section 7, as the case may be, shall be calculated at the rates shown incolumn (2) of Table I given below, compounding on an yearly basis, with reference tothe date of agreement in the case of rent agreed to between the landlord and thetenant, and the date of commencement of construction in the case of standard rent,to arrive at the rent payable for the period for which rent is to be determined:</p>
                <p>Provided that the total amount of enhancement as so calculated till the commencement of this Act shall be restricted in respect of a premises on the basis ofits size as indicated in column (1) of the Table II to such percentage as is specified inthe corresponding entries in column (2) of the said Table: 38</p>
                <p>Provided further that the enhancement in the case of a tenancy entered into before the commencement of this Act shall be effected gradually in five equal yearlyinstalments.</p>
                <p>Explanation.- The base calculation of annual enhancement of rent after thecommencement of this Act shall be the rent payable in a year as if the totalenhancement of rent due at the commencement of this Act came into effectimmediately rather than gradually over a five year period, and such annualenhancement of rent shall be payable in addition to the graduated enhancement:</p>
                <p>Provided also that in relation to a landlord, referred to in section 31, who is awidow, a handicapped or a person of the age of sixty-five years or more, theenhancement of rent shall not be spread over a period of five years but shall comeinto force immediate effect.</p>
                <table id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0.table5">
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>TABLE 1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Date agreement/ commencment of construction</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rate of annual enhancement of rent</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>2</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1. Unto 31st December, 1949</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Two per cent</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2. On and from 1st January, 1950 to 31st December, 1960.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Four per cent.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>3. on and from 1st January, 1961 to 31st December, 1970</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Six per cent</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>4. On and from 1st January, 1971 to 31st December, 1994.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Eight per cent</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>5. On and from 1st January, 1995</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Seventy- five per cent onwards cent of annual inflation rate based on whole sale price index.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
                <table id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0.table6">
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>TABLE 2</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Premises of (built up area)</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Maximum permitted enhancement of rent</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>2</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1. 50 square metres or less.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty five per cent</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2. More than 50- square metres but upto 90- square metres.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Fifty per cent.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>3. More than 90- square metres.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Seventy five per cent but upto 160- square metres.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>4. More than 160- sqaure metres</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Hundred per cent.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-fourthschedule">
      <doc name="fourthschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/fourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FOURTH SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/fourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/fourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="fourthschedule">
            <paragraph id="fourthschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>(See section 8)</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Air conditioner</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Electrical heater.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Water cooler.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Geyser</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refrigerator.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Cooking range.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Furniture</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Garden meant to be used by the tenant exclusively.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Playground meant to be used by the tenant exclusively.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Sun-brokers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fourthschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Usufructs, if any, enjoyed by the tenant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-fifthschedule">
      <doc name="fifthschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/fifthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FIFTH SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/fifthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24/fifthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2001/34/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="fifthschedule">
            <paragraph id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>(See section 47 and 48)</p>
                <p>A. Structural repairs to be got done by the landlord.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Structural repairs, except those necessitated by damage caused by the tenant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whitewashing of walls and painting of doors and windows once in three years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Changing and plumbing pipes when necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Internal and external wiring and related maintenance.</p>
                <p>B. Day to day repairs to be got done by the tenant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Changing of tap washers and taps.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Drain cleaning.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Water closet repairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Wash closet repairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bath tub repairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Geyser repairs</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Circuit breakers repairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Switches and sockets repairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Repairs and replacement of electrical equipment, except major internal and external wiring changes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Kitchen fixtures repairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Replacement of knobs and locks of doors, cup-boards, windows, etc.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Replacement of fly nets.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Replacement of glass panels of windows, doors, etc.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="fifthschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Maintenance of gardens and open spaces let-out to the tenant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
