<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/32/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/32"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Research And Development Cess Act, 1986"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/32/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/32/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/32/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/32/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Research And Development Cess Act, 1986</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Research and Development Cess Act, 1986.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            <p>The Research and Development cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Board” means the Technology Development Board constituted under the Technology Development Board Act, 1995 (44 of 1995);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“cess” means the cess levied under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“import”, in relation to any technology, means the bringing into India of, such technology from a place outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“industrial concern” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (c) of section 2 of the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964), and includes any other person in whose favour a foreign collaboration involving the import of technology is approved or automatically approved in accordance with the Industrial Policy of the Government of India in force from time to time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“specified agency” means—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the Reserve Bank of India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955); or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>such other bank or institution as may be specified in this behalf by the Central Government;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“technology” means any special or technical knowledge or any special service required for any purpose whatsoever by an industrial concern under any foreign collaboration, and includes designs, drawings, publications and technical personnel.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>The Research and Development Cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Levy and collection of cess on payments made towards import of technology.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be levied and collected, for the purposes of this Act, a cess at such rate not exceeding five per cent. on all payments made towards the import of technology, as the Central Government may, from time to time, specify, by notification, in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cess shall be payable to the Central Government by an industrial concern which imports technology on or before making any payments towards such import and shall be paid by the industrial concern to any specified agency.</p>
            <p>The Research and Development Cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Crediting proceeds of cess to Consolidated Fund of India.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The proceeds of the cess levied and collected under section 3 shall first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India and the Central Government may, if Parliament by appropriation made by law in this behalf so provides, pay to the Board, from time to time, from out of such proceeds (after deducting the cost of collection), such sums of money as it may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of the Board.</p>
            <p>The Research and Development cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Venture Capital Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by Act 45 of 1995, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-9-1996).</p>
            <p>The Research and Development cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Application of Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by Act 45 of 1995, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-9-1996).</p>
            <p>The Research and Development Cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to exempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified therein, exempt any industrial concern from the payment of the cess payable under this Act for the import of such technology as may be specified in such notification.</p>
            <p>The Research and Development Cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to call for information.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Board may require an industrial concern to furnish, for the purposes of this Act, such statistical and other information in such form and within such period as may be prescribed.</p>
            <p>The Research and Development Cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for non-payment of cess.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any cess payable by an industrial concern is not paid on or before making payments towards the import of technology, it shall be deemed to be in arrears and the same shall be recovered by the</p>
            <p>Board in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Board may, after such inquiry as it deems fit, impose on the industrial concern, which is in arrears under sub-section (l), a penalty not exceeding ten times the amount in arrears:</p>
            <p>Provided that before imposing such penalty, such industrial concern shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard, and if, after such hearing, the</p>
            <p>Board is satisfied that the default was for any good and sufficient reason, no penalty shall be imposed under this sub-section.</p>
            <p>The Research and Development Cess Act, 1986</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the foregoing power, such rules may provide for the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the period within which the information under section 8 may be furnished;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the arrears of cess may be recovered under sub-section (1) of section 9;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
