<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tea Companies (Acquisition And Transfer Of Sick Tea Units) Act, 1985"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1985-05-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tea Companies (Acquisition And Transfer Of Sick Tea Units) Act, 1985</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 37 OF 1985</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 28th May, 1985.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- sixth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the sick tea  units specified in the First Schedule and the right, title and  interest of the tea companies in respect of the said tea units with a  view to securing proper reorganisation and management of such tea  units so as to subserve the interests of the general public by  augmenting the production and manufacture of different varieties of  tea which are essential to the needs of the economy of the country and  for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS the sick tea units specified in the First Schedule had  been engaged in the production and manufacture of different varieties  of tea;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the management of the said tea units was taken over by  the Central Government under the Tea Act, 1953 (29 of 1953);</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the Central Government had invested large sums of  money with a view to making the said tea units viable;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS further investment of large sums of money is  necessary for reorganising and rehabilitating the said tea units;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the acquisition by the Central Government of the said  tea units is necessary to enable it to invest such large sums of money  and to protect the large investments already made and also the  interests of the workmen employed therein by proper reorganisation and  management of the said tea units and thereby to augment the production  and manufacture of different varieties of tea which area essential to  the needs of the economy of the country;</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Tea Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Sick Tea Units) Act, 1985.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 8th day of</p>
              <p>April, 1985.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments  appointed under section 13;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" sick tea unit" means a tea unit, specified in column</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of the First Schedule, the management of which had, before  the appointed day, been taken over by the Central Government  under the Tea Act, 1953 (29 of 1953);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" specified date", in relation to any provision of this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act, means such date as the Central Government may, by  notification, specify for the purposes of that provision and  different dates may be specified for different provisions of this</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" tea companies" means the companies being companies as  defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956). specified in  column (3) of the First Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Tea Trading Corporation" means the Tea Trading</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation of India Limited, a company incorporated and  registered under the Companies Act, 1956; (1 of 1956).</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list6.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined but  defined in the Tea Act, 1953 (29 of 1953), shall have the  meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list6.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined either  in this Act or in the Tea Act, 1953 (29 of 1953), but defined in  the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) shall have the meanings  respectively assigned to them in the Companies Act, 1956.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Acquisition of rights of tea companies in respect of sick tea  units.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the appointed day, every sick tea unit and the right,</p>
              <p>title and interest of every tea company in relation to its sick tea  units or, as the case may be, sick tea unit shall, by virtue of this</p>
              <p>Act, stand transferred to, and vest in, the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sick tea unit which stands vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government by virtue of sub- section (1) shall, immediately after it  has so vested, stand transferred to, and vested in, the Tea Trading</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sick tea unit shall be  deemed to include all assets, rights, lease- holds, powers, authorities  and privileges and all property, movable and immovable, including  lands, buildings, workshops, stores, instruments, machinery and  equipment, cash balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments,</p>
              <p>book debts and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of,</p>
              <p>such property as were, immediately before the appointed day, in the  ownership, possession, power or control of the tea company concerned,</p>
              <p>whether within or outside India, and all books of account, registers  and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto and shall  also be deemed to include the liabilities specified in sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>of section 24.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All properties as aforesaid which have vested in the Tea</p>
              <p>Trading Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3 shall, by force  of such vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation,</p>
              <p>mortgage, charge, lien and all other incumbrances affecting them and  any attachment, injunction, decree or order of any court, tribunal or  other authority restricting the use of such properties in any manner  or appointing any receiver in respect of the whole or any part of such  properties shall be deemed to have been withdrawn.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this</p>
              <p>Act in the Tea Trading Corporation and every person holding any  charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation to, any such  property shall give, within such time and in such manner as may be  prescribed, an intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage,</p>
              <p>charge, lien or other interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (3) or any other  person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation  to, any such property shall be entitled to claim, in accordance with  his rights and interests, payment of the mortgage money or other dues,</p>
              <p>in whole or in part, out of the amounts directed to be given under  sections 6 and 7 to the tea company concerned but no such mortgage,</p>
              <p>charge, lien or other interest shall be enforceable against any  property which has vested in the Tea Trading Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any licence or other instrument granted to a tea company in  relation to its sick tea unit which has vested in the Tea Trading</p>
              <p>Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3 at any time before the  appointed day and in force immediately before that day shall continue  to be in force on and after such day in accordance with its tenor in  relation to and for the purposes of such sick tea unit, and that</p>
              <p>Corporation shall be deemed to be substituted in such licence or other  instrument as if such licence or other instrument had been granted to  such Corporation and such Corporation shall hold it for the remainder  of the period for which the tea company would have held it under the  terms thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other  proceeding of whatever nature, in relation to any matter specified in  sub- section (1) of section 24, in respect of the sick tea unit of any  tea company which has vested in the Tea Trading Corporation under sub-</p>
              <p>section (2) of section 3, instituted or preferred by or against that  company, is pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be,</p>
              <p>in any way, prejudicially</p>
              <p>affected by reason of the transfer of the sick tea unit of such tea  company or of anything contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or  other proceeding may be continued, prosecuted or enforced by or  against the Tea Trading Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Tea companies to be liable for certain prior liabilities.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, every liability, other  than the liability specified in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 24, of a  tea company in respect of any period prior to the appointed day, shall  be the liability of that company and shall be enforceable against it  and not against the Tea Trading Corporation.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amount. Every tea company shall be given, by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government, for the transfer to and vesting in that Government  under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 3 of the sick tea unit or, as the  case may be, each sick tea unit of that company and the right, title  and interest of that company in relation to such sick tea unit, in  cash and in the manner specified in Chapter VI, such amount as is  specified against the name of that sick tea unit in column (4) of the</p>
              <p>First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Payment of further amount.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every tea company shall be  given, by the Central Government, per annum, for the deprivation of  the management of its sick tea unit, an amount as is specified against  the name of that sick tea unit in column (5) of the First Schedule,</p>
              <p>for the period commencing on the date on which the management of such  sick tea unit was taken over in pursuance of the order made by the</p>
              <p>Central Government under the provisions of the Tea Act, 1953 (29 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1953">
          <num>1953.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1953.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) and ending on the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1953.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every amount specified in columns (4) and (5) of the First</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleshall">
      <doc name="scheduleshall">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37"/>
              <FRBRalias value="carry simple interest at the rate of four per cent. per  annum for the period commencing on the appointed day and ending on the  date on which the payment of such amount is made by the Central"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleshall">
            <heading>Government to the Commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection id="scheduleshall.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amounts determined in relation to any tea company in  accordance with the provisions of sub- section (2) shall be given by  the Central Government to the tea company in addition to the amounts  specified in columns (4) and (5) of the First Schedule against that  company.</p>
                <p>CHAP</p>
                <p>MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <chapter id="chapter-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF THE SICK TEA UNITS OF THE TEA COMPANIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-8">
                <num>8.</num>
                <heading>Management, etc., of the sick tea units of the tea companies.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>The Tea Trading Corporation or any person which that Corporation may,</p>
                    <p>by order in writing, specify, shall be entitled to exercise the powers  of general superintendence, direction, control and management of the  affairs and business of a sick tea unit, the right, title and interest  of the tea company in relation to which have vested in the Corporation  under sub- section (2) of section 3, and do all such things as the tea  company of the sick tea unit is authorised to exercise and do.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-9">
                <num>9.</num>
                <heading>Duty of persons in charge of management of the sick tea units  to deliver all assets, etc.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-9.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On the vesting of the management of  the sick tea units of the tea companies in the Tea Trading</p>
                    <p>Corporation, the persons in charge of the management of such sick tea  units immediately before such vesting shall be bound to deliver to the</p>
                    <p>Tea Trading Corporation all assets, books of account, registers and  all other documents in their custody relating to such sick tea units.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-9.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may  deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the Tea Trading</p>
                    <p>Corporation and the said Corporation may also, if it is considered  necessary so to do, apply to the Central Government at any time for  instructions as to the manner in which the management of the sick tea  units of the tea companies shall be conducted or in relation to any  other matter arising in the course of such management.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-10">
                <num>10.</num>
                <heading>Duty of persons to account for assets, etc., in their  possession.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-10.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person who has, on the appointed day, in his  possession or under his control any assets, books, documents or other  papers relating to any sick tea unit owned by a tea company which has  vested in the Tea Trading Corporation under this Act shall be liable  to account for the said assets, books, documents and other papers to  the Tea Trading Corporation and shall deliver them up to that</p>
                    <p>Corporation or to such person or persons as that Corporation may  specify in this behalf.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-10.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Tea Trading Corporation may take or cause to be taken all  necessary steps for securing possession of the sick tea units of the  tea companies which have vested in that Corporation under this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-10.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every tea company shall, within such period as the Tea</p>
                    <p>Trading Corporation may allow in this behalf, furnish to that</p>
                    <p>Corporation a complete inventory of all property and assets, as on the  appointed day pertaining to its sick tea unit, which have vested in  that Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, and for this  purpose, the Corporation shall afford to such company all reasonable  facilities.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TEA COMPANIES</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TEA COMPANIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-11">
                <num>11.</num>
                <heading>Continuance of employees.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-11.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every person who has been,</p>
                    <p>immediately before the appointed day, employed in any sick tea unit of  any of the tea companies shall become, on and from the appointed day,</p>
                    <p>an employee of the Tea Trading Corporation and shall hold office or  service under that Corporation, with the same rights and privileges as  to pension, gratuity and other matters as would have been admissible  to him if there had been no such vesting and shall continue to do so  unless and until his employment under that Corporation is duly  terminated or until his remuneration and other conditions of service  are duly altered by that Corporation.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-11.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
                    <p>Act, 1947 (14 of 1947). or in any other law for the time being in  force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person  employed in any sick tea unit of any tea company, to the Tea Trading</p>
                    <p>Corporation, shall not entitle such officer or other employee to any  compensation under this Act or any other law for the time being in  force and no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or  other authority.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-12">
                <num>12.</num>
                <heading>Provident fund and other funds.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-12.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where a tea company has  established a provident fund, superannuation fund, welfare fund or  other funds for the benefit of persons employed in a sick tea unit  owned by it, the monies relatable to its employees whose services have  become transferred by or under this Act to the Tea Trading Corporation  shall, out of the monies standing, on the appointed day, to the credit  of such provident fund, superannuation fund, welfare fund or other  funds, stand transferred to, and vest in, the Tea Trading Corporation.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-12.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The monies which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to  the Tea Trading Corporation, shall be dealt with by that Corporation  in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-13">
                <num>13.</num>
                <heading>Appointment of Commissioner of Payments.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-13.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central</p>
                    <p>Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable  under sections 6 and 7 to the tea companies, by notification, appoint  a Commissioner of Payments.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it  may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the</p>
                    <p>Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to  exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act  and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of  the powers exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers  in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have been  conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way of  authorisation.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other  persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of India.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-14">
                <num>14.</num>
                <heading>Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-14.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified  date, pay in cash to the Commissioner, for payment to every tea  company,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>an amount equal to the amounts or amount specified  against the name of that company in column (4) of the First</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-and">
      <doc name="and">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/and"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37"/>
              <FRBRalias value="; and"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/and"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/and"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="and">
            <paragraph id="and.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="and.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="and.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>a further amount equal to the amounts or amount  specified against the name of that company in column (5) of the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>First Schedule.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="and.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government  in favour of the Commissioner in the Public Account of India, and  every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be  deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account and the  said deposit account shall be operated by the Commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="and.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in  respect of each of the tea companies in relation to which payment has  been made to him under this Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="and.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Interest accruing on the amount in relation to a tea company  standing to the credit of the deposit account referred to in sub-</p>
                <p>section (2) shall enure to the benefit of such tea company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Certain powers of the Tea Trading Corporation.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-15.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Tea</p>
                  <p>Trading Corporation shall be entitled to receive, up to the specified  date, to the exclusion of all other persons, any money due to any tea  company in relation to its sick tea unit which has vested in the</p>
                  <p>Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, and realised after the  appointed day, notwithstanding that the realisation pertains to a  period prior to the appointed day.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Tea Trading Corporation may make a claim to the</p>
                  <p>Commissioner with regard to every payment made by that Corporation,</p>
                  <p>after the appointed day, for discharging any liability of a tea  company, not being any liability specified in sub- section (1) of  section 24, in relation to any sick tea unit owned by it in respect of  any period prior to the appointed day; and every such claim shall have  priority, in accordance with the priorities attaching under this Act  to the matter in relation to which such liability has been discharged  by the Tea Trading Corporation.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities of a  tea company in relation to any sick tea unit owned by it in respect of  any transaction prior to the appointed day, which have not been  discharged on or before the specified date, shall be the liabilities  of that company.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Claims to be made to the Commissioner.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every person  having a claim against a tea company with regard to any of the matters  specified in the Second Schedule, pertaining to any sick tea unit  owned by it, shall prefer such claim before the Commissioner within  thirty days from the specified date:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant  was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the  said period of thirty days, he may entertain the claim within a  further period of thirty days, but not thereafter.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1),</p>
                  <p>all the claims preferred before the Commissioner after the period or  the further period specified in that sub- section but on or before the</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27th">
              <num>27th.</num>
              <heading>day of July, 1989, shall be deemed to have been validly  preferred.]</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Priority of claims. The claims made under section 16 shall  have priorities in accordance with the following principles, namely:--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>Category I shall have precedence over all other  categories and Category II shall have precedence over Category</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>III, and so on;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the claims specified in each of the categories shall  rank equally and be paid in full, but if the amount paid to the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Commissioner under this Act is insufficient to meet such claims  in full, they shall abate in equal proportions and be paid  accordingly; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the question of discharging any liability with regard to  a matter specified in a lower category shall arise only if a  surplus is left after meeting all the liabilities specified in  the immediately higher category.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Examination of claims.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-18.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On receipt of the claims made  under section 16, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the  order of priorities specified in the Second Schedule and examine the  same in accordance with such order.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If on an examination of the claims against a tea company, the</p>
                  <p>Commissioner is of the opinion that the amount paid to him under this</p>
                  <p>Act for payment to such company is not sufficient to meet the  liabilities specified in any lower category, he shall not be required  to examine any claim in respect of such lower category.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Admission or rejection of claims.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>After examining the  claims against a tea company, with reference to the priorities set out  in the Second Schedule, the Commissioner shall fix a date on or before  which every claimant against the tea company shall file the proof of  his claim.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed  shall be given by advertisement in one issue of any daily newspaper in  the English language having circulation in the major parts of the  country and one issue of any daily newspaper in such regional language  as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every such notice shall  call upon the claimant to file the proof of his claim with the</p>
                  <p>Commissioner within the period specified in the advertisement.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim  within the period specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from  the disbursements made by the Commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in  his opinion, be necessary and after giving the tea company concerned  an opportunity of refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a  reasonable opportunity of being heard, by order in writing, admit or  reject the claim in whole or in part.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-19.5.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own  procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his  functions, including the place or places at which he may hold his  sittings and shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under  this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under  the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit in  respect of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-19.5.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any  witness and examining him on oath;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.5.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the discovery and production of any document or other  material object producible as evidence;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.5.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the reception of evidence on affidavit;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.5.list1.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the issuing of any commission for the examination of  witnesses.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to  be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of  the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), and the Commissioner shall be  deemed to be a Civil Court for the purposes of section 195 and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-XXVI">
              <num>XXVI</num>
              <heading>of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</heading>
              <subsection id="chapter-XXVI.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the</p>
                  <p>Commissioner may prefer an appeal against such decision to the High</p>
                  <p>Court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the registered  office of the tea company concerned is situated and every such appeal  shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of that</p>
                  <p>High Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <section id="section-20">
                <num>20.</num>
                <heading>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner. After admitting a  claim against a tea company under this Act, the amount due in respect  of such claim shall be paid by the Commissioner to the person or  persons to whom such amount is due and on such payment, the liability  of such tea company in respect of such claim shall stand discharged.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-21">
                <num>21.</num>
                <heading>Disbursement of amounts to the tea companies.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-21.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If out of  the monies paid to him in relation to a tea company, there is a  balance left after meeting the liabilities as specified in the Second</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany">
      <doc name="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", the Commissioner shall disburse such balance to such tea  company."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany">
            <subsection id="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetosuchteacompany.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where the possession of any machinery, equipment or other  property possessed by a tea company has vested in the Tea Trading</p>
                <p>Corporation under this Act but such machinery, equipment or other  property does not belong to such tea company, it shall be lawful for  that Corporation to continue to possess such machinery or equipment or  other property on the same terms and conditions under which they were  possessed by such tea company immediately before the appointed day.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Undisbursed or unclaimed amounts to be deposited with the  general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which  remains undisbursed or unclaimed on the date immediately preceding the  date on which the office of the Commissioner is finally wound up,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>shall be transferred by the Commissioner, before his office is finally  wound up, to the general revenue account of the Central Government,</p>
                  <p>but a claim to any money so transferred may be preferred to the</p>
                  <p>Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and shall be  dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, and the order, if  any, for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the refund  of revenue.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-23">
                <num>23.</num>
                <heading>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act  shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or  in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-24">
                <num>24.</num>
                <heading>Assumption of liability.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-24.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where any liability of a tea  company arising out of any item specified in Category I of the Second</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleis">
      <doc name="scheduleis">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/scheduleis"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37"/>
              <FRBRalias value="not discharged fully by the Commissioner out of the  amounts paid to him under this Act, the Commissioner shall intimate in  writing to the Central Government the extent of the liability which  remains undischarged and that liability shall be assumed by the"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/scheduleis"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28/scheduleis"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/37/eng@1985-05-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleis">
            <heading>Central Government.</heading>
            <subsection id="scheduleis.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Central Government may, by order, direct the Tea Trading</p>
                <p>Corporation to take over the liability assumed by the Central</p>
                <p>Government under sub- section (1), and on receipt of such direction, it  shall be the duty of that Corporation to discharge such liability.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Management to continue to vest in certain persons until  alternative arrangements have been made. Notwithstanding the vesting  under this Act of a sick tea unit of any tea company in the Tea</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Trading Corporation--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>any person who has been managing the affairs of such  sick tea unit before the date on which that unit had so vested  shall, until alternative arrangements have been made by the Tea</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Trading Corporation for the management of such unit, continue to  manage the affairs of the unit, as if such person had been  authorised by the Tea Trading Corporation, to manage such unit;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>such person shall, until alternative arrangements have  been made by the Tea Trading Corporation, continue to be  authorised to operate, in relation to the sick tea unit of such  tea company, any account of such unit in any bank as if he had  been authorised by the Tea Trading Corporation to operate such  account.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by the Tea</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Trading Corporation. Every contract entered into by any tea company in  relation to any sick tea unit owned by it which has vested in the Tea</p>
                  <p>Trading Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, for any  service, sale or supply and in force immediately before the appointed  day, shall, on and from the expiry of a period of one hundred and  eighty days from the appointed day, cease to have effect unless such  contract is, before the expiry of that period, ratified in writing by  the Tea Trading Corporation, and in ratifying such contract, the Tea</p>
                  <p>Trading Corporation may make such alterations or modifications therein  as it may think fit:</p>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that the Tea Trading Corporation shall not omit to  ratify a contract and shall not make any alteration or modification in  a contract--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly  onerous or has been entered into in bad faith or is detrimental  to the interests of the Tea Trading Corporation; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>except after giving the parties to the contract a  reasonable opportunity of being heard and except after recording  in writing its reasons for refusal to ratify the contract or for  making any alteration or modification therein.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Penalties. Any person who,--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>having in his possession, custody or control any  property forming part of a sick tea unit owned by any tea company  wrongfully withholds such property from the Tea Trading</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Corporation; or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains any  property forming part of, a sick tea unit owned by any tea  company; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Tea</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Trading Corporation or any person or body of persons specified by  that Corporation, any document or inventory relating to a sick  tea unit owned by any tea company, which may be in his  possession, custody or control; or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>fails to deliver to the Tea Trading Corporation or any  person or body of persons specified by that Corporation, any  assets, books of account, registers or other documents in his  possession, custody or control relating to a sick tea unit owned  by any tea company; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming part  of a sick tea unit owned by any tea company or prefers any claim  under this Act which he knows or has reason to believe to be  false or grossly inaccurate, shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years and also  with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-28.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where an offence punishable under  this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the  time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible  to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as  well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and  shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
                  <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
                  <blockList id="section-28.2.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.2.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.2.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-29.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No suit,</p>
                  <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
                  <p>Government or any officer of that Government or the Tea Trading</p>
                  <p>Corporation or other person authorised by that Government or</p>
                  <p>Corporation for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done under this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the</p>
                  <p>Central Government or any of its officers or other employees or the</p>
                  <p>Tea Trading Corporation or any officer or other person authorised by  that Corporation for any damage caused or likely to be caused for  anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this</p>
                  <p>Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>Tea companies not to be wound up by the court. No proceeding  for the winding up of a tea company, the right, title and interest in  relation to a sick tea unit owned by which have vested in the Tea</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Trading Corporation under this Act or for the appointment of a  receiver in respect of the business of the sick tea unit shall lie or  be proceeded with in any court except with the consent of the Central</p>
                  <p>Government.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-31">
              <num>31.</num>
              <heading>Delegation of powers.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-31.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it  under this Act, other than the powers conferred by this section and  section 32 and 33, may also be exercised by such person or persons as  may be specified in the notification.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>, the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under  the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-32">
              <num>32.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-32.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-32.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the time within which, and the manner in which, an  intimation referred to in sub- section (3) of section 4 shall be  given;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-32.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the manner in which the monies in any provident fund or  other fund, referred to in sub- section (2) of section 12, shall  be dealt with;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-32.2.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-33">
              <num>33.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>remove the difficulty:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the appointed day.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-34.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Tea Companies (Acquisition and</p>
                  <p>Transfer of Sick Tea Units) Ordinance, 1985 (3 of 1985), is hereby  repealed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
