<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/26"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Haryana Prohibition Of Smoking In Cinema And Theatre Halls Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/26/eng@2017-01-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/26/eng@2017-01-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/26/eng@2017-01-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/26/eng@2017-01-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Haryana Prohibition Of Smoking In Cinema And Theatre Halls Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 26 of 1974]</p>
        <p>[August 5, 1974]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the prohibition of smoking in cinema and theatre halls</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Haryana in the Twenty-fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Haryana Prohibition of Smoking in Cinema and Theatre Halls Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Haryana.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“auditorium” means the portion of the building occupied by the audience or spectators during a show;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Inspector” means an officer appointed by the State Government to perform the functions of an Inspector under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“prohibited period” means the period beginning from half an hour before the commencement of a show till the end thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“show” means a cinematograph exhibition or performance of a drama or dance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“smoking” means smoking of tobacco in any form, whether as cigarette, cigar, beeri, or in pipe or Hukka.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Offences.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall smoke in cinema or theatre hall, during the prohibited period, either in the auditorium or on the stage, except in so far as the smoking may be a part of the performance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be liable to be turned out of the cinema or theatre hall without payment of any compensation or refund of any payment made by him and shall also be liable to arrest for the purposes of Section 42 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, and on conviction to a fine which may extend to twenty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power of Inspector.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Inspector may enter a cinema or theatre hall to satisfy himself that the provisions of this Act are not being contravened.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to institute prosecution.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution under this Act shall be instituted except on the complaint, in writing, of an Inspector authorized in this behalf by a general or special order of the Director of Health Services, Haryana.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to try summarily.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All cases under this Act shall be tried in the manner provided for the summary trial under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before the House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period often days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive, sessions, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following the House agrees in making any modification in the rule or the House agrees that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of any thing previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Punjab Prohibition of Smoking (Cinema and Theatre Halls) Act, 1951 (Punjab Act 8 of 1951), in its application to the State of Haryana, is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
