<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1931/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1931/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Provisional Collection Of Taxes Act, 1931"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1931/16/eng@1931-09-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1931/16/eng@1931-09-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1931-09-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1931/16/eng@1931-09-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1931/16/eng@1931-09-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Provisional Collection Of Taxes Act, 1931</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 16 OF 1931</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 28th September, 1931.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to amend the law providing for the immediate effect for a  limited period of provisions in Bills relating to the imposition or  increase of duties of customs or excise.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Provisional Collection  of Taxes Act, 1931.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act, a" declared provision" means a  provision in a Bill in respect of which a declaration has been made  under section 3.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to make declarations under this Act. Where a Bill to be  introduced in  Parliament] on behalf of Government provides for the  imposition or increase of a duty of customs or excise, the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may cause to be inserted in the Bill a declaration that it  is expedient in the public interest that any provision of the Bill  relating to such imposition or increase shall have immediate effect  under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Effect of declarations under this Act, and duration thereof.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A declared provision shall have the force of law immediately on  the expiry of the day on which the Bill containing it is introduced.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A declared provision shall cease to have the force of law  under the provisions of this Act--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>when it comes into operation as an enactment, with or  without amendment, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when the Central Government, in pursuance of a motion  passed by   Parliament], directs, by notification  in the Official Gazette, that it shall cease to have  the force of law, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if it has not already ceased to have the force of law  under clause (a) or clause (b), then on the expiry of  the  seventy- fifth day] after the day on which the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Bill containing it was introduced.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Certain refunds to be made when declarations cease to have  effect.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a declared provision comes into operation as an  enactment in an amended form before the expiry of the  seventy- fifth  day] after the day on which the Bill containing it was introduced,</p>
            <p>refunds shall be made of all duties collected which would not have  been collected if the provision adopted in the enactment had been the  declared provision:</p>
            <p>Provided that the rate at which refunds of any duty may be made  under this sub- section shall not exceed the difference between the  rate of such duty proposed in the declared provision and the rate of  such duty in force when the Bill was introduced.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a declared provision ceases to have the force of law  under clause (b) or clause (c) of sub- section (2) of section 4,</p>
            <p>refunds shall be made of all duties collected which would not have  been collected if the declaration in respect of it had not been made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Repeal. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2  and Sch.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
