<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1953/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1953/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bombay Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1953 [Gujarat Version]"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1953/40/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1953/40/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1953/40/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1953/40/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bombay Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1953</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[17th June, 1953]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>BOMBAY ACT NO. XL OF 1953</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of a Fund for the financing of activities to promote welfare of labour in the State of Gujarat for conducting such activities and for certain other purposes.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS, it is expedient to constitute a Fund for the financing of activities to promote welfare of labour in the State of Gujarat for conducting such activities and for certain other purposes it is hereby enacted as follows.-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Bombay Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1953.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Gujarat.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force in such area and on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires -</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Board" means the Gujarat Labour Welfare Board constituted under Section 4;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Contribution" means the sum of money payable as contribution to the Board in accordance with the provisions of Section 6B,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>"Employee" means any person who is employed for hire of reward to do any work, skilled or unskilled, manual, clerical, Supervisory or technical in an establishment but does not include any person.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Who is employed mainly in a managerial capacity, or.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Who, being employed in a supervisory capacity, draws wages exceeding three thousand and five hundred rupees per mensem or exercises, either by the nature of the duties attached to the office or by reason of the powers vested in him, functions mainly of a managerial nature.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>"Employer" means any person who employs either directly or through another person either on behalf of himself or any other person, one or more employees in an establishment and includes—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in a factory, any person named under Section 7 (i) (f) of the Factories Act as the manager;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in any establishment, any person responsible to the owner for the supervision and control of the employees or for the payment of wages;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>"Establishment" means-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a factory;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a tramway or motor omnibus services; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any establishment within the meaning_ of the Bombay Shops and Establishments Act, 1948, which employs, or on any working clay during the twelve months proceedings the specified date employed. ten or, more persons:Provided that, any such establishment shall, subject to the provisions contained in the succeeding proviso continue to be an establishment for the purposes of this Act notwithstanding a reduction in the number of persons to less than ten at any subsequent time:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided further that, where a continuous period of not less than three months the number of persons employed therein has been less than ten such establishment shall cease to be an establishment of the purposes of this Act with effect from the beginning of the months following the expiry of the said period of three months, and the employer shall, within one month from the date of such cessation, intimate by registered post the fact thereof to such authority as the State Government may specify in this behalf."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Factory" means a factory as defined in Section 2 (m) of the Factories Act 1948 (LXIII of 1948);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Fund" means the Labour Welfare Fund constituted under Section 3;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Independent member" means a member of the Board who is not connected with the management of any establishment or who is not an employee, and includes an officer of Government nominated as a member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Inspector" means an Inspector appointed under Section 12; 3*</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.9A">
          <num>(9A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"specified date" in relation to any establishment for the purpose of payment to the Board of any sum specified in item (a), (b), or (bb) of sub-section (2) of Section 3 shall be the date on or before which any such sum becomes payable to the Fund,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Unpaid accumulations" means all payment due to the employees but not made to them within a period of one year from the date on which they became due whether before or after the commencement of this Act including the wages, and gratuity legally payable but not including the amount of contribution if any, paid by an employer to a provident fund established under the Employees' Provident Funds Act, 1952 (XIX of 1952).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Wages" means as defined in clause (vi) of Section 2 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (IV of 1936).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Welfare Commissioner" means the Welfare Commissioner appointed under Section 11.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2A">
        <num>2A.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Welfare fund.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall constitute a fund called the Labour Welfare Fund and notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the sums specified in sub-section (2), shall subject to the provisions of sub-section (4) and Section 6A and 6B be paid into the Fund.;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund shall consist of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all fines realised from the employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all unpaid accumulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>any contribution paid under Section 6B.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.bbb">
                <num>(bbb)</num>
                <p>any interest paid under section 6c.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any voluntary donations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any fund transferred under sub-section (5) of section 7</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any sum borrowed under Section 8.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any loan, grant-in-aid or subsidy paid by the State Government or any local authority or statutory corporation</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>all sums received in any other manner or from any other source.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The sums specified in sub-section (2) shall be collected by such agencies and in such manner and the accounts of the Fund shall be maintained and audited in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force or any contract or instrument, all unpaid accumulations shall be collected by such agencies and in such manner as may be prescribed and be paid in the first instance to the Board which shall keep a separate account therefore until claims thereto have been decided in the manner provided in Section 6A.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Board.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Board for the State of Gujarat for the purpose of administering the Fund, and to perform other functions assigned to the Board by or under this Act; The Board shall consist of the following members, namely.—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such number as may be prescribed of representatives of employers and employees to be nominated by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that both employers and employees shall have equal representation on the Board;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such number of independent members as may be prescribed, nominated by the State Government ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>such number of independent members as may be prescribed, nominated by the State Government to represent women.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Board shall elect one of its independent members as the Chairman of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Board shall hold office during the pleasure of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The allowances, if any, payable to the members of the Board and the conditions of appointment of the representatives of the employers and employees shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name of the Gujarat Labour Welfare Board having pepetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire property both moveable and immoveable, and shall by said name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, until the Board for the State of Gujarat is duly constituted in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (1), the existing Board functioning and operating immediately before the commencement of the Bombay Labour Welfare, Fund (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1961 (Guj. XLVII of 1961), in any area of the State, shall continue to function and operate in that area and shall be the Board of the purposes of this Act for that area; and on the constitution of the Board for the State of Gujarat under sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such existing Board shall stand dissolved, and the members thereof shall vacate office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.6.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all properties, funds and dues which are vested in, realisable by the existing Board shall vest in, and be realisable by the Board so constituted.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.6.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all rights and liabilities which are enforceable by or against the existing Board, shall be enforceable by or against the Board so constituted, and where in any proceedings, in any Court or Tribunal the existing Board is a party thereto, the Board so constituted shall be deemed to be substituted as a party to those proceedings; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.6.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Welfare Commissioner and the other officers and servants of the existing Board shall continue to be the Welfare Commissioner and officers and servants of the Board so constituted; but the terms and conditions of service of the Welfare Commissioner and other officers and servants shall not, until duly altered by a competent authority be less favourable under the Board so constituted than those admissible to them while in service of the existing Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Omitted.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications and removals.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall be chosen as, or continue to be a member of, the Board who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is a salaried official of the Board ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is or at any time has been adjudged insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded with his creditors ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound mind ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>is or has been convicted of any offence involving moral turpitude.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may remove from office any member who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in sub-section (1); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is absent without leave of the Board for more than three consecutive meetings of the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Resignation of office by member and filling up of casual vacancies.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member may resign his office by giving notice thereof in writing to the State Government, and on such resignation being accepted, shall be deemed to have svacated his office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A causal vacancy in the office of a member shall be filled up, as soon as covenantally may be, by the authority concerned ***.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceedings of the Board shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any Vacancy in, or any defect in constitution of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Unpaid accumulations and claims thereto.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All unpaid accumulations shall be deemed to be abandoned property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any unpaid accumulation paid to the Board in accordance with the provisions of Section 3, shall on such payment, discharge an employer of the liability to make payment to an employee in respect thereof, but to the extent only of the amount paid to the Board; and the liability to make payment to the employee to the extent aforesaid shall, subject to the succeeding provisions of this section be deemed to be transferred to the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as possible after any unpaid accumulation is paid to the Board under sub-section (4) of Section 3 of the Board shall by a public notice call upon interested employees to submit to the Board their claims for any payment due to them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Such public notice shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed and it shall be—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>affixed on the notice board, or in its absence on a conspicuous part of the premises, of each establishment in which the unpaid accumulations were earned.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>published in the Official Gazette, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>published in any two newspapers in the language commonly understood in the area in which such establishment is situated, and circulating therein or in such other manner as may be prescribed, regard being had to the amount of claim.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the notice is first affixed and published under sub-section (4) it shall be again affixed and published from time to time for a period of one year from the date on which it was first affixed and published, in the manner provided in that sub-section in the months of June and December 1***.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A certificate of the Board to the effect that the provisions of sub-sections (4) and (5) were complied with shall be conclusive evidence thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any claim received, whether in answer to the notices of otherwise within a period of two years from the date of the first publication of the notice in respect of such claim, shall be transferred by the Board to the Authority appointed under Section 15 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (IV of 1936), having jurisdiction in the area in which the factory or establishment, is situated, and the Authority shall proceed to adjudicate upon, and decide, such claim. In hearing such claim, the Authority shall have the powers conferred by, and shall follow the procedure (in so far as it is applicable) followed in giving effect to the provisions of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If in deciding any claim under sub-section (7), the Authority allows the whole or part of such claim, it shall declare that the unpaid accumulation in relation to which the claim is made shall to the extent to which the claim is allowed, cease to be abandoned property and shall order the Board to pay to the claimant the amount of the claim is allowed by it; and the Board shall make payment accordingly;</p>
            <p>Provided that, the Board shall not liable to pay any sum in excess of that paid under sub-section (4) of Section 3 to the Board as unpaid accumulations, in respect of the claim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie in the City of Ahmedabad to the Court of Small Causes and elsewhere to the District Court against a decision under sub-section (7) rejecting any claim or part thereof, if made within a period of sixty days from the date of such decision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall comply with any order made in appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Authority, subject to an appeal as aforesaid, and the decision in appeal of the Court of Small Causes, or as the may be, the District Court, shall be final and conclusive as to the right to receive payment, the liability of the Board to pay and also as to the amount, if any.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If no claim is made within the time specified in sub-section (7) or a claim or part thereof has been rejected under the foregoing provisions then the unpaid accumulations in respect of such claim shall accrue to and vest in the State as bona vacantia and shall thereafter without further assurance be deemed to be transferred to, and form part of, the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.13.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in the foregoing provisions of this section shall apply to unpaid accumulations not already paid to the Board,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.13.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in respect of which no separate accounts have been maintained so that the unpaid claims of employees are not traceable, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.13.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>which are proved to have been spent before the sixth day of December 1961,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and accordingly such unpaid accumulations shall not be liable to be collected and paid under sub-section (4) of Section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6B">
        <num>6B.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-6B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Board for the purposes of this Act, Contributions a contribution payable by the employer in respect of an employee in an establishment (hereinafter referred to as "the employer's contribution"), a contribution payable by such employee (hereinafter referred to as "the employee's contribution") a contribution payable by the State Government, as hereinafter provided and every such contribution shall form part of the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of employee's contribution shall be payable every six months in respect of every employee whose name stands on the register of the establishment concerned in the month of June, or as the case may be, in the month of December, at the rate of three rupees for each such employee and the amount of employer's contribution shall be payable at every six months at the rate of six rupees for each such employee:Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette increase the said rate of employee's contribution to such amount not exceeding six rupees if it considers necessary so to do to enable the Board to fulfil the objects of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided further that where the rate of employee's contribution is so increased by the State Government, the rate of employer's contribution shall be twice the rate of employee's contribution as so increased.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall pay to the Board both the employers contribution and the employee's contribution before the 15th day of July, and 15th day of January, every year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-sections (2) and (3), the employers contributions and the employee's contribution payable for the first time after the date of the coming into force of the Bombay Labour Welfare Fund (Gujarat Amendments) Act, 1973 (Guj. 29 of 1973), (hereinafter referred to as "the appointed date") shall be payable before such date, and at the respective rates as aforesaid for every employee whose name stands on the register of the establishment concerned on such date as may be specified by the State Government by notification is the Official Gazette, and such contributions payable next thereafter shall be paid in accordance with the provisions of this Act, irrespective of whether the period of six months as specified in sub-section (2) has been passed or not.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other enactment but subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder the employer shall be entitled to recover from any such employee that employees contribution by deductions from has wages, and 'not otherwise; and such deduction shall be deemed to be a deduction authorised by or under the payment of Wages Act, 1936 (IV of 1936):</p>
            <p>Provided that no such deduction shall be made in excess of the amount of the contribution payable by such employee, nor shall any such deduction except the deduction in respect of the employee's contribution payable for the first time after the appointed date be made from any wages other than the wages for the months of June and December:</p>
            <p>Provided further, that if through in advertance or otherwise, no deduction has been made from the wages of an employee for the month's aforesaid, such deduction may be made from the Wages of such employee for any subsequent month or months with the permission in writing of the Inspector appointed under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any contract to the contrary no employer shall deduct the employer's contribution from any wages payable to an employee or otherwise recover it from the employee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any sum duly deducted by an employer from the wages of an employee under this section be deemed to have been entrusted by him by the employee for the purpose of paying the contribution in respect of which it was deducted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An employer shall pay the employer's and the employee's contribution to the Board by cheque, money order or in cash, and he shall bear the expenses of remitting to the Board such contribution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Welfare Commission shall submit to the State Government as soon as possible after the end of July and January every year in the prescribed form a statement showing the total amount of the employer's contribution in respect of his establishment for the period to which the statement relates and no receipt of the Statement from the Welfare Commissioner, the State Government shall pay to the Board a contribution of an amount equal to the employer's contribution in respect of that establishment:</p>
            <p>Provided that the statement in relation to the employee's contribution payable for the first time after the appointed date referred to in sub-section (4) shall be submitted as soon as possible after the specified date in relation to that contribution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6C">
        <num>6C.</num>
        <heading>Interest on unpaid accumulations, fines and contributions after notice of demand.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an employer does not pay to the Board any amount of unpaid accumulations or fines released from the employees or any amount of the employer's or, as the case may be, employee's contributions within the time he is required by or under the provisions of this Act to pay such amount, the Welfare Commissioner May cause to be served a notice on such employer to pay to the Board the amount within the period specified therein, which shall not be less than thirty days from the date of service of such notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6C.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the employer on whom a notice is served under sub-section (1) fails without sufficient cause to pay any such amount within the period specified in the notice, he shall without prejudice to any penalty which may be imposed on him under this Act be liable to pay to the Board simple interest on that amount for the period commencing on the date of expiry of the period specified in the notice and ending on date of the payment of that amount—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6C.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in respect of the period falling within the first three months after such expiry, at the rate of twelve per cent per annum, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6C.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in respect of the other period, at the rate of eighteen per cent per annum.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of interest payable to the Board under sub-section (2) shall be collected by the Welfare Commissioner in such manner as may be prescribed :</p>
            <p>Provided that the Welfare Commissioner may, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, remit the whole or any part of the amount of interest in respect of any period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Vesting and application of Fund.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fund shall vest in and be held and applied by the Board as Trustees subject to the provisions and for the purposes of this Act. Themoneys therein shall be utilized by the Board to defray the cost of carrying out measures which may be specified by the State Government from time to time to promote the welfare of labour and of their dependants.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of sub-section (1) the moneys in the Fund may be utilized by the Board to defray expenditure on the following:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>community and social education centres including reading rooms and libraries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>community necessities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>games and sports;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>excursions, tours and holiday homes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>entertainment and other forms of recreations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>home industries and subsidiary occupations for women and unemployed persons;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>corporate activities of a social nature;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>cost of administering the Act including the salaries and allowances of the staff appointed for the purposes of the Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>such other objects as would in the opinion of the State Government improve the standard of living and ameliorate the social conditions of labour;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Fund shall not be utilized in financing any measure which the employer is required under any law for the time being in force in carry out;</p>
            <p>Provided further that unpaid accumulations and fines shall be paid to the Board and be expended by it under this Act notwithstanding anything contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (IV of 1936), or any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the approval of the State Government, make a grant of the Fund to any employer, any local authority or any other body in aid of any activity for the welfare of labour approved by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises whether any particular expenditure is or is not debitable to the fund, the matter shall be referred to the State Government and the decision given, by the State Government shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be lawful for the Board to continue any activity financed from the labour welfare fund of any establishment, if the said fund is duly transferred to the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power of Board to borrow.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may from time to time with the previous sanction of the State Government and subject to the provisions of this Act, and to such conditions as may be specified in this behalf borrow any sum required for the purpose of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Investment of fund.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the Fund or any portion thereof cannot be applied at any early date for fulfilling the objects of the Act, the Board shall invest the same in any of the securities specified in clauses (a) to (d) and (f) of Section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (II of 1882).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Directions by State Government to Board.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may give the Board such directions as in its opinion are necessary or expedient in connection with expenditure from the Fund or for carrying out the other purposes of the Act. It shall be the duty of the Board to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Appointment and Powers of Welfare Commissioner.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list0">
              <item id="section-11.1.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>The Welfare Commissioner shall be appointed by the Board with the previous approval of the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the Welfare Commissioner shall be the principal executive officer of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list0.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>it shall be the duty of the Welfare Commissioner to ensure that the provisions of this Act and the rules made there under are duly carried out and for this purpose he shall have power to issue such order not inconsistent with the provisions of the Act and rules made thereunder as he deems fit including any order implementing the decisions taken by the Board under the Act or rules made thereunder.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Inspectors.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may appoint Inspectors to inspect records in connection with the sums payable into the Fund, Inspector appointed, whether by a local authority or the State Government under the Bombay Shops and Establishments Act, 1948 (Born. LXXIX of 1948) in relation to any area, shall be deemed to be also Inspector for the purposes of this Act, in respect of establishments, to which this Act applies and the local limits within which such Inspector shall exercise his functions under this Act shall be the area for which he is appointed under the said Act.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>with such assistance, if any, as he thinks fit, enter at any reasonable time any premises for carrying out the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Absorption of the existing staff under Commissioner of Labour.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any staff under the control of the Commissioner of Labour, Bombay which was—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>taken over by a Labour Welfare Board constituted under this Act and existing on the date of such taking over, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>allotted to the Gujarat Labour Welfare Board established under the Bombay Welfare Board (Reorganisation Order), 1960,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder:</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>during the period of such employment all matters relating to pay, leave, retirement, allowances, persons, provident fund and other conditions of service of the said staff shall be regulated by the Bombay Civil Services Rules or such other rules as may from time to time be made by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every such member shall have a right of appeal to the State Government against any order of reduction, dismissal or removed from service, fine or any other punishment:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided further than person so taken over may elect within the prescribed period that the desires to be governed by the rules made under this Act in respect of conditions of service of the staff appointed by the Board under this Act and on his electing to do so the provisions of the first proviso shall cease to apply to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the coming into force of this Act in any area to which it is extended by the Bombay Labour Welfare Fund (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1961 (Guj. XLVII of 1961), the Board shall take over and employ such of the existing staff under the control of the Commissioner of Labour, Ahmendabad as the State Government may direct, and every such person so taken over and employed shall be subject to like terms and conditions and to the same provisions as in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of clerical and other staff by Board.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall have power to appoint the necessary clerical and executive staff to carry out and supervise the activities financed from the Fund:</p>
            <p>Provided that the expenses of the staff thus appointed and other administrative expenses shall not exceed a prescribed percentage of the annual income of the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power of the State Government to remove any person on staff of the Board.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall have the power to remove any person whom it may deem unsuitable, from the service of the Board and to make an appointment in respect of whom more than one-third of the members of the Board have not agreed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government or authorised officer to call for record. etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government of any officer authorised by the State Government may call for the records of the Board, inspect the same and any supervise the working of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Mode of recovery of sums payable to the Board into Fund, etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any sum payable to the Board or into the Fund under this Act shall, without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, be recoverable on behalf of the Board as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17A">
        <num>17A.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to make payment of accumulations, etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any employer who faits to pay any amount of unpaid accumulations or fines realised from employees or any amount of the employer's or, as the case may be employee's contributions, within the period specified in a notice served on him under sub-section (1) of Section 6-C, shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17B">
        <num>17B.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for unlawful deduction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any employer who deducts the whole or any part of the employer's contribution from the wages payable to an employee or otherwise recover it from the employee shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17C">
        <num>17C.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for obstructing inspectors exercising powers of discharging duties, etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17C.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who wilfully obstructs an Inspector in the exercise of his powers or discharge of his duties under this Act or fails to produce for inspection on demand by an Inspector any document maintained in pursuance of the provision of this Act or the rules made thereunder or to supply to him on demand true copies of any such document, shall on conviction, be punishable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17C.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17C.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for a second or subsequent offences, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in the absence of special and adequate reason to the contrary to be mentioned in the judgement of the Court, in any case where the offender is sentenced to a fine only, the amount of fine shall not be less than fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17D">
        <num>17D.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act is committed by a company every person who at the time when the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly :</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-17D.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.—For the purpose of this Section—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17D.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17D.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director" in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17E">
        <num>17E.</num>
        <heading>Provisions relating to jurisdiction.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17E.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17E.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17E.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act, unless a complaint thereof is made within six months of the date on which the offence is alleged to have been committed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution for any offence under this Act shall be instituted, by any person except an Inspector and no prosecution shall be instituted by the Inspector except with the previous sanction of the Welfare Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Supervision of the Board.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the State Government is satisfied that the Board has made default in performing any duties imposed on it by or under this Act or has abused its power, the State Government may by notification in the Official Gazette shall supersede and reconstitute the Board lin the manner specified in sub-section (1) of Section 4 for constitution of the Board.</p>
            <p>Provided that before issuing the notification under this sub-section, the State Government will give a reasonable opportunity to the Board to show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the explanation objections, if any, of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the suppression of the Board and until it is reconstituted the powers, duties and functions of the Board under this Act shall be exercised or performed by the Board or by such officer or officers, as the State Government may appoint for this purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to, the condition of previous publication, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may be made for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the agency for and the manner of collection of sum specified in sub¬section (3) of Section 3; and the period within which the same shall be paid to the credit of the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Fund shall be maintained and audited under sub-section (3) of Section 3 ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the Welfare Commissioner shall collect under sub-section (3) of Section 6C the amount of interest payable under sub-section (2) of that section to the Board, and the conditions subject to which the Welfare Commissioner may remit the whole or any part of the amount of interest under the proviso to sub-section (3) of that Section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the procedure for making grants from the Fund under Section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the procedure for defraying the expenditure incurred in administering the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the number of representatives of employers and employees, independent members and representatives of women on the Board, and the allowance, if any, payable to them, under Section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the Board shall conduct their business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the duties and powers of the Inspectors and the conditions of service of the Welfare Commissioner and Inspectors and other staff appointed under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.ga">
                <num>(ga)</num>
                <blockList id="section-19.2.list1.ga.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the delegation of the powers, and functions of the Board to the Welfare Commissioner and the conditions and limitations subject to which the powers may be exercised or functions discharged :(h) the percentage of the annual income of the Fund beyond which the Board may not spend on the staff and on other administrative measures;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-19.2.list1.ga.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the registers and records to be maintained under the Act;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the publication of the report of the activities financed from the Fund together with a statement of receipts and expenditures of the Fund and statement of accounts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other matter which under this Act is or may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rules under this Section, the State Government may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine not exceeding two thousand rupees, and when the offence is a continuing one, with a daily fine not exceeding one hundred rupees during the continuance of the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall be laid for not less than thirty days before the State Legislature as soon as may be after they are made, and shall be subject to such modifications as the State Legislature may make during the session in which they are so laid or the session immediately following.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any modifications made by the State Legislature shall be notified in the Official Gazette and shall, thereupon take effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Members of Board, Welfare Commissioners, Inspectors and all officers and servants of Board to be public servants.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Board, the Welfare Commissioner, Inspectors and all officers and servants of the Board shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (XIV of 1960).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Protection to persons acting in good faith.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall be against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Exemption.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification in the Official Gazette exempt any class of establishment from all or any of the provisions of this Act subject to such conditions as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 8 of Act IV of 1936.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In Section 8 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936, (IV of 1936) to sub-section (8) the following shall be added, before the Explanation, namely:—</p>
            <p>"but in the case of any factory or establishment to which the Bombay Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1953 (Born. XL of 1953), applies all such realisations shall be paid into the Fund constituted under the said Act."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
