<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-uth/act/2003/30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-uth/act/2003/30"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Uttarakhand Prevention Of Defacement Of Public Property Act, 2003"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-uth/act/2003/30/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-uth/act/2003/30/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-uth/act/2003/30/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-uth/act/2003/30/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Uttarakhand Prevention Of Defacement Of Public Property Act, 2003</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT No. 30 OF 2003</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[January 19, 2004]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the Prevention of the Defacement of Public Property in the State of Uttarakhand.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS, it is expedient in the public interest to provide for the prevention of defacement of Public Property and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto;</p>
        <p>It Is hereby enacted in the Fifty-fourth Year of the Republic of India by the Assembly of Uttarakhand as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, Extent and Commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called The Uttarakhand  Prevention of Defacement of Public Property Act, 2003.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of State of Uttarakhand .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may by Notification, in the Gazette appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"District Magistrate means District Magistrate of the respective districts of the State of Uttarakhand .</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>"Defacement" includes impairing or interfering with the appearance or beauty, damaging, disfiguring, spoiling or injuring in any other why whatsoever and the word "deface" shall be construed accordingly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Public Property" includes any building, hut, structure, wail, tree, fence, post, pole or any other erection;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Writing" includes decoration, lettering, ornamentation etc.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for defacement of Public Property</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, defaces any property in public view by writing of marking with ink, chalk, paint or any other material including pasting of posters except for the purpose of indicating the name and address of the owner of occupier of such property, shall be punishable with imprisonment fora term which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any offence committed under sub-section (1) is for the benefit of some other person or a company or other body corporate or an association of persons (whether incorporated or not), then such other person and every President, Chairman, Director, Partner, Manager, Secretary, Agent of any otheroffice or person concerned with the management thereof, as the case may be, shall unless he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or consent, be deemed to be guilty of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognizable</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of District Magistrate to erase writing, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 3,it shall be competent for the District Magistrate to take such steps as may be necessary for erasing any writing, freeing any defacement or removing any mark from any public property.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification in the Gazette make rules or carrying out the purpose of this Act, including any rules prescribing fees in respect of any proceeding under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
