<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/7/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/7"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Suits Valuation Act, 1887"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/7/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/7/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/7/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/7/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Suits Valuation Act, 1887</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title and extent.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Suits Valuation Act, 1887 [and it extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States].</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.Gujarat.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>—(i) Section 1, shall be renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.Gujarat.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>after sub-section (1) so renumbered, insert the following:—</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>“(2) This Act as in force in the Bombay area and Kutch area of the State of Gujarat immediately before the commencement of the Suits Valuation (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1964 shall also extend to the Saurashtra Area of the State of Gujarat.”</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list4.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>For marginal note, substitute “Title and extent to State of Gujarat.”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Madhya Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 1, after the words “Part B States” add the words “other than the Madhya Bharat and Sironj regions of the State of Madhya Pradesh”.</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 23 of 1958. sec. 3(1) and Sch., Part A.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list9.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 1, after the words “comprised in Part B States” insert the words “other than the Hyderabad area of the State of Maharashtra.”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Extent and Commencement of Part I.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Part shall extend to such local areas, and come into force therein on such dates, as the State Government, by notification in the Official Gazette directs.</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—For section 2, substitute the following, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“2. Commencement of sections 3 to 5.—</p>
            <p>On the date of commencement of the Suits Valuation (Maharashtra Extension and Amendment) Act, 1960, sections 3 to 5 (both inclusive) shall cease to be in force throughout the State of Maharashtra but the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, bring the said sections into force in the whole of the State or any local area, from such date as may be specified in such notification.”</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
            <p>Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh (U.T.).—</p>
            <p>The heading “suits relating to land” of Part I was omitted.</p>
            <p>Vide Punjab Act 13 of 1942, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-11-1942).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power for State Government to make rules determining value of land for jurisdictional purposes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may *** make rules for determining the value of land for purposes of jurisdiction in the suits mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraphs v and vi and paragraph x, clause (d).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rules may determine the value of any class of land, or of any interest in land, in the whole or any part of a local area, and may prescribe different values for different places within the same local area.</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>state amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—In section 3(1), for words, figures etc., “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs (V) and (VI) and paragraph (X), clause (d) substitute the words “clause (d) of paragraph (iv), paragraphs (v), (vi) and (vii) and clause (d) of paragraph (xi), in section 6 of the Bombay Court-fee Act, 1959,”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Himachal Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 3(1) for the words and figures “the Court-fees act, 1870”, substitute the words and figures “Himachal Pradesh Court-fees Act, 1968”.</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 2-6-1970).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list7.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 3 for “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs (V) and (VI) and paragraph (X), clause (d)” substitute “paragraphs (v) and (vi) and clause (d) of paragraph (xi) in section 6 of the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Uttar Pradesh.—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list10.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>After the figure “1870” the words “as in force for the time being in United Provinces” were inserted.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list10.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>For the words and figures “and VI and paragraph X, clause (d)” the figures and letters “VA and VB” were substituted.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list10.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>For the full stop at the end a colon was substituted and the following was added as a fresh paragraph, viz:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Provided that such rules shall provide that the value of land for the purposes of jurisdiction shall in no case be less than the value as determinable for the computation of Court-fees.”</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 7 of 1939, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Valuation of relief in certain suits relating to land not to exceed the value of the land.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a suit mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraph iv, or Schedule II, article 17, relates to land or an interest in land of which the value has been determined by rules under the last foregoing section, the amount at which for purposes of jurisdiction the relief sought in the suit is valued shall not exceed the value of the land or interest as determined by those rules.</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>state amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—In section 4 amendment is the same, except for omission of “(d)” and paragraph vii as in Maharashtra.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Himachal pradesh.—</p>
            <p>For the expression, “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraph iv or Schedule II, Article 17,” substitute the words “the H.P. Court-fees Act, 1968, section 7, paragraph iv, or Schedule II, Article 13 or 18.”</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1969, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list7.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 4 for the words and figures “Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs iv or Schedule II, Article 17, “substitute the following, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Clause (c),(d),(e),(g),(i), or (j) of paragraph iv or paragraph vii in section 6 or Article 3,5,6 or 7 in Schedule I or clause (f) of Article 23 in Schedule II to the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
            <p>Punjab: Haryana and Chandigarh U.T.: Delhi.—</p>
            <p>After the word and figures “Article 17” the word and figures “or 22” were inserted.—</p>
            <p>Vide Punjab Act 1 of 1938, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 30-4-1938).</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>For section 4, the following section was substituted, viz.—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Valuation of certain suits for the purposes of jurisdiction.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Suits mentioned in paragraphs IV</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>, IVA, IVB, V, VA, VB, VI, VIA; VIII and X(d) of section 7 and Arts. 17, 18 and 19 of Sch. II of the Court-fees Act, 1870, as in force for the time being in the Uttar Pradesh, shall be valued for the purposes of jurisdiction at the market value of the property involved in or affected by or the title to which is affected by the relief sought, or at the amount involved in or affected by or the title to which is affected by the relief sought, and such value shall, in the case of land, be deemed to be the value as determinable in accordance with the rules framed under section 3.”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide U.P. Act 7 of 1939, sec.3 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Making and enforcement of rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The [State Government shall, before making rules under section 3, consult the High Court with respect thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A rule under that section shall not take effect till the expiration of one month after the rule has been published in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of section 14 of the Madras Civil Courts Act, 1873. —On and from the date on which rules under section 3 take effect in any part of the territories under the administration of the Governor of Fort Saint George in Council to which the Madras Civil Courts Act, 1873 (3 of 1873) extends, section 14 of that Act shall be repealed as regards that part of those territories.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>STATE AMENDMENTS</p>
            <p>Gujarat.  —Delete section 6.</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Maharashtra.  —Omit section 6.</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Commencement of Part II.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Part</p>
            <p>*** shall come into force on the 1st day of July, 1887.</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>State Amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—In section 7, add the following proviso:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Provided that, in the Saurashtra Area of the State of Gujarat, it shall come into force on the date of the coming into force of the Suits Valuation (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1964.”</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Madhya Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 7, re-number section 7 as sub-section (1) thereof and after sub-section (1) as so renumbered insert the following sub-section (2), namely:—</p>
            <p>“(2) This Part shall be in force in the Madhya Bharat and Sironj regions of the State of Madhya Pradesh from the commencement of the Madhya Pradesh Extension of Laws Act, 1958 (23 of 1958).”</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Vide M.P. Act 23 of 1958, sec. 3(1) and Schedule, Part A.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list10.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 7 add the following Proviso:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Provided that, in the Hyderabad area of the State of Maharashtra it shall come into force on the date of commencement of the Suits Valuation (Maharashtra Extension and Amendment) Act, 1960.”</p>
            <p>Vide Maharastra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
            <p>Punjab: Haryana:Chandigarh U.T.—</p>
            <p>In Part II the heading “Other Suits” was omitted.—</p>
            <p>Vide Punjab Act 13 of 1942, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 22-11-1942).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Court-fee value and jurisdictional value to be the same in certain suits.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where in suits other than those referred to in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraphs v, vi and ix, and paragraph x, clause (d), court-fees are payable ad valorem under the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), the value as determinable for the computation of court-fees and the value for purposes of jurisdiction shall be the same.</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>state amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—In section 8, for “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs v, vi and ix and paragraph x, clause (d), Court-fees are payable ad valorem, under Court-fees Act, 1870,” substitute the words “clause (d) of paragraph iv, paragraphs v, vi, vii and x and clause (d) of paragraph (xi) in section 6 of Bombay Court-fees Act 1959, Court-fees are payable under the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Himachal Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 8, for the words “the Court-fees Act, 1870,” wherever they occur, substitute the words “the Himachal Pradesh Court-fees Act, 1968.”—</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list7.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—In section 8, for “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs v, vi and ix, and paragraph x, clause (d), Court-fees are payable ad valorem under the Court-fees Act, 1870” substitute the following, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Paragraphs v,</p>
            <p>vi and x and clause (d) of paragraph xi in section 6 of the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959, Court-fees are payable ad valorem under the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>For the words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs V, VI and IX and paragraph X, clause (d),” the word and figure “section 4” were substituted; and after the figures and comma “1870,” occurring for the second time, the words “as in force for the time being in the Uttar Pradesh” were added.</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 7 of 1939, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Determination of value of certain suits by High Court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When the subject-matter of suits of any class, other than suits mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraphs v and vi, and paragraph x, clause (d), is such that in the opinion of the High Court it does not admit of being satisfactorily valued, the High Court may with the previous sanction of the State Government, direct that suits of that class shall, for the purposes of the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), and of this Act and any other enactment for the time being in force, be treated as if their subject-matter were of such value as the High Court thinks fit to specify in this behalf.</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>state amendment</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <p>—(i) In its application to the Bombay area, Kutch area and Saurashtra area of the State of Gujarat, in section 9 omit the words and figures “of the court-fees Act, 1870, and.”—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Bombay Act of 36 of 1959, sec. 50 and Schedule V (w.e.f. 1-8-1959).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>In section 9, for the words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs v and vi, and paragraph x, clause (d),” substitute “clause (d) of paragraph iv, paragraphs v, vi and vii and clause (d) of paragraph xi in section 6 of the Bombay Court-fees Act,1959.”</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Himachal Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>In section 9, for the words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870” wherever occurring, substitute the words and figures “the Himachal Pradesh Court-fees Act, 1968.”—</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Vide Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list9.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <p>—For section 9 following section shall be substituted and deemed always to have been so:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“9. Value of certain suits to be three hundred rupees.—</p>
            <p>Where the subject-matter of suits other than suits mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs v and vi, paragraph x, clause (d), or in any corresponding provision of the Court-fees Act, for the time being in force in any area in the State, is such that it does not admit of being satisfactorily valued, then such suits shall, for the purpose of this act, and if the High Court with the previous sanction of the State Government, so directs also for the purposes of any other enactment for the time being in force specified in that behalf by the High Court, be treated as if their subject-matter is of the value of three hundred rupees; and the provisions of the last preceding section shall apply as if the Court-fees therein are payable ad valorem under the relevant Court-fees Act.</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 9 of 1970, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-3-1970).</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>For the words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs V and VI and paragraph X, clause (d)” the words and figures “section 4 or 8” were substituted.—</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 7 of 1939, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of section 32, Punjab Courts Act, 1884 (18 of 1884).—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), sec. 2 and Sch. 1, Part I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of section 32, Punjab Courts Act, 1884 (18 of 1884).—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), sec. 2 and Sch. 1, Part I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Procedure where objection is taken on appeal on revision that a suit or appeal was not properly valued for jurisdictional purposes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1section">
        <num>1section.</num>
        <heading>578 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882), an objection that by reason of the over-valuation or under-valuation of a suit or appeal a Court of first instance or lower Appellate Court which had no jurisdiction with respect to the suit or appeal exercise jurisdiction with respect thereto shall not be entertained by an Appellate Court unless—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1section.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1section.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1section.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the objection was taken in the Court of first instance at or before the hearing at which issues were first framed and recorded, or in the lower Appellate Court in the memorandum of appeal to that Court, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1section.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Appellate Court is satisfied, for reasons to be recorded by it in writing, that the suit or appeal was over-valued or under-valued, and that the over-valuation or under-valuation thereof has prejudicially affected the disposal of the suit or appeal on its merits.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1section.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the objection was taken in the manner mentioned in clause (a) of sub-section (1), but the Appellate Court is not satisfied as to both the matters mentioned in clause (b) of that sub-section and has before it the materials necessary for the determination of the other grounds of appeal to itself, it shall dispose of the appeals as if there had been no defect of jurisdiction in the Court of first instance or lower Appellate Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1section.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the objection was taken in that manner and the Appellate Court is satisfied as to both those matters and has not those materials before it, it shall proceed to deal with the appeal under the rules applicable to the Court with respect to the hearing of appeals; but if it remands the suit or appeal, or frames and refers issues for trial, or requires additional evidence to be taken, it shall direct its order to a Court competent to entertain the suit or appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1section.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the section with respect to an Appellate Court shall, so far as they can be made applicable, apply to a Court exercising revisional jurisdiction under section 622 of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882) or other enactment for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1section.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section *** shall come into force on the first day of July, 1887.</p>
            <blockList id="section-1section.5.list2">
              <listIntroduction>state amendments</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1section.5.list2.Gujarat">
                <num>(Gujarat)</num>
                <blockList id="section-1section.5.list2.Gujarat.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>—In section 11.—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-1section.5.list2.Gujarat.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in sub-section (1), for the words and figures “section 578 of the Code of Civil Procedure” substitute “section 99 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908.”</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-1section.5.list2.Gujarat.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in sub-section (4), for the words and figures “section 622 of the Code of Civil Procedure” substitute the words “section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908;”—and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-1section.5.list2.Gujarat.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>to sub-section (5) add the following proviso, namely:—</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Provided that in the saurashtra Area of the State of Gujarat, it shall come into force on the date of the coming into force of the suits Valuation (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1964.”</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).</p>
            <p>Himachal Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>To section 11 (1), add the following proviso:—</p>
            <p>“Provided that in a suit for accounts, the value for the purposes of jurisdiction as determined by the Court at any stage of the trial shall be final and conclusive and shall not be liable to be contested in appeal or revision.”</p>
            <blockList id="section-1section.5.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Vide H.P. Act 30 of 1969, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1section.5.list9.Maharashtra">
                <num>(Maharashtra)</num>
                <blockList id="section-1section.5.list9.Maharashtra.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>—In section 11—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-1section.5.list9.Maharashtra.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in sub-section (1) for the words and figures “section 578 of the Code of Civil Procedure” substitute “section 99 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908;”</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-1section.5.list9.Maharashtra.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in sub-section (4) for the words and figures “section 622 of the Code of Civil Procedure” substitute “section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908;”</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-1section.5.list9.Maharashtra.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>to sub-section (5), add the following proviso, namely:—</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“Provided that, in the Hyderabad area of the State of Maharashtra it shall come into force on the date of commencement of the Suits Valuation (Maharashtra Extension and Amendment) Act, 1960.</p>
            <p>Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960. sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).</p>
            <p>Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—</p>
            <p>The heading of Part III “Supplemental Provisions” was omitted.</p>
            <p>To sub-section (1) the following Proviso was added:—</p>
            <p>“Provided that in a suit for accounts the value for purposes of jurisdiction as determined by the Court at any stage of the trial shall be final and conclusive and shall not be liable to be contested in appeal or revision.”</p>
            <p>Vide Punjab Act 13 of 1942, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 22-11-1942).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings pending at commencement of Part I or II.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in Part I or Part II shall be construed to affect the jurisdiction of any Court—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>with respect to any suit instituted before rules under Part I applicable to the valuation of the suit take effect, or Part II has come into force; as the case may be, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>with respect to any appeal arising out of any such suit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
