<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/60/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/60"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The State Agricultural Credit Corporations Act, 1968"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/60/eng@1968-12-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/60/eng@1968-12-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1968-12-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/60/eng@1968-12-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/60/eng@1968-12-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The State Agricultural Credit Corporations Act, 1968</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 60 OF 1968</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 29th December, 1968.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment in the States and Union  territories of Agricultural Credit Corporation and for matters  connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>State Agricultural Credit Corporations Act, 1968.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint,</p>
              <p>different dates may be appointed for different States or for different</p>
              <p>Union territories.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" agricultural marketing society" means a co- operative  society the objects of which include the marketing of  agricultural produce;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" agricultural operation" includes animal husbandry,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>dairy farming, pisciculture and poultry farming.</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- The expression" pisciculture" includes the  development of fisheries, both inland and marine, catching of  fish and all activities connected therewith or incidental  thereto;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" agricultural processing society" means a co- operative  society the objects of which include the processing of  agricultural produce;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" agricultural produce" includes the produce of an  agricultural operation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" appropriate Government" means,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>in relation to any Corporation established in  a Union territory, the Central Government, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in relation to any corporation established at  any other place, the State Government;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" banking company" has the meaning assigned to it in  clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1949">
          <num>1949.</num>
          <heading>(10 of 1949);</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1949.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" Board" means the Board of directors of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list2.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list2.h.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" co- operative farming society" means a co- operative  society the objects of which include the cultivation of  land on a co- operative basis;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list2.h.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>" Corporation", in relation to a State or Union  territory, means the Agricultural Credit Corporation  established under section 3 in that State or Union  territory, as the case may be;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list2.h.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>" corresponding new bank" means a corresponding new  bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings)</p>
              <p>Act, 1970 (5 of 1970)  or a corresponding new bank  constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies</p>
              <p>(Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980</p>
              <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>(40 of 1980)];]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list7.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" director" means a member of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list7.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" Food Corporation" means the Food Corporation of India  established under the Food Corporations Act, 1964 (27   of 1964);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list7.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list9.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India  constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list11">
                <listIntroduction>(2 of 1934);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list11.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>" subsidiary banks" has the meaning assigned to it in  the State Bank of India (subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list13">
                <listIntroduction>(38 of 1959);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1949.paragraph-0.list13.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>" Central Co- operative Bank"," co- operative Bank"," Co-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>operative Society", Primary Agricultural Credit</p>
              <p>Society"," Scheduled Bank"," State Bank" and" State Co-</p>
              <p>operative Bank", have the meanings respectively  assigned to them in section 2 of the Reserve Bank of</p>
              <p>India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934).</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>INCORPORATION OF STATE AGRICULTURAL CREDIT CORPORATIONS AND THEIRCAPITAL</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>INCORPORATION OF STATE AGRICULTURAL CREDIT CORPORATIONS AND THEIR</p>
            <p>CAPITAL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of State Agricultural Credit Corporations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The appropriate Government may, by notification in the official</p>
              <p>Gazette, establish in any State or Union territory an Agri-</p>
              <p>cultural Credit Corporation under such name as may be specified in the  notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such Corporation shall be established in any</p>
              <p>State or Union territory other than the States of Assam, Bihar,</p>
              <p>Orissa, Rajasthan and West Bengal and the Union territories of Manipur  and Tripura, except with the previous approval of the Central</p>
              <p>Government, and no such approval shall be given by the Central</p>
              <p>Government except after consultation with the Reserve Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation established under this Act shall be a body  corporate by the name specified in the notification referred to in  sub- section (1), having perpetual succession and a common seal with  power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and  dispose of property, and to contract, and may by that name sue or be  sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Head office and other offices.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall  establish its head office at such place in the State or Union  territory as the appropriate Government may, after consultation with  the Reserve Bank, specify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may, after consultation with the appropriate</p>
              <p>Government, establish offices or agencies at other places in the State  or Union territory, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Share capital and share- holders.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised capital of  each Corporation shall be such sum as the appropriate Government may  initially fix but it shall, in no case, be less than one crore of  rupees or more than five crores of rupees:</p>
              <p>Provided that where the authorised capital initially fixed is  less than five crores of rupees, the appropriate Government may, from  time to time, increase the authorised capital to such sum not  exceeding five crores of rupees:</p>
              <p>Provided further that where the appropriate Government is not the</p>
              <p>Central Government, the initial fixation of the authorised capital and  any subsequent increase or reduction thereof, shall be made with the  prior approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised capital of each Corporation shall be divided  into such number of shares as the appropriate Government may determine  and shall be issued as fully paid- up shares to the parties mentioned  in sub- section (3) at such times and in such manner and to such extent  as the appropriate Government may determine and each of such shares  shall have the same face value.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Out of the capital issued under sub- section (2),-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a Corporation established in a State,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the Central Government shall subscribe for thirty per  cent. of the share capital, and in the case of a</p>
              <p>Corporation established in a Union territory, the</p>
              <p>Central Government shall subscribe for fifty per cent.</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>of the share capital;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Reserve Bank shall subscribe for twenty per cent.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list8">
                <listIntroduction>of the share capital;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list8.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a Corporation established in a State,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list10">
                <listIntroduction>the State Government shall subscribe for twenty per  cent. of the share capital:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list10.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Food Corporation, State Bank, subsidiary banks    corresponding new banks] and banking companies may  subscribe for, in the aggregate, thirty per cent, of  the share capital:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that none of the said parties shall subscribe for more  than fifteen per cent. of the share capital.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The parties referred to in sub- section (3) shall subscribe  for the shares before such date as may be specified in this behalf by  the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall determine the number of shares which are to be  allotted to the parties referred to in clause (d) of that sub- section:</p>
              <p>Provided that if any of the parties referred to in clause (d) of  sub- section (3) fails to subscribe, by the date specified by the</p>
              <p>Central Government under sub- section (4), for any share allotted to  it, such share shall be subscribed for by the Central Government, the</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank and the appropriate Government in such proportions as may  be determined by the Central Government:</p>
              <p>Provided further that the shares subscribed for by the Central</p>
              <p>Government, the Reserve Bank and the appropriate Government, in  pursuance of the provisions of the foregoing proviso, may be  transferred to any party who is eligible under clause (d) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (3) to subscribe for such shares in the first instance, so,</p>
              <p>however, that the total number of shares held by any of the parties  referred to in that clause does not exceed fifteen per cent. of the  share capital of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Restrictions on transfer of shares. Save as otherwise provided  in the second proviso to sub- section (5) of section 5, the shares of  the Corporation shall not be transferable.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MANAGEMENT OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MANAGEMENT OF THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Management.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The general superintendence, direction and  management of the affairs and business of the Corporation shall vest  in a Board of directors who may exercise all the powers and discharge  all the functions which may be exercised or discharged by the</p>
              <p>Corporation other than those which are expressly directed or required  by this Act to be done by the Corporation in general meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board in discharging its functions shall act on business  principles, regard being had to public interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to be guided by directions of Central Government.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In the discharge of its functions, the Corporation shall be guided by  such directions in matters of policy involving public interest as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, give to  it in writing and, if any question arises whether a direction relates  to a matter of policy involving public interest, the decision of the</p>
              <p>Central Government thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Board. The Board of directors of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation shall consist of the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>one directors to be nominated by the Central Government  who shall be the Chairman of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>two directors nominated by the appropriate Government,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>one of whom shall be a person who has special knowledge  of co- operation and who is not an employee of the</p>
              <p>Central or State Government or of the Reserve Bank,</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>State Bank, subsidiary bank,  corresponding new  bank,] banking company, or Food Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>one director to be nominated by the Reserve Bank;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>two directors to be elected in such manner as may be  prescribed by the parties subscribing for shares in  pursuance of the provisions of clause (d) of sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>section (3), and sub- section (5) of section 5;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>a managing director, to be appointed by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government and, except in the case of first  appointment, after consultation with the Board:</p>
              <p>Provided that, in appointing a managing director of a</p>
              <p>Corporation established in a State, the Central Government  may also consult the Government of that State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Managing director.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The managing director shall-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be a whole- time officer of the Corporation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>perform such duties as the Board may, by regulations or  otherwise, assign to him;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>hold office for such term, not exceeding three years,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>as the Central Government may specify at the time of  the appointment and be eligible for re- appointment;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>receive such salary and allowances and be governed by  such terms and conditions of service as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government may-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in the case of first appointment determine, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list5.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in the case of any subsequent appointment,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>determine after consultation with the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, after consultation with the Board  and for sufficient cause, remove the managing director from office;</p>
              <p>Provided that no managing director shall be so removed unless he  has been given an opportunity of showing cause against his removal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the managing director is by infirmity or otherwise  rendered incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent on leave or  otherwise in circumstances not involving the vacation of his  appointment, the Central Government may, after consultation with the</p>
              <p>Board, appoint another person to act in his place during his absence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Term of office of directors other than managing director.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A nominated director, other than the managing director, shall hold  office during the pleasure of the authority nominating him and the  period of such office, unless terminated earlier, shall be two years:</p>
              <p>Provided that a nominated director shall be eligible for  renomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An elected director shall hold office for a period of two  years from the date of his election:</p>
              <p>Provided that an elected director shall continue in office until  the election of his successor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications. No person shall be a director, who,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>except in the case of the managing director, is a  salaried official of the Corporation, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is, or at any time has been, adjudged insolvent or has  suspended payment of his debts or has compounded with  his creditors, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a  competent court, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>is or has been convicted of an offence which, in the  opinion of the Central Government, involves moral  turpitude.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Vacation of seats of directors.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If a director,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes subject to any disqualification specified in  section 12, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is absent without leave of the Board for more than  three consecutive meetings thereof,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>his seat shall thereupon become vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The managing director or any other director may resign his  office by giving notice thereof in writing to the authority by which  he was appointed or nominated, or if he is a director elected under  clause (d) of section 9, to the Board, and on such resignation being  accepted, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Executive Committee and other committees of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may constitute and Executive Committee consisting of the</p>
              <p>Chairman of the Board, who shall be the Chairman thereof, the managing  director and two other directors, one of whom shall be a person  nominated by the appropriate Government under clause (b) of section 9.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Executive Committee shall discharge such functions as may  be prescribed, or may be delegated to it, by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may constitute such other committees, whether  consisting wholly of directors or wholly of other persons or partly of  directors and partly of other persons, as it may think fit for such  purposes as it may decide.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Board and committees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board or the</p>
              <p>Executive Committee or any other committee shall meet at such times  and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the  transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Three directors personally present at any meeting of the</p>
              <p>Board and two members personally present at a meeting of a committee  shall be the quorum for such meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, for any reason, the Chairman of the Board or of any  committee is unable to attend any meeting of the Board or the</p>
              <p>Committee, as the case may be, the members present at the meeting  shall elect one of them to preside at the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If for any reason a director nominated under clause (a),</p>
              <p>clause (b) or clause (c) of section 9 is unable to attend any meeting  of the Board or of any committee if he is a member thereof, the</p>
              <p>Government or the Reserve Bank by which such director was nominated  may depute any other person to attend such meeting and the person so  deputed shall, for the purposes of the said meeting, be deemed to be a  director nominated under clause (a), clause (b) or clause (c), as the  case may be, of the said section 9 or a member of the committee  concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions which may come up before any meeting of the</p>
              <p>Board or a committee shall be decided by a majority of votes of the  members present, and in the event of an equality of votes, the</p>
              <p>Chairman of the Board or of the Committee, as the case may be, or in  his absence the person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Directors of Board or members of a committee not to vote in  certain cases. Every director or member of a committee who has any  direct or indirect pecuniary or other interest in any matter coming up  for consideration at a meeting of the Board or a committee shall, as  soon as possible, after the relevant facts or circumstances have come  to his knowledge, disclose the nature of his interest at such meeting  and the disclosure so made shall be recorded in the minutes of the  meeting of the Board or of the Committee, as the case may be, and no  such director or member shall thereafter take any part in any  deliberation or decision of the Board or committee with respect to  that matter nor shall his presence at such meeting be taken into  account for the purpose of determining the quorum for the meeting at  the time of such deliberation or voting, and if he does vote, his vote  shall be void:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to  such director or member of a committee by reason only of his being a</p>
              <p>shareholder holding not more than two per cent. of the paid- up capital  in any public company as defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), or in any other Corporation established by any law for the time  being in force in India or in any co- operative society, with which or  to which the Corporation has entered into or made, or proposes to  enter into or make, a contract, loan, arrangement or proposal.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Defects in appointments not to invalidate acts, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No  act or proceeding of the Board or of any of its committees shall be  questioned or be invalid on the ground merely of the existence of any  vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Board or the  committee, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No act done by any person acting in good faith as a director  or member of any committee shall be deemed to be invalid merely on the  ground that he was disqualified to be a director or member or that  there was any other defect in his nomination of appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Fees and allowances of directors and members of committees.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every director and every member of a committee shall be paid such fees  and allowances as the Board may, by regulations, determine, for  attending the meetings of the Board or, as the case may be, any of its  committees, or attending to any other work of the Corporation:</p>
              <p>Provided that no fees be paid to the Chairman, managing director  or any other director, if he is an officer of the Government, Reserve</p>
              <p>Bank, State Bank, subsidiary bank,  corresponding new bank,] banking  company or Food Corporation.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>BUSINESS AND FUNDS OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>BUSINESS AND FUNDS OF THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Business which the Corporation may transact. Subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Corporation may transact the following  kinds of business, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the granting of loans and advances, repayable within a  period, not exceeding five years, to agriculturists,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>agricultural marketing societies, agricultural  processing societies, Central Co- operative Banks, co-</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>operative farming societies or primary agricultural  credit societies for agricultural operations or for  such other operations connected there- with as the Board  may by regulations determine;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the drawing, making, accepting, discounting, buying,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>selling, collecting and dealing in bills of exchange,</p>
              <p>hundies, promissory notes, coupons, drafts, bills of  lading, railway</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>receipts, warrants, debentures, certificates, scrips  and other instruments, and securities whether  transferable or negotiable or not;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list7.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the granting and issuing of letters of credit and  acquiring, holding, issuing on commission, underwriting  and dealing in stock, funds, shares, debentures,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>debenture stock, bonds, obligations, securities and  investments of all kinds;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the purchasing and selling of bonds, scrips or other  forms of securities on behalf of constituents or  others, the negotiating of loans and advances, the  receiving of all kinds of bonds, scrips of valuables on  deposit or for safe custody or otherwise, providing of  safe deposit vaults, and collecting and transmitting  money and securities;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the carrying on of agency business of any description  including the clearing and forwarding of goods, giving  of receipts and discharges;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the entering into contracts of indemnity, suretyship or  guarantee with specific security or otherwise;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>receiving in consideration of the services mentioned in  clauses (b), (c), (d), (e) and (f) such commission as may  be agreed upon;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>managing or selling of any property which may come into  the possession of the Corporation in satisfaction or  part satisfaction of any of its claims;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list9.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>acquiring or holding of any property or any right,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list11">
                <listIntroduction>title or interest in any property which may form the  security or a part of the security for any loan or  advance or which may be connected with any business of  the Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list11.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>any other kind of business which the Central Government  may, on the recommendation of the Reserve Bank,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list13">
                <listIntroduction>authorise;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list13.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>generally the doing of such things and matters as may  be incidental to or consequential upon the discharge of  its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing by the Corporation. Subject to the provisions of  this Act, the Corporation may, for the purposes of carrying out its  functions under this Act,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>re- discount with or sell to the Reserve Bank or borrow  money from that Bank and for that purpose, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation shall be deemed to be a State Co- operative</p>
              <p>Bank within the meaning of clause 2 (a), clause 2 (b),</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>clause</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list4.bb">
                  <num>(bb)</num>
                  <p>and clause (4) of section 17, sub- section (2) of  section 46A and sub- section (2) of section 46B of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>borrow money from the Central Government or the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government or such other authority or institution as  approved in this behalf by the Central Government, on  such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Deposits with the Corporation. The Corporation may, with the  prior approval of the Reserve Bank, accept deposits from the  appropriate Government, a local authority or any other person whether  incorporated or not.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Limits on borrowings and deposits. The aggregate of the  amounts borrowed and deposits accepted by the Corporation and  outstanding shall not at any time exceed ten times the amount of the  paid- up share capital and the reserve fund of the Corporation or, with  the prior approval of the Central Government, fifteen times the amount  of such paid- up share capital and reserve fund.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to maintain two funds. The Corporation shall  establish two separate funds, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Agricultural Credit (Stabilization) Fund (hereinafter   referred to as the Stabilization Fund), and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Reserve Fund.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Stabilization Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To the Stabilization Fund shall be  credited such sum, not being less than ten and not more than fifteen  per cent. as the Corporation may deem fit from out of its net annual  profits before declaring a dividend.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such conditions as may be specified by the Board  by regulations, the amount lying to the credit of the Stabilization</p>
              <p>Fund shall be utilised solely for the purpose of making loans or  advances with a view to enabling any co- operative society or other  person to pay its or his dues in cases where, in the opinion of the</p>
              <p>Corporation, such society or other person is unable to pay such dues  in time owing to drought, famine or other natural calamities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Reserve Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To the Reserve Fund shall be credited such  sums not being more than fifteen per cent. as the Corporation may deem  fit out of its net annual profits before declaring a dividend.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amounts lying to the credit of the Reserve Fund shall be  utilised solely for such purposes as the Board may by regulations  specify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Payment of dividend. After making provision for bad and  doubtful debts, depreciation of assets and all other matters which are  usually provided for by bankers, and after crediting to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Stabilization Fund under section 24 and to the Reserve Fund under  section 25, the Corporation may, out of its annual net profits,</p>
              <p>declare a dividend.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Investment of surplus funds. All moneys belonging to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation which may not, for the time being be required by it shall  be-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>deposited with the Reserve Bank or with any agency of  the Reserve Bank or in consultation with the Reserve</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Bank with a Scheduled Bank, State Co- operative Bank or</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Central Co- operative Bank; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>invested in the securities of the Central Government or  any State Government or in securities in which a  trustee may invest money under clause (a), clause (b),</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>clause (bb), clause (c) or clause (d) of section 20 of  the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882); or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>utilised in such other manner as may be approved by  the Reserve Bank.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of moneys due to the Corporation. Where any amount  is due to the Corporation in respect of loans or advances or other  financial accommodation granted by it to any person, the Corporation  or any person authorised by it in writing in this behalf, may, without  prejudice to any other mode of recovery. make an application to the  appropriate Government for the recovery of the amount due to it, and  if the appropriate Government, or such authority, as that Government  may specify in this behalf, is satisfied, after following such  procedure as may be prescribed, that any amount is so due, it may  issue a certificate for that amount to the Collector, and the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector shall proceed to recover that amount in the same manner and  under the same conditions as if it were an arrear of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Acquisition or transfer by the Corporation of business,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>assets and liabilities from or to co- operative societies.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject  to the provisions of any law relating to co- operative societies for  the time being in force, the Corporation may-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>acquire the whole or any part of the business including  the assets and liabilities of a co- operative society;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>transfer the whole or any part of its business,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>including its assets or liabilities to a co- operative  society.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions relating to such acquisition or  transfer, if agreed upon by the Board and the co- operative society  concerned shall be submitted to the Reserve Bank for its approval and  that Bank may by order in writing (hereafter in this section referred   to as the order of approval) accord its approval thereto:</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that where such acquisition or transfer involves the  acquisition of the assets of the co- operative society or a transfer of  the liabilities of the Corporation to the co- operative society, no  such approval shall be accorded by the Reserve Bank, unless it is  satisfied that-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.2.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the co- operative society has given notice of the  proposed acquisition or transfer, in such manner as may  be provided under the law relating to co- operative  societies applicable to it, to all its members and  creditors, giving them the option, of demanding payment  of their share or dues, as the case may be, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>all the members and creditors have assented to the  proposal or deemed to have assented thereto by virtue  of any member or creditor failing to exercise his  option within such period as may be specified in  accordance with such law relating to co- operative  societies for the time being in force.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions as approved by the Reserve Bank  shall come into effect from the date specified by the Bank in this  behalf in the order of approval and be binding upon the Corporation  and its shareholders and creditors and if such law relating to co-</p>
              <p>operative societies so provides be binding also upon the co- operative  society and its shareholders and creditors.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If for any reason the terms and conditions cannot come into  effect on the date specified in the order of approval, the Reserve</p>
              <p>Bank may fix another suitable date for that purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the date on which the terms and conditions as aforesaid  come into effect, the business, assets and liabilities of the</p>
              <p>Corporation, or as the case may be, the co- operative society  concerned, shall, by virtue of and in accordance with the provisions  of the aforesaid order of approval, and if such law relating to co-</p>
              <p>operative societies so provides, stand transferred to, and become the  business, assets and liabilities of the co- operative society or the</p>
              <p>Corporation, as the case may be.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>GENERAL MEETINGS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>GENERAL MEETINGS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>General meetings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A general meeting (in this Act referred   to as an annual general meeting) of the Corporation shall be held at  the Head Office of the Corporation within three months from the date  on which the annual accounts of the Corporation are closed, and any  other general meeting may be convened by the Board at any other time:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Central Government may extend the time within  which any annual general meeting shall be held, by a period not  exceeding one month.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The shareholders present at an annual general meeting shall  be entitled to discuss the balance- sheet and profit and loss account  of the Corporation, the report of the Board on the working of the</p>
              <p>Corporation for the period covered by the accounts and the auditor' s  report on the balance- sheet and accounts.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND RETURNS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND RETURNS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Accounts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The balance- sheet and accounts including the  profit and loss account of the Corporation shall be prepared and  maintained in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall cause the books and accounts of the</p>
              <p>Corporation to be balanced and closed on the thirtieth day of June  each year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited  by an auditor duly qualified to act as auditor under sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>of section 226 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) who shall be  appointed by the Board with the previous approval of the Reserve Bank  and shall receive such remuneration from the Corporation as the Board  may with the approval of the Reserve Bank, fix:</p>
              <p>Provided that the first auditor shall be appointed by the Central</p>
              <p>Government within one month from the establishment of Corporation on  such terms and conditions as the Central Government may determine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor so appointed shall hold office from the  conclusion of the annual general meeting of the Corporation until the  conclusion of the next annual general meeting:</p>
              <p>Provided that the first auditor shall hold office until the  conclusion of the first annual general meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall supply its auditor with a copy of its  annual balance- sheet and it shall be the duty of the auditor to  examine such balance- sheet together with the accounts and vouchers  relating thereto and he shall have a list delivered to him of all  books kept by the Corporation and shall at all reasonable times have  access to the books, accounts, vouchers and other documents of the</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor may, in relation to the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Corporation of which he is the auditor, examine any director or any  officer or employee of the Corporation and shall be entitled to  require from the officers of the Corporation such information and  explanation as he may think necessary for the performance of his  duties.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.5.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The auditor shall make a report to the Corporation upon the  annual balance- sheet and accounts examined by him and in every such  report he shall state whether in his opinion the accounts exhibit a  true and fair view,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.5.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the balance- sheet, of the state of  affairs of the Corporation at the end of the year, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.5.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the profit and loss account, of the  profit or loss for the year, and, in case he had called  for any explanation or information from the Board,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>whether it has been given and whether it is  satisfactory.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to anything contained in the preceding  sub- sections, the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India may, if so  requested by the Central Government, examine and report upon the  accounts of the Corporation and any expenditure incurred by him in  connection with such examination and report shall be payable by such</p>
              <p>Corporation to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Returns.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall furnish, from time to  time, to the appropriate Government and to the Reserve Bank such  returns as the appropriate Government or the Reserve Bank may require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall furnish to all its shareholders within  three months from the date on which the annual accounts of the</p>
              <p>Corporation are closed, or within such further time not exceeding one  month as the Central Government may specify, a copy of the balance-</p>
              <p>sheet as at the close of that year and profit and loss account for the  year, the auditor' s report and a report of the Board on</p>
              <p>the working of the Corporation during the year, and copies of the said  balance- sheet, profit and loss account and reports shall be published  in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall furnish a statement in such form as may  be prescribed of its assets and liabilities as at the close of  business on the last Friday of each month or if that day is a public  holiday under the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (26 of 1881), as at  the close of business at the preceding working day, to the Reserve</p>
              <p>Bank within ten days from the date to which the statement relates.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>APPLICATION OF CERTAIN ACTS TO THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPLICATION OF CERTAIN ACTS TO THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Certain provisions of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949, to  apply to the Corporation. The provisions of sections 8, 9, 20, 20A,</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, 23, 24, 26, 34A,  excluding sub- section (4)], 35A, clause (a)</p>
              <p>of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 36, and sections 46, 47, 50, 53 and 54  of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949), shall apply to or  in relation to the Corporation as they apply to or in relation to co-</p>
              <p>operative banks.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Certain provisions of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2   of 1934), to apply to the Corporation. The provisions of sections 18  and 42 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934, shall apply to or in  relation to the Corporation as they apply to or in relation to a State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Co- operative Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and Banking Regulation Act,</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1949">
          <num>1949.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1949.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, not to apply except as otherwise provided. Save as otherwise  provided in this Act, nothing contained in the Reserve Bank of India</p>
              <p>Act, 1934 (2 of 1934), and the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1949">
          <num>1949.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1949.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), shall apply to or in relation to the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>The Bankers' Books Evidence Act, 1891 to apply. The Bankers'</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Books Evidence Act 1891 (18 of 1891), shall apply to or in relation  to the Corporation as it applies to or in relation to a bank as  defined in section 2 of that Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to be deemed to be a co- operative society for the  purposes of Income- tax Act, 1961. For the purposes of the Income- tax</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other enactment for the time being in  force relating to any tax on income, profits or gains the Corporation  shall be deemed to be a co- operative society.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Court, Tribunal, etc., not to require production of report on  inspection made by the Reserve Bank. Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), or any other  law for the time being in force, no Court, Tribunal or other authority  shall have power to require the Corporation, the Reserve Bank or any  officer of the Corporation or the Reserve Bank to produce before such</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court, Tribunal or other authority the report of any inspection, or  any copy thereof, made by the Reserve Bank in pursuance of section 35  of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949), as applied to the</p>
              <p>Corporation under section 34.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of fidelity and secrecy. Every director, member  of a committee, auditor, officer or other employee of the Corporation  shall, before entering upon his duties, make a declaration of fidelity  and secrecy in the form set out in the Schedule.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity of director.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every director shall be  indemnified by the Corporation against all losses and expenses  incurred by him in the discharge of his duties except such as are  caused by his own wilful act or default.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A director shall not be responsible for anything done or  omitted to be done by any other director or officer or other employee  of the Corporation or for any loss or expenses resulting to the</p>
              <p>Corporation by the insufficiency or deficiency of value of, or title  to, any property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the</p>
              <p>Corporation</p>
              <p>in good faith, or by the wrongful act of any auditor or any person  under obligation to the Corporation, or by anything done in good faith  in the execution of the duties of his office or in relation thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other  legal proceeding shall lie against the Corporation or the Central or</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government or the Reserve Bank or any director or officer of the</p>
              <p>Corporation or of the Central or State Government or of the Reserve</p>
              <p>Bank or any other person authorised by the Corporation to discharge  any functions under this Act, for any loss or damage caused or likely  to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done in pursuance of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Liquidation of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No provision of law  relating to the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to  the Corporation and the Corporation shall not be placed in liquidation  save by order of the Central Government made in consultation with the</p>
              <p>State Government and in such manner as it may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), any  order made by the Central Government for the liquidation of a</p>
              <p>Corporation may provide for all matters for effectively winding up the  affairs of the Corporation, including the repayment of capital,</p>
              <p>disposal of any fund established under this Act, the transfer of the  business, property, assets and liabilities, rights, interests,</p>
              <p>privileges and obligations of whatever nature of the Corporation to  such institution or institutions as the Central Government may direct  and payment, receipt or disposal of compensation arising out of such  transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Reserve Bank to submit report. The Reserve Bank shall, on the  expiry of a period of three years, from the date of establishment of  the Agricultural Credit Corporation in a State or Union territory and  thereafter at an interval of three years and within such time as the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government may specify, submit a report to that Government as  to the working of the Corporation and forward a copy thereof to the</p>
              <p>State Government concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Staff of the Corporation and delegation of powers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Corporation may appoint such officers, advisers and employees as it  considers necessary for the efficient performance of its function and  determine, by regulations or otherwise, their conditions of  appointment and service and the remuneration payable to them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, by general or special order, delegate to the</p>
              <p>Managing Director or to any other officer of the Corporation, subject  to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified, such  of its powers and duties under this Act as it may deem necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Powers of the Central Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make  rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-46.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-46.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>functions which shall be discharged by the Executive</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-46.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-46.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>rules of procedure with regard to the transaction of  business at a meeting of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-46.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>rules of procedure with regard to the transaction of  business at a meeting of any committee constituted by  the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-46.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed by the appropriate</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-46.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government or the authority specified by the  appropriate Government for issuing the certificate  under section 28;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-46.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the general meeting shall be  convened, the quorum therefor, the procedure to be  followed thereat and the manner in which voting rights  may be exercised;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-46.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>form and manner in which accounts shall be maintained  the balance- sheet and profit and loss account shall be  prepared;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-46.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>form in which statement of assets and liabilities shall  be furnished;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-46.2.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be  prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised  in one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if,</p>
              <p>before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or  the successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Power of the Board to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board    after consultation with the Reserve Bank, may, by notification in  the Official Gazette"] make regulations not inconsistent with the  provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, to provide for  all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the  purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing provisions, such regulations may provide for all or any of  the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>duties which the managing director shall perform;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fees and allowances which may be paid to every director  for attending any meeting of the Board or any committee  thereof or for attending to any other work of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-47.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>duties, conduct, salaries and allowances and conditions  of service of officers and other employees of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-47.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>establishment and maintenance of provident and other  benefit funds for the employees of the Corporation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the delegation of powers and functions to the officers  and employees of the Corporation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the purposes connected with agricultural purposes for  which the Corporation may grant loans and advances;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which the amount in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-47.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Stabilisation Fund may be utilised;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.2.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the amount in the Reserve Fund may  be utilised;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>conditions which the Corporation may impose on any loan  or advance made by it;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list7.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is, or may be, necessary for the  efficient conduct of the affairs of the Corporation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank may at any time within three months from the commencement  of this Act make regulations with regard to any of the matters  specified in sub- section (2) but the regulations so made may</p>
              <p>be rescinded or modified by the Board in exercise of the powers  conferred on it by sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as  soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation, or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Act 10 of 1963. In clause (f) of section 2 of  the Agricultural Refinance Corporation Act, 1963, after sub- clause</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-48.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>, the following sub- clause shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>" (iii) an Agricultural Credit Corporation established under  section 3 of the State Agricultural Credit Corporations</p>
              <p>Act, 1968 (60 of 1968.)".</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
