<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/22"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Rampur Raza Library Act, 1975"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/22/eng@1975-05-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/22/eng@1975-05-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1975-05-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1975/22/eng@1975-05-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1975/22/eng@1975-05-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Rampur Raza Library Act, 1975</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 22 OF 1975</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 9th May, 1975.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the Rampur Raza Library to be an institution of  national importance and to provide for its administration and matters  connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Rampur Raza Library Act, 1975.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of Rampur Raza Library as an institution of  national importance. It is hereby declared that the Rampur Raza</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Library, at Rampur, is an institution of national importance.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Board" means the Board established under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" deed of trust" means the deed of trust executed by the  late Nawab Sir Syed Raza Ali Khan Bahadur of Rampur, on  the 6th August, 1951, and registered as No. 103, Book</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>IV, Volume No. 8, on pages 74 to 93 of the Office of  the officiating Chief Sub- Registrar, Rampur;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Fund" means the Fund referred to in section 19;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" library" means the Rampur Raza Library, which is  declared by this Act to be an institution of national  importance;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman, and also includes the Vice- Chairman, if any;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Rampur" means the headquarters of the District of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Rampur in the State of Uttar Pradesh;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" State Government" means the Government of the State of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Uttar Pradesh.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>RAMPUR RAZA LIBRARY BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>RAMPUR RAZA LIBRARY BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and incorporation of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from  such date  as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be established, for the  purposes of this Act, a Board, to be known as the" Rampur Raza Library</p>
              <p>Board".</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid,</p>
              <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to  the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property  and to contract, and may, by that name, sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Composition of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the  following persons, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Governor of the State of Uttar Pradesh, ex officio,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>who shall be the Chairman;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Shri Syed Murtaza Ali Khan, for life, who shall be the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Vice- Chairman;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Colonel Bashir Hussain Zaidi, for life;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Accountant- General, Uttar Pradesh, ex officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>a descendant of the late Nawab Sir Syed Raza Ali Khan</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Bahadur of Rampur, to be nominated by the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>four persons to be nominated by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Government, out of whom-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>two shall be persons who, in the opinion  of the Central Government, have expert knowledge  with regard to the collections in the library or  are distinguished historians or scholars of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list12">
                <listIntroduction>Arabic, Persian or Urdu,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list12.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>one shall be an officer, not below the  rank of a Deputy Secretary to the Government of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list14">
                <listIntroduction>India in the Department dealing with matters  connected with the library,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list14.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>one shall be a person who, in the  opinion of the Central Government, has expert  knowledge of, and experience in, management of  public libraries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list14.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the Collector and District Magistrate, Rampur, ex  officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list14.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>three other persons, of whom at least two shall be  scholars of repute, to be nominated by the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list16">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list16.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Director of the Library, ex officio, who shall be  the Member- Secretary.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every nomination made under this section shall be notified by  the Central Government in the Official Gazette and every nomination so  notified shall take effect from the date of the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and fresh nomination in certain cases.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  term of office of nominated members shall be such as may be  prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any nominated member may resign his office by giving notice  in writing to the Government nominating him, and on such resignation  being notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette, he  shall be deemed to have vacated his office on the date of publication  of such notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the office of any nominated member is vacated before the  expiry of the term of his office, the resulting vacancy may be filled  by fresh nomination by the Government by which such member was  nominated, and the member so nominated shall hold office for the  remainder of the term of office of the member in whose place he is  nominated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re- nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any nominated member is, by infirmity or otherwise,</p>
              <p>rendered temporarily incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent  on leave or otherwise in circumstances not involving the vacation of  his office, the Central Government or the State Government, as the  case may be, may nominate another person to act in his place during  his absence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts. No act of the Board  shall be invalid merely by reason of-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Board, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the nomination of a person acting as a  member thereof, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the  merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Duty of Government nominating persons.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before nominating a  person to be a member of the Board, the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>State Government, as the case may be, shall satisfy itself that the  person will have no such financial or other interest as is likely to  affect prejudicially the exercise or performance by him of his  functions as a member, and the Central Government or the State</p>
              <p>Government, as the case may be, shall also satisfy itself from time to  time with respect to every member nominated by it that he has no such  interest; and any person who is or whom the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>State Government, as the case may be, proposes to nominate and who has  consented to be a member shall, whenever requested by the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the State Government so to do, furnish to it such  information with regard to his financial or other interest in the  library as that Government considers necessary for the performance by  it of its duties under this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A nominated member who is, in any way, whether directly or  indirectly, concerned or interested in a contract or arrangement or  proposed contract or arrangement, entered into or to be entered into,</p>
              <p>by or on behalf of the Board shall, as soon as possible, after  relevant circumstances have come to his knowledge, disclose the nature  of his concern or interest at a meeting of the Board and the  disclosure shall be recorded in the minutes of the Board and the  member shall not take any part after such disclosure in the  discussion, or vote, on the contract or arrangement; and if he does  vote, his vote shall be void.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall meet at such times and  places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2), (3)</p>
              <p>and (4), observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction  of business at its meetings (including the quorum at meetings) as may  be provided by regulations made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or, in his absence, the Vice- Chairman, if any,</p>
              <p>or in the absence of both, any member chosen by the members</p>
              <p>present from amongst themselves, shall preside at a meeting of the</p>
              <p>Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If an officer of Government who is nominated as a member of  the Board by virtue of his office is unable to attend any meeting of  the Board, he may, with the previous approval of the Chairman,</p>
              <p>authorise in writing, any person to attend that meeting, but the  person so authorised shall not be entitled to vote at that meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions at a meeting of the Board shall be decided by a  majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in the  case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or, in his absence, the</p>
              <p>Vice- Chairman, if any, or, in the absence of both, the member  presiding shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Temporary association of persons with Board for particular  purposes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may associate with itself in such manner and  for such purposes as may be provided by regulations made under this</p>
              <p>Act, any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to have with  regard to the performance of any of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person associated with it by the Board under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the  discussions of the Board relating to that purpose, but shall not, by  virtue of this section, be entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Authentication of orders and other instruments of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>all orders and decisions of the Board shall be authenticated by the  signature of the Chairman or the Vice- Chairman, if any, or any other  member authorised by the Board in this behalf, and all other  instruments issued by the Board shall be authenticated by the  signature of an officer of the Board authorised in like manner in this  behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Orders, decisions or instruments authenticated in accordance  with the provisions of sub- section (1) shall be evidence of the  matters recorded therein and shall be admissible in evidence  notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872</p>
              <p>(1 of 1872), or in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any member, officer or other employee of the Board or any  other person interested in the library shall be entitled to be  furnished, within seven days after he has made a request in that  behalf to the library, with a copy of the order, decision or  instrument authenticated in the manner specified in sub- section (1),</p>
              <p>on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Staff of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the Board may, for the purpose of enabling it efficiently to  perform its functions under this Act, appoint such number of officers  and other employees as it may think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The recruitment and conditions of service of such officers  and employees shall be such as may be provided by regulations made  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of service of existing employees to Board. Subject  to the provisions of this Act, every person employed in the library  immediately before the date of establishment of the Board shall, on  and from such date, become an employee of the Board with such  designation as the Board may determine and shall hold his office or  service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon  the same terms and conditions as he would have held the same on such  date if the Board had not been established and shall continue to do so  unless and until his employment in the Board is duly terminated or  until such tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly  altered by the Board:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions  of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage  without the previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Location of library. The library and the collections thereof  shall continue to be located at Rampur.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROPERTY, LIABILITIES AND FUNCTIONS OF BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROPERTY, LIABILITIES AND FUNCTIONS OF BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Properties and liabilities of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On the establishment  of the Board-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>all properties, funds and dues which are vested in, or  realisable by, the trustees of the library constituted  by the deed of trust, in their capacity as such, shall  vest in, and be realisable by, the Board; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>all liabilities in relation to the library, which are  enforceable against the said trustees, shall be  enforceable only against the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All properties, which may, after the establishment of the</p>
              <p>Board, be given, bequeathed or otherwise transferred to the library or  acquired by the Board, shall vest in the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of the deed of  trust, it shall be the general duty of the Board to manage the library  and to plan, promote, organise and implement programmes for the  development of the library on modern scientific lines (including  provision of adequate facilities for preservation and photo-</p>
              <p>duplication of rare manuscripts) and to perform such other functions  as the Central Government may, from time to time, assign to the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing provisions, the Board may take such steps as it thinks fit--</p>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to provide for instruction and research in matters  relating to libraries and for the advancement of  learning and dissemination of knowledge in such  matters;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to protect, enlarge and improve the collections in the  library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to promote study and research and to provide facilities  to scholars for this purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to do all such other things as may be necessary for the  discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such conditions and  restrictions as the Central Government may think fit to impose, the</p>
              <p>Board may exercise all such powers as may be necessary or expedient  for the purpose of carrying out its functions and duties under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such regulations as may be made by the Board in  this behalf, the Board may, from time to time, purchase or otherwise  acquire such manuscripts, books, articles or things as may, in the  opinion of the Board, be worthy of preservation in the library.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Grants by Central Government to Board. For the purpose of  enabling the Board to discharge its functions efficiently under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by</p>
              <p>Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the Board in each financial  year such sums of money as that Government considers necessary by way  of grant, loan or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Fund of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall maintain a Fund to which  shall be credited-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all moneys paid to it by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such sums of money as the State Government may pay  annually for specified purposes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all fees and other charges levied by it under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all moneys received by the Board by way of grant, gift,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>donation, benefaction, bequest, subscription,</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>contribution or transfer;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.1.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>all other moneys received by the Board in any other  manner or from any other source.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for  performing its functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated  as expenditure payable out of the Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A sum of money, not exceeding such sum as may be specified by  regulations made under this Act, shall be kept in current account with  any nationalised bank, or any other scheduled or other bank approved  by the Central Government in this behalf, but any moneys in excess of  that sum shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or with the  agents of the Reserve Bank of India or invested in such manner as may  be generally or specially approved by the Central Government.</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.3.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- In this sub- section,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.3.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" nationalised bank" means a corresponding new bank as  defined in the Banking companies (Acquisition and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.3.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.3.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" scheduled bank" means a bank included for the time  being in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Budget.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall, by such date in each financial  year as may be specified by the Central Government, submit to it for  approval a budget for the next financial year in the form specified by  that Government, showing therein the estimated receipts and  expenditure, and the sums which would be required from the Central</p>
              <p>Government during that financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The budget for a financial year, as approved by the Central</p>
              <p>Government for any financial year, shall be the budget of the library  for that financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any sum granted by the Central Government to the library  for any financial year remains wholly or partly unspent in that  financial year, the unspent sum may be carried forward to the next  financial year and taken into account in determining the sum to be  provided for by the Central Government for that year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (5), no sum shall be  expended by or on behalf of the Board, unless the expenditure is  covered by provision in the budget approved by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such conditions and restrictions as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may think fit to impose, the Board may sanction any re-</p>
              <p>appropriation from one head of expenditure to another or from a  provision made for one purpose to that for another purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts, including the balance- sheet in such form as may be  specified, in accordance with such general directions as may be issued  by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and</p>
              <p>Auditor- General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any officer authorised by  him in this behalf, and any expenditure incurred by him in connection  with such audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and</p>
              <p>Auditor- General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  authorised by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Board shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
              <p>India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
              <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect the office of the Board, and the library.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board, as certified by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India or any other person authorised by him in  this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be  forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government  shall, as soon as may be after the receipt thereof, cause the same to  be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall furnish to the</p>
              <p>Central Government, at such time and in such form and in such manner  as the Central Government may direct, such returns, statements and  particulars as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
              <p>Board shall, as soon as possible after the commencement of each  financial year, submit to the Central Government, within such time as  may be specified by the Central Government, a report giving true and  full account of the activities of the Board during the previous  financial year and an account of activities likely to be undertaken  during the current financial year.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions to Board. In  the discharge of its functions under this Act, the Board shall be  bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may give to it from time to time:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Board shall be given an opportunity to express  its views before any direction is given to it under this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers and duties. The Board may, by general or  special order in writing, direct that all or any of the powers or  duties, which may be exercised or discharged by it, shall, in such  circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified  in the order, be exercised or discharged also by any member, officer  or employee of the Board specified in this behalf in the order.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Officers and employees of Board to be public servants. Every  officer or employee of the Board shall, when acting or purporting to  act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or  regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be a public servant within  the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860.)</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken under the Act. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or  any member, officer or other employee of the Board for anything which  is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act  or of any rule or regulation made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to  give effect to the provisions of this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that when the Board has been established, no such rules  shall be made without consulting the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, the members nominated under clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>, clause (f) or clause (h) of sub- section (1) of  section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the travelling and other allowances payable to a member  other than the Chairman and to a person associated with  the Board under section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the disqualifications for membership of the Board and  the procedure to be followed in removing a member who  is or becomes subject to any disqualification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of on effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, with  the previous approval of the Central Government  by notification in  the Official Gazette,] make regulations, not inconsistent with the  provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, with regard to  the discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the conditions and restrictions subject to which  manuscripts and books in the library may be used;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which, and the purposes for which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>persons may be associated with the Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the time and place of meetings of the Board, the  procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction  of business at such meetings and the quorum necessary  for the transaction of business at a meeting of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the Board and  the transmission of copies thereof to the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the recruitment and conditions of service of officers  and other employees of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the maximum amount that may be kept by the Board in a  current account;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of registers and accounts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the compilation of catalogues and inventories of the  manuscripts, books and other articles and things in the  library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the steps to be taken for the preservation of the  manuscripts, books and other articles and things in the  library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the general management of the library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the fees and other charges to be levied for the use of  any manuscript or book in the library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list10.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>any other matter in respect of which provision is, in  the opinion of the Board, necessary for the performance  of its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, after consultation with the</p>
              <p>Board, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend, vary or rescind  any regulation which it has approved and thereupon the regulation  shall have effect as so amended or varied or be of no effect, as the  case may be, but without prejudice to the exercise of the powers of  the Board under sub- sections (1) and (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every regulation made under this section shall be laid,</p>
              <p>as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Act to override other enactments and instruments. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any law other than this Act for  the time being in force or any instrument having effect by virtue of  any enactment other than this Act.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
