<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Asian Development Bank Act, 1966"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/18/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/18/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/18/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/18/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Asian Development Bank Act, 1966</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Asian Development Bank Act, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Agreement” means the Agreement for the establishment and operation of the international body known as the Asian Development Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Bank” means the Asian Development Bank established under the Agreement.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Payments to Bank.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be paid out of the Consolidated Fund of India, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, all such sums as may, from time to time, be required for the purpose of paying,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the subscriptions payable by the Central Government to the Bank under paragraphs 1, 2 and 3 of Article 5 of the Agreement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any commission, fees or other charges payable by the Central Government to the Bank under Article 16 of the Agreement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any sums payable by the Central Government to the Bank under paragraph 1 of Article 25 of the Agreement.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, if it thinks fit so to do, create and issue to the Bank, in such form as it thinks fit, any such non-interest bearing and non-negotiable notes or other obligations as are provided for by paragraph 3 of Article 6 of the Agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Reserve bank to be depository for Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Reserve Bank of India shall be the depository of the Indian currency holdings of the Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Conferment of status and certain immunities, exemptions and privileges on Bank and conferment of certain immunities, exemptions and privileges on its officers and employees.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law, the provisions of the Agreement set out in the Schedule shall have the force of law in India:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing in Article 56 of the Agreement shall be construed as—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>entitling the bank to import into India goods free of any duty of customs without any restriction on their subsequent sale therein; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>conferring on the Bank any exemption from duties or taxes which form part of the price of goods sold; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>conferring on the Bank any exemption from duties or taxes which are in fact no more than charges for services rendered.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity with any amendments, duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the Agreement set out therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Notifications issued under section 5 and rules made under section 6 to be laid before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued under sub-section (2) of section 5 and every rule made under section 6 shall be laid as soon as may be after it is issued or made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification or, as the case may be, in the rule, or both Houses agree that the notification or rule should not be issued or made, the notification or rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that notification or rule.</p>
            <p>The ASIan development bank act, 1966</p>
            <p>The Schedule</p>
            <p>(See section 5)</p>
            <p>Provisions of the Agreement which shall have force of law</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Status, Immunities, Exemptions and Privileges</p>
            <p>Article 48</p>
            <p>Purpose or Chapter</p>
            <p>To enable the Bank effectively, to fulfill its purpose and carry out he functions entrusted to it, the status, immunities, exemptions and privileges set forth in this Chapter shall be accorded to the Bank in the territory of each member.</p>
            <p>Article 49</p>
            <p>Legal Status</p>
            <blockList id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>The Bank shall possess full juridical personality and, in particular, full capacity:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to contract;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0.list7.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to acquire, and dispose of, immovable and movable property; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0.list7.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to institute legal proceedings.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Article 50</p>
            <p>Immunity from judicial proceedings</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>The Bank shall enjoy immunity form every form of legal process, except in cases arising out of or in connection with the exercise of its powers to borrow money, to guarantee obligations, or to buy and sell or under-write the sale of securities, in which cases actions may be brought against the Bank in a court of competent jurisdiction in the territory of a country in which the Bank has its principal or a branch office, or has appointed an agent for the purpose of accepting service or notice of process, or has issued or guaranteed securities.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 1 of this Article, no action shall be brought against the Bank by any member, or by any agency or instrumentality of a member, or by any entity or person directly or indirectly acting for or deriving claims from a member or from any agency or instrumentality of a member. Members shall have recourse to such special procedures for the settlement of controversies between the Bank and its members as may be prescribed in this Agreement, in the by-laws and regulations of the Bank, or in contracts entered into with the Bank.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Property and assets of the Bank shall, wheresoever located and by whomsoever held, be immune from all forms of seizure, attachment or execution before the delivery of final judgment against the Bank.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Article 51</p>
              <p>Immunity of Assets</p>
              <p>Property and assets of the Bank wheresoever located and by whomsoever held, shall be immune from search, requisition, confiscation, expropriation or any other form of taking or foreclosure by executive or legislative action.</p>
              <p>Article 52</p>
              <p>Immunity of Archives</p>
              <p>The archives of the Bank and, in general, all documents belonging to it, or held by it, shall be inviolable wherever located.</p>
              <p>Article 53</p>
              <p>Freedom of Assets From Restrictions</p>
              <p>To the extent necessary to carry out the purpose and functions of the bank effectively, and subject to provisions of this Agreement, all property and assets of the Bank shall be free from restrictions, regulations, controls and moratoria of any nature.</p>
              <p>Article 54</p>
              <p>Privilege for communications</p>
              <p>Official communications of the Bank shall be accorded by each member treatment not less favorable than that it accords to the official communications of any other member.</p>
              <p>Article 55</p>
              <p>Immunities and Privileges of Bank personnel</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15">
                <listIntroduction>All Governors, Directors, alternates officers and employees of the Bank, including experts performing missions for the Bank:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>shall be immune from legal process with respect to acts performed by them in their official capacity except when the Bank waives the immunity;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>where they are not local citizens or nationals, shall be accorded the same immunities from immigration restrictions, alien registration requirements and national service obligations, and the same facilities as regards exchange regulations, as are accorded by members to the representatives, officials and employees of comparable rank of other members; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>shall be granted the same treatment in respect of travelling facilities as is accorded by members to representatives, officials and employees of comparable rank of other members.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Article 56</p>
              <p>Exemption from taxation</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>The Bank, its assets, property, income and its operations and transactions, shall be exempt from all taxation and from all customs duties. The Bank shall also be exempt from any obligation for the payment, withholding or collection of any tax or duty.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>No tax shall be levied on or in respect of salaries and emoluments paid by the Bank to Directors, alternates, officers or employees of the Bank, including experts performing missions for the Bank, except where a member deposits with its instrument of ratification or acceptance a declaration that such member retains for itself and its political sub-divisions the right to tax salaries and emoluments paid by the Bank to citizens or nationals of such member.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>No tax of any kind shall be levied on any obligation or security issued by the Bank, including any dividend or interest thereon, by whomsoever held:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>which discriminates against such obligations or security solely because it is issued by the Bank; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>if the sole jurisdictional basis for such taxation is the place or currency in which it is issued, made payable or paid, or the location of any office or of place of business maintained by the Bank.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>No tax of any kind shall be levied on any obligation or security guaranteed by the Bank, including any dividend or interest thereon, by whomsoever held:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>which discriminates against such obligation or security solely because it is guaranteed by the Bank; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>if the sole jurisdictional basis for such taxation is the location of any office or place of business maintained by the Bank</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Article 58</p>
              <p>Waiver or immunities, exemptions and Privileges</p>
              <p>The Bank at its discretion may waive any of the privileges, immunities and exemptions conferred under this Chapter in any case or instance, in such manner and upon such conditions as it may determine to be appropriate in the best interest of the Bank.</p>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
