<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1867/25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1867/25"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Press And Registration Of Books Act, 1867"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1867/25/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1867/25/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1867/25/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1867/25/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Press And Registration Of Books Act, 1867</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation-clause.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless there shall be something repugnant in the subject or context,—</p>
            <p>“Book” includes every volume, part or division of a volume, and pamphlet, in any language, and every sheet of music, map, chart or plan separately printed ***;</p>
            <p>***</p>
            <p>“editor” means the person who controls the selection of the matter that is published in a newspaper;</p>
            <p>*** ***"</p>
            <p>“Magistrate” means any person exercising the full powers of a</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6Magistrate">
        <num>6Magistrate.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-6Magistrate.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, and includes a Magistrate of police ***;</p>
            <p>“newspaper” means any printed periodical work containing public news or comments on public news;</p>
            <p>***</p>
            <p>“paper” means any document, including a newspaper, other than a book;</p>
            <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made by the Central Government under section 20A;</p>
            <p>“Press Registrar” means the Registrar of newspapers for India appointed by the Central Government under section 19A and includes any other person appointed by the Central Government to perform all or any of the functions of the Press Registrar;</p>
            <p>“printing” includes cyclostyling and printing by lithography;</p>
            <p>“Register” means the Register of newspapers maintained under section 19B.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6Magistrate.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law in force in that State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Act 11 of 1835.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of 1870), sec. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Particulars to be printed on books and papers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every book or paper printed within India shall have printed legibly on it the name of the printer and the place of printing, and (if the book or paper be published) the name of the publisher, and the place of publication.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Keeper of printing press to make declaration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall within India, keep in his possession any press for the printing of books or papers, who shall not have made and subscribed the following declaration before</p>
            <p>the District, Presidency or Sub-divisional Magistrate within whose local jurisdiction such press may be:</p>
            <p>“I, A.B., declare that I have a press for printing at—”.</p>
            <p>And this last blank shall be filled up with a true and precise description of the place where such press may be situate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As often as the place where a press is kept is changed, a new declaration shall be necessary:</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where the change is for a period not exceeding sixty days and the place where the press is kept after the change is within the local jurisdiction of the Magistrate referred to in sub-section (1), no new declaration shall be necessary if—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a statement relating to the change is furnished to the said Magistrate within twenty-four hours thereof; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the keeper of the press continues to be the same.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Rules as to publication of newspapers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No newspaper shall be published in India, except in conformity with the rules hereinafter laid down:</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 3, every copy of every such newspaper shall contain the names of the owner and editor thereof printed clearly on such copy and also the date of its publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The printer and the publisher of every such newspaper shall appear in person or by agent authorised in this behalf in accordance with rules made under section 20, before a District, Presidency or Sub-divisional Magistrate within whose local jurisdiction such newspaper shall be printed or published [*** and shall make and subscribe, in duplicate, the following declaration:</p>
            <p>“I A.B., declare that I am the printer (or publisher, or printer and publisher) of the newspaper entitled—and to be printed or published, or to be printed and published, as the case may be at—”.</p>
            <p>And the last blank in this form of declaration shall be filled up with a true and precise account of the premises where the printing or publication is conducted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every declaration under rule (2) shall specify the title of the newspaper, the language in which it is to be published and the periodicity of its publication and shall contain such other particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2B">
          <num>(2B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the printer or publisher of a newspaper making a declaration under rule (2) is not the owner thereof, the declaration shall specify the name of the owner and shall also be accompanied by an authority in writing from the owner authorising such person to make and subscribe such declaration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2C">
          <num>(2C)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A declaration in respect of a newspaper made under rule (2) and authenticated under section 6 shall be necessary before the newspaper can be published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2D">
          <num>(2D)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the title of any newspaper or its language or the periodicity of its publication is changed, the declaration shall cease to have effect and a new declaration shall be necessary before the publication of the newspaper can be continued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2E">
          <num>(2E)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As often as the ownership of a newspaper is changed, a new declaration shall be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As often as the place of printing or publication is changed, a new declaration shall be necessary:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where the change is for a period not exceeding thirty days and the place of printing or publication after the change is within the local jurisdiction of the Magistrate referred to in rule (2), no new declaration shall be necessary if—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a statement relating to the change is furnished to the said Magistrate within twenty-four hours thereof; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the printer or publisher or the printer and publisher of the newspaper continues to be the same.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As often as the printer or the publisher who shall have made such declaration as is aforesaid shall leave India for a period exceeding ninety days or where such printer or publisher is by infirmity or otherwise rendered incapable of carrying out his duties for a period exceeding ninety days in circumstances not involving the vacation of his appointment, a new declaration shall be necessary.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every declaration made in respect of a newspaper shall be void, where the newspaper does not commence publication—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>within six weeks of the authentication of the declaration under section 6, in the case of a newspaper to be published once a week or oftener; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>within three months [of the authentication of the declaration under section 6, in the case of any other newspaper,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and in every such case, a new declaration shall be necessary before the newspaper can be published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, in any period of three months, any daily, tri-weekly, bi-weekly, weekly or fortnightly newspaper publishes issues the number of which is less than half of what should have been published in accordance with the declaration made in respect thereof, the declaration shall cease to have effect and a new declaration shall be necessary before the publication of the newspaper can be continued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any other newspaper has ceased publication for a period, exceeding twelve months, every declaration made in respect thereof shall cease to have effect, and a new declaration shall be necessary before the newspaper can be re-published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every existing declaration in respect of a newspaper shall be cancelled by the Magistrate before whom a new declaration is made and subscribed in respect of the same:]</p>
            <p>Provided that no person who does not ordinarily reside in India, or who has not attained majority in accordance with the provisions of the Indian Majority Act, 1875 (9 of 1875), or of the law to which he is subject in respect of the attainment of majority, shall be permitted to make the declaration prescribed by this section, nor shall any such person edit a newspaper.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Keepers of printing presses and printers and publishers of newspapers in Jammu and Kashmir to make and subscribe fresh declarations within specified period.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person who has made and subscribed a declaration in respect of any press under section 4 of the Jammu and Kashmir State Press and Publications Act, S. 1989 (Jammu and Kashmir Act, No. I of S. 1989) shall keep the press in his possession for the printing of books or papers [after the 31st day of December, 1968, unless before the expiry of that date he makes and subscribes a fresh declaration in respect of that press under section 4 of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person who has subscribed to any declaration in respect of a newspaper under section 5 of the Jammu and Kashmir State Press and Publications Act, S. 1989 (Jammu and Kashmir Act, No. 1 of S. 1989) shall cease to be the editor, printer or publisher of the newspaper mentioned in such declaration</p>
            <p>after the 31st day of December, 1968 unless before the expiry of that date he makes and subscribes a fresh declaration in respect of that newspaper under rule (2) of the rules laid down in section 5 of this Act.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Authentication of declaration.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Each of the two originals of every declaration so made and subscribed as is aforesaid, shall be authenticated by the signature and official seal of the Magistrate before whom the said declaration shall have been made:</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where any declaration is made and subscribed under section 5 in respect of a newspaper, the declaration shall not, save in the case of newspapers owned by the same person, be so authenticated unless the Magistrate is, on inquiry from the Press Registrar, satisfied that the newspaper proposed to be published does not bear a title which is the same as, or similar to, that of any other newspaper published either in the same language or in the same State.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2.Deposit">
                <num>(Deposit)</num>
                <p>—One of the said originals shall be deposited among the records of the office of the Magistrate, and the other shall be deposited among the records of the High Court of Judicature, or other principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction for the place where the said declaration shall have been made.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Inspection and supply of copies.—</p>
            <p>The Officer-in -charge of each original shall allow any person to inspect that original on payment of a fee of one rupee, and shall give to any person applying a copy of the said declaration, attested by the seal of the Court which has the custody of the original, on payment of a fee of two rupees.</p>
            <p>A copy of the declaration attested by the official seal of the Magistrate, or a copy of the order refusing to authenticate the declaration, shall be forwarded as soon as possible to the person making and subscribing the declaration and also to the Press Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Office copy of declaration to be prima facie evidence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In any legal proceeding whatever, as well civil as criminal, the production of a copy of such declaration as is aforesaid, attested by the seal of some Court empowered by this Act to have the custody of such declarations,</p>
            <p>or, in the case of the editor, a copy of the newspaper containing his name printed on it as that of the editor shall be held (unless the contrary be proved) to be suficient evidence, as against the person whose name shall be subscribed to such declaration,</p>
            <p>or printed on such newspaper, as the case may be that the said person was printer or publisher, or printer and publisher (according as the words of the said declaration may be) of every portion of every</p>
            <p>newspaper whereof the title shall correspond with the title of the</p>
            <p>newspaper mentioned in the declaration,</p>
            <p>or the editor of every portion of that issue of the newspaper of which a copy is produced.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>New declaration by persons who have signed a declaration and subsequently ceased to be printers or publishers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person has subscribed to any declaration in respect of a newspaper under section 5 and the declaration has been authenticated by a Magistrate under section 6 and subsequently that person ceases to be the printer or publisher of the newspaper mentioned in such declaration, he shall appear before any District, Presidency or Sub-divisional Magistrate, and make and subscribe in duplicate the following declaration:—</p>
            <p>“I, A.B., declare that I have ceased to be the printer or publisher or printer and publisher of the newspaper entitled—”.</p>
            <p>Authentication and filing.—</p>
            <p>Each original of the latter declaration shall be authenticated by the signature and seal of the Magistrate before whom the said latter declaration shall have been made, and one original of the said latter declaration shall be filed along with each original of the former declaration.</p>
            <p>Inspection and supply of copies.—</p>
            <p>The Officer-in-charge of each original of the latter declaration shall allow any person applying to inspect that original on payment of a fee of one rupee, and shall give to any person applying a copy of the said latter declaration, attested by the seal of the Court having custody of the original, on payment of a fee of two rupees.</p>
            <p>Putting copy in evidence.—</p>
            <p>In all trials in which a copy, attested as is aforesaid, of the former declaration shall have been put in evidence, it shall be lawful to put in evidence a copy, attested as is aforesaid, of the latter declaration, and the former declaration shall not be taken to be evidence that the declarant was, at any period subsequent to the date of the latter declaration, printer or publisher of the newspaper therein mentioned.</p>
            <p>A copy of the latter declaration attested by the official seal of the Magistrate shall be forwarded to the Press Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Person whose name has been incorrectly published as editor may make a declaration before a Magistrate.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person, whose name has appeared as editor on a copy of a newspaper, claims that he was not the editor of the issue on which his name has so appeared, he may, within two weeks of his becoming aware that his name has been so published, appear before a District, Presidency or Sub-Divisional Magistrate and make a declaration that his name was incorrectly published in that issue as that of the editor thereof, and if the Magistrate after making such inquiry or causing such inquiry to be made as he may consider necessary is satisfied that such declaration is true, he shall certify accordingly, and on that certificate being given the provisions of section 7 shall not apply to that person in respect of that issue of the newspaper.</p>
            <p>The Magistrate may extend the period allowed by this section in any case where he is satisfied that such person was prevented by sufficient cause from appearing and making the declaration within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8B">
        <num>8B.</num>
        <heading>Cancellation of declaration.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, on an application made to him by the Press Registrar or any other person or otherwise, the Magistrate empowered to authenticate a declaration under this Act, is of opinion that any declaration made in respect of a newspaper should be cancelled, he may, after giving the person concerned an opportunity of showing cause against the action proposed to be taken, hold an inquiry into the matter and if, after considering the cause, if any, shown by such person and after giving him an opportunity of being heard, he is satisfied that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the newspaper, in respect of which the declaration has been made is being published in contravention of the provisions of this Act or rules made thereunder; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the newspaper mentioned in the declaration bears a title which is the same as, or similar to, that of any other newspaper published either in the same language or in the same State; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the printer or publisher has ceased to be the printer or publisher of the newspaper mentioned in such declaration; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the declaration was made on false representation or on the concealment of any material fact or in respect of a periodical work which is not a newspaper;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Magistrate may, by order, cancel the declaration and shall forward as soon as possible a copy of the order to the person making or subscribing the declaration and also to the Press Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8C">
        <num>8C.</num>
        <heading>Appeal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of a Magistrate refusing to authenticate a declaration under section 6 or cancelling a declaration under section 8B may, within sixty days from the date on which such order is communicated to him, prefer an appeal to the Appellate Board to be called the Press and Registration Appellate Board consisting of a Chairman and another member to be nominated by the Press Council of India, established under section 4 of the Press Council Act, 1978 (37 of 1978), from among its members:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Appellate Board may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an appeal under this section, the Appellate Board may, after calling for the records from the Magistrate and after making such further inquiries as it thinks fit, confirm, modify or set aside the order appealed against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (2), the Appellate Board may, by order, regulate its practice and procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8C.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Appellate Board shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Copies of books printed after commencement of Act to be delivered gratis to Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Printed *** copies of the whole of every book which shall be printed *** in India after this Act shall come into force, together with all maps, prints or other engravings belonging thereto, finished and coloured in the same manner as the best copies of the same, shall, notwithstanding any agreement (if the book be published) between the printer and publisher thereof, be delivered by the printer at such place and to such officer as the State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, from time to time direct, and free of expense to the Government, as follows, that is to say:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any case, within one calendar month after the day on which any such book shall first be delivered out of the press, one such copy, and,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if within one calendar year from such day the State Government shall require the printer to deliver other such copies not exceeding two in number, then within one calendar month after the day on which any such requisition shall be made by the State Government on the printer, another such copy, or two other such copies, as the State Government may direct,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the copies so delivered being bound, sewed or stitched together and upon the best paper on which any copies of the book shall be printed</p>
            <p>***.</p>
            <p>The publisher or other person employing the printer shall, at a reasonable time before the expiration of the said month, supply him with all maps, prints and engravings finished and coloured as aforesaid, which may be necessary to enable him to comply with the requirements aforesaid.</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in the former part of this section shall apply to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any second or subsequent edition of a book in which edition no additions or alterations either in the letter-press or in the maps, prints or other engravings belonging to the book have been made, and a copy of the first or some preceding edition of which book has been delivered under this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any newspaper published in conformity with the rules laid down in section 5 of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Receipt for copies delivered under section 9.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The officer to whom a copy of a book is delivered under the last foregoing section shall give to the printer a receipt in writing therefor. foregoing section shall give to the printer a receipt in writing therefor."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of copies delivered under section 9.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The copy delivered pursuant to clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of the first paragraph of section 9 of this Act shall be disposed of as the State Government shall from time to time determine.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Any copy or copies delivered pursuant to clause (b) of the said paragraph shall be transmitted to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11A">
        <num>11A.</num>
        <heading>Copies of newspapers printed in India to be delivered gratis to Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The printer of every newspaper in India shall deliver at such place and to such officer as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct, and free of expense to the Government, two copies of each issue of such newspaper as soon as it is published.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11B">
        <num>11B.</num>
        <heading>Copies of newspapers to be delivered to Press Registrar.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules that may be made under this Act, the publisher of every newspaper in India shall deliver free of expense to the Press Registrar one copy of each issue of such newspaper as soon as it is published.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for printing contrary to rule in section 3.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall print or publish any book or paper otherwise than in conformity with the rule contained in section 3 of this Act, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished by fine not exceeding</p>
            <p>two thousand rupees, or by simple imprisonment for a term not exceeding</p>
            <p>six months, or by both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for keeping press without making declaration required by section 4.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall keep in his possession any such press as aforesaid. In contravention of any of the provisions contained in section 4 of this Act, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished by fine not exceeding two thousand rupees, or by simple imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or by both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for making false statement.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who shall, in making any declaration or other statement under the authority of this Act, make a statement which is false, and which he either knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to be true, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished by fine not exceeding two thousand rupees, and imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for printing or publishing newspaper without conforming to rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall</p>
            <p>edit, print or publish any</p>
            <p>newspaper, without conforming to the rules hereinbefore laid down, or whoever shall</p>
            <p>edit, print or publish, or shall cause to be</p>
            <p>edited, printed or published, any</p>
            <p>newspaper, knowing that the said rules have not been observed with respect to</p>
            <p>that newspaper, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished with fine not exceeding</p>
            <p>two thousand rupees, or imprisonment for a term not exceeding</p>
            <p>six months or both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence is committed in relation to a newspaper under sub-section (1), the Magistrate may, in addition to the punishment imposed under the said sub-section, also cancel the declaration in respect of the newspaper.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to make a declaration under section 8.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person who has ceased to be a printer or publisher of any newspaper fails or neglects to make a declaration in compliance with section 8, he shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punishable by fine not exceeding two hundred rupees.</p>
            <p>The Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for not delivering books or not supplying printer with maps.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any printer of any such book as is referred to in section 9 of this Act shall neglect to deliver copies of the same pursuant to that section, he shall for every such default forfeit to the Government such sum not exceeding fifty rupees as a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the place where the book was printed may, on the application of the officer to whom the copies should have been delivered or of any person authorised by that officer in this behalf, determine to be in the circumstances a reasonable penalty for the default, and, in addition to such sum, such further sum as the Magistrate may determine to be the value of the copies which the printer ought to have delivered.</p>
            <p>If any publisher or other person employing any such printer shall neglect to supply him, in the matter prescribed in the second paragraph of section 9 of this Act with the maps, prints or engravings which may be necessary to enable him to comply with the provisions of that section, such publisher or other person shall for every such default forfeit to the Government such sum not exceeding fifty rupees as such a Magistrate as aforesaid may, on such an application as aforesaid, determine to be in the circumstances a reasonable penalty for the default, and, in addition to such sum, such further sum as the Magistrate may determine to be the value of the maps, prints or engravings which such publisher or other person ought to have supplied.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16A">
        <num>16A.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to supply copies of newspapers gratis to Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any printer of any newspaper published in</p>
            <p>India neglects to deliver copies of the same in compliance with section 11A, he shall, on the complaint of the officer to whom copies should have been delivered or of any person authorised by that officer in this behalf, be punishable, on conviction by a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the place where the newspaper was printed, with fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every default.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16B">
        <num>16B.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to supply copies of newspapers to Press Registrar.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any publisher of any newspaper published in India neglects to deliver copies of the same in compliance with section 11B, he shall, on the complaint of the Press Registrar, be punishable, on conviction by a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the place where the newspaper was printed, by fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every default.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of forfeitures and disposal thereof and of fines.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any sum forfeited to the Government under</p>
            <p>section 16 may be recovered, under the warrant of the Magistrate determining the sum, or of his successor in office, in the manner authorised by the Code of Criminal Procedure (10 of 1882)3 for the time being in force, and within the period prescribed by the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), for the levy of a fine.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Registration of memoranda of books.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be kept at such office, and by such officer as the State Government shall appoint in this behalf, a book to be called a Catalogue of Books printed in</p>
            <p>India, wherein shall be registered a memorandum of every book which shall have been delivered</p>
            <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>pursuant to clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of the first paragraph of section 9 of this Act. Such memorandum shall (so far as may be practicable) contain the following particulars (that is to say):—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the title of the book and the contents of the title-page, with a translation into English of such title and contents, when the same are not in the English language;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the language in which the book is written;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the name of the author, translator, or editor of the book or any part thereof;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the subject;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the place of printing and the place of publication;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the name of firm of the printer and the name of firm of the publisher;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the date of issue from the press or of the publication;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the number of sheets, leaves or pages;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the size;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the first, second or other number of the edition;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the number of copies of which the edition consists;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>whether the book is printed,</p>
            <p>cyclostyled or lithographed;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the price at which the book is sold to the public; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the name and residence of the proprietor of the copyright or of any portion of such copyright.</p>
            <p>Such memorandum shall be made and registered in the case of each book as soon as practicable after the delivery of the</p>
            <p>copy thereof pursuant to clause (a) of the first paragraph of section 9</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Publication of memoranda registered.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The memoranda registered during each quarter in the said Catalogue shall be published in the Official Gazette, as soon as may be after the end of such quarter, and a copy of the memoranda so published shall be sent</p>
            <p>*** to the Central Government</p>
            <p>***.</p>
            <p>*19A.  Appointment of Press Registrar and other officers.—</p>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint a Registrar of newspapers for India and such other officers under the general superintendence and control of the Press Registrar as may be necessary for the purpose of performing the functions assigned to them by or under this Act, and may, by general or special order, provide for the distribution or allocation of functions to be performed by them under this Act.</p>
            <p>*19B.  Register of newspapers.—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Press Registrar shall maintain in the prescribed manner a Register of newspapers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Register shall, as far as may be practicable, contain the following particulars about every newspaper published in India, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the title of the newspaper;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the language in which the newspaper is published;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>periodicity of the publication of the newspaper;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the name of the editor, printer and publisher of the newspaper;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the place of printing and publication;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the average number of pages per week;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the number of days of publication in the year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the average number of copies printed, the average number of copies sold to the public and the average number of copies distributed free to the public, the average being calculated with reference to such period as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>retail selling price per copy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the names and addresses of the owners of the newspaper and such other particulars relating to ownership as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other particulars which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receiving information from time to time about the aforesaid particulars, the Press Registrar shall cause relevant entries to be made in the Register and may make such necessary alterations or corrections therein as may be required for keeping the Register up-to-date.</p>
            <p>*19C.  Certificates of registration.—</p>
            <p>On receiving from the Magistrate under section 6 a copy of the declaration in respect of a newspaper</p>
            <p>and on the publication of such newspaper, the Press Registrar shall, as soon as practicable thereafter, issue a certificate of registration in respect of that newspaper to the publisher thereof.</p>
            <p>*19D.  Annual statement, etc., to be furnished by newspapers.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-19.3.list6">
              <listIntroduction>It shall be the duty of the publisher of every newspaper—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.3.list6.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to furnish to the Press Registrar an annual statement in respect of the newspaper at such time and containing such of the particulars referred to in sub-section (2) of section 19B as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.3.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to publish in the newspaper at such times and such of the particulars relating to the newspaper referred to in sub-section (2) of section 19B as may be specified in this behalf by the Press Registrar.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>*19E.  Returns and reports to be furnished by newspapers.—</p>
            <p>The publisher of every newspaper shall furnish to the Press Registrar such returns, statistics and other information with respect to any of the particulars referred to in sub- section (2) of section 19B as the Press Registrar may from time to time require.</p>
            <p>*19F.  Right of access to records and documents.—</p>
            <p>The Press Registrar or any gazetted officer authorised by him in writing in this behalf shall, for the purpose of the collection of any information relating to a newspaper under this Act, have access to any relevant record or document relating to the newspaper in the possession of the publisher thereof, and may enter at any reasonable time any premises where he believes such record or document to be and may inspect or take copies of the relevant records or documents or ask any question necessary for obtaining any information required to be furnished under this Act.</p>
            <p>*19G.  Annual report.—</p>
            <p>The Press Registrar shall prepare, in such form and at such time each year as may be prescribed, an annual report containing a summary of the information obtained by him during the previous year in respect of the newspapers in India and giving an account of the working of such newspapers, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government.</p>
            <p>*19H.  Furnishing of copies of extracts from Register.—</p>
            <p>On the application of any person for the supply of the copy of any extract from the Register and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed, the Press Registrar shall furnish such copy to the applicant in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            <p>*19-I.  Delegation of powers.—</p>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and regulations made thereunder, the Press Registrar may delegate all or any of his powers under this Act to any officer subordinate to him.</p>
            <p>*19J.  Press Registrar and other officers to be public servants.—</p>
            <p>The Press Registrar and all officers appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            <p>*19K.  Penalty for contravention of section 19D or section 19E, etc.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-19.3.list21">
              <listIntroduction>If the publisher of any newspaper—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.3.list21.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refuses or neglects to comply with the provisions of section 19D or section 19E; or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-19.3.list23">
              <listIntroduction>***</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.3.list23.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>publishers in the newspaper in pursuance of clause (b) of section 19D any particulars relating to the newspaper which he has reason to believe to be false,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
            <p>*19L.  Penalty for improper disclosure of information.—</p>
            <p>If any person engaged in connection with the collection of information under this Act wilfully discloses any information or the contents of any return given or furnished under this Act otherwise than in the execution of his duties under this Act or for the purposes of the prosecution of an offence under this Act or under the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such rules (not inconsistent with the rules made by the Central Government under section 20A) as may be necessary or desirable for carrying out the objects of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20A">
        <num>20A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribing the particulars which a declaration made and subscribed under section 5 may contain;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2and">
        <num>2and.</num>
        <heading>the form and manner in which the names of the printer, publisher, owner and editor of a newspaper and the place of its printing and publication may be printed on every copy of such newspaper;</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2and.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>prescribing the manner in which copies of any declaration attested by the official seal of a Magistrate or copies of any order refusing to authenticate any declaration may be forwarded to the person making and subscribing the declaration and to the Press Registrar;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>prescribing the manner in which copies of any newspaper may be sent to the Press Registrar under section 11B;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>prescribing the manner in which a Register may be maintained under section 19B and the particulars which it may contain;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>prescribing the particulars in which an annual statement to be furnished by the publisher of a newspaper to the Press Registrar may contain;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>prescribing the form and manner in which an annual statement under clause (a) of section 19D, or any returns, statistics or other information under section 19E, may be furnished to the Press Registrar;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>prescribing the fees for furnishing copies of extracts from the Register and the manner in which such copies may be furnished;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>prescribing the manner in which a certificate of registration may be issued in respect of a newspaper;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2and.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>prescribing the form in which, and the time within which, annual reports may be prepared by the Press Registrar and forwarded to the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2and.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>[in two or more successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid both houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20B">
        <num>20B.</num>
        <heading>Rules made under this Act may provide that contravention thereof shall be punishable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any rule made under any provision of this Act may provide that any contravention thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Power to exclude any class of books from operation of Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exclude any class of books</p>
            <p>or papers from the operation of the whole or any part or parts of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such notification in respect of any class of newspapers shall be issued without consulting the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Extent.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act extends to the whole of India</p>
            <p>***.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Commencement of Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of 1870), sec. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
