<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/51/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/51"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Post- Graduate Institute Of Medical, Education And Research, Chandigarh, Act, 1966"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/51/eng@1966-12-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/51/eng@1966-12-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1966-12-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/51/eng@1966-12-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/51/eng@1966-12-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Post- Graduate Institute Of Medical, Education And Research, Chandigarh, Act, 1966</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 51 OF 1966</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 17th December, 1966.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the institution known as the Post- Graduate</p>
        <p>Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, to be an  institution of national importance and to provide for its  incorporation and matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Post- Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh,</p>
            <p>Act, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of Post- Graduate Institute of Medical Education and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Research, Chandigarh, as an institution of national importance.</p>
            <p>Whereas the objects of the institution known as the Post- Graduate</p>
            <p>Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh in the Union  territory of Chandigarh are such as to make the institution one of  national importance, it is hereby declared that the institution known  as the Post- Graduate Institute of Medical Education. and Research,</p>
            <p>Chandigarh is an institution of national importance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Fund" means the Fund of the Institute referred to in  section 16;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Governing Body" means the Governing Body of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Institute" means the institution known as the Post-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh,</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>incorporated under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" member"' means a member of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" regulation" means a regulation made by the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" rule" means a rule made by the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation of Institute. The Post- Graduate Institute of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Medical Education and ReSearch, Chandigarh, is hereby constituted a  body corporate by the</p>
            <p>name aforesaid and as such body corporate, it shall have perpetual  succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of  this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and  shall, by that name, sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Composition of Institute. The Institute shall consist of the  following members, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Vice- Chancellor of the Punjab University, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Director- General of Health Services, Government of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>India, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Director of the Institute, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>three representatives of the Central Government to be  nominated by that Government, one each from the Ministry of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Finance, Ministry of Education and Ministry of Health and</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Family Planning;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>seven persons of whom one shall be a non- medical  scientist representing the Indian Science Congress</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Association, to be nominated by the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>four representatives of the medical faculties of Indian</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Universities to be nominated by the Central Government in the  manner prescribed by rules; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list9.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be  elected from among themselves by the members of the House of  the People (Lok Sabha) and one from among themselves by the  members of the Council of States (Rajya Sabha).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Terms of office of, and vacancies among members.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as  otherwise provided in this section, the term of office of a member  shall be five years from the date of his nomination or election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of a member elected under clause (g) of  section 5 shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a member of  the House from which he was elected.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so  long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is such a member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of a member nominated or elected to fill  a casual vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the  member in whose place he is nominated or elected.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An out- going member other than a member elected under clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.5.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>of section 5 shall, unless the Central Government other-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>wise directs, continue in office until another person is nominated as  a member in his place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An out- going member shall be eligible for re- nomination or  re- election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member may resign his office by writing under his hand  addressed to the Central- Government but he shall continue in office  until his resignation is accepted by that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The manner of filling vacancies among members shall be such  as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>President of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a President of the</p>
            <p>Institute who shall be nominated by the Central Government from among  the members other than the Director of the Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President shall exercise such powers and discharge such  functions as are laid down in this Act or as may be prescribed by  rules or regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Allowances of President and members. The President and other  members shall receive such allowances, if any, from the Institute as  may be prescribed by rules.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of Institute. The Institute shall hold its first  meeting at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the  transaction of business at the first meeting as may be laid down by  that Government; and thereafter the Institute shall meet at such times  and places and observe such rules of procedure in regard to the  transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed by  regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Governing Body and other committees of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There  shall be a Governing Body of the Institute which shall be constituted  by the Institute in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations:</p>
            <p>Provided that the number of persons who are not members of the</p>
            <p>Institute shall not exceed one- third of the total membership of the</p>
            <p>Governing Body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Governing Body shall be the executive committee of the</p>
            <p>Institute and shall exercise such powers and discharge such functions  as the Institute may, by regulations made in this behalf, confer or  impose upon it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President of the Institute shall be the Chairman of the</p>
            <p>Governing Body and as Chairman thereof shall exercise such powers and  discharge such functions as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be followed in the exercise of its powers  and discharge of its functions by the Governing Body, and the term of  office of, and the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of  the Governing Body shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be  prescribed by rules, the Institute may constitute as many standing  committees and as many ad hoc committees as it thinks fit for  exercising any power or discharging any function of the Institute or  for inquiring into, or reporting or advising upon, any matter which  the Institute may refer to them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman and members of the Governing Body and the</p>
            <p>Chairman and members of a standing committee or an ad hoc committee  shall receive such allowances, if any, as may be prescribed by  regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Staff of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a chief executive  officer of the Institute who shall be designated as the Director of  the Institute and shall, subject to such rules as may be made by the</p>
            <p>Central Government in this behalf, be appointed by the Institute:</p>
            <p>Provided that the first Director of the Institute shall be  appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall act as the Secretary to the Institute as  well as the Governing Body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall exercise such powers and discharge such  functions as may be prescribed by regulations or as may be delegated  to him by the Institute or the President of the Institute or by the</p>
            <p>Governing Body or the Chairman of the Governing Body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Govern-</p>
            <p>ment in this behalf, the Institute may appoint such number of other  officers and employees as may be necessary for the exercise of its  powers and discharge of its functions and may determine the  designations and grades of such other officers and employees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Govern-</p>
            <p>ment in this behalf, the Director and other officers and employees of  the Institute shall be entitled to such salary and allowances and  shall be governed by such conditions of service in respect of leave,</p>
            <p>pension, provident fund and other matters as may be prescribed by  regulations made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Objects of Institute. The objects of the Institute shall be-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to develop patterns of teaching in undergraduate and  postgraduate medical education in all its branches so as to  demonstrate a high standard of medical education;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to bring together, as far as may be, in one place  educational facilities of the highest order for the training  of personnel in all important branches of health activity;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to attain Self- sufficiency in post- graduate medical education  to meet the country' s needs for specialists and medical  teachers.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Institute. With a view to the promotion of the  objects specified in section 12, the Institute may-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>provide for undergraduate and post- graduate teaching in  the science of modem medicine and other allied sciences,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>including physical and biological sciences;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>provide facilities for research in the various branches  of such sciences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>provide for the teaching of humanities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>conduct experiments in new methods of medical  education, both undergraduate and post- graduate, in order to  arrive at satisfactory standards of such education;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>prescribe courses and curricula for both undergraduate  and post- graduate studies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>not- withstanding anything contained in any other law for  the time being in force, establish and maintain-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>one or more medical colleges with different  departments, including a department of preventive and social  medicine, sufficiently staffed and equipped to undertake not  only undergraduate medical education but also post- graduate  medical education in different subjects,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>one or more well- equipped hospitals,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>a dental college with such institutional  facilities for the practice of dentistry and for the  practical training of students as may be necessary,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>a nursing college sufficiently staffed and equipped for  the training of nurses,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>rural and urban health organisations which will form  centers for the field training of the medical, dental</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and nursing students of the Institute as well as for research  into community health problems, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>other institutions for the training of different types  of health workers, such as physiotherapists, occupational  therapists, pharmacists, drug analysts and medical  technicians of various kinds;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>train teachers for the different medical colleges in</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>India;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>hold examinations and grant such degrees, diplomas and  other academic distinctions and titles in undergraduate and  post- graduate medical education as may be laid down in the  regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>institute, and appoint persons to, professorships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>reader- ships, lecturerships and posts of any description in  accordance with regulations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list8.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>receive grants from the Government and gifts,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>donations, benefactions, bequests and transfers of  properties, both movable and immovable, from donors,</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>benefactors, testators or transferors, as the case may be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list11.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>deal with any property belonging to, or vested in, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Institute in any manner which is considered necessary for  promoting the objects specified in section 12;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list13.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>demand and receive such fees and other charges as may be  prescribed by regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list13.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>construct quarters for its staff and allot such housing  to the staff in accordance with such regulations as may be  made in this behalf.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list13.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>borrow money, with the prior approval of the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list15">
              <listIntroduction>Government, on the security of the property of the Institute.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list15.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>do all such other acts and things as may be necessary  to further the objects specified in section 12.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of property. The properties of the Institute which  had, by virtue of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, 1966 (31 of 1966),</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>vested in the Central Government shall, on the commencement of this</p>
            <p>Act, vest in the Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Payment of Institute. The Central Government may, after due  appropriation made by parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Institute in each financial year such sums of money and in such manner  as may be considered necessary by that Government for the exercise of  its powers and discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Fund of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Institute shall maintain a Fund to  which shall be credited-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all moneys provided by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all fees and other charges received by the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Institute by way of grants,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>gifts, donations; benefactions, bequests or transfers; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Relettered and Ins. by Act 30 of 1987, s. 3</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Institute in any other manner  or from any other source.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All moneys credited to the Fund shall be deposited in such  banks or invested in such manner as the Institute may, with the  approval of the Central Government, decide.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the expenses of  the Institute including expenses incurred in the exercise of its  powers and discharge of its functions under section 13.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Budget of Institute. The Institute shall prepare in such form  and at such time every year as may be prescribed by rules a budget in  respect of the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated  receipts and expenditure of the Institute and shall forward to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government such number of copies thereof as may be prescribed  by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Institute shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may by rules prescribe, and in accordance with such general  directions as may be issued by that Government, in consultation with  the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Institute shall be audited by the Comp-</p>
            <p>troller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by  him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Institute to  the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
            <p>Institute shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <p>India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and,</p>
            <p>in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
            <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect the offices of the Institute as well as of the institutions  established and maintained by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Institute as certified by the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed  by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be  forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall  cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Annual report. The Institute shall prepare for every year a  report of its activities during that year and submit the report to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central</p>
            <p>Government in such form and on or before such date as may be  prescribed by rules and a copy of this report shall be laid before  both Houses of Parliament within one month of its receipt.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Pention and provident funds.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Institute shall  constitute for the benefit of its officers, teachers and other  employees in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be  prescribed by regulations, such pension and provident funds as it may  deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such pension or provident fund has been  constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provisions of  the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 19225), shall apply to, such fund  as if it were a Government Provident Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Authentication of orders and instruments of Institute. All  orders and decisions of the Institute shall be authenticated by the  signature of the President or any other member authorised by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Institute in this behalf and all other instruments shall be  authenticated by the signature of the Director or any other officer of  the Institute authorised in like manner in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act done or proceeding taken by the Institute, Governing Body or  any standing or ad hoc committee under this Act shall be questioned on  the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the  constitution of the Institute, Governing Body or such standing or ad  hoc committee.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Grant of medical degrees, diplomas, etc., by Institute.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being  in force, the Institute shall have power to grant medical degrees,</p>
            <p>diplomas and other academic distinctions and titles under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Recognition of medical qualifications granted by Institute.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Medical Council Act,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1956">
        <num>1956.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, (1022 of 1967) the medical degrees and diplomas granted by the</p>
            <p>Institute under this Act shall be recognised medical qualifications  for the purposes of that Act and shall be deemed to be included in  the First Schedule to that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Control by Central Government. The Institute shall carry out  such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Dispute between INstitute and Central Government. If in, or in  connection with, the exercise of its powers and discharge of its  functions by the Institute under this Act, any dispute arises between  the Institute and the Central Government, the decision of the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government on such dispute shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Returns and information. The Institute shall furnish to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government such reports, returns and other information as that</p>
            <p>Government may require from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of service of existing employees. Subject to the  provisions of this Act, every person who is employed in the Post-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh,</p>
            <p>immediately before the commencement of this Act shall, on and from  such commencement, become an employee, of the Institute and shall hold  his office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same  remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and with the same  rights and privileges as to pension, leave, gratuity, provident fund  and other matters as he would have held the same on the date of  commencement of this Act if this Act had not been passed, and shall  continue to do so unless and until his employment is terminated or  until such tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly  altered by regulations:</p>
            <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions  of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage  without the previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of facilities at Institute. The Institute shall  continue to provide facilities to the Governments of the States of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Haryana and Punjab and the Central Government in relation to the Union  territories of Chandigarh and Himachal Pradesh and the people of the</p>
            <p>States and territories aforesaid and such facilities shall not, in  any respect, be less favourable to such Governments and people than  what were being provided to them before the 1st day of November, 1966  and shall be made available for such period and upon such terms and  conditions (including those relating to any contributions to be made   for the provision of such facilities) as may be agreed upon between  the Institute, Governments of the States of Haryana and Punjab and the</p>
            <p>Central Government before the 1st day of April. 1967, or if no  agreement is reached, by the said date, as may be fixed by order of  the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, within a period of three years from the commencement of this Act,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>by order published in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, make such provision or give such directions not  inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appears to it to be  necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, after  consultation with the Institute, may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that consultation with the Institute shall not be neces-</p>
            <p>sary on the first occasion of the making of rules under this section,</p>
            <p>but the Central Government shall take into consideration any  suggestions which the Institute may make in relation to the amendment  of such rules after they are made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the follow-</p>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>ing matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner of nomination of members under clause (f) of  section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the control and restrictions in relation to the  constitution of standing and ad hoc committees under sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>section (5) of section 10;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service of, the procedure to be  followed by, and the manner of filling vacancies among,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>members of the Institute;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged  by the President of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the allowances, if any, to be paid to the President and  other members of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the number of officers and employees that may be  appointed by the Institute and the manner of such  appointment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list6.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the form in which, and the time at which, the budgets  and reports shall be prepared by the Institute and the number  of copies thereof to be forwarded to the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list6.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which returns and information  are to be furnished by the Institute to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list8.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed  by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised</p>
            <p>in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if,</p>
            <p>before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or  the successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any  modi- fication in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should  not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Institute  with the  previous approval of the Central Government, may, by notification in  the Official Gazette,"] make regulations consistent with this Act and  the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act, and  without prejudice to the generality of this power, such regulations  may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the summoning and holding of meetings, other than the  first meeting, of the Institute, the time and place where  such meetings are to be held, the conduct of business at such  meetings and the number of members necessary to form a quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner of constituting the Governing Body and  standing and ad hoc committees, the term of office of, and  the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Governing Body and standing and ad hoc committees;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged  by the President of the Institute and the Chairman of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Governing Body;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the allowances, if any, to be paid to the Chairman and  the members of the Governing Body and of standing and ad hoc  committees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the Governing Body and  standing and ad hoc committees in the conduct of their  business. exercise of their powers and discharge of their  functions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the tenure of office, salaries and allowances and other  conditions of service of the Director and other officers and  employees of the Institute including teachers appointed by  the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the Chairman of the Governing</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Body;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list7.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the Director and other  officers and employees of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the management of the properties of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list7.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the degrees, diplomas and other academic distinctions  and titles which may be granted by the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list7.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the professorships, readerships, lecturerships and  other posts which may be instituted and persons who may be  appointed to such professorships, readerships, lecturerships  and other posts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list7.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the fees and other charges which may be demanded and  received by the institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list7.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to  which, pension and provident funds may be constituted for the  benefit of officers, teachers and other employees of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Institute;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list9.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>any other matter for which under this Act provisions  may be made by regulations.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the  first regulations under this Act shall be made by the Central Govern-</p>
            <p>ment; and any regulations so made may be altered or rescinded by the</p>
            <p>Institute in exercise of its powers under sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, as  soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
            <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation."]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
