<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1958/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1958/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Industrial Establishments (National And Festival Holidays) Act, 1958"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1958/33/eng@2017-05-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1958/33/eng@2017-05-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1958/33/eng@2017-05-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1958/33/eng@2017-05-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Industrial Establishments (National And Festival Holidays) Act, 1958</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the grant of National and festival holidays to persons employed in industrial establishments in the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the grant of National and festival holidays to persons employed in industrial establishments in the State of Tamil Nadu;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted in the Ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Industrial Establishments (National and Festival Holidays) Act, 1958.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the con-text otherwise requires</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“day" means a period of twenty-four hours beginning at midnight;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"employee" means</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any person (including an apprentice) employed in any industrial establishment to do any skilled or unskilled, manual, supervisory, technical or clerical work for hire or reward, whether the terms of employment be expressed or implied;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any other person employed in any industrial establishment whom the Government may, by notification, declare to be an employee for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"employer" when used in relation to an industrial establishment means a person who has the ultimate control over the affairs of the industrial establishment, and where the affairs of any industrial establishment are entrusted to any other person, (whether called a managing agent, manager, superintendent or by any other name) such other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>"industrial establishment" means,</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any establishment as defined in clause (6) of section 2 of the Tamil Nadu Shops and Establishments, Act, 1947 (Tamil Nadu Act XXXIII of 1947);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any factory as defined in clause (m) of section 2 of the Factories Act, 1948 (Central Act LXIII of 1948), or any place which is deemed to be a factory under sub-section (2) of section 85 of that Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any plantation as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (Central Act LXIX of 1951);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list1.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>any other establishment which the Government may, by notification, declare to be an industrial establishment for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Inspector" means an inspector appointed under sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>"wages" means all remuneration capable of being expressed in terms of money, which would, if the terms of employment, express or implied, were fulfilled, be payable to an employee in respect of his employment or of the work done by him in such employment, and includes</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list2.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>such allowances (including dearness allowance) as the employee is for the time being entitled to;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list2.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the value of any house accommodation; or of supply of light, water, medical attendance or other amenity or of any service or of any concessional supply of foodgrains or other articles; but does not include</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any bonus;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any contribution paid or payable by the employer to any pension fund or provident fund, or for the benefit of the employee under any law for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any gratuity payable on the termination of his service;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any sum paid to the employee to defray special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his employment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any travelling concession.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Grant of National and Festival Holidays</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every employee shall be allowed in each calendar year a holiday of one whole day on the 26th January, the first May, the 15th August and the 2nd October and five other holidays each of one whole day for such festivals as the Inspector may, in consultation with the employer and the employees, specify in respect of any industrial establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Employer to send statement to Inspector</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall send to the Inspector having jurisdiction over the area in which the industrial establishment is situated, and display in the premises of the industrial establishment, a statement showing the holidays allowed in each calendar year under section 3, in such form, within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Wages</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding any contract to the contrary, every employee shall be paid wages for each of the holidays allowed to him under section 3. Such wages shall be paid along with the wages for the wage period in which such holiday falls.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3, any employee may be required by the employer to work on any holiday allowed under that section if the employer has, not less than twenty-four hours before such holiday,</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>served in the prescribed manner on the employee a notice in writing reviling him to work as aforesaid; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>sent to the Inspector having jurisdiction over the area in which the industrial establishment is situated and displayed in the premises of the industrial establishment a copy of such notice.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list1.b.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Where an employee works on any holiday allowed under section 3, he shall, at his option, be entitled to</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.b.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>twice the wages or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.b.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>wages for such day and to avail himself of a substituted holiday with wages on one of the three days immediately before or after the day on which he so works.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), an employee who is paid wages by the day or at piece rates shall be entitled to be paid wages for any holiday allowed under section 3</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>only at a rate equivalent to the daily average of his wages to be calculated in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>where he works on any such holiday, only at twice the rate mentioned in clause (i), or in lieu thereof, at the rate mentioned in that clause and to avail himself of a substituted holiday with wages at that rate on one of the three days immediately before or after the day on which he so works</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no such employee shall be entitled to be paid any wages for any of the holidays allowed under section 3 other than the 26 January, the 1 May, the 15 August and the 2 October unless he has been in the service under the employer for a total period of 30 days, within a continuous period of ninety days immediately preceding such holiday.Explanation - For the purpose of this proviso, a weekly or any other holiday or authorized leave availed of by an employee shall be included in computing the period of thirty days mentioned therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, appoint such persons or such class of persons as they think fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act for such local limits as the Government may specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Inspectors</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made by the Government in this behalf, an Inspector may, within the local limits for which he is appointed,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enter, at all reasonable times and with such assistants, if any, who are persons in the service of the Government or of any local authority as he thinks fit to take with him, any place which is, or which he has reason to believe is, an industrial establishment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>make such examination of the premises and of any prescribed registers, records and notices and take on the spot or otherwise, the evidence of such person as he may deem necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>seize or take copies of such registers, records or notices or portions thereof which he considers relevant in respect of an offence under this Act, on giving the employer a receipt therefor. The registers, records or notices or portions thereof so seized shall be returned by the Inspector, on completion of examination or inquiry or proceeding under this ActProvided that such registers, records or notices or portions thereof shall not be retained by the Inspector for more than thirty days except with the permission of the Commissioner of Labour.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>exercise such other powers as may be necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no one shall be required under this section to answer any question or give any evidence tending to incriminate himself.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any employer who contravenes any of the provisions of sections 3 or 5 shall be punishable with fine which, for the first offence, shall not be less than five hundred rupees but which may extend to one thousand rupees and for the second and subsequent offences, shall not be less than one thousand rupees but which may extend to two thousand and five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Compounding of offences</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any offence punishable under section 8 or any rule made under section 12 may, either before or after the institution of the prosecution, be compounded by the Commissioner of Labour or such other officer as may be authorised in this behalf by the Commissioner of Labour, on payment, for credit to the Government of such sum as the Commissioner of Labour or such other officer may specify</p>
            <p>Provided that such sum shall not, in any case, exceed the maximum amount of fine which may be imposed under this Act for the offence so compounded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence has been compounded under sub-section (1), no proceeding or further proceeding, as the case may be, shall be taken against the offender, in respect of the offence so compounded and the offender, if in custody, shall be discharged forthwith</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No offence punishable under this Act shall be com-pounded except as provided by this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for obstructing Inspector</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever wilfully obstructs an Inspector in the exercise of any power conferred on him by or under this Act, or fails to produce of demand in writing by an Inspector any register, record or notice in his custody which may be required to be kept in pursuance of this Act or of any rule made thereunder, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any employee in a position of management;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any employee whose work involves travelling</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any industrial establishment under the control of the Central or any State Government, local authority, Reserve Bank of India, a railway administration operating any railway as defined in clause (20) of Article 366 of the Constitution or a cantonment authority or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any mine or oil-field.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification* exempt either permanently or for any specified period any establishment or class of establishments, or person or class of persons from all or any of the provisions of this Act, subject to such conditions as the Government may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Rights and privileges under other laws, etc., not affected</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall affect any rights or privileges which any employee is entitled to, on the date on which this Act comes into force under any other law, contract, custom or usage, if such rights or privileges are more favourable to him than those to which he would be entitled under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11A">
        <num>11A.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faithNo suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government or any officer of the Government for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making a rule under this Act, the Government may provide that the contravention thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published in the Fort St. George Gazette and, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come into force on the day on which they are so published.Every rule made under this Act shall, as soon as possible, after it is made, be placed on the table of the Legislative Assembly, and if, before the expiry of the session, in which it is so placed or the next session, the Legislative Assembly agrees in making any modification in any such rule or the Legislative Assembly agrees that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
