<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1934/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1934/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Sugar- Cane Act, 1934"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1934/15/eng@1934-05-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1934/15/eng@1934-05-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1934-05-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1934/15/eng@1934-05-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1934/15/eng@1934-05-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Sugar- Cane Act, 1934</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 15 OF 1934</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 1st May, 1934.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to regulate the price of sugar- cane intended for use in sugar  factories.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Sugar- cane Act, 1934.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India, except  the  territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were  comprised in Part B States].]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section shall come into force at once; the remaining  sections of this Act shall come into force in any State  or part of  a State] on such date as the State Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, appoint in that behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" controlled area" means any area specified in a  notification issued under sub- section (1) of section 3;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" factory" means any premises (including the precincts   thereof) wherein twenty or more workers are working or  were working on any day of the preceding twelve months  and in any part of which any manufacturing process  connected with the production of sugar is being carried  on or is ordinarily carried on with the aid of power;</p>
            <p>and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" sugar" means any form of sugar containing more than  ninety per cent. of sucrose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of controlled areas and fixing of prices.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare  any area specified in the notification to be a controlled area for the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, fix a minimum price or minimum prices for the purchase in any  controlled area of sugar- cane intended for use in any factory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, prohibit in any controlled area the purchase of sugar- cane  intended for use in any factory otherwise than from the grower of the  sugar- cane or from a person licensed by the State Government to act as  a purchasing agent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Previous publication of notifications under section 3. Not  less than thirty days before the issue of any notification under sub-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>or sub- section (2) of section 3, the State Government  shall publish in the Official Gazette and in such other manner (if   any) as it thinks fit a draft of the proposed notification specifying  a date on or after which the draft will be taken into consideration,</p>
            <p>and shall consider any objection or suggestion which may be received  from any person with respect to the draft before the date so  specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for purchase of sugar- cane in contravention of  notification under section 3. Whoever in any controlled area purchases  any sugar- cane intended for use in a factory at a price less than the  minimum price fixed therefor by notification under sub- section (2) of  section 3 or in contravention of any prohibition made under sub-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>section (3) of section 3 shall be punishable with fine which may  extend to two thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Sanction for prosecution under this Act. No Court shall take  cognizance of any offence punishable under section 5 except upon  complaint made by order of, or under authority from, the District</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  for the purpose of carrying into effect the objects of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the carrying out of inquiries preliminary to the  exercise of the powers conferred by section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>establishing Advisory Committees for any purpose  connected with the administration of this Act and  defining the powers, functions and procedure of such</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Committees;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the issue of licences to purchasing agents, the fees for  such licences, and the regulation of the purchase and  sale of sugar- cane by and to such agents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the organisation of growers of sugar- cane into societies  for the sale of sugar- cane to factories;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the authorities by which any functions under this Act or  the rules made thereunder are to be performed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the records, registers and accounts to be maintained for  ensuring compliance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rule under sub- section (1) or under clause (c)</p>
            <p>or clause (f) of sub- section (2), the State Government may provide  that a breach of the rule shall, where no other penalty is provided by  this Act, be punishable with fine not exceeding two thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make rules. The State Government  after previous publication may, by notification in the Official</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Gazette, make rules providing for the exemption of factories or any  class of factories from the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
