<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/45/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/45"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tezpur University Act, 1993"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tezpur University Act, 1993</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 45 OF 1993</docNumber>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[ 1st June, 1993</p>
        <p>An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and residential</p>
        <p>Uni-</p>
        <p>versity in the State of Assam at Tezpur and to provide for matters  connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Tezpur University Act, 1993.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Govern-</p>
            <p>ment may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made  hereunder, unless the context otherwise requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are  designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Board of Management" means the Board of Management of  the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chancellor" mean, respectively, the Chancellor, Vice-</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Chancellor and Pro- Vice- Chancellor of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" College" means a College maintained by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" Department" means a Department of Studies, and  includes Centre of Studies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" distance education system" means the system of  imparting education through any means of communication, such  as broadcasting, telecasting, correspondence courses,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>seminars, contact programmes or the combination of any two or  more such means;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" employee" means any person appointed by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University, and includes teachers and other staff of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" Finance Committee" means the Finance Committee of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life  for the students of the University, or of a College or of an</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16">
              <listIntroduction>Institution maintained by the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" Institution" means an academic institution, not being  a College, maintained by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>" Planning and Academic Committee" means the Planning  and Academic Committee of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>" Planning Board" means the Planning Board of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institution maintained by the University, and includes, where  there is no Principal, the person for the time being duly  appointed to act as Principal, and, in the absence of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21">
              <listIntroduction>Principal or the acting Principal, a Vice- Principal duly  appointed as such;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>" recognised institution" means an institution of higher  learning recognised by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>" recognised teachers" means such persons as may be re-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>cognised by the University for the purpose of imparting  instructions in a College or an Institution maintained by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any  authority of the University under this Act for the time being  in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24.t">
                <num>(t)</num>
                <p>" Statutes" and" Ordinances" mean respectively, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes and Ordinances of the University for the time being  in force;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26.u">
                <num>(u)</num>
                <p>" teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Lecturers and such other persons as may be appointed for  imparting instruction or conducting research in the</p>
            <p>University or in any College or Institution maintained by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list30">
              <listIntroduction>University and are designated as teachers by the Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list30.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>" University" means the Tezpur University established  under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>The University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established a University by  the name of" Tezgur University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The headquarters of the University shall be at Tezpur and it  may also establish campuses at such other places within its  jurisdiction as it may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Vice- Chancellor and the first members of the Board  of Management, the Planning and Academic Committee or the Academic</p>
            <p>Council or the Planning Board and all persons who may hereafter become  such officers or members, so long as they continue to hold such office  or membership, are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of</p>
            <p>" Tezpur University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal and shall sue and be sued by the said name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Objects of the University. The objects of the University  shall be to disseminate and advance knowledge by providing  instructional and research facilities in such branches of learning as  it may deem fit; to make provisions for integrated courses in  humanities, natural and physical sciences, social sciences,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>agricultural science and forestry and other allied disciplines in the  educational programmes of the University; to take appropriate measures  for promoting innovations in teaching- learning processes, inter-</p>
            <p>disciplinary studies and research; to educate and train manpower for  the development of the State of Assam; and to pay special attention to  the improvement of the social and economic conditions and welfare of  the people of that State, their intellectual, academic and cultural  development; and the University shall, in organising its activities,</p>
            <p>have due regard to the objects specified in the First Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning  as the University may, from time to time, determine and to  make provision for research and for the advancement and  dissemination of knowledge;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University  may determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer  degrees or other academic distinctions on the basis of  examinations, evaluation or any other method of testing on  persons, and to withdraw any such diplomas, certificates,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>degrees or other academic distinctions for good and  sufficient cause;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to organise and to undertake extra- mural  studies, training and extension services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the  manner prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>to provide facilities through the distance education  system to such persons as it may determine;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>to institute Principalships, Professorships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Readerships, Lecturerships and other teaching or academic  positions, required by the University and to appoint persons  to such Principalships, Professorships, Readerships,</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Lecturerships or other teaching on academic positions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>to recognise an institution of higher learning for  such purposes as the University may determine and to withdraw  such recognition;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>to recognise persons for imparting instructions in  any College or Institution maintained by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>to appoint persons working in any other University or  organisation as teacher of the University for a specified  period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts  and to make appointments thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any  other University or authority or institution of higher  learning in such manner and for such purposes as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>University may determine;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list7.xii">
                <num>(xii)</num>
                <p>to establish such campuses, special centres,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>specialised laboratories or other units for research and  instruction as are, in the opinion of the University,</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>necessary or the furtherance of its objects;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10.xiii">
                <num>(xiii)</num>
                <p>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12.xiv">
                <num>(xiv)</num>
                <p>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>Halls;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xv">
                <num>(xv)</num>
                <p>to make provision for research and advisory services  and for that purpose to enter into such arrangements with  other institutions, industrial or other organisations, as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list16">
              <listIntroduction>University may deem necessary;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list16.xvi">
                <num>(xvi)</num>
                <p>to organise and conduct refresher courses, workshops,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18">
              <listIntroduction>seminars and other programmes for teachers, evaluators and  other academic staff;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xvii">
                <num>(xvii)</num>
                <p>to make special arrangements in respect of the  residence, discipline and teaching of women students as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list20">
              <listIntroduction>University may consider desirable;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list20.xviii">
                <num>(xviii)</num>
                <p>to appoint on contract or otherwise visiting</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list22">
              <listIntroduction>Professors, Emeritus Professors, Consultants, Scholars and  such other persons who may contribute to the advancement of  the objects of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list22.xix">
                <num>(xix)</num>
                <p>to confer autonomous status on a College or an Institu-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list24">
              <listIntroduction>tion or a Department, as the case may be, in accordance with  the Statutes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list24.XX">
                <num>(XX)</num>
                <p>to determine standards of admission to the University,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list26">
              <listIntroduction>which may include examination, evaluation or any other method  of testing;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list26.xxi">
                <num>(xxi)</num>
                <p>to demand and receive payment of fees and other  charges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list26.xxii">
                <num>(xxii)</num>
                <p>to supervise the residences of the students of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list28">
              <listIntroduction>University and to make arrangements for promoting their  health and general welfare;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list28.xxiii">
                <num>(xxiii)</num>
                <p>to lay down conditions of service of all  categories of employees, including their code of conduct;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list28.xxiv">
                <num>(xxiv)</num>
                <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among the  students and the employees, and to take such disciplinary  measures in this regard as may be deemed by the University to  be necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list28.xxv">
                <num>(xxv)</num>
                <p>to make arrangements for promoting the health and  general welfare of the employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list28.xxvi">
                <num>(xxvi)</num>
                <p>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and  to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable  or immovable, including trust and endowment properties for  the purposes of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list28.xxvii">
                <num>(xxvii)</num>
                <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government, on the security of the property of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list31">
              <listIntroduction>University, money for the purposes of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list31.xxviii">
                <num>(xxviii)</num>
                <p>to do all such other acts and things as may be  necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of all  or any of its objects.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction. The jurisdiction of the University shall ex-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>tend to the whole of the State of Assam.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever  caste, creed, race or class, and it shall not be lawful for the Uni-</p>
            <p>versity to adopt or impose on any person, any test whatsoever of  religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be appointed  as a teacher of the University or to hold any other office therein or  be admitted as a student in the University or to graduate thereat or  to enjoy or exercise any privilege thereof:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  the University from making special provisions for the employment or  admission of women, physically handicapped or of persons belonging to  the weaker sections of the society and, in particular, of the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/45/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/45"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Castes and the Scheduled Tribes."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/45/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Residence of students. Every student of the University</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>(other than a student who pursues a course of study by distance   education system) shall reside in a Hall or hostel or under such  conditions as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>The Visitor.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor  of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more  persons to review the work and progress of the University, including</p>
                  <p>Colleges and Institutions managed by it, and to submit a report there-</p>
                  <p>on; and upon receipt of that report, the Visitor may, after obtaining  the views of the Board of Management thereon through the Vice-</p>
                  <p>Chancellor, take such action and issue such directions as he considers  necessary in respect of any of the matters dealt with in the report  and the University shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to  be made by such person or persons as he may direct of the University,</p>
                  <p>its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or</p>
                  <p>Institution maintained by the University and also of the examinations,</p>
                  <p>teaching and other work conducted or done by the University and to  cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in respect of any matter  connected with the administration or finances of the University,</p>
                  <p>Colleges or Institutions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor shall, in every matter referred to in sub-</p>
                  <p>section (2), give notice of his intention to cause an inspection or  inquiry to be made to the University and the University shall have the  right to make such representations to the Visitor, as it may consider  necessary.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>After considering the representations, if any, made by the</p>
                  <p>University, the Visitor may cause to be made such inspection or  inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (3).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made  by the Visitor, the University shall be entitled to appoint a  representative, who shall have the right to be present and be heard at  such inspection or inquiry.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in  respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by  it, address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such  inspection or inquiry together with such views and advice with regard  to the action to be taken thereon, as the Visitor may be pleased to  offer, and on receipt of address made by the Visitor, the Vice-</p>
                  <p>Chancellor shall communicate to the Board of Management the views of  the Visitor with such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action  to be taken thereon.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board of Management shall communicate, through the Vice-</p>
                  <p>Chancellor, to the Visitor such action, if any, as it proposes to take  or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Board of Management does not, within a reasonable  time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may,</p>
                  <p>after considering any explanation furnished or representation made by  the Board of Management, issue such directions as he may think fit and  the Board of Management shall comply with such directions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this  section, the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of  the Uni-</p>
                  <p>versity which is not in conformity with the Act, the Statutes or the</p>
                  <p>Ordinances:</p>
                  <p>Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon  the Registrar to show cause why such an order should not be made, and  if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the  same.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Officers of the University. The following shall be the  officers of the University:-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-10.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Chancellor;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Vice- Chancellor;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Pro- Vice- Chancellor;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Deans of Schools;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Registrar;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Finance Officer; and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes  to be officers of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>The Chancellor.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Governor of the State of Assam shall  be the Chancellor of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head  of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocation  of the University held for conferring degrees.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>The Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and  academic officer of the University and shall exercise general  supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give  effect to decisions of all the authorities of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate  action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any  authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to  such authority the action taken by him on such matter:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such  action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the</p>
                  <p>Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that any person in the service of the University  who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this  sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the</p>
                  <p>Board of Management within three months from the date on which  decision on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Board  of Management may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the</p>
                  <p>Vice- Chancellor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- chancellor, if he is of the opinion that any  decision of any authority of the University is beyond the powers of  the authority conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes  or the Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the interest of  the University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision  within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to  review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken  by it within the said period of sixty days, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and  perform such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the</p>
                  <p>Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>The Pro- Vice- Chancellor. The Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform  such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Deans of Schools. Every Dean of a School shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>The Registrar.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-15.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreement,</p>
                  <p>sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University  and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>The Finance Officer. The Finance Officer shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be Prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and  duties of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by  the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Authorities of the University. The following shall be the  authorities of the University:-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-18.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Board of Management;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Planning and Academic Committee;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Academic Council;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Planning Board;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Boards of Studies;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Finance Committee; and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>such other authorities as may be declared by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes to be the authorities of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>The Board of Management.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board of Management shall  be the principal executive body of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Board of Management, the term of  office of its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed  by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>The Planning and Academic Committee.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-20.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>There shall be  constituted a Planning and Academic Committee of the University which  shall advise the Board of Management on matters relating to the</p>
                  <p>University academic and development activities and oversee, review,</p>
                  <p>monitor the development of the University and keep under review the  standard of education and research in the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Planning and Academic Committee, the  term of office of its members and its powers and duties shall be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the</p>
                  <p>Planning and Academic Committee shall stand dissolved.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>The Academic Council.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-21.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Academic Council shall be the  principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, co- ordinate  and exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the</p>
                  <p>University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-21.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office  of its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>The Planning Board.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-22.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Planning Board, as and when  constituted, shall be the principal planning body of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Planning Board, term of office of its  members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>The Boards of Schools. The constitution, powers and  functions of the Boards of Schools shall be prescribed by the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>The Finance Committee. The constitution, powers and  functions of the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Other authorities of the University. The constitution,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>powers and functions of other authorities, as may be declared by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes to be the authorities of the University, shall be prescribed  by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the constitution, powers and functions of the  authorities and other bodies of the University, as may be  constituted from time to time;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the election and continuance in office of the members  of the said authorities and bodies, the filling up of  vacancies of members,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>and all other matters relating to those authorities and  other bodies for which it may be necessary or desirable to  provide;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of  the University and their emoluments;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of teachers, academic staff and other  employees of the University, their emoluments and other  conditions of service;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of teachers, academic staff working in  any other University or organisation for a specific period  for undertaking. a joint project;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of service of employees including  provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, the  manner of termination of service and disciplinary action;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the principles governing the seniority of service of  the employees of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute  between employees or students and the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the procedure for appeal to the Board of Management by  any employee or student against the action of any officer or  authority of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list3.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the conferment of autonomous status on a College or an</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>Institution or a Department;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>the establishment and abolition of Schools,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>Departments, Centres, Halls, Colleges and Institutions;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.l">
                      <num>(l)</num>
                      <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.m">
                      <num>(m)</num>
                      <p>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.n">
                      <num>(n)</num>
                      <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list9">
                    <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list9.o">
                      <num>(o)</num>
                      <p>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or  officers of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list9.p">
                      <num>(p)</num>
                      <p>the maintenance of the discipline among the employees  and students;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list9.q">
                      <num>(q)</num>
                      <p>all other matters which by this Act are to be or may be  provided for by the Statutes.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Statutes how to be made.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-27.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The first Statutes are those  set out in the Second Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board of Management may, from time to time, make new or  additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in  sub- section (1):</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Board of Management shall not make, amend or  repeal any Statutes affecting the status, powers or constitution of  any</p>
                  <p>authority of the University until such authority has been given an  opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed  changes, and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the Board  of Management.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every new Statute or addition to the Statute or any  amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the assent of the</p>
                  <p>Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the</p>
                  <p>Board of Management for consideration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
                  <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
                  <p>Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
                  <p>sections, the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or  repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1), during the period  of three years immediately after the commencement of this Act:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period  of three years, make within one year from the date of such expiry,</p>
                  <p>such detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed</p>
                  <p>Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
                  <p>section, the Visitor may direct the University to make provisions in  the Statutes in respect of any matter specified by him and if the</p>
                  <p>Board of Management is unable to implement such direction within sixty  days of its receipt, the Visitor may, after considering the reasons,</p>
                  <p>if any, communicated by the Board of Management for its inability to  comply with such direction, make or amend the Statutes suitably,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Power to make Ordinances.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-28.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of  this Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any  of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the admission of students to the University and their  enrolment as such;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>diplomas and certificates of the University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the medium of instruction and examination;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other  academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same and  the means to be taken relating to the granting and obtaining  of the same;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list3.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>University and for admission to the examinations, degrees and  diplomas of the University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list5.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the conditions for award of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list7.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the conduct of examinations, including the term of  office and manner of appointment and the duties of examining  bodies, examiners and moderators;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list7.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of residence of the students of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list9">
                    <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list9.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for  the residence, discipline and teaching of women students and  the prescribing of special courses of studies for them;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list9.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the appointments and emoluments of employees other than  those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list9.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Studies, Special Centres, Specialised Laboratories and other</p>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list12">
                    <listIntroduction>Committees;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list12.l">
                      <num>(l)</num>
                      <p>the manner of co- operation and collaboration, with  other Universities and authorities including learned bodies  or associations;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list12.m">
                      <num>(m)</num>
                      <p>the creation, composition and functions of any other  body which is considered necessary for improving the academic  life of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list12.n">
                      <num>(n)</num>
                      <p>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers  and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.1.list14">
                    <listIntroduction>Statutes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list14.o">
                      <num>(o)</num>
                      <p>the management of Colleges and Institutions established  by the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list14.p">
                      <num>(p)</num>
                      <p>the setting up of a machinery for redressal of  grievances of employees; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.1.list14.q">
                      <num>(q)</num>
                      <p>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may  be provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor  with the previous approval of the Central Government and the</p>
                  <p>Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time  by the Board of Management in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances  for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees, if  any, appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes  or the Ordinances, in the manner prescribed by the Statutes,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>Annual report.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-30.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual report of the University shall  be prepared under the direction of the Board of Management, which  shall include, among other matters, the steps taken by the University  towards the fulfilment of its objects.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual report so prepared shall be submitted to the</p>
                  <p>Visitor on or before such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual report as prepared under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>, shall also be submitted to the Central Government. which shall,</p>
                  <p>as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-31">
              <num>31.</num>
              <heading>Annual accounts.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-31.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual accounts and balance- sheet  of the University shall be prepared under the directions of the Board  of Management and shall, once at least every year and at intervals of  not more than fifteen months, be audited by the Comptroller and</p>
                  <p>Auditor- General of India or by such persons as he may authorise in  this behalf.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report  thereon shall be submitted to the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts  shall be brought to the notice of the Board of Management and the  observations of the Board of Management, if any, shall be submitted to  the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report  as submitted to the Visitor, shall also be submitted to the Central</p>
                  <p>Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid  before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before  both Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Gazette of India.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-32">
              <num>32.</num>
              <heading>Conditions of service of employees.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-32.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every employee of  the University shall be appointed under a written contract, which  shall be lodged with the University and a copy of which shall be  furnished to the employee concerned,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the</p>
                  <p>University and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be  referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member  appointed by the Board of Management, one member nominated by the  employee concerned and an umpire appointed by the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final and no suit  shall lie in any civil court in respect of the matters decided by the</p>
                  <p>Tribunal.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2),</p>
                  <p>shall be deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of  this section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, 1940</p>
                  <p>(2 of 1940).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall  be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-33">
              <num>33.</num>
              <heading>Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases  against students.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-33.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any student or candidate for an examination  whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the  orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or</p>
                  <p>Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who Ms been debarred  from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one  year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or  copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Board of Management and  the Board of Management may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of  the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-33.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by  the University against a. student shall, at the request of such  student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions  of sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 32 shall, as far as  may be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University  or of a College or Institution maintained by the University shall,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, have a right to appeal  within such time as may be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Board of</p>
                  <p>Management against the decision of any officer or authority of the</p>
                  <p>University or of the Principal of any College or Institution, as the  case may be, and thereupon the Board of Management may confirm, modify  or reverse the decision appealed against.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-35">
              <num>35.</num>
              <heading>Provident and pension funds.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-35.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The University shall  constitute for the, benefit of its employees such provident or pension  fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such  manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so  constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provision of  the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), shall apply to such  fund, as if it were a Government provident fund.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and  bodies. If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly  elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any  authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint</p>
                  <p>Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist  of the members of the authority concerned and of such other person, if  any as the authority in each may think fit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the  members (other than ex officio members) of any Authority or other body  of the University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person or  body who appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose place has  become vacant and person appointed, elected of co- opted to a casual  vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for the residue of  the term for which the person whose place he fills would have been a  member.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not  invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority  or other body of the University shall be invatlid merely by reason  of the existence of vacancy or vacancies among its members.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other  legal proceedings shall lie against any officer or other employee of  the University for anything which is in good faith done or intended  to be done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Statutes or the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-41">
              <num>41.</num>
              <heading>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or</p>
                  <p>Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the</p>
                  <p>University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the</p>
                  <p>University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima  facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order,</p>
                  <p>proceeding, resolution or documents or the existence of entry in the  register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and  transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced,</p>
                  <p>have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained  in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or in any other law for  the time being in force.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-42">
              <num>42.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-42.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any difficulty arises  in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central</p>
                  <p>Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such  provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as  appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after  the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-42.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained  in this Act and the Statutes,-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-43.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-43.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Visitor and the said officer shall hold office for a term of  five years;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall  be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers  shall hold office for a term of three Years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the, first Board of Management shaft consist of not  more than eleven members who shall be nominated by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-43.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Visitor and they shall hold office for a term of three years;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the first Academic Council and the first Planning</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Board, shall be constituted on the expiry of a period of ten  years from the commencement of this Act and during the said  period of ten years, the powers and functions of. these two  authorities shall be exercised and performed by the Planning  and Academic Committee constituted under section 20:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or  authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be, by the Visitor, and the persons so appointed or  nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in  whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held that office,</p>
                  <p>if such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44">
              <num>44.</num>
              <heading>Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-44.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every Statute,</p>
                  <p>Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-44.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days Which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the</p>
                  <p>Statute, Ordinance or Regulation or both Houses agree that the</p>
                  <p>Statute, Ordinance or Regulation should not be made, the Statute,</p>
                  <p>Ordinance or Regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
                  <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that Statute, Ordinance  or Regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-44.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall  include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier  than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinances  or Regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be  given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudicially  affect the interests of any person to whom such Statute, Ordinance or</p>
                  <p>Regulation may be applicable.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
