<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1995/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Kerala Beedi And Cigar Workers’ Welfare Fund Act, 1995"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Kerala Beedi And Cigar Workers’ Welfare Fund Act, 1995</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act 18 Of 1995)</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of a fund to grant relief to, promote the welfare of, and to pay pension to beedi and cigar workers and self-employed persons in beedi and cigar industries in the State of Kerala.</p>
        <p>Preamble.—</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of a fund to grant relief to, to promote the welfare of and to pay pension to beedi and cigar workers and self-employed persons in beedi and cigar industries in the State of Kerala and matters connected therewith or incidental thereto;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted in the Forty-sixth Year of the Republic of India as follows: —</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Kerala Beedi and Cigar Workers' Welfare Fund Act, 1995.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Kerala.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification in the Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>'Board' means the Kerala Beedi and Cigar Workers' Welfare Fund Board constituted under section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>'Chief Welfare Fund Inspector' means the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) of section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>'contribution' means the sum of money payable to the Fund under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>'employee' means a person employed directly or through any agency, whether for wages or not, in any beedi or cigar establishment to do any work, skilled, unskilled, manual or clerical and includes,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any person who is given raw materials by an employer or a contractor for converting them into beedi or cigar at home;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any person not employed by an employer or a contractor but working with the permission of, or under agreement with the employer or contractor; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any person employed by a petty shop owner for wages or not, for making beedi or cigar;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>‘employer’ means,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.e.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in relation to contract labour, the principal employer; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.e.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in relation to any other labour, the person who has the ultimate control over the affairs of any establishment or who has, by reason of his advancing money, supplying goods or otherwise, a substantial interest in the control of the affairs of any establishment and includes any other person to whom the affairs of the establishment are entrusted, whether called the manager, superintendent or by any other name;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.f.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>‘family’ means,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.f.list2.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>husband, wife, minor sons, unmarried daughters; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.f.list2.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>father and mother who are solely dependent on the beedi or cigar worker or the self employed person;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>‘Fund’ means the Kerala Beedi and Cigar Workers’ Welfare Fund established under section 3 and the Scheme;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>‘member’ means an employee or self-employed person registered in the Scheme under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>‘prescribed’ means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>‘Schedule’ means the Schedule to this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>‘Scheme’ means the Scheme framed under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>‘self-employed person’ means a person who purchases raw materials and produces beedi or cigar and sells in the market for his livelihood, but does not include an employee as defined in clause (d);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.m.list3">
                  <listIntroduction>‘wages’ means all emoluments which are earned by an employee while on duty or on leave with wages in accordance with the terms of the contract of employment and which are paid or payable in cash to him, but does not include,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list3.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the cash value of any food concession;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list3.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>overtime allowance, bonus and commission;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>‘Welfare Fund Inspector’ means a Welfare Fund Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) of section 10.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>‘year’ means the financial year.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other words and expressions used but not defined in this Act but defined in the Beedi and Cigar Workers (Conditions of Employment) Act, 1966 (Central Act 32 of 1966), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Beedi and Cigar Workers' Welfare Fund Scheme.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the Gazette, frame a Scheme to be called the Beedi and Cigar Workers' Welfare Fund Scheme for the establishment of a Fund under this Act for employees and self-employed persons in beedi and cigar industry and there shall be established, as soon as may be after the framing of the Scheme, a Fund in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the Fund,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the contribution specified under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>grants or loans or advances made by the Government of lndia or the State Government or any authority or institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any donation from whatever source;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any amount raised by the Board from other sources to augment the resources of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>penalties and fines realised or imposed under sections 19, 20 and 21.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall vest in, and be administered by, the Board constituted under section 7.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Scheme may provide for all or any of the matters specified in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund may be utilised for all or any of the following purposes, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.5.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for payment of pension,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.5.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to a person who, immediately before the commencement of this Act, was an employee or self-employed person for a continuous period of not less than three years and has completed the age of fifty-eight years; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.5.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to a member who is paying contribution to the Fund continuously for a period of not less than three years and has completed the age of fifty-eight years;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for payment of educational assistance to the children of the members;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for payment of medical benefits to the members and their family;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for payment of financial assistance to the members for constructing houses for their residential purposes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for payment of financial assistance to the dependents of the members who die in harness;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for meeting the administrative expenses of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for any other purposes as may be provided in the Scheme.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Scheme framed under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is framed, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and, if before the expiry of the session in which it is so 1aid or the session immediately following, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in the Scheme, the Scheme shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form; so however that, any such modification shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Registration of beedi and cigar workers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every employee or self-employed person who is entitled to be a member shall register his name in the manner specified in the Scheme as a beneficiary of the Fund in the Register to be maintained by the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector or other officers authorised by him in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Contribution to the Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The contribution which shall be paid by the employer to the Fund shall be at the rate of six rupees per mensem in respect of each employee and the employee’s contribution to the Fund shall be at the rate of three rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every self-employed person shall contribute to the Fund five rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall, along with his contribution, pay to the Fund, the contribution in respect of the employees engaged by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall contribute to the Fund every year by way of grant or on a matching basis an amount equal to the contribution paid by the employees under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the employer shall be entitled to recover the employees’ contribution paid by him by deduction from his wages or in such other manner as may be prescribed, and such deduction shall be deemed to be a deduction authorised by or under the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (Central Act 4 of 1936).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Modification of the Scheme.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the Gazette,</p>
            <p>add to,</p>
            <p>amend or vary the Scheme either prospectively or retrospectively.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is</p>
            <p>issued, before</p>
            <p>the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days, which may be</p>
            <p>comprised in one</p>
            <p>session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid</p>
            <p>or the session</p>
            <p>immediately following, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in the notification or</p>
            <p>decides that the</p>
            <p>notification should not be issued, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such</p>
            <p>modified form or be of no</p>
            <p>effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or amendment shall be without</p>
            <p>prejudice to the</p>
            <p>validity of anything previously done under that notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the Gazette, constitute, with effect from such date as may be specified in such notification, a Board to be called the “Beedi and Cigar Workers' Welfare Fund Board" for the administration of the Fund and to supervise or carry out the activities financed from the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal and shall, by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall consist of such number of Directors as may be appointed by the Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Board shall include an equal number of Directors representing the Government, the employers and the employees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>One of the Directors of the Board shall be appointed by the Government to be its Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall publish in the Gazette the names of the Chairman and Directors of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall administer the Fund in such manner as may be specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the previous approval of the Government, delegate to the Chairman or to the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector or to any Welfare Fund Inspector such of its powers and functions under this Act or the Scheme as it may consider necessary for the efficient administration of the Fund, subject to such restrictions and conditions, if any, as it may specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of the Directors.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Director appointed under sub-section (3) of section 7 shall hold office for a period of three years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 9, the Government may, at any time, for reasons to be recorded in writing, remove from office any Director of the Board after giving him reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed removal:</p>
            <p>Provided that it shall not be necessary to record in writing, the reason for removal or to give an opportunity of showing cause against the proposed removal, if the Government are of opinion that it is not expedient, in the public interest, to record the reasons in writing or to give such opportunity.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Director may resign his membership by giving notice in writing to the Government, but shall continue in office until his resignation is accepted by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Removal of non-official Directors.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government may, by notification in the Gazette, remove any non-official Director of the Board from office,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he has, without the permission of the Board been absent from the meetings of the Board for three consecutive meetings:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such absence may be condoned by the Board before the publication of the notification in the Gazette;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>If in the opinion of the Government, he is unsuitable, or has become incapable of acting as a Director or has so abused his position as a Director as to render his continuance as such Director detrimental to the public interest:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that before removing a Director under this sub-section, he shall be given a reasonable opportunity to show cause why he should not be removed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A non-official Director of the Board removed under clause (a) of sub-section (1) shall be disqualified for reappointment as a Director of the Board for a period of three years from the date of his removal unless otherwise ordered by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A non-official Director of the Board removed under clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall not be eligible for re-appointment until he is declared by an order of the Government to be no longer ineligible.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of officers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may appoint a Chief Welfare Fund Inspector and as many Welfare Fund Inspectors and such other staff as they consider necessary to assist the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector in the discharge of his duties under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Welfare Fund Inspector shall be the Chief Executive Officer of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The method of appointment, salary and allowances, discipline and other conditions of service of the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector and the Welfare Fund Inspectors and other staff shall be such as may be prescribed by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Duty of employer to file return.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall, before fifth day of every month, file a return showing the details of contributions paid into the Fund, in such manner as may be specified in the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Determination of amount due from employers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Welfare Fund Inspector or any other Welfare Fund Inspector authorised by him in this behalf may, by order, determine the amount due from any employer under the provisions of this Act or of the Scheme and for this purpose, may conduct such inquiry as he may deem necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any Officer conducting the inquiry under sub-section (1) shall, for the purpose of such inquiry, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Central Act 5 of 1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any inquiry under this section shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 193 and section 228 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (Central Act 45 of 1860) and for the purposes of section 196 of that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order determining the amount due from any employer shall be made under sub-section (1) unless the employer has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may, within sixty days from the date of receipt of the order, prefer an appeal to the Government or any other authority as may be specified by the Government in this behalf and the decision of the Government or of such authority on such appeal shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Provisional assessment of contribution.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer shall, pending determination under section 12 of the amount due from him, pay on or before the 5th day of every month by way of advance contribution an amount equivalent to one-twelfth of the amount payable annually by him in respect of his establishment, according to the latest determination under the said section or, if the amount due from him has not been previously determined under the said section,an amount quivalent to one-twelfth of the amount which, according to the assessment of the employer is payable by him annually in respect of his establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The contribution shall be remitted to the individual account of each member and the employer shall file a statement showing the amount due to each member while remitting the monthly contribution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The contribution in respect of a self- employed person for a month shall become payable on or before the 5th day of the succeeding month.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the advance contribution is not paid on or before the due date, the Welfare Fund Inspector shall issue a notice to the defaulter showing the amount of arrears and, if the amount is not paid within seven days of the receipt of such notice, it may be recovered in the same manner as arrears of public revenue due on land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount paid under sub-section (1) by an employer shall be adjusted against the amount determined under section 12 of that year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Mode of recovery of money due from employer.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any amount due from the employer in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or the Scheme, other than an amount payable under sub-section (1) of section 12 may, if the amount is in arrears, be recovered together with interest thereon at the rate of sixteen per cent per annum in the same manner as an arrear of public revenue due on land.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Protection against attachment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount standing to the credit of any member in the Fund shall not in any way be capable of being assigned or charged and shall not be liable to attachment under any decree or order of any court in respect of any debt or liability incurred by the member, and no receiver appointed under the Insolvency Act, 1955 (2 of 1956) shall be entitled to or have any claim on any such amount.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount standing to the credit of a member in the Fund at the time of his death and payable to his nominee under the Scheme shall, subject to any deduction authorised by the Scheme, vest in the nominee and shall be free from any debt or other liability incurred by the deceased or the nominee before the death of the member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Priority of payment of contributions over other debts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any employer liable to pay contribution under section 5 is adjudicated insolvent or in case the employer is a company and an order for winding up of such company is made, the amount due from such employer under this Act or the Scheme shall, where the liability therefore has accrued before the order of adjudication or winding up is made, be deemed to be included among the debts which under section 64 of the Insolvency Act, 1955 (2 of 1956) or under section 530 of the Companies Act, 1956 (Central Act 1 of 1956 ) are to be paid in priority to all other debts in the distribution of the property of the insolvent or the assets of the company being wound up, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Employer not to reduce wages, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No employer shall by reason only of his liability for the payment of any contribution to the Fund, reduce, whether directly or indirectly, the wages of any employee to whom the Scheme applies or the total quantum of benefits to which the employee is entitled under the terms of his employment, express or implied.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Directors of Board, etc., to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Director of the Board, the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector and other officers and members of the Board shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (Central Act 45 of !860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, for the purpose of avoiding any payment to be made by him under this Act or under the Scheme or of enabling any other person to avoid any payment to be made under this Act or the Scheme, knowingly makes or causes to be made any false statement or false representation, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes or makes default in complying with any of the provisions of this Act or of the Scheme shall, if no other penalty is elsewhere provided by or under this Act for such contravention or non-compliance, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except on a report in writing of the facts constituting such offence made with the previous sanction of the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Enhanced punishment for default in payment of employees’ contribution already deducted.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever makes default in the payment of the employees' share of the contribution to the Fund after having deducted it from the wages of the employees in accordance with the provisions of this Act or the Scheme, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, but which shall not be less than three months, and with fine which may extend to four thousand rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that the court may, or any adequate and special reason to be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than three months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Central Act 2 of 1974), an offence under sub-section (1) shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Enhanced punishment for second or subsequent offence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever having been convicted by a court of an offence punishable under this Act, again commits the same offence shall be punishable for every such subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, but which shall not be less than three months, and with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that the court may, for any adequate and special reasons to be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than three months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub section shall render any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he has exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-22.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>For the purpose of this section, —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director” in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Directions by Government.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, after consultation with the Board, give to the Board general directions to be followed by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the exercise of its powers and performance of its duties under this Act the Board shall not depart from any general directions issued under sub-section (1), except with the previous permission of the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power to order inquiry.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, at any time , appoint any person to inquire into the working of the Board and to submit a report to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall give the person so appointed all facilities for the proper conduct of the inquiry and furnish to him such documents, accounts and information in the possession of the Board as he may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Power to supersede the Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If on consideration of the report under section 24 or otherwise, the Government are of opinion that the Board has persistently made default in the performance of the duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act or the Scheme or has exceeded or abused its powers, the Government may, by notification in the Gazette, supersede the Board for such period not exceeding six months as may be specified in the notification:</p>
            <p>Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-section, the Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Board to show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Upon the publication of a notification under sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all the Directors of the Board shall, as from the date of such publication, vacate their offices, as such Directors;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all the powers and duties which may be exercised or performed by the Board shall, during the period of supersession, be exercised or performed by such officer or officers as may be specified in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all funds and other properties vested in the Board shall, during the period of supersession, vest in the Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the expiration of the period of supersession, the Government shall reconstitute the Board in the manner provided in section 7.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against any Director of the Board or the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector or any other person in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule made thereunder or under the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of civil courts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall have jurisdiction to settle, decide or deal with any question or to determine any matter which is by or under this Act or the Scheme require to be settled, decided or dealt with or to be determined by the Government or the Board or the Chief Welfare Fund Inspector or any other officer appointed under section 10.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the Gazettee, make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in the rule or decides that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Kerala Beedi and Cigar Workers’ Welfare Fund Ordinance, 1995 (12 of 1995) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1995/18"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1995/18/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>(See sub-section (4) of section 3)</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Matters for which provision may be made in the Scheme</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>Registration of employees and self employed persons.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which contributions shall be made to the Fund by employers and by, or on behalf of, employees (whether employed directly, or through an agency) and by self employed persons and the manner in which such contributions may be recovered.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which employees' contribution may be recovered by contractors from employees employed by or through such contractors.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>The constitution of any committee for assisting the Board.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which account shall be kept, the investment of moneys belonging to the Fund in accordance with any directions issued or conditions specified by the Government, the preparation of the budget, the audit of accounts and the submission of reports to the Government.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>The conditions under which withdrawals from the Fund may be permitted and any deduction or forfeiture may be made and the maximum amount of such deduction or forfeiture.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>The conditions and procedure for the payment of pension, Financial assistance, educational assistance and medical benefit to the members, children and family, as the case may be.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>The fixation by the Government in consultation with the Board of the rate of interest payable to members.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>The form in which an employee shall furnish particulars about himself and his family whenever required.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>The nomination of a person to receive the amount standing to the credit of a member after his death and the cancellation or variation of such nomination.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>The registers and records to be maintained with respect to employees and the returns to be furnished by the employers or agencies.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>The form or design of any identity card for the purpose of identifying members and for issue, custody and replacement thereof.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>The fees to be levied for any of the purposes specified in this Schedule.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>The further powers, if any, which may be exercised by the officers appointed under this Act.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>The manner in which the Directors of the Board shall be chosen and appointed.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>The conditions of service, duties and remuneration of officers appointed under this Act.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>The conditions under which any amount due to the Board may be written off.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Any other matter which is to be provided for in the Scheme or which may be necessary or proper for the purpose of implementing the Scheme.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
