<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/43/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/43"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Diplomatic Relations (Vienna Convention) Act, 1972"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1972-08-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Diplomatic Relations (Vienna Convention) Act, 1972</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 43 OF 1972</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 29th August, 1972.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to give effect to the Vienna Convention on diplomatic</p>
        <p>Relations,</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1961">
        <num>1961.</num>
        <heading>and to provide for matters connected therewith.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1961.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- third Year of the</p>
            <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Diplomatic Relations (Vienna Convention) Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Application of Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law,</p>
            <p>the provisions set out in the Schedule to this Act of the Vienna</p>
            <p>Convention on Diplomatic Relations, adopted by the United Nations</p>
            <p>Conference on Diplomatic Intercourse and Immunities on the 14th day of</p>
            <p>April, 1961, shall have the force of law in India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity  with any amendments, duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the  said Convention set out therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of certain privileges and immunities to diplomatic  missions and their members pursuant to international agreement.- Where  in pursuance of any agreement, convention or other instrument it is  necessary to accord to any diplomatic mission and its members, the  sending State of which is not a party to the Vienna Convention on</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Diplomatic- Relations, 1961 or to any other special mission and its  members, privileges and immunities in India similar to those contained  in the provisions set out in the Schedule, the Central Government may,</p>
            <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the provisions  set out in the Schedule shall, subject to such modifications, if any,</p>
            <p>as it may consider necessary or expedient for giving effect to the  said agreement, convention or other instrument, apply mutatis mutandis  to the diplomatic mission and its members, or to the other special  mission and its members, as the case may be, and thereupon the said  provisions shall apply accordingly, and notwithstanding anything to  the contrary contained in any other law, shall in such application  have the force of law in India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions on privileges and immunities.- If it appears to  the Central Government that a State which is a party to the Vienna</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Convention on Diplomatic Relations, 1961 is in breach of its  obligations arising thereunder or, that the privileges and immunities</p>
            <p>accorded to an Indian Mission or members thereof in the territory of  any State which is a party to the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic</p>
            <p>Relations, 1961, are less than those conferred by this Act on the</p>
            <p>Diplomatic mission of that State or members thereof, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, by  notification in the Official Gazette, withdraw such of the privileges  and immunities so conferred from the diplomatic mission of that State  or from members thereof as may appear to the Central Government to be  proper.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Waiver.- For the purpose of article 32 of the Convention set  out in the Schedule, a waiver by the head of the mission of any State  or any person for the time being performing his functions shall be  deemed to be a waiver by that State.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions on certain exemptions from customs duty, etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in article 36 of the Convention set out in the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleshall">
      <doc name="scheduleshall">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/43/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/43"/>
              <FRBRalias value="be construed to entitle a diplomatic mission or member  thereof to import into India goods free of any duty of customs without  any restrictions on their subsequent sale therein."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/43/eng@1972-08-29"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleshall">
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Privileges and immunities of citizens of India.- For the  purpose of article 38 of the Convention set out in the Schedule, a  citizen of India shall be entitled only to such additional privileges  and immunities, other than those set out in that article, as are  granted to him by the Central Government by notification in the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Official Gazette.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Restrictions on entry into diplomatic premises.- No public  servant or agent of the Central Government, a State Government or any  public authority shall enter the premises of a diplomatic mission for  the purpose of serving legal process, except with the consent of the  head of the mission. Such consent may be obtained through the Ministry  of External Affairs of the Government of India.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Evidence.- If in any proceedings any question arises whether or  not any person is entitled to any privilege or immunity under this</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Act, a certificate issued by or under the authority of the Secretary  to the Government of India in the Ministry of External Affairs stating  any fact relating to that question shall be conclusive evidence of  that fact.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.- The Central Government may , by  notification in the official Gazette,] make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Notifications issued and rules made under this Act to be laid  before Parliament.- Every notification issued and every rule made under  this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is issued or made  before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total  period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two  or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>in the notification or, as the case may be, in the rule, or both</p>
                  <p>Houses agree that the notification or rule should not be issued or  made, the notification or rule shall thereafter have effect only in  such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so,</p>
                  <p>however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without  prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that  notification or rule.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
