<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2000/52/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2000/52"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Immigration (Carriers' Liability) Act, 2000"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2000/52/eng@2000-12-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2000/52/eng@2000-12-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2000-12-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2000/52/eng@2000-12-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2000/52/eng@2000-12-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Immigration (Carriers' Liability) Act, 2000</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 52 OF 2000</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 11th December, 2000.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make the carriers liable in respect of passengers brought by  them into India in contravention of the provisions of the Passport</p>
        <p>(Entry into India) Act, 1920 and the rules made thereunder and matters  connected therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Immigration</p>
            <p>(Carriers' Liability) Act, 2000.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" carrier" means a person who is engaged in the business of  transporting passengers by water or air and includes any association  of persons, whether incorporated or not, by whom the aircraft or the  ship is owned or chartered;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Competent Authority" means the civil authority appointed under  sub- paragraph (2) of paragraph 2 of the Foreigners Order, 1948 made  under the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946) or any other officer  notified by the Central Government in this behalf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Words and expressions not defined in this Act but defined in the</p>
            <p>Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946) or the Passport (Entry into India)</p>
            <p>Act, 1920 (34 of 1920) shall have the meanings respectively assigned  to them in those Acts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Liability of carriers for passengers brought into India.- Where the  competent authority is of the opinion that any carrier has brought a  person in contravention of the provisions of the Passport (Entry into</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>India) Act, 1920 (34 of 1920) and rules made thereunder into India, he  may by order impose a penalty of rupees one lakh on such carrier:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order shall be passed without giving the carrier an  opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Appeals.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie against the order made under  section 3 of this Act to the Joint Secretary to the Government of</p>
            <p>India in the Ministry of Home Affairs authorised in this behalf by  that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such appeal shall be preferred within thirty days from the  date of the order appealed against:</p>
            <p>Provided that the appellate authority may, if it is satisfied that the  appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal  within the said period of thirty days, permit the appellant to prefer  the appeal within a further period of thi ty days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of any such appeal, the appellate authority shall,</p>
            <p>after giving the parties a reasonable opportunity of being heard and  after making such inquiry as it deems proper, make such order, as it  may think fit, confirming, modifying or reversin the order appealed  against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal shall be preferred on payment of such fees as may be  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of penalty due to Government.- Where any penalty imposed  under this Act is not paid, the competent authority may recover the  penalty so payable by seizing, detaining or selling-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the aircraft or the ship; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any goods on the ship or aircraft, belonging to the carrier.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Bar of legal proceedings.- No suit, prosecution or other legal  proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the competent  authority or any officer of the Central Government or any other person  exercising any powers or discharging any functi ns or performing any  duty under this Act for anything in good faith done or intended to be  done under this Act or any rule made thereunder.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Application of Acts 16 of 1939, 34 of 1920 and 31 of 1946 not  barred.- The provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder shall  be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the Registration of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Foreigners Act, 1939, the Passport (Entry into Indi) Act, 1920 and  the Foreigners Act, 1946 or the rules or orders made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the fees which shall be paid for appeals under sub- section (4) of  section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Rules to be laid before Parliament.- Every rule made under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or i two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses  agree that the rule should not be m de, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions for  the purpose of removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of two  years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be  after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
            <p>SUBHASH C. JAIN,</p>
            <p>Secy. to the Govt. of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
